<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tl216">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Articles of Agreement] 1794 Oct. 12 [between] Governor William Blount and David Moore : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>tl216</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 49961536</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Articles of Agreement] 1794 Oct. 12 [between] Governor William Blount and David Moore</title>
               <date when="1794-10-12">October 12, 1794</date>
               <extent> 4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is an article of agreement dated October 12, 1794 between William Blount, Governor of the territory of the United States south of the river Ohio and David Moore of Knoxville. The article states that David Moore will deliver goods by boat for the Chickasaw and Choctaw Indians from the Tennessee River near Holston to the mouth of Bear Creek. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor William Blount Correspondence</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">tl216</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Moore, David</term>
               <term>Chickasaw Indians</term>
               <term>Choctaw Indians</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tl216a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>Articles of agreement</head>
            <p>made and entered into between <name type="person">William Blount</name> Governor in and over the <name type="place">territory of the <name type="place">United States of America</name> south of the river Ohio,</name> and superintendent of  <choice>
                  <orig>indian</orig>
                  <reg>Indian</reg>
               </choice> affairs for the southern district on the part of the <name type="place">United States</name> on the one part and <name type="person">David Moore</name> of <name type="place">Knoxville</name> on the other part, respecting the working a large flat bottomed boat from this place down the <choice>
                  <orig>tennessee</orig>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice> with a quantity of goods belonging to the <name type="persons">Chickasaw</name> and <name type="persons">Choctaw</name> nations of <choice>
                  <orig>indians</orig>
                  <reg>Indians</reg>
               </choice>, being the same goods that were given by the United States to the said nations and in July last delivered at <name type="place">Philadelphia </name> to <name type="person">Opoia Mingo</name> and others of his nation then at Philadelphia. Witness, that the said David Moore engages to hold himself in readiness to take charge of the said boat now laying in the <choice>
                  <orig>holston</orig>
                  <reg>Holston</reg>
               </choice> river near the camp of the said Opoia Mingo about four hundred yards below this place on saturday the 18th instant, by which time it is supposed the whole of the said goods will have arrived at that place and be put on board the said boat in the character of commander thereof and to provide six good oarsmen by the aforesaid day to work the said boat down the <choice>
                  <orig>tennessee</orig>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice> to the mouth of Bear Creek, or to such other place above as Opoia Mingo shall <pb n="2" facs="tl216b.small.jpg"/> direct the said goods to be landed, and he the said David Moore further engages and agrees with the said William Blount that in the character of commander of the said flat bottomed boat he will use the utmost skill and attributes in commanding conducting and defending her with her lading down the <choice>
                  <orig>tennessee</orig>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice> against all attacks that may be made upon the said boat by any hostile party or parties of <name type="persons">Creeks</name> or <name type="persons">Cherokees</name> and that he will take special care of Opoia Mingo and his party of Chickasaws who are to pass down the <choice>
                  <orig>tennessee</orig>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice> in the said boat with the goods as before described belonging to the Chickasaws and Choctaws—and the said William Blount engages on the part of the United States that the said David Moore shall be paid for his own skill trouble and service in commanding and conducting the said boat to the mouth of Bear Creek or to such other place above as Opoia Mingo shall order their goods to be landed two hundred dollars and that each of the six oarsmen shall be paid one dollar per day for their services counting from the time they appear at the boat ready to go on board provided such appearance be not before the 18th instant to the day they return to this place provided more than twenty <add place="supralinear">four</add> days shall not be allowed to return to this place from the place where the goods shall be landed.—and it is further agreed that provisions shall be put on board the said boat at this place at the cost of  <pb n="3" facs="tl216c.small.jpg"/> the United States in such quantity as shall be judged sufficient for the said David Moore and the six oarsmen for the voyage down the river and for their support on their return, but in case of deficiency no allowance shall be claimed on their return for such deficiency.—</p>
            <p>Knoxville <date when="1794-10-12">October 12th 1794</date>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                     <expan>William</expan>
                  </choice> Blount</signed>
               <signed>David Moore</signed>
               <add>Witness</add>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">James King</name>
               </signed>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <emph>Willie Blount</emph>
                  </name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="tl216d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Articles of agreement Governor Blount with David Moore <date when="1794-10-12">October 12th 94</date>
               </add>
               <add rend="penciled in ">1794</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
