<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0055">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> [Legal document] 1837 Feb. between Spencer Jarnagin and the Cherokee Nation East / Spencer Jarnagin : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Jarnagin, Spencer</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0055</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Legal document] 1837 Feb. between Spencer Jarnagin and the Cherokee Nation East / Spencer Jarnagin </title>
               <author> Jarnagin, Spencer </author>
               <date when="1837-02"> 
			 February 1837</date>
               <extent> 3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a legal document between the Cherokee Nation East and Spencer Jarnagin who served as attorney for them from 1820 to 1837. The document shows that the Cherokee Nation paid Mr. Jarnagin two hundred and fifty dollars per year for a total of four thousand dollars. The document then has a written statement from Mr. Jarnagin disputing the correctness of the amount paid to him.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> n/a</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Legal documents</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Legal status, laws, etc.</term>
               <term>Jarnagin, Spencer, 1792-1853</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2008078368"
                        role="Associated name http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/asn">Jarnagin, Spencer, 1792-1853</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0055a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>The Cherokee Nation East <lb/> To <name>Spencer Jarnagin</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                  <expan>Debtor</expan>
               </choice>
               <lb/>  For Services as an attorney at law, rendered <lb/> to the <name>Cherokee Nation</name>, within the limits <lb/> of the state of <name>Tennessee</name> from the year 1820 <lb/> to February 1837 at $250 per year........$4000.</opener>
            <p>My first engagement was in the latter part of the year 1820, <choice>
                  <abbr>tho'</abbr>
                  <expan>though</expan>
               </choice> I rendered but little service till the beginning of 1821. Since that time, every year has afforded more or less cases, before the courts of Tennessee, perhaps, up to this time, the number of five or six hundred_ My engagement was by the Nation, and was to attend to all cases as they might arise. There was no agreement as to the amount of compensation I should receive. When I was about to make out my account, not wishing to value my own services, I applied to the Honorable <name>Charles F. Kritt</name>, who had presided as Judge in all the courts of Tennessee bordering on the Indian Country, and when their business was, from the year 1819, also <name>Thomas J. Campbell</name>, who was the former Attorney General in Kritts circuit, <name>James F. Bradford</name> who had <unclear>practiced</unclear> as an attorney in the same circuit for <unclear>much of the time</unclear>, and others who had a personal knowledge of <gap agent="damage"/> services. Their certificate is here <unclear>annexed</unclear> marked A I have conformed my account to their <unclear>climate</unclear>, tho' I think myself it is less than I should receive_ As confirmatory <unclear>evidence</unclear> I beg leave <del type="overstrike">leave</del> here to present the certificates of  <name>Samuel Frazier</name>, the present Attorney General in Judge Kritts ciruit, marked B., <unclear>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Col</abbr>
                        <expan>Colonel</expan>
                     </choice>. Henry Brise</name> judge</unclear> marked C. <name>Samuel McCamel</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Esg.</abbr>
                  <expan>Esquire</expan>
               </choice> marked D. To show that I have not been paid, the certificate of <name>John Martin</name>, marked E. Upon the first point that of Col. <name>John Williams</name>, marked F. My own affidavit marked G. Also the affidavit of <name>Samuel C. Farris</name>, marked H. The certificate of <name>James Berry</name>, the clerk of the County court of <name>Rhea County</name>, marked J. Of <name>Henry Price</name>, the Clerk of the circuit court of <name>Bradly County</name>, marked K. and of <name>John C. Kennedy</name>, marked L. Tho' certificate A refers to the case of the State Tennessee against <pb n="2" facs="pa0055b.small.jpg"/>
               <name>Forman</name>and <name>Springston</name>, charged with murder of John Walker Jr, I claim nothing for my attention to that cause. I attended to it for them as individuals the Cherokee Nation <unclear>refraining</unclear> to interfere, and have their note for my  services, and it is referred to as a class of cases and perhaps the <unclear>gentlemen</unclear> who gave the certificate knew not the facts that it is my duty to disclose._</p>
            <p>All of which is respectfully submitted to the Commission at <name>New Echota, Georgia</name> by their</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Most <choice>
                     <abbr>Obt. Servt</abbr>
                     <expan>Obedient Servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Spencer Jarnagin</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="pa0055c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Act</abbr>
                     <expan>Account</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/> Spencer Jarnagin <lb/> for <lb/> legal services to the <lb/> Cherokee Nation <lb/> $4000. <lb/> ―</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
