<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0217">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1814 May 6 [to] Col. Return J. Meigs / Charles Hicks : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Hicks, Charles R.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0217</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 45869961</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1814 May 6 [to] Col. Return J. Meigs / Charles Hicks  </title>
               <author>Hicks, Charles R. </author>
               <date when="1814-05-06">May 6, 1814</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated May 6, 1814 from Cherokee leader Charles Hicks to Colonel Return J. Meigs concerning a number of topics including the requesting of supplies and corn for food.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> pa00217</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Cherokee Indians</term>
               <term>Annuities</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr2001025844"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Hicks, Charles R.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0217a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Fortville</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>May 6th 1814</date>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <name>Taw, law, coo, saws</name> account which you had forwarded one <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> McGhee I have had it Settled, and I had also <choice>
                  <orig>supplyed</orig>
                  <reg>supplied</reg>
               </choice> the <name>Deer bites</name> and <name>John <add>Spears</add>
               </name> , with their<choice>
                  <orig>partys</orig>
                  <reg>parties</reg>
               </choice> , with provisions, <unclear>but</unclear> Mr McGhee and Hender <add>son</add> would not settle them, without you would make out the amount <choice>
                  <orig>Simalar</orig>
                  <reg>similar</reg>
               </choice> to the former one__ it is true the provision is but trifling <choice>
                  <orig>inself</orig>
                  <reg>itself</reg>
               </choice> but the people were in real need and could not be got Else where, and it was <unclear>disobliging</unclear> my family to Spare what I did.  if you think I acted right in this little affair, you will <choice>
                  <orig>oblidge</orig>
                  <reg>oblige</reg>
               </choice> me to send me an order <add>on</add> Mr McGhee and the <choice>
                  <orig>recept</orig>
                  <reg>receipt</reg>
               </choice> of the provision I enclose for you__ which will show the quantity <add>of provision</add> given out__</p>
            <p>I also send you the ridges account Given by Saunders when they party was on their way to <name>fort armstrong</name> for their <choice>
                  <orig>randeavouz</orig>
                  <reg>rendezvous</reg>
               </choice> for Second <unclear/> where all the Cherokees were Discharged for the first Term of service__</p>
            <p>the second acct. of the <name>ridge</name> and <name>saunders</name> , which was Contracted at <name>Hightower</name> on their return with their Company from the <unclear/> c the <choice>
                  <orig>accout</orig>
                  <reg>account</reg>
               </choice> of the hogs got of <name>little John field</name> was to supply Foster party on their way to join <name>Gen. Jackson</name> last battle c</p>
            <p>
               <name>James Foster</name>
               <name>
                  <unclear>kelachulee</unclear>
               </name>    has being here in order to have their account made out and to be <choice>
                  <orig>transmited</orig>
                  <reg>transmitted</reg>
               </choice> to you.  of which I enclose you their provision <add>account</add> of, they had got to take them on the <name>Fort armstrong</name> __ and beside what was got <add>at</add>
               <name>Coosewatee</name> , they have Stated from who the provision was got when on <gap/>
               <name>armstrong</name> __ perhaps the provision might exceed the <choice>
                  <orig>usal</orig>
                  <reg>usual</reg>
               </choice> quantity allowed each man, but they wee detained some days at <name>oostenaleh</name> before the startd fro armstrong__ and you'll be please to <unclear>made</unclear> out their account on <name>Mr McGhee</name>   and I <del type="overstrike">te</del> get it for them, as I shall have to attend a council at Coosewatee and I can take it to them__</p>
            <p>I also enclose <del type="overstrike">you</del> five <unclear>due</unclear> bills for corn, which I need for corn in the last boat to ad you had send down and I told <name>
                  <unclear>Mr Huss</unclear>
               </name>  to left all the corn due bills that might be brought in <del type="overstrike">and</del> but I have received no answer to my letter which I had wrote to him the first of this month.  I had received few lines from him before mine, that he borrowed some more corn from the quarter master.  to <orig>relieve</orig> Some of the most needy.  and <unclear>
                  <del/>
               </unclear> in consequence of these loans, I have received a letter from <unclear>Major</unclear>
               <name>Baxter</name> .  <name>L Master</name> informing me that he lent the corn to <name>Mr Ross</name> and desires me to inform you that he wished it might be replaced again, and <unclear>he</unclear> self would have wrote up to you, but being in hurry in preparing to <unclear/> to <name>Huntsvilles</name> , to meet <name>Genl. Jackson</name> __</p>
            <p>There is a general cry for corn in the <choice>
                  <orig>uper</orig>
                  <reg>upper</reg>
               </choice>
               <add>or rather middle</add> parts of the nation that if you could send down fifteen Hundred <choice>
                  <orig>bushells</orig>
                  <reg>bushels</reg>
               </choice> of corn, it would relieve great many Distressed people as the waring par <add>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>tys</orig>
                     <reg>ies</reg>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="pa0217b.small.jpg"/>
               <del>have</del> in going and returning through <name>Hightower</name> fork <name>Selliwah</name> and <unclear/> has reduced their scanty stocks of provisions, and it was on this amount <name>the ridge</name> informed me that <name>Chuleva</name> , and <name>the sour mush</name> wished to <unclear/> , as I did not meet them at <name>the ridges</name>  house as I expected, if this corn could be got, can be sent down to <name>Mr Ross</name> and <name>Mr. Henderson</name>
               <name>McGhee</name> to as proposing to let you have three <add>hundred</add>
               <choice>
                  <orig>berrels</orig>
                  <reg>barrels</reg>
               </choice> of meal for the use of the <name>Cherokees</name> but if corn can be had, is much preferable then meal <add>it</add> and please to let me know on this subject.</p>
            <p>When I was at <name>camp Ross</name>
               <name>the flute</name> complained that he did not get the <choice>
                  <orig>quatity</orig>
                  <reg>quantity</reg>
               </choice> of corn of the man who let him <add>have it</add> as was contained in the order you had given him, and he brought up <name>Mr Thompson</name> to substantiate this deficiency of corn, and Mr Thompson says he was present when the corn was measured which was <add>brought</add> by <name>the flute</name> .  and that there was only a Hundred and twenty two <choice>
                  <orig>bushells</orig>
                  <reg>bushels</reg>
               </choice> Scant measure</p>
            <p>Mr Thompson informs me that he got one of his creaturs which he had lost <add>near</add> for armstrong __ which creature is entered in my reports of the stocks destroyed by the army this creature was got at <name>South west point</name> by the big <name>Ratling goard</name> __</p>
            <p>At the time when I was at <name>camp Ross</name>
               <name>the old Broom</name> came and complained that the <choice>
                  <orig>waggoners</orig>
                  <reg>wagoners</reg>
               </choice> who had brought this things to <name>Joseph Coodys</name> ) he has moved to that place, had <choice>
                  <orig>robed</orig>
                  <reg>robbed</reg>
               </choice>
               <add>him</add> of his <choice>
                  <orig>duebills</orig>
                  <reg>due bills</reg>
               </choice> for corn which was in a trunk and <choice>
                  <orig>wraped</orig>
                  <reg>wrapped</reg>
               </choice> in a shawl <unclear>Hand</unclear>
               <unclear/>
               <name>
                  <abbr>Majr</abbr> Baxter</name> was informed of this circumstance and search and <choice>
                  <orig>examiniation</orig>
                  <reg>examination</reg>
               </choice> was made out <gap/> and the blame <add>was</add> laid to <name>the <unclear>brooms</unclear>
               </name>
               <choice>
                  <orig>negroe</orig>
                  <reg>negro</reg>
               </choice> fellow <del type="overstrike">but</del> if the fellow is guilty it will be found <add>out</add> but I suspect this act was <choice>
                  <orig>commited</orig>
                  <reg>committed</reg>
               </choice> by other <choice>
                  <orig>waggoners</orig>
                  <reg>wagoners</reg>
               </choice> in com <add>pany</add> because these was great many beads of Different sorts in the trunk which the did not take.  and their bills contains about forty Dollars and signed, I suppose some by <choice>
                  <orig>waggon</orig>
                  <reg>wagon</reg>
               </choice> master and perhaps <name>Merideth</name> has signed some of them please to have the payment of <choice>
                  <orig>Stoped</orig>
                  <reg>stopped</reg>
               </choice> at the office where such bills are to be discharged__</p>
            <p>I have also enclosed in the bundle an account of more stock destroyed at <del type="overstrike">the</del> least.  <unclear>
                  <del/>
               </unclear>
               <add>was</add> done by the first army <add>and some since</add> and I have continued the numbers agreeable to my report of the stock destroyed and some of these account now will have reference to the numbes in my report.</p>
            <p>I am <choice>
                  <orig>truely</orig>
                  <reg>truly</reg>
               </choice> rejoiced to hear the restoration of peace with these deluded race of <name>creeks</name> who have being seeking for such <unclear>flaging</unclear> for great many years, and hoping in our good Lord that will enlighten their Understanding to <choice>
                  <orig>repect</orig>
                  <reg>respect</reg>
               </choice> the <name>United States</name> for their humanity towards all the red people within the limits of the united Staes, <choice>
                  <abbr>c</abbr>
                  <expan>etcetera</expan>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am Sir yours <choice>
                     <orig>repectfully</orig>
                     <reg>respectfully</reg>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Ch</abbr>
                        <expan>Charles</expan>
                     </choice> Hicks</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                        <expan>Colonel</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name>Return J Meigs</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Agent war Department</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Highwassee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="3" facs="pa0217c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <name>Charles Hicks</name> letter <date>6th May 1814__</date> accounts of supplies to the Cherokee troops on their return and <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                        <expan>Colonel</expan>
                     </choice> Return J Meigs</name> an additional Statement of Spoliation. <address>
                     <addrLine>Agent War Department</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>at Highwassee Garrison <lb/> by oosookee</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
