<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl719">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1803 Jun 27, Frankfort, Kentucky [to] Archibald Roane, Nashville, Tennessee / James Garrard : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Garrard, James</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl719</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1803 Jun 27, Frankfort, Kentucky [to] Archibald Roane, Nashville, Tennessee / James Garrard</title>
               <author>Garrard, James</author>
               <date when="1803-06-27"> 
			 June 27, 1803</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated June 27, 1803 from James Garrard, governor of Kentucky to the governor of Tennessee, Archibald Roane.  The purpose of the letter is the request the apprehension and delivery  of Robert Wiley, who has been charged with a felony in that state.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Archibald Roane Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">7</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl719</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Roane, Archibald, 1759-1819</term>
               <term>Tennessee. Office of the Governor.</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n81116089"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Garrard, James, 1749-1822</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl719a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Frankfort</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>27th June 1803</date>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>In conformity with the provisions of an act of the congress of the <name>united states</name>, passed in the year 1793, entitled "an act respecting fugitives from justice and persons escaping from the service of their masters," I have transmitted to your Excellency an affidavit made before a magistrate of this state, charging a certain <name>Robert Wiley</name> with felony and have certified the said affidavit to be authentic.  Information  has been communicated to me, and is indeed fully corroborated by the affidavit of <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Early, that the said Robert Wiley, being a fugitive from the justice of this state, was apprehended in consequence of the charge exhibited against him by Mr Early, &amp; committed to the district jail in <name>Nashville</name>.  It is therefore my request that he may be delivered to <name>David Early</name>, whom I have appointed agent to receive and conduct him to this state, and that your Excellency will be pleased to consider this request as an official demand of the said Robert Wiley, as a fugitive from justice, under the authority of the before mentioned act of congress.   <pb n="2" facs="sl719b.small.jpg"/>   I would request your excellency moreover to cause a statement of all costs or expenses incurred in apprehending, securing and delivering up the said fugitive to be transmitted to me; and have the honor to be, with high consideration, Sir   </p>
            <closer>
               <add>Your most <choice>
                     <abbr>obedt servt</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <signed>
                  <name>James Garrard</name>
               </signed>
               <add>Governor of the commonwealth of <name>Kentucky</name>.__  By the Governor <name>Harry Toulmin</name> Secretary of State   <lb/> To His Excellency the Governor of the State of <name>Tennessee</name>
                  <pb n="3" facs="sl719c.small.jpg"/>   1803 <choice>
                     <orig>Warrent</orig>
                     <reg>Warrant</reg>
                  </choice> for <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Robt</abbr>
                        <expan>Robert</expan>
                     </choice> Wiley</name> from <choice>
                     <abbr>Gov</abbr>
                     <expan>Governor</expan>
                  </choice> of <choice>
                     <abbr>Ky</abbr>
                     <expan>Kentucky</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
