<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl658">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1839 Jan. 28, Ross Landing, Tennessee [to] Newton Cannon / James A. Whiteside : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Whiteside, James A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl658</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1839 Jan. 28, Ross Landing, Tennessee [to] Newton Cannon / James A. Whiteside</title>
               <author> Whiteside, James A.</author>
               <date when="1839-01-28"> 
			 January 28, 1839</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated January 28, 1839 from James A. Whiteside to the governor of Tennessee, Newton Cannon.  The purpose of the letter is railroad construction and transportation improvements.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Newton Cannon Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">10</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl658</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007057518"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Whiteside, Jas. A. (James A.)</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl658a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Ross Landing <choice>
                        <abbr>Tn</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jany</abbr>
                     <expan>January</expan>
                  </choice>. 28 1839</date>
               <add>To his Excellency <choice>
                     <abbr>Gov</abbr>
                     <expan>Governor</expan>
                  </choice>. Cannon,</add>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Two of the commissioners of the Western &amp; Atlantic Rail Road of <name>Georgia</name> arrived at this place on yesterday, having come out with a view of locating the <unclear>terminus</unclear> of that Road on the <name>Tennessee river</name>.__  The legislature of this state has, as I understand by resolution or otherwise, directed them to elect the<unclear>terminus</unclear>  with reference to the most direct <choice>
                  <orig>connexion</orig>
                  <reg>conection</reg>
               </choice> practicable with the West generally, but particularly with West <name>Tennessee</name>  __ This is so obviously the interest of Georgia as well as of Tennessee, that explorations and <choice>
                  <orig>recoginozances</orig>
                  <reg>recognizances</reg>
               </choice> for a short distance west of the river were thought advisable by the commissioners to <choice>
                  <orig>asertain</orig>
                  <reg>ascertain</reg>
               </choice> the most eligible route for a prolongation of the improvement.__ The privilege granted by Tennessee to Georgia for surveys, construction of roads<choice>
                  <abbr> &amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>and et cetera</expan>
               </choice> only extends to the Eastern margin of the river,__ and the <choice>
                  <abbr>commrs</abbr>
                  <expan>commissioners</expan>
               </choice> have not felt <choice>
                  <orig>authorised</orig>
                  <reg>authorized</reg>
               </choice> to cross the river, without some intimation from the executive of our states that it would not be regarded as an intrusion.__  The two who are here, have been brought out an engineer  with them for the purpose indicated; but meeting here with an apparently semi official paragraph in a late member of the <name>Nashville</name> Whig on the subject.  they seem to understand from it that <name>Tennessee</name> knows and <pb n="2" facs="sl658b.small.jpg"/> cares but little about their enterprize__ and above all that their grand object of connecting the <name>Atlantic</name> with <add>the</add> valley of the <name>mississippi</name> by as direct a communication as possible is likely to receive but little consideration or encouragement in Tennessee__ If the river instead of a railway, is to be relied on as affording the means of a permanent connection it is obviously proper that the Rail Road, by Georgia or Tennessee, be contained down below the Suck &amp; Boiling Pot from where there is uninterrupted steam Boat navigation at almost all stages of water to the head of the <name>muscle shoals</name>.__ Such a continuation, if no other be thought of; cannot be made without crossing the river above the obstructions, and Georgia is anxious to terminate her road with a view to this continuation at least.__ Her commissioners, I am persuaded, feel that their proposition to make an examination west of the river, has been declined by the authorities of Tennessee, and in consequence of it, not being able to carry out the views of their state satisfactorily, they have determined to return without making any examination or location.__ I know they feel somewhat mortified at the seeming indifference of Tennessee on this subject as manifested in your views as given in the paragraph above alluded to, and knowing that they misunderstood the matter, (and of which I have endeavoured to satisfy them) and that you in common with a large portion of our state must <pb n="3" facs="sl658c.small.jpg"/> feel the liveliest interest in the construction of this great work, I take the liberty of informing you of what has transpired that you may <unclear>treat</unclear> the subject as you may think most advisable under the circumstances.__</p>
            <p>The commissioners &amp; <unclear>engineer</unclear> will leave this place early tomorrow morning for Georgia and I have no doubt but that the tone if your communication to them will determine the question whether they will cross the line of Tennessee at all with their improvement; at least for the present.__</p>
            <closer>
               <add>Very respectfully Your <choice>
                     <abbr>obt. Servt</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient servant</expan>
                  </choice>.</add>
               <signed>
                  <name>James A. Whiteside</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl658d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <name>J. A. Whiteside</name>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
