<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mc020">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1847 Mar. 27 [to] Mrs. William R. Caswell, Russelville, Tennessee / William Richard Caswell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Caswell, William Richard</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>mc020</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50473851</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1847 Mar. 27 [to] Mrs. William R. Caswell, Russelville, Tennessee / William Richard Caswell </title>
               <author>Caswell, William Richard</author>
               <date when="1847-03-27">March 27, 1847</date>
               <extent>3 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by William Richard Caswell to his wife from Vera Cruz, Mexico during the Mexican-American War. Caswell explains that the take over of Vera Cruz was victorious for the Americans and that his wife should hear from intelligence soon. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">William R. Caswell Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-18, b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">4</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mc020</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Mexican War, 1846-1848</term>
               <term>Mexico</term>
               <term>United States</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Caswell, William Richard</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mc020a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Vera Cruz</name>
                     <date when="1847-03-27">27th March 1847</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear Wife</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I landed here on day before <choice>
                  <orig>yesturday</orig>
                  <reg>yesterday</reg>
               </choice> in the midst of the storming of the city after a long and tempestuous voyage of twenty five days, I had been in hearing of all the guns, and within sight of  the flash—but could not land, until day before yesterday—And when I put my foot upon the shore, I found my company upon the beach for the first time under arms. I drew off my coat and having left my arms on board, I borrowed a carbine and led the company out into the interior of  the country to attack a body of Mexicans who were fortified at a bridge— they were routed before we got there but the march there of and back (about 12 miles) made me so sore and tired that I haven't been able to walk about much until <choice>
                  <orig>to-day</orig>
                  <reg>today</reg>
               </choice>. <choice>
                  <orig>To day</orig>
                  <reg>Today</reg>
               </choice> I have been trying to get my horse off the brig— but the surf rolls so high that it is still <choice>
                  <orig>impracticable</orig>
                  <reg>impracticle</reg>
               </choice>, and I expect he will be lost or so much abused as to be worthless. My health is good as usual, that is to say about as when I left home, and perhaps better as I am a little heavier—My men who came from <name type="place">Tampico</name> are all well—We have lost 12 horses— in crossing the gulf— I cannot tell yet whether we shall be discharged previous to the end of our term or not— I  shall know something more upon this subject in a few days and I will write to, you in a short time— and will write you a long letter, especially if I am not coming home immediately—<pb n="2" facs="mc020b.small.jpg"/> you will receive intelligence as early as you will receive this letter, of the fall of <name type="place">Vera Cruz</name> and the Castle <name type="place">San Juan De Ulloa—</name>  It is considered one of the greatest victories ever achieved to have taken the strongest place upon the continent with loss of only about a dozen men— Except three skirmishes, the battle has been fought entirely by our Artillery— producing great havoc, and devastation— The Commissioners on each side are adjusting the terms of capitulation whilst I write— And the Mexican flag still floats over the city &amp; castle— I suppose we shall march in <choice>
                  <orig>to — morrow</orig>
                  <reg>tomorrow</reg>
               </choice>— But you will see all the particulars published— I have not time to write news now. I write to relieve you from apprehension for my safety— for when I landed it was generally believed that I had been lost at sea—I write too as a token of my affection which requires a letter. My love to Eliza to "that boy" your Ma, Ann &amp; all the family—</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your affectionate husband</salute>
            </closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm R.</abbr>
                     <expan>William Richard</expan>
                  </choice> Caswell</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb n="3" facs="mc020c.small.jpg"/>
            <closer>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mrs. <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm R.</abbr>
                        <expan>William Richard</expan>
                     </choice> Caswell</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Russelville</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Jefferson County</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
