<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl110">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1838 August    1st, Clover Dale, [TN] [to] Ann  Jane Bell, Cornplanter, Penn[sylvania] / C[aroline] D.  Bell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Bell, Caroline D.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl110</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50499345</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1838 August    1st, Clover Dale, [TN] [to] Ann  Jane Bell, Cornplanter, Penn[sylvania] / C[aroline] D.  Bell </title>
               <author>Bell, Caroline D.</author>
               <date when="1838-08-01">August 1, 1838</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Caroline Bell in Cloverdale, TN,  to her sister Ann Jane Bell, in Cornplanter, PA, dated August 1, 1838. Caroline writes about the latest happenings in their Presbyterian church in Charlotte.  She says that she took her first communion, and she comments on the preaching styles of the ministers. She writes that the weather has been too dry for the farms and that there are no peaches. She also writes that their mother will be expecting Jane to visit in about two weeks.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl110</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Religious gatherings</term>
               <term>Religious awakening</term>
               <term>Crop losses</term>
               <term>Tennessee </term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Bell, Caroline D.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl110a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Clover Dale</name>
                     <date when="1838-08-01">August 1st 1838</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear sister</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> As you are aware of my aversion to letter writing, or to writing anything, I deem it unnecessary to make an apology for my long silence; had I been at home when I received your last letter I should have answered it  immediately, as I generally feel more like answering a letter when I <choice>
                  <orig>recieve</orig>
                  <reg>receive</reg>
               </choice> it than sometime afterwards; but I was in <name type="place">Charlotte</name>  attending Presbytery and went from there to <name type="place">Harpeth</name>with <name type="person">Major</name> and <name type="person">Mrs. Bell</name>.  I spent two weeks very agreeably with them and our cousin I mean <name type="person"> John I Bell's</name> family, for we claim kin. I think <name type="person">Mary</name> more <choice>
                  <orig>inteligent</orig>
                  <reg>intelligent</reg>
               </choice> than <name type="person">Elizabeth</name> or <name type="person">Jane</name> and <name type="person">Blunt</name> is very well named, at least he is not at all smart. if I may be  permitted to judge by the exterior. <name type="person">Mr. Bell</name> is very easy, kind, and agreeable, indeed they are all so and if  I had been their own cousin they could not have treated me more affectionately, <name type="person">Eveline</name>is very zealous in the cause of  religion, and very eloquent on the subject, but the change is not so great in her particularly as it regards her   temper as we would wish, but she excuses herself by saying God gave her her tongue  and temper as well as her religion, and  that she has never had any doubts or fears on the subject,  nor does she think a  christian should have any.  If this were true my religion is all a pretence, for I am often  assailed with strong doubts and fears; but I am disposed to think otherwise, if I know <pb n="2" facs="sl110b.small.jpg"/>  my own heart it is the predominant desire of it to love and serve the Lord, but amidst doubts and temptations  I can indulge a pleasing hope that I know in <choice>
                  <orig>whoom</orig>
                  <reg>whom</reg>
               </choice> I have trusted  and that he will not forsake me, nor will he  suffer me to be tempted above  what I can bear. The sacrament was administered during  Presbytery and for the first time I was permitted to partake of that holy ordinance, for sometime previous to it I felt myself <choice>
                  <orig>wholy</orig>
                  <reg>wholly</reg>
               </choice> unworthy to partake of it, but upon accidently picking up a number of the Prebyterian, which contained some answers to objections against receiving the communion, which in a great measure removed my fears, and I  trust enabled me to approach that holy table with deep humility and an humble reliance on the merits of my <choice>
                  <orig>Saviours</orig>
                  <reg>Savior's</reg>
               </choice> blood alone <add place="supralinear">for</add> pardon and acceptance, and for future guidance and direction, there were a great many communicants  particularly of young persons, there were no converts and but two added  to the church <name type="person">Robert Dunaway</name> a nephew  of   <name type="person">Mr. Livingston</name> and <name type="person">Margaret</name> she never  <del type="overstrike">her sentiments</del> made known her sentiments until the  day before the Presbytery, when she declared from the change in ⁁ <add place="supralinear">her</add> feelings and  disposition she felt it her duty to join the  Church we were all made very happy at hearing her determination being so sudden and unexpected it created a great excitement among her friends the Session met at <name type="person">Mr. Balthrop's</name> saturday evening when she gave her experience to the Church there were several persons present they  <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear>staid</unclear>
               </del> to were very much affected <name type="person">Benjamin Robertson</name> shed tears freely and observed   to some one that he liked ⁁ <add place="supralinear">her</add> a great deal better now. There were  four candidates for ordination <name type="person">John T Smith</name> delivered the charge <pb n="3" facs="sl110c.small.jpg"/> it was very <choice>
                  <orig>solem</orig>
                  <reg>solemn</reg>
               </choice> and impressive, beyond any thing I had ever witnessed before. <name type="person">Mr. Burnie</name> has improved in his preaching very much but I do not like his gestures I think them rather theatrical. We had a two days meeting at    <name type="place">New Hope</name> the middle of last month, there was a Temperance address delivered on saturday that society has lately had an <choice>
                  <orig>adition</orig>
                  <reg>addition</reg>
               </choice> of 18 or 20 members among <choice>
                  <orig>whoom</orig>
                  <reg>whom</reg>
               </choice> are two of the  <name type="person">Mr. Neerly's</name> who 6 months since were interested in a grocery in <name type="place">Charlotte</name>. The Presbytery wish the Church to consider it a duty incumbent on <add place="supralinear">them</add>  there to become members of that society, indeed in that I think they are perfectly right. <name type="person">D. Hardwick</name>, wife &amp; sister have ar<add place="supralinear">r</add>ived in <name type="place">Charlotte</name>,  <name type="person">Mrs.<choice>
                     <abbr>H</abbr>
                     <expan>Hardwick</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> is small, &amp; pretty but not near as intelligent looking as <name type="person">Eliza</name>, she resembles the family very much. I saw a daughter of  <name type="person">Tom Napiers</name>
               <unclear>mow</unclear>
               <name type="person">Mrs. Carpenter</name>  at the Presbytery she is pretty, intelligent, and agreeable, and by far superior to any of the name  I have ever seen. The weather has been  extremely warm and dry for some weeks past. If it does not rain shortly the farmers will not make the third of a crop in this neighbor<add place="supralinear">hood</add>  but we have a plenty of old corn and as much wheat as we can make use of. This <choice>
                  <orig>neighbourhood</orig>
                  <reg>neighborhood</reg>
               </choice> has been very healthy since the scarlet fever left it. <name type="person">Sally</name> has been complaining for two weeks partly  with the tooth <choice>
                  <orig>acke</orig>
                  <reg>ache</reg>
               </choice> and bowel complaint, she took a dose of  tartar &amp; salts it made her very sick, but she is better this evening. I hope <name type="person">Miss Gormly</name> has regained her health. Mother <choice>
                  <orig>sympathises</orig>
                  <reg>sympathizes</reg>
               </choice> very much with <name type="person">Theodore</name> in his illness she feels very much interested in your youngest <unclear>pet</unclear>. If  peaches is the object of your contemplated visit to <name type="place">Dickson</name> you had better stay at home there is not one on the place, nor are there as many in the neighborhood as will be sufficient for making preserves. I hope the failure of peaches <pb n="4" facs="sl110d.small.jpg"/> here will not prevent your visiting us this fall Mother says she will look for you after the middle of this month, <name type="person">Mrs. Mills</name> ⁁ <add place="supraliner">will</add> cheerfully give you her share of peaches for a sight of you. <name type="person">Mrs. Collier</name> says there is no person excepting her relations she  had rather see than you. I resolved in my own mind before the <unclear>steelpens</unclear>
               <add place="rotated 90 degrees ccw in center of page">
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Charlotte</name>
                        <name type="place">
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                              <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <date when="1838-08-05">August 5th 1838</date>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>} 25<address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="person">Mrs. Ann Jane Bell.</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Cornplanter</name>.</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Venango County</name>.</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Penn</abbr>
                              <expan>Pennsylvania</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>  came that I would endeavor if possible to write a very pretty neat body hand, but I am very sorry to say  they are so indifferent that I have ceased to <unclear>witle</unclear> with them and we have not a pen on the place but a quantity of feathers. We all join in best love to you, Brother, children and Miss Gormly</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>very sincerely and <choice>
                     <orig>afftionately</orig>
                     <reg>affectionately</reg>
                  </choice> yours</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>C.</abbr>
                        <expan>Caroline</expan>
                     </choice> D. Bell</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
