<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc188">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1842 Jul. 15, Nashville, Tennessee [to] D.G. Broom, Natchez, Mississippi  / F.H. Knapp : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Knapp, F.H.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc188</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1842 Jul. 15, Nashville, Tennessee [to] D.G. Broom, Natchez, Mississippi  / F.H. Knapp</title>
               <author>  Knapp, F.H.</author>
               <date when="1842-07-15">July 15, 1842</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter from the year 1842.  It is from F.H. Knapp to D.G. Broom, a dental surgeon in Natchez, Mississippi.  The purpose of Knapp's  letter is to update his friend on his numerous travels and adventures.  In the letter, Knapp tells Broom that he has had a very agreeable trip, and has spent time with some of the greatest men of the age, including Andrew Jackson.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Knapp Letter</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-1873</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc188 </note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Knapp, F. H.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc188a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Nashville <choice>
                        <abbr>Tenn.</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>July 15-42</date>
               <salute>My Dear Friend</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Agreeable to promise I with you, and apologize for being silent so long.</p>
            <p>I made a stay at <name>memphis</name> of about two weeks and found things rather dull there, and then proceeded to his place.  Here also I find the hard times are felt even more than in <name>Mississippi</name>.__ </p>
            <p>I have here received some patronage, but do not think I shall have enough to keep me busy more the three or four weeks longer, when I shall likely either to go <choice>
                  <abbr>Balto</abbr>
                  <expan>Baltimore</expan>
               </choice> or to the <name>Warren Springs</name> or <name>North Carolina</name>, but as yet I am undecided.__ Since I have been here I have spent my time very agreeably.  I have seen all the wonders of this section and among them the greatest men of the age.  the Hero of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N</abbr>
                     <expan>New</expan>
                  </choice>. Orleans</name> I spent the day with <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice>. Jackson (by invitation) and found him in an enfubled &amp; debilitated state, yet as Easy and affable as ever.  I should have been pleased to have had the pleasure of your company in this visit.  When I arrived here <choice>
                  <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                  <expan>Doctor</expan>
               </choice>
               <name>J.H. Badger</name> was here__ he has since left &amp; will return in <choice>
                  <abbr>augt</abbr>
                  <expan>August</expan>
               </choice>
               <unclear>He plugs a tooth well</unclear>__ Two Dentists reside here named Gunn &amp; Backut__ both ala Dubbs <pb n="2" facs="sc188b.small.jpg"/> ala <name>Dickinson Hill</name> &amp; <choice>
                  <abbr>Co</abbr>
                  <expan>Company</expan>
               </choice>__ of course you may know their standing by this <choice>
                  <orig>comparrison</orig>
                  <reg>comparison</reg>
               </choice>.</p>
            <p>On the whole it is rather a <unclear>picaune</unclear> place at least much more so than <name>Natchez</name>, although the town is twice or more than twice as large and much better built &amp; improved.  It is beautifully situated on a solid rock on the banks of the <name>Cumberland</name>.  I will send you a paper soon with a view of the <name>Hermitage</name> over the head of the Editorial Columns__</p>
            <p>Please request <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Daimphon to send my weekly paper here.</p>
            <p>Write me all how business goes &amp; havethe illustrious Mountain (not hill) comes on, also the man who dubbs himself Doctor, and this dickens, &amp; the ninth part of a man (you know it takes nine tailors to make a man), so write me have they all move ahead &amp; <choice>
                  <abbr>e&amp;.</abbr>
                  <expan>etcetera</expan>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <p>I hope you maintain <choice>
                  <abbr>yr</abbr>
                  <expan>your</expan>
               </choice> position as cock of the walk, and that the small fry do not discover any large fish.</p>
            <p>Write me soon as I may leave before your letter arrives unless you do.  Is it hot with you?  It is cool &amp; pleasant here.  Myself &amp; family are in usual health.  Remember me to my friends and believe me Sir</p>
            <closer>Yours Very Sincerely <signed>
                  <name> H Knapp</name>
               </signed>
               <add>DG Broom <choice>
                     <abbr>M.D</abbr>
                     <expan>Medical Doctor</expan>
                  </choice>.</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
