<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc119">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1838 Jan. 2, Decatur, Alabama [to] James F. Smith, Newark, New Jersey / J.J.G. Smith  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Smith, J.J.G.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc119</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1838 Jan. 2, Decatur, Alabama [to] James F. Smith, Newark, New Jersey / J.J.G. Smith  </title>
               <author> Smith, J.J.G.</author>
               <date when="1838-01-02"> 
			 January 2, 1838</date>
               <extent> 4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated January 2, 1838, from J.J.G. Smith to his brother James Smith regarding a trip he plans to take up North. Smith also mentions that he hopes to see his brother and family while he is up North. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">J. J.G. Smith Document</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc119 </note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Alabama</term>
               <term>New Jersey</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Smith, J.J.G.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc119a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Decatur </name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Al Jany</abbr>
                        <expan>Alabama January</expan>
                     </choice> 2 1838</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Before answering your letter of the 11th November I must <choice>
                  <orig>appologise</orig>
                  <reg>apologize</reg>
               </choice> for my answer not being made at an earlier date than this </p>
            <p>In the first place it did not get to Knoxville until after I had left and in the 2d place It was brought down from Knoxville and handed to me on the 12th of December and a few minutes before the boat left for <name>Ross Landing</name> from which place I did not return until the 20th <choice>
                  <abbr>ult</abbr>
                  <expan>ultimo</expan>
               </choice> &amp; the same evening I got here I left again for <name>Tuscumbia</name> &amp; <name>Waterloo</name> Al_ and did not return until this morning</p>
            <p>I now embrace a few <choice>
                  <orig>leasure</orig>
                  <reg>leisure</reg>
               </choice> moments to write to you_</p>
            <p>It afforded me a great deal of pleasure to learn that you were all well I was also much pleased with the name you gave your little boy I would like <choice>
                  <orig>verry</orig>
                  <reg>very</reg>
               </choice> much to see Ellen &amp; the children &amp; yourself I expect <choice>
                  <orig>ther</orig>
                  <reg>there</reg>
               </choice> is a <choice>
                  <orig>grat</orig>
                  <reg>great</reg>
               </choice> change in the <choice>
                  <orig>apperance</orig>
                  <reg>appearance</reg>
               </choice> of you all. With myself the change is <choice>
                  <orig>verry</orig>
                  <reg>very</reg>
               </choice> perceptible I am at least 30 pounds heavier than when I say you and feel better in health than I ever did before I have <choice>
                  <orig>entirly</orig>
                  <reg>entirely</reg>
               </choice> recovered from the affect of my sickness and I hope that next Spring or Summer I may have the pleasure of seeing all of you There is a probability of my going to the North early in the Spring. If I do go it will be <pb n="2" facs="sc119b.small.jpg"/> soon and by way of <name>St Louis</name>. I would have gone to <name>St. Louis</name> next week but I learned that the <name>Mississippi River</name> was Frozen up so that Boats could not go so high as St. Louis   The business that will take me to <choice>
                  <abbr>St L</abbr>
                  <expan>St. Louis</expan>
               </choice>- is to deliver to the <choice>
                  <abbr>US Qr</abbr>
                  <expan>United States Quarter</expan>
               </choice> Master US Army One hundred and Fifty tons of Commissary &amp; Ordinance Stores for which I made a contract <del type="overstrike">frth</del>
               <add>with</add> the Qr Master at Cherokee agency in the name of <unclear>NB French &amp; Co</unclear> at the same time I made a contract <add>for them</add> with the Qr Master to transport the 4th Regiment of Us Infantry from the <name>Cherokee agency</name> to <name>Tuscumbia <choice>
                     <abbr>Ala</abbr>
                     <expan>Alabama</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>. They will clear on the 2 contracts about six Thousand dollars. Both these contracts I could have made in my own name but I was just by NBF &amp;Co to make it for them and was in honour bound to do so</p>
            <p>You ask me how, and in what business I am now engaged. In one of my former communications to you I asked your advice as to whether it would be best to still continue on the Holston or to take a situation at a lower <choice>
                  <orig>salery</orig>
                  <reg>salary</reg>
               </choice> in the owners House in Knoxville You have not said anything in your letters on the subject a short time since I spoke to them on the Subject they <choice>
                  <orig> offerd</orig>
                  <reg>offered</reg>
               </choice> me the command of the <name>Holston</name> or a situation in their house in Knoxville the former I declined and the latter I excepted But promised to take command of the boat for <unclear>Mrs arthur</unclear>
               <pb n="3" facs="sc119c.small.jpg"/> until she gets family underway. I will leave her and go to <name>Knoxville</name> in a few days to which place you in future will please direct your letters to me I received a letter from Rebecca Jane a few days since She says but little She speaks of Fathers death and of the good attention that was paid him during his illness She also says that his<name> Johnstown</name> business was all settled But that his <name>Pittsburgh</name> debts were not paid. She says she has about 275$ of money She says that <unclear>albru</unclear> &amp; childs have not been paid for their debts I <gap agent="damage"/> responsible and I intend to pay them they <gap agent="damage"/> like Gentlemen with him &amp; I will <choice>
                  <orig>endevour</orig>
                  <reg>endeavor</reg>
               </choice> to follow their example I would go to the North this <unclear>minute</unclear> but I do not want to go until I have money enough to pay their claims</p>
            <p>I am very much pleased with both the country and the people and I am doing business for the best house in Knoxville</p>
            <p>How do you get along. You never <del type="overstrike">speak</del>
               <add>write</add> of your business to me are you doing well</p>
            <p>Rebecca is in a good place and Samuel I think is well provided for. give my Love to Ellen Eliza and a kiss to Mary Jane &amp; Samuel Crawford and for yourself Except my warmest wishes for your welfare</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Affectionatly</orig>
                     <reg>Affectionately</reg>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>J J G Smith</signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sc119d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>the news paper you sent me are all to hand</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Mr James F. Smith</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <orig>cival</orig>
                        <reg>civil</reg>
                     </choice> engineer</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Newark <choice>
                           <abbr>N</abbr>
                           <expan>New</expan>
                        </choice> Jersey</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jany</abbr>
                     <expan>January</expan>
                  </choice> 1838 J. J. G. Smith Letter</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
