<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0249">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>  [Letter] 1834 Apr. 9, [to] the Cherokee Delegation / members of the Cherokee Nation : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0249</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 45959465</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>  [Letter] 1834 Apr. 9, [to] the Cherokee Delegation / members of the Cherokee Nation</title>
               <date when="1834-04-09">April 9, 1834</date>
               <extent> 2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated April 9th 1834 to the Cherokee Delegation from several members of the Cherokee Nation regarding people who are not of Cherokee descent occupying and claiming land within the Cherokee Nation.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033, b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">139</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> pa0249</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Land tenure</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0249a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>To the Members of the Cherokee Delegation}<salute>Gentlemen</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We beg very earnestly to solicit your attention <add>to</add> and interference in the following cases. It it appears that in addition to the injustice practiced on many of our <del type="overstrike">cit</del> people by suffering <add>emigrants, who are</add> citizens of the country to have places assessed to them which belong <del type="overstrike">to their persons</del> not to them, a number of persons <del type="overstrike">negroes</del> whites, spaniards, negroes, &amp; mulattoes are permitted to alienate our land by having places assessed to them as emigrant <name>Cherokees</name> . Of this <choice>
                  <orig>discription</orig>
                  <reg>description</reg>
               </choice> is <name>Hosea Morgan</name>  with a negro wife and six children of the same cast having no right nor title nor pretence of a title in the Nation. And yet he has enrolled with his family and has a field belonging to <name>Mr. John Smith</name> of <name>Peach Creek </name> in this <choice>
                  <abbr>Dist</abbr>
                  <expan>District</expan>
               </choice>. assessed to him. <name>Woody Russel</name> is another case. He is a white man his wife a colonial woman apparently Bright <choice>
                  <abbr>Multto</abbr>
                  <expan>Mulatto</expan>
               </choice>. they have no claim nor pretence of rights in the Nation. This Russel has had assessed to him the field of the Old Sailors widow and has produced a bill of sale for it which was witnessed by <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm </abbr>
                     <expan>William</expan>
                  </choice>Griffin</name> an emigrant. He has sold the good will of it and a white man named Joel McCrary <del type="overstrike">has</del>
               <add>who</add> has taken possession of the field and threatens to turn the old woman out of the house. The old lady denys having made any sale of the property, and the genuineness of the Bill of sale is rendered very doubtful from the circumstance that neither <del type="overstrike">of the </del> Russel nor Griffin can speak Cherokee and the old widow cannot speak English, so that it was impossible for them to make a bargain of that kind without an interpreter.</p>
            <p>Now we beg leave through you most earnestly to remonstrate against the practice of enrolling aliens to us <pb n="2" facs="pa0249b.small.jpg"/> and allowing them to sell our property and violate our rights in  <del type="overstrike">repo</del> opposition to the protection stipulated to be extended to us in our Treaties with the United States.</p>
            <closer>Signed this day of April 1834 <signed>
                  <name>George Blain</name>
                  <add>his x mark</add>
                  <name>Sitnagi</name>
                  <add>his x mark</add>
                  <name>Sweetwater</name>
                  <add>his x mark</add>
                  <name>Peter</name>
                  <add>his x mark</add>
               </signed>
               <add>No. 1</add>
               <name>Old Soldiers widow</name>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
