<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl565">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1815 Feb. 21, Alabama Bluff [to] James Winchester, Mobile, Alabama / George Fisher   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Fisher, George</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl565</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1815 Feb. 21, Alabama Bluff [to] James Winchester, Mobile, Alabama / George Fisher</title>
               <author>Fisher, George</author>
               <date when="1815-02-21">February 21, 1815</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Colonel George Fisher to Brigadier General James Winchester, dated February 21, 1815. Fisher is reporting about attacks from the Native Americans that are allied with England. He asks that some men in the army from this settlement be allowed to return in order to protect their home from these attacks.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">James Winchester Papers </note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl565</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Alabama</term>
               <term>War of 1812</term>
               <term>Indians of North America</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Fisher, George</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl565a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Alabama Bluff</name>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Feby</abbr>
                           <expan>February</expan>
                        </choice> 21st 1815</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                           <expan>General</expan>
                        </choice> Winchester</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The alarming appearance of a party of hostile Indians on our frontiers, and the weak &amp; unprotected State, not only of the adjoining County, East of <name>Tombigbee</name>, but especially of the settlements on this River, induces me to State to your <choice>
                  <orig>excelency</orig>
                  <reg>excellency</reg>
               </choice> and suggest  the propriety of making some adequate provision  to secure the Citizens against their attacks___ I beg you to be assured that while I am perfectly satisfied of your attention to every part of the District over which you command I State this circumstance only on  the recollection that you have more important Sections of the country to protect, but at the same time Knowing it to be perfectly agreeable to your feelings to extend that protection as far as <choice>
                  <orig>possable</orig>
                  <reg>possible</reg>
               </choice>, and equally desirable to know where it may be wanting ____ permit me to suggest <choice>
                  <orig>father</orig>
                  <reg>farther</reg>
               </choice>, that your permission of the return of the Citizens drafted from this Settlement would give the country, perhaps the most efficient force that could be provided, as they have every thing to protect, and father add the pleasing consideration, that they can be providing bread for which the country will inevitably suffer ere long___ You will no doubt here learn that the Indians have <pb n="2" facs="sl565b.small.jpg"/> plundered &amp; fired on the Citizens, and evinced every determination again to second their British Allies.____ I take the liberty to Suggest heads of families, persons <choice>
                  <orig>extreamly</orig>
                  <reg>extremely</reg>
               </choice> necessary to their Settlements residing on the frontiers, whose return would be peculiarly desirable_ <name>Geo Morgan</name>__ <name>William Hays</name>__ <name>Richd Odem</name>_ and <name>Caleb Monterief</name>__   <name>David Simmons</name>, <name>Rubin Pearson</name>
               <name>James Ford</name>
               <name>Stephens Williams</name> Should the above Citizens be returned we Shall be, we hope, perfectly Safe__</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I beg you to be assured of the high Sentiments of esteem with which I am most respectfully <lb/> Your Excelencys <choice>
                     <abbr>Mst Obt Servt</abbr>
                     <expan>Most Obedient Servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>George Fisher</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>His Excelency</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Genl Winchester</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P.S.</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> Should you think proper to release the above mentioned men, &amp; let them be commanded by some person whom you may think adequate to the task_ They would no doubt be of great Service in assisting to destroy the Indians now lurking in the settlements. even should you <unclear>think</unclear> proper to order them back____</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl565c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Fishers <choice>
                        <abbr>PO</abbr>
                        <expan>Post Office</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name>Alabama</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>Feby 22d</date>}</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Free <choice>
                     <abbr>Geo</abbr>
                     <expan>George</expan>
                  </choice> Fisher <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P.</abbr>
                     <expan>Post</expan>
                  </choice> Master</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Brig</abbr>
                        <expan>Brigadier</expan>
                     </choice> Genl Winchester</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Mobile</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>mail }</add>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Geo Fisher PM <lb/> 21st <choice>
                     <abbr>Feb</abbr>
                     <expan>February</expan>
                  </choice> 1815 <lb/> answered</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
