<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl369">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1833 Nov. 24, Hendersonville, Ten[nessee] [to] Andrew J. Donelson, Washington City D.C. / Dan[ie]l S. Donelson  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Donelson, Daniel S.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl369</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1833 Nov. 24, Hendersonville, Ten[nessee] [to] Andrew J. Donelson, Washington City D.C. / Dan[ie]l S. Donelson</title>
               <author>Donelson, Daniel S.</author>
               <date when="1833-11-24">November 24, 1833</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated November 24, 1833, to Andrew Jackson Donelson, nephew and personal secretary of President Andrew Jackson, from his brother Daniel S. Jackson in Hendersonville, Tennessee.  Daniel writes mainly about personal financial matters, and explains that he has sold his farm and is in search of another one either in Florida or Mississippi.  He also beseeches Andrew to welcome and assist a Cumberland Presbyterian minister who will be seeking the position of Chaplain to Congress.  </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bettie M. Donelson Papers </note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">III-E-2-3 b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl369</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Donelson, Andrew Jackson 1799-1871</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Financial, Personal</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Donelson, Daniel S.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl369a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Nov</abbr>
                           <expan>November</expan>
                        </choice> 24th 1833</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear Andrew</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have received a letter from you since you were with us, that written soon after you reached <name>Washington</name>  making a request of me that I should visit your place, this I certainly intended to do and give you an answer; but a few d<add>a</add>ys after you set out my Overseer left me, and I have been so closely confined at home <add>since</add> that I have been unable to leave it, <unclear>exerting every <choice>
                     <abbr>thurs</abbr>
                     <expan>thursday</expan>
                  </choice>
               </unclear> to the utmost to set out my cotton and send the Negroes I had in my possession to <name>Florida</name>- this I <unclear>effected</unclear> a week ago, and they are now upon the way- we expect in a few days to go (margaret and myself) on the other side of the river, when I will take a survey of your premises, and give you the result.</p>
            <p>I have lately made an important move which will probably be disapproved of by <pb n="2" facs="sl369b.small.jpg"/> you- I have sold my farm to <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Tho.</abbr>
                     <expan>Thomas</expan>
                  </choice> S Watson</name> for $15 per Acre ½ half to be paid on the <date>25th <choice>
                     <abbr>Decr.</abbr>
                     <expan>December</expan>
                  </choice> 1834</date> when I give it up the remainder  in annual <choice>
                  <orig>instalments</orig>
                  <reg>installments</reg>
               </choice>- I have a <unclear>lean</unclear>
               <add>on the land</add> until all the payments are made; as soon as the land is surveyed the <del type="overstrike">sale</del> trade will be closed by my  obligation for the deed.  The next year I expect to <choice>
                  <orig>looke</orig>
                  <reg>look</reg>
               </choice> out for a country where I can make money by planting, if Florida should prove healthy I will probably go there, if not I shall expect to live in <name>Mississippi</name>  9 months in the year the remaining <add>3</add> in same healthy clime.  I might live where I am for years without a few working hands <del type="overstrike">persons</del>and  maintain my own with difficulty; this I have tried long enough and am now determined to <choice>
                  <orig>seeke</orig>
                  <reg>seek</reg>
               </choice> my fortune elsewhere; I regret it but my necessities compel me to this course, which you must approve after <pb n="3" facs="sl369c.small.jpg"/>  reflection.</p>
            <p>I saw Stockly a few days since all are well on the other side of the river- on this side they are equally so.</p>
            <p>margaret joins me in love to you Sister Emily and the children</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am sincerely your Brother</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Danl.</abbr>
                        <expan>Daniel</expan>
                     </choice> S. Donelson</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <gap/> had forgotten to say to you that <name>Mr. Capp</name> a very intelligent and eloquent Cumberland Presbyterian minister of <name>Nashville</name> has gone to Washington for the purpose of being a candidate for Chaplain to Congress and that it is the request of our brother Margaret, <unclear>Harvey</unclear> and our relations generally that you should interest yourself in his behalf- he is modest and unassuming, a gentleman of fine education  be pleased  therefore to do what you can in order to his success</add>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>DSD</abbr>
                     <expan>Daniel S. Donelson</expan>
                  </choice>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl369d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Hendersonville <choice>
                              <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                              <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </name> 25</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <date>Nov. 26th 1833</date>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
               <add>D.S. Donelson</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Andrew J. Donelson</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Washington City</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <abbr>D C</abbr>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
