<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um090">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1843 May, Columbia, Tenn[essee] [to]    Col[onel] R[obert] J. Chester, Jackson, Tenn[essee] / M[ary Jane] Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um090</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50323655</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1843 May, Columbia, Tenn[essee] [to]    Col[onel] R[obert] J. Chester, Jackson, Tenn[essee] / M[ary Jane] Chester</title>
               <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
               <date when="1843-05">May  1843</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter from Mary Jane Chester to her father Colonel Robert J. Chester, postmarked on either May 19 or 29, 1843. Mary writes to her father from her school in Columbia, TN, and she explains that her examination is soon approaching and that she is excited about the prospects of returning home afterwards.  She also describes an encounter she had with an old friend of her father's by the name of Mr. Trotter.  Enclosed is a letter addressed to her sister, in which she discusses the death of a man by the name of  W. Patton and expresses her anticipation at her sister's expected arrival in Columbia.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers MS-25 (Jan.-June 1843)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um090</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Mary Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um090a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn.</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1843-05">
                        <date when="1843-05">May  <gap agent="damage"/> 1843</date>
                     </date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Father,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I received your kind letter to day, with great delight.  Being Friday evening I think it perhaps the best opportunity that I shall have for answering it, for as I have before informed you I am <emph>extremely busy</emph>, and am compelled from this circumstance to  leave unwritten many letters to my relations, which I feel disposed to write.  Do not infer from this, that I have not time to read them, I assure you I can always find a leisure moment. I am afraid from my oft-repeated complaints about time, you are of this opinion, &amp; therefore I have the misfortune of receiving so very few letters from you.</p>
            <p>The Examination will commence on the last Wednesday in June.  will continue until Friday night, I believe it is generally dreaded by the girls, for <name type="person">Mr. Smith</name> tells us it will be more thorough than any he has ever yet had.  I expect there will be a great many persons here, for you are aware, that is the time that the girls return home.  Indeed I can scarcely contain myself when I think of returning <pb n="2" facs="um090b.small.jpg"/> and of seeing you and my dear Sister in Columbia.  I am really <emph>very</emph> impatient for that time to arrive.  You wish to know if I have <emph>grown</emph> any, I have the happiness of telling you, that I have not grown the <emph>least particle</emph>, to give you my own opinion, I think, I have rather decreased in size, though Cousin <name type="person">Ellen</name> will not agree to it. I was very much pleased that you have purchased me so handsome a dress. If it is equally as convenient I should rather that you would send it with my riding dress <emph>unmade</emph>. Cousin <choice>
                  <abbr>E.</abbr>
                  <expan>Ellen</expan>
               </choice> thinks the <emph>fashions</emph> are newer <emph>here</emph>. You might send them in a box by mail.  We have a very good <unclear>Mantanmaker</unclear> here, But you of course know best, in which manner to act.</p>
            <p>I was delighted to see, yesterday, a very old friend of yours he informs me that he lived several years in the same town with you, &amp; that he corresponded with you longer, after you left school— I believe he said— than any other of his friends.  <name type="person">Mr. Trotter</name>, he inquired very particularly about you, and when I told ⁁ <add place="supralinear">him</add> that you would be in Columbia at the Examination, said he would also try to make it convenient to do the same He brought his daughter up to school with, who boards at <name type="person">Mrs Wormelys</name>. I am very much pleased with her.</p>
            <p>As you wish me to take your advice and study hard you certainly excuse my short letter.  Do write me often and tell me about the dear children.  Kiss them all for me. Give my love to my relations.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>affectionately,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <emph>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>M.</abbr>
                           <expan>Mary Jane</expan>
                        </choice> Chester</name>
                  </emph>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="um090c.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>My dear Sister,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I cannot send this letter to Father, with a whole blank side, So, although you write to me so <emph>very</emph> seldom, I shall return "good for evil," and address you a few lines, remember, you will now be in debt to me for two letters, which I am very anxious to receive.</p>
            <p>I was much distressed to hear from Papa's letter of the death of <name type="person">W. Patton</name>, Poor Cousin <name type="person">Jane</name>, she has certainly been very unfortunate, this should be a warning to all boys. I shall hereafter feel more uneasy about my dear Brothers.  Oh! Sister, in four weeks from this time, How <emph>very</emph> happy do I expect to be.  I wish you to write me the day that  you expect to arrive, and whether you intend <choice>
                  <orig>comming</orig>
                  <reg>coming</reg>
               </choice> in the <choice>
                  <orig>Carrige</orig>
                  <reg>Carriage</reg>
               </choice> or Stage. I should be delighted if <name type="person">Aunt Narcissa</name> would accompany you, I think the trip would be more pleasant to her than the last — I had the pleasure of seeing <name type="person">Mrs. L. Polk</name> the other day she apologized for not <choice>
                  <orig>comming</orig>
                  <reg>coming</reg>
               </choice> to see me before, her health has been very bad.  She told me to tell <name type="person">Aunt Frances</name>  for her, that nothing would afford her more pleasure, than to see her, &amp; that she wishes very much that she would pay her a visit—  I like her, for she appears so very friendly.  I wonder if <name type="person">Aunt <choice>
                     <abbr>P.</abbr>
                     <expan>Patsy</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> intends permitting me to return home without writing me, <emph>even one</emph> letter. I am really distressed.  My Composition for the Examination, I must being to think about it.  A very excellent one is expected from me.  I intend asking <name type="person">Mr. Patterson</name>, our Episcopal Minister to give me a subject.  Oh! how sincerely I wish it was over</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Yours truly</salute>
               <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>signature (Mary)</unclear>
               <pb n="4" facs="um090d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="left of address">postmark on May <unclear>29</unclear> 18</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Col. R.</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel Robert</expan>
                        </choice> J. Chester</name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson</name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn.</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address" rend="different hand, ink">My Dear Mary Jane <lb/>
                  <date when="1843-05-09">9 May 1843</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
