<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0243">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Claim] 1820 July 27, State of Tennessee, to the Sheriff of Rhea County  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0243</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 45959449</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Claim] 1820 July 27, State of Tennessee, to the Sheriff of Rhea County  </title>
               <date when="1820-07-27">July 27, 1820</date>
               <extent> 4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document, dated July 27, 1820, is a legal claim concerning a legal suit brought against Joseph Tompson by William Cochrine. Tompson was sued by Cochrine over money he owed to Cochrine in the amount of 250.00.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033, b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">131</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> pa0243</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Claims</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0243a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>State of <name>Tennessee</name> To the sheriff of <name>Rhea County</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>Greetings. We command you to take <name>William Cochrine</name> if to be found in your county and him <choice>
                  <orig>safly</orig>
                  <reg>safely</reg>
               </choice> keep so as to hear him at the next court of pleas and quarter sessions to be held for the county of <name>Rhea</name>
               <del type="overstrike">and</del> in the town of <name>Washington</name> at the courthouse on the first Monday of August next to answer <name>Joseph Tompson</name> of a plea of <choice>
                  <orig>Trespas</orig>
                  <reg>Trespass</reg>
               </choice> on the case to his damages five hundred Dollars and have you then there this Writ ――― Witness <name>Daniel Rollings</name>
            </p>
            <p>Clerk of said county court at office in <name>Washington</name> the first monday of may 1820 <unclear> &amp;</unclear> 44 year of our Independence ― <name>D. Rollings</name>, Clerk</p>
            <p>―――――</p>
            <p>Know all men by this presents that we Joseph Tompson and <name>James Prentice</name> are Bound to <name>William Cochrine</name> in the sum of $250. to be paid of the said Joseph Tompson shall with effect prosecute a suit by him <del type="overstrike"/> this day commenced against the said William Cochrine or in case of <choice>
                  <orig>falure</orig>
                  <reg>failure</reg>
               </choice> pay all costs of this suit Witness our hands and seals the 27th of July 1820. Joseph Thompson <figure>
                  <figDesc>hand drawn seal</figDesc>
               </figure> James Prentice <figure>
                  <figDesc>hand drawn seal</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>on the back of the above <add>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>casses</orig>
                     <reg>cases</reg>
                  </choice> &amp; bond</add> The Endorsement, <del type="overstrike">follows</del> was as follows</p>
            <p>Case &amp; respondent Joseph Thompson vs William Cochrine <unclear>signed</unclear> 27 July 1820 Came to hand the same day signed <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                     <expan>William</expan>
                  </choice> Francis</name> Sheriff not to be found in my county Wm Francis</p>
            <p>}The above <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear/>
               </del>casses and bond is the first that appears and should therefore <choice>
                  <abbr>preced</abbr>
                  <expan>preceed</expan>
               </choice> the casses on the foregoing page <name>R. Frague</name> C Clerk{<lb/>
               <name>Jarnagan</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>atty</abbr>
                  <expan>attorney</expan>
               </choice>
               <pb n="2" facs="pa0243b.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>State of Tennessee</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Rhea County</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>}</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>February session 1821</date> Joseph Tompson by his <choice>
                  <orig>atorney</orig>
                  <reg>attorney</reg>
               </choice>
               <del type="overstrike"> comp</del> complains of <name>William Cocrine</name> in the custody of the sheriff of a plea of trespass on the case for that where as the said Joseph Tompson now is a good true honest great and faithful <choice>
                  <orig>citesin</orig>
                  <reg>citizen</reg>
               </choice> and as such hath <unclear> allways likeined</unclear> and <del type="overstrike"> shall continue to behave</del> conducted himself and <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> the <choice>
                  <orig>commiting</orig>
                  <reg>committing</reg>
               </choice> of the <del type="overstrike"> said</del> grievances by the said William Cocrine as hereinafter mentioned was always respected <unclear> esteemed and acredited</unclear> by and among <del type="overstrike"> his</del> all his neighbours and other good and worth citizens to whom he was in any way known to be a person of good name <unclear>fame and credit</unclear> at to wit in the county <choice>
                  <orig>afforesaid</orig>
                  <reg>aforesaid</reg>
               </choice> and whereas also the said Joseph Thompson hath not ever been guilty as <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> the time of the commiting of the of the said several grievances by the said William Cochrine as hereinafter mentioned been suspected to have been guilty of <choice>
                  <orig>larciny</orig>
                  <reg>larceny</reg>
               </choice> or any other such crimes by means of which said <unclear>premises</unclear> he the said Joseph Tompson before the commiting of the said <choice>
                  <orig>grevances</orig>
                  <reg>grievances</reg>
               </choice> by the William Cochrine as hereinafter mentioned had <choice>
                  <orig>universaly</orig>
                  <reg>universally</reg>
               </choice> obtained the good opinion and credit of all his neighbours and other good and worthy citizens to whom he was in any way known at to wit in the county aforesaid Yet the said William well knowing the <unclear>premises</unclear> but greatly injuring the happy state and condition of the said Joseph and contriving and wickedly <add>and <unclear>maliciously</unclear>
               </add> intending to injure the said Joseph in his said good name fame and credit and to bring him into public scandal infamy and disgrace with and among all his neighbours and other good and worthy citizens and to cause it to be suspected and believed by more neighbours and citizens that he the said Joseph had been <del type="overstrike">guilty</del> and was guilty of larceny <pb n="3" facs="pa0243c.small.jpg"/> and to subject him to the pains and penalties by the laws of the land made and provided against and inflicted upon persons guilty thereof and to harrass oppress impoverish and wholly ruin him the said Joseph heretofore to wit on this day and year last afforesaid at to wit in the county afforesaid lately wickedly maliciously in a certain conversation then and there held by and between him the said William and a certain--- and in the presence and hereing of diverse other good and worthy citizens did speak and publish of and concerning the said Joseph these <choice>
                  <orig>falce</orig>
                  <reg>false</reg>
               </choice> and slanderous words following that is to say" he (meaning the said Joseph) has <unclear>stolen</unclear> corn and I can prove it" By means of the <unclear>commity</unclear> of the said greavances by the said William as afforesaid he the said Joseph hath been and is greatly injured in his said good name fame and credit and brought into public scandal infamy and disgrace with and among all his neighbours and other good and worthy citizens insomuch that <choice>
                  <orig>divers</orig>
                  <reg>diverse</reg>
               </choice> of those neighbours <add>and</add> citizens to whom the <choice>
                  <orig>inocence</orig>
                  <reg>innocence</reg>
               </choice> and integrity of the said Joseph in the <unclear>premises</unclear> were unknown have on ocassion of the committing of the said <choice>
                  <orig>greviances</orig>
                  <reg>grievances</reg>
               </choice> by the said William as aforesaid from thence hitherto suspected and believed and still do suspect and believe the said Joseph to have been and to be a person guilty of larceny and have by reason of the commiting of the said greivances by the said William as aforesaid from these hitherto wholly refused and still do refuse to have any <del type="overstrike">thing to do with </del> transactions acquaintance or discourse with him the said Joseph as they were before used and sustained to have and otherwise would whereof the said Joseph saith that he is injured and hath sustained damages five hundred dollars and therefore <unclear>the suit &amp;c</unclear>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>S </abbr>
                        <expan>Spencer</expan>
                     </choice> Jarnagan</name>
               </signed>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>atto</abbr>
                  <expan>attorney</expan>
               </choice>. for plaintiff</closer>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1">
            <p>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Joseph Thompson</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>vs</abbr>
                        <expan>versus</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>William Cochrine</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>{<unclear>Stander</unclear> The defendent by <choice>
                  <orig>atorney</orig>
                  <reg>attorney</reg>
               </choice> comes and defends the wrong and injury <unclear>&amp; have &amp;c</unclear> and plea<choice>
                  <orig> sais</orig>
                  <reg>saith</reg>
               </choice> the plaintiff his actions <sic>action</sic> thereof  against <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear>him</unclear>
               </del> ought not to have and <choice>
                  <orig>mantain</orig>
                  <reg>maintain</reg>
               </choice> because he sais he is not guilty in manner and form as the plaintiff against him hath <choice>
                  <orig>alledged</orig>
                  <reg>alleged</reg>
               </choice> of this he puts him self upon the County</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>Mitchele</name> atto. for <choice>
                     <abbr>deft</abbr>
                     <expan>defendant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </signed>
               <add>and the plaintiff doth the like</add>
               <signed>
                  <name>Jarnagan</name>atto.</signed>
               <add>And for further plea in this behalf the said defendant says the plaintiff his action against him ought not to have and mantain Because he says the said plaintiff before the speaking and publishing words supposed to have been spoken and published by the said defendant of and concerning the said plaintiff <unclear>(Yes)</unclear> the day and year in the plaintiff declaration mentioned did steal and take corn and therefore the said plaintiff is as bad a man as he represented him to be all which he is ready to verify Wherefore he pays Judgement <choice>
                     <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                     <expan>and et cetera</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <signed>Michel</signed> atto. for Deft. <lb/> Replication &amp; <unclear>Speus</unclear>
               <name>Jarnagan and Mitchel atto.</name>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
