<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc197">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1848 Jan.16, Abingdon, Va. [to] Moses W. White, Knoxville, Tennessee / William G. Campbell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Campbell, William G.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc197</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1848 Jan.16, Abingdon, Va. [to] Moses W. White, Knoxville, Tennessee / William G. Campbell</title>
               <author>Campbell, William G.</author>
               <date when="1848-01-16">January 16, 1848</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by William G. Campbell to his friend Moses White in 1848. Campbell writes of his social life in Virginia and inquires about his lady friends back in Knoxville, Tennessee.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">William G. Campbell Letter</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-1721</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc197</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Social life and customs</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Virginia</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Campbell, William G.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc197a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Abingdon</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jany</abbr>
                     <expan>January</expan>
                  </choice> 16 1848</date>
               <salute>Friend Moses</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I will now make an attempt to answer your favor which was received by last mail and as to receiving your letter of sometime since I did not receive it Mose if I had I should certainly have answered it if only to tell you that I am in the land of the Living.</p>
            <p>As I don't wish to take up your time with unaccustomed <choice>
                  <orig>fooley</orig>
                  <reg>folly</reg>
               </choice>, to begin I will answer your questions which begins with my size, I am exactly five feet and eight inch height to the square and weigh one hundred twenty pounds so you see I am not a man yet by several years</p>
            <p>But at all events if not a man I have been looking at a great <choice>
                  <orig>May</orig>
                  <reg>Many</reg>
               </choice> young ladies since I left Knoxville but I believe the prettiest one I have seen yet is Miss <name>Susan Wallace</name> of Knox There are more pretty girls in this town and vicinity than are one place I ever was in, <del type="overstrike">to</del> And to come out Plainly I have an old sweet heart who lives in Old Knox in the person of the above named, I have seen several here who I like very well but as to love I am totally unacquainted, And here Mose before I forget I will ask you a few questions firstly I should like to ask you to pump Miss Susan and see what she thinks of Billy I use to be a favorite or at least she told me so when I was in Knoxville, and if she has any beaus and who they are, you must not think that I am in love no but I simply want to know how I stand in my native town <pb n="2" facs="sc197b.small.jpg"/> and now Mose since I have expressed myself to you so openly I bind you to secrecy and now I want you to tell me who <del type="overstrike">you</del> is your sweetheart now tell me the truth and I bind myself to disclose it no one</p>
            <p>We have had several very pleasant parties here this winter I have attended nearly all of them and have found the young ladies very pleasant and some one or two I like very much but as to love I am totally unacquainted.</p>
            <p>What is <name>Bruce Armstrong</name> doing, he promised me he would write to me and give me a history of Old Knox and Inhabitants since I left their tell him I want him to fulfill his promise</p>
            <p>I shall now close by giving my best respects to your father and mother and except a large share for yourself, <del type="overstrike">give sister</del> tell sister that I am well and I shall now bid you good bye until next time Give my respects to all inquiring friends and I ask you to show this to know one not even your most intimate acquaintances</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I remain your Obedient <choice>
                     <abbr>Sevt</abbr>
                     <expan>Servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm </abbr>
                        <expan>William</expan>
                     </choice>G. Campbell</name>
               </signed>
               <add>Burn as soon as read</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sc197c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Mr Moses W. White</name>
                        <name>Knoxville </name>
                        <name>
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                              <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
