<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch003">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1826 Nov. 15, Valley Towns, [North Carolina to] James Barbour, Sec[retar]y of War / Evan Jones: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Jones, Evan, 1788-1873</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Angela Pulley</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch003</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44749987</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The  Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1826 Nov. 15, Valley Towns, [North Carolina to] James Barbour, Sec[retar]y of War / Evan Jones</title>
               <author>Jones, Evan, 1788-1873</author>
               <date when="1826-11-15">November 15, 1826</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter from Evan Jones, a Baptist missionary at the Valley Towns (North Carolina) of the Cherokee Nation, to James Barbour, Secretary of War (1825-1828), dated November 15, 1826.  Jones communicates information to Barbour relative to the progress of various industries in the Cherokee Nation,  most notably the establishment of several mills.  The improvements have been made under the direction of the Board of managers of the Baptist General Convention and also include a well attended school.  Jones also remarks on the general "progress" of the Cherokees with respect to Christianity and the "civilized arts."</note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville,TN</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true"> 10</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch003</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Economic conditions--19th century</term>
               <term>Baptists--Missions</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n88199018"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Jones, Evan, 1788-1873</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch003a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Valley Towns</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <date when="1826-11-15">Nov. 15th 1826</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have the <choice>
                  <orig>honour</orig>
                  <reg>honor</reg>
               </choice> to submit to your inspection a report of mills and other Buildings erected at this station from the year <date when="1822">1822</date> to the present time.</p>
            <p>These improvements have been made under the direction of the Board of managers of the Baptist General convention and the utmost <choice>
                  <orig>Econemy</orig>
                  <reg>Economy</reg>
               </choice> has been uniformly observed in carrying them on.</p>
            <p>The Erection of the mills, which are now just finished became <choice>
                  <orig>nessesary</orig>
                  <reg>necessary</reg>
               </choice> in consequence of the former ones, situated on cabin creek 5 miles from the Mission house, being completely destroyed, by a <choice>
                  <orig>tremendious</orig>
                  <reg>tremendous</reg>
               </choice> Freshet on the night of the <date when="--02-20">20th of February</date> last, which rendered our situation <add place="supralinear">with regard to provisions</add> very distressing: there being no mill that could supply the Establishment, within a distance of fifty miles. The present mills are situated on the River <name type="place"> 
                  <reg>River</reg> Hiwasee</name>. The works are all good and substantial, Both Mills are in operation and perform well. They will be a most valuable acquisition to this <choice>
                  <orig>neighbourhood</orig>
                  <reg>neighborhood</reg>
               </choice> and will greatly facilitate the progress which is making in Buildings, agriculture, and the civilized arts, though the state of the country as yet does not warrant the expectation of any profit from them.  All the items contained <add place="supralinear">in the</add> enclosed statement are finished , but a considerable portion of the  <choice>
                  <orig>expence</orig>
                  <reg>expense</reg>
               </choice> is unpaid, on account of the funds of our Board being at present very depressed.</p>
            <p>The aid of Government would therefore be peculiarly Acceptable at this time and I feel persuaded that the funds thus applied will very powerfully promote the cause of humanity which has been espoused by the <name type="place">U.S.</name> Govt. and so zealously prosecuted by the Executive.</p>
            <p>In conclusion, I beg leave to observe that in this vicinity which has always been deemed the darkest part of the Nation<pb n="2" facs="ch003b.small.jpg"/> Agriculture, Female industry, general knowledge, good order and decency of appearance are making very sensible progress, And our holy religion has produced in some of the natives that happy change which no human efforts can <choice>
                  <orig>posibly</orig>
                  <reg>possibly</reg>
               </choice> effect!  Our school has been very well <choice>
                  <orig>attend</orig>
                  <reg>attended</reg>
               </choice> the past year and many of our pupils have made very pleasing improvements.  Several who have left the school have become respectable and useful members of society, among their people   Thus under the benign <choice>
                  <orig>influance</orig>
                  <reg>influence</reg>
               </choice> of our happy Government and the prudent management of its principal organs   Ignorance and confusion and wretchedness are being chased from the abodes of man.
               </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>That every blessing for time and eternity may be yours is the sincere desire of <lb/>Honoured Sir<lb/>Your <choice>
                     <abbr>very ob Servt</abbr>
                     <expan>very obedient Servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <lb/>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Evan Jones</name>
               </signed>
               <lb/>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>N.B.</abbr>
                  <expan>Nota Bene</expan>
               </choice> Should any further information be <choice>
                  <orig>nessesary</orig>
                  <reg>necessary</reg>
               </choice> I shall feel much pleasure in affording it   and any aid which you may be pleased to afford will be gratefully <choice>
                  <orig>Recieved</orig>
                  <reg>Received</reg>
               </choice> and acknowledged by us, and the poor little Indians on whose behalf it is solicited.
                  
               </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="ch003c.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Honble</abbr>
                        <expan>Honorable</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name type="person">James Barbour</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Secy </abbr>
                        <expan>Secretary</expan>
                     </choice> of War</addrLine>
               </address>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
