<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl764">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Address] 1818 Mar. 14, Executive Department, Knoxville, Tennessee [to the] Public / Joseph McMinn : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>McMinn, Joseph												</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl764</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Address] 1818 Mar. 14, Executive Department, Knoxville, Tennessee [to the] Public / Joseph McMinn </title>
               <author> McMinn, Joseph</author>
               <date when="1818-03-14">March 14, 1818</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a public address dated March 14, 1818 from the governor of Tennessee, Joseph McMinn.  The subject of the address is a treaty with the Cherokee Indians regarding boundary lines within the state. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Joseph McMinn Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl764</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Treaties</term>
               <term>McMinn, Joseph, 1758-1824</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr94022129"
                        role="Creator http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/cre">McMinn, Joseph, 1758-1824</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl764a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <add>A Copy</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Executive Department <lb/>  Knoxville</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>14th March 1818</date>
               <add>To the public</add>
            </opener>
            <p>By a Law of the last session of the Legislature of this state, making provision for entering the Land Lying within the limits of this State acquired from the <name>cherokees</name> by a late treaty between that nation and the <name>United States</name> it is made the duty of the Executive of the State of <name>Tennessee</name> on being notified of the ratification of the treaty, to give three months previous notice by proclamation to be published in the <name>Knoxville</name> &amp; <name>Nashville</name> newspapers of the time when the respective surveyor generals office will be opened for the receiving of Entries &amp; and as these appear to be some interest felt by many relative to the time of issuing the proclamation, I deem it proper to inform all concerned, that by the provisions of the Eleventh article of the treaty, the President of the United States is to appoint  a commissioner or Commissioners, who shall in conjunction with such persons as the cherokees may appoint for that purpose, proceed to run a boundary line, laying off the tract of Country  &amp; did agreeably to the provisions of the first and second articles of the Treaty, whereby the limits within which the warrants are to be located will be defined and every person interested will then know, the precise bounds liable to the satisfaction of Warrants; likewise many evils and difficulties <pb n="2" facs="sl764b.small.jpg"/> will be avoided that would result from making entries in an unlimited and undefined tract of country</p>
            <p>Under these circumstances, upon mature consideration I feel constrained by a regard to the interest of my fellow citizens to suspend the issuance of the proclamation and decline acting under the <choice>
                  <orig>authoirty</orig>
                  <reg>authority</reg>
               </choice> of the Law above referred to until the lines described by the Treaty shall have been duly run as stipulated; after which event the public are assured, no time will be lost in complying on my part with the requisitions of the said act of Assembly.__</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Jos M Minn</abbr>
                        <expan>Joseph M. McMinn</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl764c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>A copy <name>Joseph M Minn</name> address on the subject of <name>Cherokee</name> Lands North of the <name>Tennessee River</name>
                  <date>14th March 1818</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
