<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mc048">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1837 Sep. 13, Clinton  [to] Mr. Charles F. Welcker, Kingston, Tennessee / J. C. Mitchell  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Mitchell, J. C.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">mc048</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1837 Sep. 13, Clinton [to] Mr. Charles F. Welcker, Kingston, Tennessee / J. C. Mitchell</title>
               <author>Mitchell, J. C.</author>
               <date when="1837-09-13">September 13, 1837</date>
               <extent>4 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated September 13, 1837, from Judge James C. Mitchell to his son-in-law Charles F. Welcker in Kingston, Tennessee.  Mitchell talks about the good health that he and the family are enjoying, and he gives Welcker and his daughter Caroline the good news that he has recently remarried.  He also discusses the various schools throughout Tennessee to which he may send his children and grandchildren.  The remainder of the letter involves family matters and Mitchell's personal business.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Welcker Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-12, b2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1837</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mc048</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Mitchell, James Coffield, 1786-1843</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Mitchell, James C.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mc048a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Clinton <unclear>
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Mi</abbr>
                              <expan>Michigan</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </unclear>
                     </name>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Sepr</abbr>
                           <expan>September</expan>
                        </choice> 13th 1837</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear Charles</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I <choice>
                  <abbr>recd.</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> your esteemed <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice> a few mails since It gave me much pleasure to hear of the health of you all; and I am extremely thankful to be able to inform you that every soul of us both white and black are in the possession of fine health and have so <choice>
                  <orig>injoyed</orig>
                  <reg>enjoyed</reg>
               </choice> health ever since we recovered from the diseases produced from the Big Black swamps _ I have never known any town in Tennessee or any where else of as large a population as Clinton  so universally healthy_ Our Town is as large as <name>Knoxville</name> and we have had but two or three cases of fever this Season and one of them <name>Thomas W McCall</name> (the son of Old <name>Alexander McCall</name> well known to your father) contracts his fever at another town and came home and by extreme imprudence killed himself in a few days after taken sick_</p>
            <p>I am pleased with your visit to Tennessee for your quarter of the country is most unhealthy in this month of any season of the year and besides all your <choice>
                  <orig>frinds</orig>
                  <reg>friends</reg>
               </choice> will be so glad to see you up <choice>
                  <orig>their</orig>
                  <reg>there</reg>
               </choice> with your little family_ I am also glad to hear of your determination to leave Margaret Elizabeth up their a season to go to school_ And I should have no great repugnance to my little boys Tazwell, Henry &amp; Tom, being there at school but for the extreme trouble in getting them there and the very great distance they would be from me And what is worse than all the deranged state of the currency forbids the idea of transmitting money from this to any Other quarter of the world. The last letter I had from James spoke of a good school a <name>Winchester</name> and if that is the fact I had determined not to change his position until I sent him to <name>Princeton, <choice>
                     <abbr>Ky.</abbr>
                     <expan>Kentucky</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> The <name>Cumberland College</name> or the <name>University of Nashville</name>_ The Other little boys can do better here during the Winter Season than at any other point and next spring I may make some arrangements to send them up the country_ If the school of <pb n="2" facs="mc048b.small.jpg"/> Kingston shall not be a good one <unclear>yea</unclear> a first rate one  I would be glad to have Margaret Elizabeth finish her education at Winchester as that is the best female institution any where to my knowledge</p>
            <p>This letter is also intended as the median of conveying to you the <choice>
                  <orig>inteligence</orig>
                  <reg>intelligence</reg>
               </choice>  (whether pleasing or not I can not say) that I have given to you and lovely Caroline another Mother and to my little <choice>
                  <abbr>Bet.</abbr>
                  <expan>Betty</expan>
               </choice> a grand mother.  I was married to <name>Mrs Ann Eliza Young</name> on tuesday morning the 5th <choice>
                  <abbr>inst</abbr>
                  <expan>instant</expan>
               </choice>, at her residence six miles above <name>Lexington <unclear>Holsey</unclear> County Mi</name>  did about 80 miles above this on the Western District road to Tennessee_ She is a lovely woman in her 33d year of age fair complexion blue eyes and every way more like my former wife than any woman upon earth except that she is considerably larger_ She was the Widow of <name>Peter R. Young</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>esqr.</abbr>
                  <expan>esquire</expan>
               </choice> A lawyer of distinction who died two years and more <add>ago</add> at <name>Benton Yazoo County</name> _ She was Originally a <name>Miss Ann Brown</name>  the daughter of <name>Henry Brown</name> of <name>Paris Henry County <choice>
                     <abbr>Ten.</abbr>
                     <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> _ She has two daughters_ The eldest Geraldine about 12 years old and Eliza Jane about nine years old They are said to be smart and lovely little girls, for I have not had the pleasure of seeing them They are at Paris in Henry County Ten. at school but we are looking for them down here every day_ Their mother has property enough to maintain them genteelly and when they are old enough to marry then favourably tho not rich (viz, two  <unclear>snug</unclear> small tracks of land favourably located and ten <choice>
                  <orig>negros</orig>
                  <reg>negroes</reg>
               </choice>_ To all these I now have none or will I ever claim my title_</p>
            <p>I am farming on a small scale Only raising corn and peas of which I have made a good crop The corn crops are more abundant here this season than ever known before, but the cotton crops will be tight Owing to heavy falls of rain the last of July and first of <choice>
                  <abbr>Augt</abbr>
                  <expan>August</expan>
               </choice> which occasioned the squares to fall and the stock to grow too large_ My professional <choice>
                  <orig>persuits</orig>
                  <reg>pursuits</reg>
               </choice> are <choice>
                  <orig>proffitable</orig>
                  <reg>profitable</reg>
               </choice> to me beyond any thing known in Tennessee and <name>Alabama</name> but still not equal to many other lawyers who have engrossed a large share of the <unclear>cattleling</unclear>
               <pb n="3" facs="mc048c.small.jpg"/> business_ But if I live I think in a year or so I shall be doing as much as any one in the state</p>
            <p>I hope you and Virginia will visit her uncles and aunts in <name>Marion County</name> If you neglect them they will never forgive you I wish you to urge Caroline to write more frequent and not forgetting to do so yourself-</p>
            <p>Present me in the most acceptable manner to your father and mother Of them I always hope to cherish the most lovely remembrance.  Tell them that it would give me great pleasure to see and converse with them a few days at least Sister sends her love to them And we ask to be kindly presented to all the rest of the family Newton writes for himself you know, but he sometimes is lazy_</p>
            <p>We all would be very glad to see you Catty and Betty down here but more particularly your newly accepted mother and me hope that you can find leisure this fall or winter to come to see us.</p>
            <p>Little <name>Mary Mariah Graham</name> is always wishing to see you all but none more than her niece Elizabeth</p>
            <p>Write us immediately after the receipt of this and tell my daughter and grand daughter to do so too.  and write frequent and if you do not receive a letter every fortnight do not attribute it to sickness, but to business or negligence as I believe we will injoy more and better health than we have done at any other place at which we have ever lived.  It is true that your Aunts health is quite delicate ever since she had the <choice>
                  <orig>meazles</orig>
                  <reg>measles</reg>
               </choice> in the spring_ The consumption is showing itself strongly I fear upon her. She has just past through a mercurial courses and what the final result is to be time can only determine.</p>
            <p>The whole family beg to be remembered to you Caroline &amp; Betty_ And I would on my own account admonish you all to remember that you must die and after that the Judgment <pb n="4" facs="mc048d.small.jpg"/>  Therefore endeavor to love and serve the Lord from a pure heart Take up your crop and follow the Lord Jesus through evil and well as good repent_  May God almighty bless you all in time and eternity And</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>believe me my Dear Charles to be yours most sincerely</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>J.</abbr>
                        <expan>James</expan>
                     </choice> C. Mitchell</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mr <choice>
                        <abbr>Chas.</abbr>
                        <expan>Charles</expan>
                     </choice> F. Welcker</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Mr. Charles F. Welcker</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Kingston</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Tennessee</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <add>Mail</add>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
