<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl351">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1826 Jan. 10, Chickasaw Nation, Cotton Gin Port [Mississippi] [to] Finis Ewing, Cooper C[oun]ty, Missouri / Robert Bell   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Bell, Robert</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl351</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1826 Jan. 10, Chickasaw Nation, Cotton Gin Port [Mississippi] [to] Finis Ewing, Cooper C[oun]ty, Missouri / Robert Bell </title>
               <author>Bell, Robert</author>
               <date when="1826-01-10">January 10, 1826</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to Finis Ewing from Rev. Robert Bell, dated January 10, 1826. Bell writes about his school for Chickasaw children, named Charity Hall. Bell mentions that most of the young natives are barefoot. He has them making shoes so that they are able to help in the field work. Bell writes of his hopes for resolving the school's  funding problems. He wants to earn respect for the school. Bell also asks Ewing for a loan of some money and flour, because they are having such a difficult time.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Finis Ewing Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">I-A-4</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">4</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl351</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Chickasaw Indians</term>
               <term>Mississippi</term>
               <term>Cumberland Presbyterian Church.</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Bell, Robert</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl351a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Charity Hall, <name>Chickasaw Nation</name>, <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Jan.</abbr>
                           <expan>January</expan>
                        </choice> 10th 1826</date>.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Rev.</abbr>
                     <expan>Reverend</expan>
                  </choice> &amp; Dear Brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>A few days after my return from the synod, on the <date>9th of November</date>, I <choice>
                  <abbr>resum'd</abbr>
                  <expan>resumed</expan>
               </choice> teaching school, nearly all the <choice>
                  <orig>schollars</orig>
                  <reg>scholars</reg>
               </choice> who were at school last year have come on to school, and the rest are expected, The school will be <choice>
                  <abbr>compos'd</abbr>
                  <expan>composed</expan>
               </choice> of the same schollars this year that it was last.</p>
            <p>Their progress has been retarded by the long vacation, but not as much as I <choice>
                  <abbr>fear'd</abbr>
                  <expan>feared</expan>
               </choice> it would, They are now advancing, and I hope some of them will finish their course this year</p>
            <p>As they were nearly all barefooted, I have set the largest of them at making shoes for themselves, and also for the smaller boys, They perform exceedingly well, I want them shod to prepare ground early for the ensuing crop. ____ </p>
            <p>The <choice>
                  <orig>liberallity</orig>
                  <reg>liberality</reg>
               </choice> of the patrons of this Institution, manifested on the last year, The Unanimous interest the members of the Board appeared to feel in its success, <add>at their last meeting.</add> and the Judicious plan adopted by them for the purpose of raising funds this year, for its support, and to meet the arrearages, encourages a hope, that after this year, those painful embarrassments, so oppressive to our feelings <add>for the want of friends to defray the expense of the school</add> will be removed, and the Institution will gain that credit &amp; respectability, which  <pb n="2" facs="sl351b.small.jpg"/> will place it on an equality with similar Institutions, to which it is Justly entitled, from the proficiency of the students. ___ </p>
            <p>I hope we shall realize <add>the advantages of</add> that <choice>
                  <orig>uninimity</orig>
                  <reg>unanimity</reg>
               </choice> which pervaded the Synod &amp; Missionary Board, in the fruits of the united exertions of all the members, &amp; especially the agent appointed to procure funds for the Establishment &amp; support of the adopted College, &amp; Theological School, and also for the cont <add>i</add> nuance of the Establishment ___</p>
            <p>Dear Brother, perhaps a few barrels of flour could be sent to the <name>Chickasaw bluff</name> for this station from your Country, (it can easily be conveyed from there to this place) and a little money to the next meeting of the Board, to help us through our difficulties, with the abundance that I trust will be sent on for the College &amp; Theological School ___</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>With sentiments of respect, I am your unworthy Brother in the Gospel of a dear Redeemer.</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Robert Bell</name>.</signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Rev. Finis Ewing</name>.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P.S.</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> Finis Ewing, the Indian boy we <choice>
                     <abbr>nam'd</abbr>
                     <expan>named</expan>
                  </choice> for you can read tolerably well and writes a Legible hand He talks good English He is learning the Tanning business &amp; he has just made two pair of shoes &amp; performs well ___ <lb/> I have understood that pork is plenty in that Country <unclear>
                     <del>it would</del>
                  </unclear>  bacon would sell well this year in this <pb n="3" facs="sl351c.small.jpg"/> if there could be any of that article or any other sent to the Bluff or to <name>Florence</name> or <name>south port</name> opposite to Florence on <name>Tennessee River</name> it would be very acceptable and I will do the best I can with them for the benefit of the Institution ___</add>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>R,,</abbr>
                     <expan>Robert</expan>
                  </choice> Bell</signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Rev. Finis Ewing</addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl351d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Cotton Gin Port</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <date>
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Jany</abbr>
                              <expan>January</expan>
                           </choice> 14</date>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Rev. Finis Ewing.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Cooper <choice>
                           <abbr>Cty.</abbr>
                           <expan>County</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                     <choice>
                        <orig>Mesourie</orig>
                        <reg>Missouri</reg>
                     </choice> .</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
