<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm014">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Map of Overhill Cherokee sites, 18th century], / the University
			 of Tennessee: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>University of Tennessee</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Catherine Michelle Love</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. 3k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>mm014</idno>
            <idno>OCLC 45077304</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Museum, University of
				Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Map of Overhill Cherokee sites, 18th century], / the
				University of Tennessee</title>
               <author>University of Tennessee</author>
               <date>1967</date>
               <date when="1982">1982</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This is a photograph of a map of the Overhill
				Cherokee sites that were occupied during the 18th century. The map is based on
				Henry Timberlake's 1762 map of the area as well as archaeological
				investigations made in 1967 through 1982, by The University of Tennessee as
				part of the Tellico Archaeological Project in anticipation of the flooding of
				the Lower Little Tennessee River by the Tellico Dam Reservoir. The excavations
				were conducted under contract with the National Park Service and the Tennessee
				Valley Authority (TVA). These well- known Overhill settlements of Mialoquo,
				Tuskeegee, Toqua, Chota, Citico, Tallassee, and Chilhowee are now all under
				water. The Cherokees who were located in north Georgia, northwest South
				Carolina, and Western North Carolina had to travel over the mountains from
				South Carolina to reach their brethren who lived in the lower Tennessee and
				Hiawasee River Valleys and thus they were referred to as the Overhill
				Cherokees. </note>
               <note type="collection">Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note type="document">mm014</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Maps</term>
               <term>Historic sites</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Little Tennessee River Valley (Ga.-Tenn.)</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2017180154"
                        role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">University of Tennessee</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mm014.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Map of Overhill Cherokee sites. These were occupied during
				  the 18th century, map based on Timberlake [see mm012] and archaeological
				  investigations 1967 through 1982, by the University of Tennessee. This
				  information was provided by the Frank H. McClung Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
