<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl657">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1838 Apr. 11, Washington City [to] N[ewton] Cannon, Tennessee / Winfield Scott : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Scott, Winfield</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl657</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> 1838 Apr. 11, Washington City [to] N[ewton] Cannon, Tennessee / Winfield Scott</title>
               <author> Scott, Winfield</author>
               <date when="1838-04-11"> 
			 April 11, 1838</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Winfield Scott, the Federal officer in charge of Cherokee Removal. It is to Governor Newton Cannon, dated April 11, 1838. Scott is asking Cannon to send him troops for his army. He details the positions he needs filled.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Newton Cannon Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">8</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl657</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Trail of Tears, 1838</term>
               <term>Scott, Winfield, 1786-1866</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79059770"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Scott, Winfield, 1786-1866.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl657a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Head <choice>
                        <abbr>Tn</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice> Eastern Division of the Army</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Washington City</name>, <date>april 11, 1838</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>His Excellency,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>N.</abbr>
                        <expan>Newton</expan>
                     </choice> Cannon,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Governor of <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>In pursuance of authority conferred upon me by the Executive of the <name>United States</name>, of which you have been officially advised I have the honor to ask your Excellency to detach by volunteering or draughting, to be mustered into the service of the United States for three months, unless sooner discharged, one regiment of ten companies &amp; one battalion of five companies, both of infantry to serve on foot, from the militia of Tennessee</p>
            <p>This force being part of that destined to be employed by me in the removal of the <name>Cherokee</name>s from the East to the West of the <name>Mississippi</name> under the treaty of <date>December 1835</date>, between the United States &amp; the Indians of that name, I have further to request that the regiment &amp; battalion be both ordered to <choice>
                  <orig>rendeyvous</orig>
                  <reg>rendezvous</reg>
               </choice> at <name>Calhoun</name> Tennessee, where it will be daily mustered into the service of the United States &amp; receive my instructions or those of some other <pb n="2" facs="sl657b.small.jpg"/> other superior officer of the Jane Service. And it is proper to add that no troops will be received,  subsisted on paid by the United States, for the service in question, other than such as may be specifically called for.</p>
            <p>On account of the particular service &amp; the apprehended scarcity of forage for horses, in &amp; about the Cherokee country, I have, in this requisition specified infantry on foot.</p>
            <p>I will ask that the regiment &amp; battalion may appear at Calhoun, or near the tenth of the ensuing month as practicable, &amp; already armed. I shall, however, endeavour to have, by that time at, or near the rendeyvous, some United States muskets &amp; rifles to supply deficiencies &amp; all the ammunition which may be needed.</p>
            <p>Field &amp; staff of the regiment One colonel, one lieutenant colonel, one major; one adjutant &amp; one quarter-master (each with the rank of first lieutenant;) one <pb n="3" facs="sl657c.small.jpg"/> one sergeant major one quarter master sergeant one drum-major &amp; one fife-major</p>
            <p>Field &amp; staff of the battalion One major one adjutant &amp; one quarter master (each with the rank of first lieutenant;) one sergeant major no quarter-master sergeant, one drum-major &amp; no fife-major.</p>
            <p>Composition of a company. One captain, one first lieutenant, one ensign (to be paid as second lieutenant;) four sergeants four corporals, two musicians &amp; sixty-four privates</p>
            <p>I beg leave to impress upon your Excellency that, under the acts of Congress organizing the militia the above full complement of officers cannot be paid by the United States, without the full complement of privates___ sixty-four per company</p>
            <p>I enclose certain printed memoranda which I beg may be addressed &amp; distributed</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>With high respect <lb/> I have the <choice>
                     <orig>honour</orig>
                     <reg>honor</reg>
                  </choice> to be, <lb/> Your Excellency's <lb/> Most <choice>
                     <abbr>Obt Ser</abbr>
                     <expan>Obedient Service</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Winfield Scott</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
