<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch046">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter], 1831 June 7, Haweis [Mission, Cherokee Nation] to George R. Gilmer, Governor of Georgia / Elizur Butler: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Butler, Elizur, 1794-1857</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch046</idno>
            <idno>oclc: 44844536</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter], 1831 June 7, Haweis [Mission, Cherokee Nation] to George R. Gilmer, Governor of Georgia / Elizur Butler</title>
               <author>Butler, Elizur, 1794-1857</author>
               <date when="1831-06-07">June 7, 1831</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">Letter dated June 7, 1831 from Elizur Butler, Christian missionary living in the Cherokee Nation, to Georgia Governor George R. Gilmer in response to a letter Butler received from Gilmer. Butler explains his purposes in living within the Cherokee Nation. He says that he arrived ten years ago to assist the United States in its policy to "civilize" and Christianize the Cherokees, and his only concern is the spiritual growth of the Cherokees and not political issues.  He indicates that he cannot in good conscience take the oath of Georgia since it would imply that the state has jurisdiction over the Cherokee Nation.</note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1 </note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">29</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch046</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Cherokee Indians</term>
               <term>Missions</term>
               <term>Georgia--Politics and government--1775-1865</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr92005730"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Butler, Elizur, 1794-1857</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch046a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>
               <add place="top">K.<lb/>
                  <name type="person">Dr. Butler</name>'s reply to <name type="person">Governor Gilmer</name>.
                  </add>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Haweis</name>,</addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <date when="1831-06-07">June 7, 1831</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>To his Excellency <name type="person">George R. Gilmer</name>, Governor of <name type="place">Georgia</name>.<lb/>Sir,
                  </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>A few days since, I received a communication purporting to be from your excellency</p>
            <p>Suffer me to say, I was not a little surprised at some ideas that communication  contained.  It is due to the cause in which I am engaged, definitely and concisely to state the object of my residence in the <name>Cherokee nation</name> of Indians.</p>
            <p>My sole object in commencing my residence among this people, more than ten years since, was to assist the government of the <name type="place">United States</name> in promoting the civilization and Christianization of the <name type="person">Cherokees</name>.</p>
            <p>I have, during my life, studiously avoided all connection or interference with political affairs, and more particularly since my residence among this people.  Since living among them, I have invariably pursued that course of conduct, which I conceived would tend most for their spiritual good.  Though I may have been accused of being " a mortal enemy to <name type="place">Georgia</name> and her measures,"  I solemnly affirm I am not, although I could not in conscience subscribe to all her enactments.  For instance, I could not take the oath required of white men who reside in her chartered<pb n="2" facs="ch046b.small.jpg"/>limits, as this would acknowledge the jurisdiction of <name type="place">Georgia</name> over the <name type="person">Cherokees</name>, which would be adverse to my opinion, and essentially effect my usefulness.  My principles of action are founded on the work of God; and if adhering to the "law and the testimony," and endeavoring to follow the examples of holy writ, my conduct be construed into an unjustifiable interference with political transactions,  I cannot help it.  I cannot change my religious views, or general religious conduct, with the various political changes of the times.  It is what neither your excellency nor any other person can expect.  Rather than change my religious views, to meet the exigencies of political affairs, permit me to say, I should sacrifice my life.  I wish you distinctly to understand, that I came into the nation for no political or selfish purposes; and that I remain here only for the spiritual good of this people; and that no sufficient reasons have ever been presented to my mind for me to leave the infant church collected here, to be broken to pieces and scattered.   If I must suffer for the above course of conduct, I hope the Lord will enable me to meet suffering, with Christian meekness and fortitude.  Wishing you and your state, the greatest and best blessings heaven can bestow,
               </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am very respectfully Your obedient servant,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Elizur Butler</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
