<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch051">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Survey report containing Path Killer's plat and certificate, 1820 Aug. 15, Tennessee / [signed by] David Taylor ... [et al.]: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch051</idno>
            <idno>oclc: 44846202</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Survey report containing Path Killer's plat and certificate, 1820 Aug. 15, Tennessee / [signed by] David Taylor ... [et al.]</title>
               <date when="1820-08-15">August 15, 1820</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">Survey report of the Cherokee leader Path Killer's plat and certificate of 640 acres dated August 15, 1820. The surveyors and commissioners mark the property boundary according to the Treaty of the Cherokee Agency, 1817 and the Treaty of Washington, 1819.  Path Killer had filed a claim at the Cherokee Agency on April 14, 1819.</note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch051</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Land tenure</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Treaties</term>
               <term>Boundaries</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch051a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>No. 7.<lb/>
               <name type="person">Path Killer</name>'s Plat and Certificate<lb/>
               <hi>640 Acres</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="2" facs="ch051b.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>State of <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>A small map of the property discussed below appears in the upper left corner of the page.</figDesc>
               </figure> The undersigned Commissioner and Surveyor (duly authorized) have agreeably to the terms of a Treaty concluded at the <name type="place">Cherokee Agency</name> on the <date when="1817-07-08">eighth day of (of) July one thousand eight hundred Seventeen</date>  and a Treaty concluded at the city of <name type="place">Washington</name> on the <date when="1819-02-27">twenty seventh day of February one thousand eight hundred and nineteen</date> between the <name type="place">United States</name> and the <name>Cherokee Nation</name> of Indians surveyed and laid <unclear>off</unclear> to the <name type="person">Path Killer</name> six hundred and forty acres of land corresponding with the registration of his claim filed in the office of the Che<pb n="3" facs="ch051c.small.jpg"/>rokee agent on the <date when="1819-04-14">fourteenth day of April one thousand eight hundred and nineteen</date>
               <unclear/> and <unclear/> a fellow Viz  Beginning at an ash, elm and white oak on the bank <del type="overstrike">of</del> of <name type="place">Tennessee River</name> about twenty poles above the upper end of an Island in said River: thence West one hundred and ninety five poles to a <unclear>slate</unclear> near a marked walnut on the bank of said River thence down its <unclear>meanders</unclear> two hundred poles to a <choice>
                  <orig>chesnut</orig>
                  <reg>chestnut</reg>
               </choice> and spanish oak on a rocky Bluff  thence South one hundred and seventy two poles to a post oak: thence East three hundred and seventy six poles to a <unclear>slate</unclear> near a marked hickory, red Oak and dogwood on a rocky bluff near the <unclear>River</unclear> crossing a branch at one hundred and <choice>
                  <orig>eigthty</orig>
                  <reg>eighty</reg>
               </choice> poles thence down the River as it  meanders three hundred and fifty four poles to the Beginning, passing the Ferry landing and the mouth of a branch at one hundred and eighty 8 poles.  Including his dwelling house, Ferry and improvement.
               </p>
            <p>Surveyed this <date when="1820-08-15">15th day of August 1820</date>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <unclear>R. Houson</unclear>
                  </name>
               </signed>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Robert Armstrong</name>
               </signed> Surveyor<signed>
                  <name type="person">David Taylor</name>
               </signed>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Taylor Eldridge</name>
               </signed>
               <unclear>S.C.C.</unclear>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
