<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc242">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Deposition] 1789 Mar. 4, Joseph McDowell, Burke County, North Carolina : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>McDowell, Joseph</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc242</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Deposition] 1789 Mar. 4, Joseph McDowell, Burke County, North Carolina</title>
               <author>McDowell, Joseph</author>
               <date when="1789-03-04"> 
			 March 4, 1789</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a deposition dated March 4, 1789.  It is given to Colonel Joseph McDowell in a case between James Cook and David Nelson.  The case involves a dispute over the theft of a gun and the payment of money.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Joseph McDowell Deposition</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">New Accession</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc242</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Legal documents</term>
               <term>Courts</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Witness http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/wit">McDowell, Joseph</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc242a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <name>Burke County</name>
               <name>North Carolina</name>
               <date>March the 4th 1789</date>
            </opener>
            <p>Personally <choice>
                  <orig>appeard</orig>
                  <reg>appeared</reg>
               </choice>
               <name>Joseph McDowell</name> before me the subscriber and Made Oath In discourse of Law that Some time in September 1783 as well as he Remembers <name>James Cook</name>.  <unclear>Son in law</unclear> to <name>George Winter</name> Came to him.  and Informed him that <name>David Nelson</name> Had Taken a gun from him the said <add place="supralinear">Cook</add> and Otter Skin shotpouch in the Year of 1780  Shortly before the action at  <name>Kings Mountain</name> and Cook further said I have <choice>
                  <orig>applyd</orig>
                  <reg>applied</reg>
               </choice> to nelson to pay me for said articles.  But nelson will  not pay me.  This <choice>
                  <orig>Deponant</orig>
                  <reg>Deponent</reg>
               </choice> further says Cook Intimated he <gap agent="damage"/> Bring Suit and Prosecute nelson <gap agent="damage"/> upon which the deponant <unclear>prefered</unclear> to go with said Cook to  nelson.  upon which they <del type="overstrike">started</del>  went Immediately to the house of nelson.  this Deponant Further <gap agent="damage"/> that when he went to Nelson where he was at work and Informed him of Cooks Conversation.  and Desired Nelson to pay said Cook or otherwise he would be <unclear>at</unclear> considerable  Expense  which would Injure his small Family and the orphans under his care.  upon which nelson went to his own house to see Cook and after some conversation Nelson said to James Cook what makes you want to prosecute me when you know I was your gun and <unclear>Pouch</unclear> to Save  them for you, Cook then <choice>
                  <orig>Replyd</orig>
                  <reg>Replied</reg>
               </choice>.  I lost my gun and otterskin  shot pouch and you are the only person I can Recover them  from <add>Turn Over </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sc242b.small.jpg"/> A considerable Time <choice>
                  <orig>passd</orig>
                  <reg>passed</reg>
               </choice> in Conversation which this Deponant Does not Remember the Express Words But the Substance convinced him that an agreement had been made between Cook and Nelson in 1780 for nelson to give said Cook notice when the Enemy was Coming The Conversation was as Follows Concerning the gun Nelson Said to James Cook you surely have got your gun and Shot pouch.  Cook <choice>
                  <orig>answerd</orig>
                  <reg>answered</reg>
               </choice> that he was had got Either.  then Nelson agreed to pay Cook for said gun upon condition that If Cook Ever let his gun and pouch he would Return the pay.   or if Nelson Could make it appear that said Cook <gap/> them before that time and after nelson had taken them.  Cook Likewise agreed to Repay this agreement was <choice>
                  <orig>Enterd</orig>
                  <reg>Entered</reg>
               </choice> into in presence of this Deponant and they <unclear>Parties</unclear> agreed on It he <gap/> witness do their Bargain.  This Deponant further adds that he does not believe that Cook in all the Conversation that passed Ever made mention of a <choice>
                  <orig>Pare</orig>
                  <reg>Pair</reg>
               </choice> of <name>Silver Spurs</name>.  which he since understood Cook charged nelson with Sworn and Subscribed In Open Court.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joseph M McDonnel</signed>Sworn in open court March 4th 1789 <unclear>
                  <name/>
               </unclear>
               <add>agreed to by the <choice>
                     <orig>attornies</orig>
                     <reg>attorneys</reg>
                  </choice> on both sides</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sc242c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Morganton <lb/> David Nelson <unclear>vs</unclear> James Cook  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> McDowells Deposition</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
