<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0320">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Legal document]  1838 Mar. 27, Jane &amp; Willie Blair vs. The Pathkiller &amp; Gardenhire : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0320</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Legal document]  1838 Mar. 27, Jane &amp; Willie Blair vs. The Pathkiller &amp; Gardenhire </title>
               <date when="1838-03-27"> 
			 March 27, 1838</date>
               <extent> 6p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a legal document, dated March 27, 1838,  against The Pathkiller, a Cherokee Indian who lost his land during the removal of the Cherokees west of the Mississippi River. The Pathkiller wants to re-claim his land which was sold to Jane and Willie Blair.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> n/a</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Legal document</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Land tenure</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0320a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Jane &amp; Willie Blair</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>vs</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>The PathKiller</name> &amp; <name>Gardenhire</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>The bill charges that the State issued a grant to <name>James Blair</name> for 317s acres of land__ dated the 30th Nov, 1822. That at the land Sales in <name>Knoxville </name>in the year 1820 <name>Charles McClung </name>purchased 159 <choice>
                  <abbr>a</abbr>
                  <expan>acres</expan>
               </choice>  also 80 acres_ which said McClung transfered to said Blair_ Blair took possession in 1821 &amp; held that possession up to the time of the death of said Blair which happened in <add>November</add> 1826_ That the above Complaint hold as devisees_</p>
            <p>Bill further charges that an Indian by the name of PathKiller claimed a reserve of 640 a including the above lands_ founded on the treaties of 1817 &amp; 1819_ That said Indian brought his action of ejectment to gain the possession of said land_ in said action he has succeeded_ and the complainants are likely to be turned out of possession_</p>
            <p>The grounds of equity laid are two_ That said PathKiller with a certain PM Miller an <choice>
                  <abbr>atto</abbr>
                  <expan>attorney</expan>
               </choice>. committed an act of champerty_ said Path agreeing to give a part of the land if recovered_ and that this interest was afterwards transferred to a certain <choice>
                  <abbr>Wm </abbr>
                  <expan>William</expan>
               </choice>Gardenhire who manages the suit. The second ground of equity is that the right of PathKiller had been extinguished_ That he had sold his interest in an improvement at a place called the Peach trees (beyond the limits of the 640 a sued for)_ and that the reserve claimed had not been taken at the place where the said Indian resided in <choice>
                  <abbr>Jany</abbr>
                  <expan>January</expan>
               </choice> 1820 and that said PathKiller had removed within the cherokee nation of indians_ leaving Garenshire to manage the suit under an unlawful contract tainted with champerty___</p>
            <p>These pacts it is charged were not Known to <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>sd</abbr>
                     <expan>said</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add> complainants or those defending the suit at law_</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Prayre</orig>
                  <reg>prayer</reg>
               </choice> for an injunction &amp;c_</p>
            <p>To this bill the defendants filed a general <pb n="2" facs="pa0320b.small.jpg"/> demurrer_ This was overruled on argument_ &amp; &amp; defendants PathKiller and Gardenhire ordered to answer_ PathKiller in his answer <choice>
                  <orig>shews</orig>
                  <reg>shows</reg>
               </choice> that <del type="overstrike">that</del> he was unlawfully and oppressively turned out of his reserve by a Summary process from a circuit Judge Avers that his reserve was well taken under the treaties insists on the trial at law as evidence of that fact_ and that James Blair had been instrumental in fixing his reserve at the spot gained in the action of ejectment_ and that said Blair purchased with full notice_ PathKiller denies that he removed with an intention to abandon his right_ denies that the sale to Gardenshire was with a view to quit the land_ on the contrary that it has always been his intention to return and reside on the land when he can regain his possession_ Denies the champerty &amp; &amp; pleads that he is not bound to answer such matters as may Subject him to a forfeiture or a prosecution_ Gardenhire puts in a like plea of privilege from answering as to the champerty and maintainance__ Replications are filed_ and much evidence taken_ cases arising under the treaties in questions being somewhat new in their characters_ is one apology for the novelty presented in the bill before us__ There can be no doubt that it was the object of the contracting parties when the treaties were framed to make the rights of the Indians taking reserves to depend upon a few simple rules and such as could be comprehended by any one__ The treaties upon their face__ The entry or registry with the agents possession and survey of the land designated_ gave the right_ Treaty Stipulations must be construed as compacts__ The view the parties had of the subject at the time must not be lost sight of _ had the Indians  <pb n="3" facs="pa0320c.small.jpg"/> when taking reserves been told that the rights thus set up by them under the treaty would be <add>the</add> subject of much litigation__ That legislation touching those rights would be endless_ and made too with a view to effect them directly__ The Indian would have hesitated before he would have made his Registry for a reserve_ But he either Knew or was told that on his reserve he was a Citizen and as such entitled to the protection the constitution afforded to others he looked therefore to the Constitution and to the magnanimity of those into whose Society he was admitted</p>
            <p>Having briefly shewn the footing on which the indian took his right to this land and that under such right he was in possession the <unclear>will</unclear> for a moment glance at the manner it has been effected by legislature acts__</p>
            <p>Act 1819- ch 59 St 2 olig 140 Recognises rights of the character of PathKillers but does not authorise the Surveyor to lay down the reserve, unless taken before 1st July 1818_ act 1819 ch 60 (2_olig_ 143) To the same effect_ but the Surveyor may bear testimony and lay down or reject the claim__</p>
            <p>Act 1822 ch 27__ Life reserve may <unclear> ban</unclear>  razing $1.25 per acre__ procure a Grant for the land in fee to himself or to his  <unclear>assignee</unclear>__ 2 olig 144__ This act is revived and prolonged 12 months__ by the act 1823__ ch175__ (2. olig. 148) _ and the purchasor of life reserve placed on a footing with the purchaser of the fee simple reservee_____ act of 1825. ch. 12. comes in aid of the provision in favor of purchasers of the reserve by authorising an entry razing the $1.25__ act 1825_ ch 256__ (2.olig 150) authorising Registry to be read as evidence in Suits brought by reserves_ But this act is repeated by an act of the next Session___</p>
            <p>Act 1826 ch 33_ (2 olig 152) purchaser of the Reservees land not to pay his principal or interest <unclear>accruing</unclear> until the suit against him finally settled_ <pb n="4" facs="pa0320d.small.jpg"/> Act 1827_ ch. 46 (2 olig. 154) give the value of the improvement made on the reserves land__ even in suit already brought_ and fixes the evidence &amp; made of <choice>
                  <orig>leting</orig>
                  <reg>letting</reg>
               </choice> it in on the trial_ </p>
            <p>Act 1827 ch 33 S 1 provides what shall be champerty and maintainance touching these lands_ the act in its terms is made applicable to these cases alone_ and applies to suits already commenced_ and in connection we will here notice an act of 1819 ch S12 authorising a Circuit Judge to issue a visit of possession on the exparte application of a purchaser at the land sales__ This act provides for employing councel to attend to the rights of the state in suits brought by reserves_ authorises such counsel to employ &amp; commission persons to take testimony_ and on the application of the counsel employed either verbally made or in writing_ a change of venue shall be directed to any county where most convenient to the said <choice>
                  <abbr>att.o</abbr>
                  <expan>attorney</expan>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <p>Extraordinary as this course of Legislation has been in relation to reserves in general_ The proceeding under the acts cited have not in a particular manner effected the case before us one or two of these laws have been put in operation perhaps the only one material to be noticed at present is that unser which the writ possession issued by which PathKiller was turned out thereby making it necessary for him to resort to the action of <unclear>Ejectmt</unclear> to regain his possession_ Some of these acts speak of the assigned of the reserve by using this turn assignee we infer that the act contemplates the possibility of a sale__ other acts as far as Legislation can do it places life reserves on the same footing with those in fee__ puting it in the <unclear>power </unclear>
               <pb n="5" facs="pa0320e.small.jpg"/>of the head of the indian family ( if an act of assembly could have that effect) to defeat the remainder over_ if the  state can profit one dollar twenty five cents per acre__ We merely notice these to show that while the indian claiming a reserve is prosecuting his suit to gain the possession he is cramped and limited at every point by laws passed with a view to effect his case and not that of any other member of the community_ So far we cannot help Seeing a one sided legislation much to be regreted</p>
            <p>Shfting a view of the subject so that they might be presented in another aspect__ We find <unclear>Life</unclear> reserve Indian generally indulged_ The treaty which limits the nature of the rights of some indians for reasons obvious to every man who will read it are enlaged by the atcs of assembly in question Gruards thrown around the Indian holding the life estate &amp; which were intended to protect it in the hands of the Imbecile are looking away_and by the acts of assembly he stands exposed to the very evils the treaty had designed to obviate that of dealing with the white man_ Taking therefore the nature of this little into view in its first stage simple__ and seeing how it has been embarrassed by repeated acts of the Legislature__ Seeing also that Blair was a purchasee with notice__ That the state has given him the aid of counsel with other advantages not common to his adversary_ It is reasonable to suppose that this Court would apply the extraordianry remedy sought in the Bill_ whether we look to the ction of ejectment or to the bill before us In whom is the legal title is the question to be determined__ Taking all the allegation in the bill as true what fraud what concealment or what hardship in the case is presented that cannot be corrected by the court of law on another trial of  the title <pb n="6" facs="pa0320f.small.jpg"/> It is said there is one a case of hardship That should complaints recover The<choice>
                  <orig>meene</orig>
                  <reg>mean</reg>
               </choice> profits may be lost by the removal of the Indian__ mense profits are consequent upon the recovery in ejectment_ and it would be going far indeed to hold but the plaintiff in ejectment who has succeeded_ on two remote contingincies__ <unclear>another</unclear>removal of the Indian_ and the other the possiblity of a recovery by the devisees of Blair in case where the title is only made questionable by the fact that Gardenshire &amp; miller have been dealing about it__ he who would have equity must do it. Let the devised restore the possession improperly taken by the elder Blair__ and the law is competent to  determine the right_ See the case of Blount and Geeren__ 3. may. R.go__</p>
            <closer>
               <add>Let the decree be affirmed_</add>
               <name>. Her. Brown,</name>
               <add>Clerk of the Supreme Court of the  </add>
               <add>state of Tennessee at Knoxville by my Deputy Jas. W. Campbell do hereby certify that the foregoing is a full, true, and complete copy from the original on fill in my office, of the opinion of law supreme court in the case of Jane &amp; Willie Blir ws The PathKiller and Gardenshire__</add>
               <add>Given under my hand and seal of office at Office in Knoxville this 27th day of March 1838__</add>
               <signed>
                  <name>Her Brown</name>
                  <add>clerk</add>
               </signed>
               <add>By his Deputy Jas. W. Campbell</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
