<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl627">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1843 Dec. 22, Columbia, Tennessee [to] Nashville, Tennessee / Jas. H. Oley : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Oley, Jas. H.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl627</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> 1843 Dec. 22, Columbia, Tennessee [to] Nashville, Tennessee / Jas. H. Oley</title>
               <author> Oley, Jas. H.</author>
               <date when="1843-12-22"> 
			 December 22 1843</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Jas. H. Oley to Governor James C. Jones, dated December 22, 1843. Oley is writing to enquire if an institution can be funded or a governmental program be created to aid the blind.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Govenor James Jones Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl627</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Law and legislation</term>
               <term>Society</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Oley, Jas. H.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl627a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Columbia</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Decr</abbr>
                           <expan>December</expan>
                        </choice> 22 1843</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Govr</abbr>
                        <expan>Governor</expan>
                     </choice> Jones,</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Will you pardon me for <unclear>attending</unclear>upon your notice, the fact, (unless I am misinformed) that no provision is made by Legislative enactment in this state, for the maintenance &amp; instruction of the blind. Surely they are a class of unfortunates that most justly claim our sympathy &amp; properly may demand protection &amp; support at the hands of an enlightened government. It would be alike creditable to your administration and to the Legislature of the state which ranks as fifth in the union in population, &amp; which falls behind none in sentiments of honor and justice that some provision be made for this purpose. If an institution cannot be established within the state for the blind, at least an appropriation might be authorized from the Treasury, to aid this unfortunate class in availing themselves of the benefits &amp; privileges of such institutions in neighboring states__</p>
            <p>In the multiplicity of cases which claim the attention of the statesman, it is not surprising if such a subject as this, should be overlooked. I have deemed it only necessary to present it to your notice, feeling confident that you will judge wisely whether to make any suggestion or not <pb n="2" facs="sl627b.small.jpg"/> to the Legislature now in session.</p>
            <p>Although I address you under your official title I wish this communication to be considered as entirely private &amp; confidential. If you do not deem it a suggestion worthy of notice, commit this to the flames and say nothing about it. I remain dear Sir very truly &amp; </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>sincerely <choice>
                     <abbr>yr</abbr>
                     <expan>your</expan>
                  </choice> friend</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Jas H. Oley</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl627c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>His Excellency</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Governor Jones</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
