<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl589">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1846 Jun. 8, Nashville, Tennessee [to] William. L. Marcy, Sec. of War / Aaron Brown   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Brown, Aaron</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl589</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1846 Jun. 8, Nashville, Tennessee [to] William. L. Marcy, Sec. of War / Aaron Brown</title>
               <author>Brown, Aaron</author>
               <date when="1846-06-08">June 8, 1846</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated June 8, 1846 from Tennessee Governor, Aaron Venable  Brown to the Secretary of War, William L. Marcy.  The subject of the letter concerns infantry troop formation, provisioning and movements in Tennessee. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Aaron V. Brown Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl589</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Military history -- 19th century</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Brown, Aaron V. (Aaron Venable), 1795-1859</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr90000566"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Brown, Aaron V. (Aaron Venable), 1795-1859</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl589a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Nashville Executive Office</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>June 8th 1846</date>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Honl Wm</abbr>
                     <expan>Honorable William</expan>
                  </choice> L. Marcy <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Sec</abbr>
                     <expan>Secretary</expan>
                  </choice> of War</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>On the 4. 5 &amp; 6th <choice>
                  <abbr>Inst</abbr>
                  <expan>Instant</expan>
               </choice> 12 companies of Infantry embarked from this place for <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N</abbr>
                     <expan>New</expan>
                  </choice>. Orleans</name> under your requisition of the 16th <choice>
                  <abbr>ult</abbr>
                  <expan>ultimo</expan>
               </choice>.  They were from Middle <name>Tennessee</name> &amp; being all here together &amp; uncertain, whether they would unite   (any portion of them) with any other troops of the States, they were organized into one Regiment  &amp; officered accordingly.  I provisioned them with ten days rations &amp; chartered Steam Boats for their Transportation to N. Orleans, ordering the <choice>
                  <abbr>Col</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> to report himself &amp;  Regiment to <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice>. Gaines for further orders &amp; the means of transportation to the Seat of War. 4 companies Infantry will be off in like manner from <name>Memphis</name> in a few days if not already gone, organized into a <choice>
                  <orig>Battallion</orig>
                  <reg>Battalion</reg>
               </choice> Four companies from <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>E</abbr>
                     <expan>East</expan>
                  </choice>. Tennessee</name> formed also into a Battalion  are descending the <name>Tennessee River</name> &amp; will be at Memphis in the course of about 2  weeks or a little more, where they will be dispatched after the others &amp; so soon as they overtake them the <choice>
                  <orig>Battallions</orig>
                  <reg>Battalions</reg>
               </choice> will be formed into a Regiment &amp; their organization completed. This has all  been done under my order no. 2 which I forwarded to you.  The cavalry companies will be at Memphis by the 15th  Inst. except three from E. Tennessee which will be there in a few days after  There to await the orders of <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Wool <lb/> you will perceive that <pb n="2" facs="sl589b.small.jpg"/> to make this prompt movement, that I found it necessary as directed by you in your letter of the 16th to appoint an Inspector to muster them into the service, there being no <name>United States </name>officer here for the purpose.  I have no doubt the duty has been well done &amp; the companies selected very fine ones, both infantry &amp; cavalry__ The East Tennessee infantry &amp; the cavalry every where I concluded to muster into service near their homes instead of waiting until the general Rendezvous at Memphis The latter place is 4 or 500 miles from the homes of many of them &amp; such as could not pass muster would be often in a deplorable condition at that distance often without the means of return.  Besides this, it would often happen that volunteers could not have money enough of their own to defray their expenses that distance when mustered into service the State could make advances under the head of Transportation &amp; provisioning, which the <choice>
                  <abbr>U</abbr>
                  <expan>United</expan>
               </choice>. States could refund.  For these &amp; other reasons not necessary now to be mentioned.  I made arrangements to muster the troops into the service before leaving their respective grand divisions of the state &amp; if you have any doubts about the propriety of my having done so, a little conversation with the President in relation to our geographical &amp; Civil Divisions will remove them I desire earnestly that you will give direction to the genl in command to permit the 2 Battallions to be united into a Regiment &amp; complete their organization</p>
            <closer>very respectfully <pb n="3" facs="sl589c.small.jpg"/> Your <choice>
                  <abbr>obt. Servt</abbr>
                  <expan>obedient Servant</expan>
               </choice>. <pb n="4" facs="sl589d.small.jpg"/> copy of <unclear>Letter to Sec of War informing him of the departure of the troops &amp; regarding the completion of the 2 regiment </unclear>
               <add>1846</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
