<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl326">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] ca. 1850 Washington [City, D.C.] [to Adam Fergusson] / Andrew Ewing   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Ewing, Andrew</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl326</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] Washington ca. 1850 [City, D.C.] [to Adam Fergusson] / Andrew Ewing</title>
               <author>Ewing, Andrew</author>
               <date when="1850">ca. 1850</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Andrew Ewing to Adam Fergusson. Ewing explains why he voted for a Whig candidate for clerk instead of the  Democratic candidate.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers </note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">IV-G-1 b2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl326</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee --Politics and government -- To 1865</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr2001010974"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Ewing, Andrew, 1813-1864</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl326a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Washington</name>
                     <gap agent="damage"/>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Enclosed you will receive a Bounty land Patent <gap agent="damage"/> of the Heirs of <name type="person">Samuel White</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>decd</abbr>
                  <expan>deceased</expan>
               </choice> on Military Land Warrant <gap agent="damage"/> W ½ of Section 32. Township 47 of Range 28 in the Distric <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>t</unclear> subject to sale at <name type="place">Clinton</name>
               <name type="place">Missouri</name> Please acknowledge the <gap agent="damage"/> immediately. Your other Papers to <name type="person">Mr Edwards</name> have been re<gap agent="damage"/> of the result of which you will be informed immediately on th <gap agent="damage"/> to me —</p>
            <p>You will <unclear>perceive</unclear> by the Newspapers that I voted on the last Ballot for <name type="person">Thomas J Campbell</name>. Whig of <name type="place">Tennessee</name> and elected him clerk. I do not know how this may suit the views of my Democratic friends in Tennessee but my action was predicated on the clearest and most satisfying view of my duty and upon this I must stand or fall — <name type="person">Mr Forney</name> of <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Penn</abbr>
                     <expan>Pennsylvania</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> was the the Democratic Candidate for clerk. I voted for him two weeks and during twenty <choice>
                  <orig>ballottings</orig>
                  <reg>balloting</reg>
               </choice> continuously. on the day before Mr Campbells election several Northern Democrats deserted Mr Forney and left him only 96 votes and it was evident that his chance of election was utterly hopeless. yet he would not withdraw and there was danger that the Whigs and Free Soilers would unite and elect a Free Soiler as they had already tried to do in the person of <name type="person">Solomon Forte</name> — Under these circumstances the House being disorganized the business of the Country stopped. every thing deranged and no prospect of any Democrat being elected <pb n="2" facs="sl326b.small.jpg"/>
               <gap agent="damage"/> Southern Democrats voted for Mr Campbell which brought him in <gap agent="damage"/> to of his election. Representing as I did a large Whig District <gap agent="damage"/> of whom voted for me through courtesy. Mr Campbell being <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>T</unclear> ennessee Whig and a good Southern man. his office being a <gap agent="damage"/> trial one involving in his election no principle of our Party. I thought <gap agent="damage"/> due to the Country and the People I represent that my vote <gap agent="damage"/> cast the election. Upon consultation with several <del type="overstrike">with</del> of my Democratic Colleagues from Tennessee they thought it right for me to vote for Campbell and it was done</p>
            <p>I trust my old friends will appreciate my motives</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Yrs &amp;c</abbr>
                     <expan>Yours etcetera</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Andrew Ewing</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
