<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc104">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1815 Apr. 12, Nashville, Tennessee [to] Colonel John Sevier, Knoxville, Tennessee / Judge Overton :a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Judge Overton</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc104</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1815 Apr. 12, Nashville, Tennessee [to] Colonel John Sevier, Knoxville, Tennessee / Judge Overton</title>
               <author>Judge Overton</author>
               <date when="1815-04-12">April 12, 1815</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated April 12, 1815 from Judge Overton to Colonel John Sevier.  The contents of the letter include instructions regarding a law suit.  </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">John Sevier Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-1941 b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">15</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc104</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Conduct of court proceedings</term>
               <term>Actions and defenses</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n89613198"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Overton, John, 1766-1833</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc104a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Nashville</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>April 12th 1815</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Yours from <name>Winchester</name> in <name>Virginia</name> has been duly <choice>
                  <orig>recieved.</orig>
                  <reg>received</reg>
               </choice>  The point on which the <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>dist</abbr>
                     <expan>district</expan>
                  </choice>
               </unclear>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>ct</abbr>
                  <expan>court</expan>
               </choice>. decided your case is the only one  on which <del>the</del> any person could for a moment entertain a doubt  nor could that doubt  win except for the interest which a third party had in the <unclear>liveless</unclear> land in this state  I mean the <choice>
                  <abbr>N</abbr>
                  <expan>Northern</expan>
               </choice> States, and I had always thought that it made no difference, but it <unclear>from</unclear> the Supreme Court thought otherwise</p>
            <p>It seems to me however that the decision can make no difference in the avant of the case, and that you certainly must prevail, on the ground that the warrants on which the grants issued, were genuine warrants- They were signed by the proper office I know for I have seen them in the office of the Secretary of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>No</abbr>
                     <expan>North</expan>
                  </choice> Carolina</name>.  It will be necessary that you make this proof by some person who has seen <name>Landon Carter</name> write, know his hand writing well and has seen the warrants in the office <pb n="2" facs="sc104b.small.jpg"/> of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>No</abbr>
                     <expan>North</expan>
                  </choice> Carolina</name>- You will also prove that <name>Landon Cartre</name> was the <unclear>entry taker</unclear> I think the words of Washington County will show this- If it does not, some person perhaps <unclear> Jos Green</unclear> knows he <unclear>was entry taker</unclear>
            </p>
            <p>Perhaps also the records will also show that the <unclear>rest</unclear> was recorded, which <choice>
                  <abbr>Jno</abbr>
                  <expan>John</expan>
               </choice> Carter said was not his fathers hand writing-as your Fan is <unclear>Clerk</unclear> let some man of <unclear>respectibility</unclear>
               <unclear>misput</unclear> the <unclear>clerks</unclear> books,  and see if the record from the books of the books of the record of the <choice>
                  <abbr>acct</abbr>
                  <expan>account</expan>
               </choice> does not appear to have been made at the time it purports to have been </p>
            <p>I would be will for either <choice>
                  <abbr>mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Lee or <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Hinet who have been clerks to the <unclear>commerce</unclear> of <choice>
                  <abbr>E</abbr>
                  <expan>East</expan>
               </choice>
               <choice>
                  <abbr/>
                  <expan>Tennessee</expan>
               </choice>. and knows how warrants filed from Carters books, - to be a witness at the trials-Either of them can <choice>
                  <orig>shew</orig>
                  <reg>show</reg>
               </choice> that nothing can be collected or inferred shewing that the Warrants were fraudulent from the Numbers of the warrants</p>
            <p>You can get some friend of respectable character, to go to <name>Raleigh</name>
               <pb n="3" facs="sc104c.small.jpg"/>  who knows <name>Landon Carter</name>'s hand writing well, having seen him write- Let him when there imprint each warrant and testify as to there being genuine, taking a note of the <choice>
                  <abbr>no</abbr>
                  <expan>number</expan>
               </choice> of each warrant, and quantity of <unclear>aris </unclear>
            </p>
            <p>You can have <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Jos Green also at the trial- It will be agreeable to you, and no doubt to all your friends, to have the case decided at <unclear>once viz</unclear> at next June term, and with some <choice>
                  <orig>acertion</orig>
                  <reg>assertion</reg>
               </choice> it can be done, and I  have no doubt it will <choice>
                  <orig>evintually</orig>
                  <reg>eventually</reg>
               </choice>
               <gap agent="damage"/> in your favor when at Raleigh <gap agent="damage"/> your friend will get the Secretarys Certificate, showing the <choice>
                  <abbr>no</abbr>
                  <expan>number</expan>
               </choice> of the <choice>
                  <orig>warants</orig>
                  <reg>warrants</reg>
               </choice> on which the grant issued, and quantity in each number- I shall be at <name>Knoxville</name> by the 25th this month, and if you desire it will call &amp; see you</p>
            <closer>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Yr</abbr>
                  <expan>Yours</expan>
               </choice>. very truly <signed>Judge Overton</signed>
               <add>The <choice>
                     <abbr>Hon</abbr>
                     <expan>Honorable</expan>
                  </choice>. <choice>
                     <abbr>Jno</abbr>
                     <expan>John</expan>
                  </choice> Sevier</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sc104d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>The <choice>
                        <abbr>Honble</abbr>
                        <expan>Honorable</expan>
                     </choice> John Sevier<lb/> Knoxville</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Judge <name>Overton</name> instructions respecting the suit with Polk</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
