<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl144">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Legal Contract] 1793 Mar. 10, [between] William Taitt, John Gordon, [and] Andrew Jackson   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl144</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50556059</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Legal Contract] 1793 Mar. 10, [between] William Taitt, John Gordon, [and] Andrew Jackson   </title>
               <date when="1793-03-10">March 10, 1793</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a contract between William Taitt, John Gordon, And Andrew Jackson. It is dated March 10, 1793, and is set to expire July 15, 1793. It involves the holding of a house, cellar, and a slave named Nelly, by Gordon for Taitt, for the duration of the contract.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">John Cocke Papers V-J-3</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">B:3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">F:9</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl144</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Legal documents</term>
               <term>Contracts</term>
               <term>Slavery</term>
               <term>Territory of the United States, South of the River Ohio</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl144a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <add place="top, right" rend="different hand, ink">[<date when="1793-03-10">March 10, 1793</date>]</add> Articles of an agreement entered into and concluded on between <name type="person">William Taitt</name>, Merchant, of the County of <name type="place">Davidson</name> and <name type="place">Territory of  The United States of  America South of the River Ohio</name>  of the one part; And <name type="person">John Gordon</name> and <name type="person">Andrew Jackson Esquire</name> of the County &amp; Territory aforesaid, of the other part, this <date when="1793-03-10">tenth day of March Anno Domini 1793</date>
            </p>
            <p>First It is Agreed on the part of the Said Taitt that he will deliver into the possession of the Said John Gordon merchandize as pr. Invoice of this date Signed by himself &amp; the Said Gordon and <name type="person">
                  <unclear>Howel</unclear> Tatum <choice>
                     <abbr>Eqr.</abbr>
                     <expan>Esquire</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> and lodged with these articles amounting, at the <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>
               <unclear>cost</unclear>, to Six hundred &amp; Seventy three pounds ten shillings &amp; three pence three farthings, <name type="place">Pennsylvania</name> currency as an advance of Eighty pounds Pr. Centum Amounting in the whole to the Sum of twelve hundred &amp; twelve pounds, six shillings and six pence three farthings Pennsylvania currency, and <unclear>pirwit</unclear> the said Gordon to have the <unclear>Year</unclear> of  his Stort, Houses &amp; <choice>
                  <orig>Celler</orig>
                  <reg>Cellar</reg>
               </choice> in the Town of <name type="place">Nashville</name>, <unclear>receiving</unclear> an Equal <choice>
                  <orig>Priviledge</orig>
                  <reg>privilege</reg>
               </choice> in the fire rooms &amp; <choice>
                  <orig>celler</orig>
                  <reg>cellar</reg>
               </choice> of the said Houses, for himself &amp; <name type="person">Andrew <unclear/> Esquire</name>; and that the said Gordon shall have the said Houses &amp; Celler and a negroe <unclear>cosman</unclear> named <name type="person">Nelly</name> free from rent or hire until the expiration of the Tour of this agreement, which is to be <choice>
                  <orig>consedered</orig>
                  <reg>considered</reg>
               </choice> to expire on <date when="1793-07-15">fifteenth of July</date> next, unless the said Taitt should return from Philadelphia or <name type="place">Knoxville</name> sooner, in which case the agreement is to expire on demand of the said Taitt</p>
            <p>Secondly It is agreed on the part of the said Gordon and Jackson, that the said Gordon shall re- <pb n="2" facs="sl144b.small.jpg"/> turn to the said Taitt the Houses <choice>
                  <abbr>celler</abbr>
                  <expan>cellar</expan>
               </choice> of Negroe (death excepted, in as good order as the expiration of this Agreement, as he receives them in, and  also as all the merchandize which at that time may remain unsold, at the same price he the said Gordon receives them at as Pr Invoice and for the merchandize sold the said Gordon &amp; Jackson is to pay the said Taitt at the Invoice price with the advance within one year from the receipt of  the merchandize one half of the amount in Cash and the other half in Certificates for Military Services performed, or which hereafter may be performed, by the  militia of <name type="place">Mero District</name>. And the said Gordon &amp; Jackson does further agree that the said Taitt shall have  as many of the goods mentioned in the aforesaid Invoice at the Invoice prices with the advance as he may want, not exceeding two hundred dollars, to discharge such contracts as the said Taitt may have heretofore made for merchandize — It is to be Observed that the certificates herein mentioned is to be paid unto the said Taitt at the time the merchandise unsold is delivered up: And all <choice>
                  <orig>houshold</orig>
                  <reg>household</reg>
               </choice> furniture left by the said Taitt with the said Gordon is to be returned at the same time; And in as good as when <choice>
                  <orig>recieved</orig>
                  <reg>received</reg>
               </choice>.</p>
            <p>Thirdly It is agreed on the part of the said Taitt that he will Receive from the said Gordon at the expiration of this Agreement, either in person or by Attorney, all the merchandise mentioned in the aforesaid Invoice, which remains unsold in the hands of the said Gordon, and which are in as good order as when received, at the same prices as charged in the said Invoice with the advance thereon calculated <add place="lower right corner">And</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl144c.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>And the said Taitt doth furthermore agree that the said Gordon, in case he should have made any contracts payable in merchandize, previous to the expiration of this agreement which the party has not received &amp; that the said Gordon in such case shall have  as many of the goods remaining on hand as the expiration of the Agreement, as the Invoice prices with the <unclear/> as will discharge such Contracts. And it is furthermore agreed by <unclear>I on</unclear> behalf of the said Taitt that in case he does not return to <name type="place">Davidson County</name> before the <date when="1793-07-15">fifteenth day of July</date> aforesaid and it shall then be the wish of the said Gordon to keep the Merchandize on hand at that time for any longer Terms he shall have it in his the said Gordons person so to do for such time as may be agreed on between the said Gordon and the said Taitts Attorney in fact upon the same Conditions as herein before recited subject how to be delivered within the time agreed on if requested by the said Taitt in case he returns sooner.</p>
            <p>Fourthly the said Gordon &amp; Jackson do hereby consider themselves bound as fully to deliver the goods  <unclear/> agreeable to the second clause of this agreement in case the said Gordon should be indulged with keeping them agreeable to the power given him in the last clause of article the third as if delivered at the time first mentioned.</p>
            <p>And for the true &amp; faithful performance of each and every part of this agreement the parties <unclear/> so each of them bind themselves, their &amp; each of their heirs executors &amp; administrators &amp; assigns to the other in the final Sum of five thousand hard dollars. In witness whereof the parties aforesaid have hereunto set their hands and seals this  <date when="1793-03-10">Tenth day of March Anno <gap agent="damage"/>
                  <unclear>Domini 1793</unclear>
               </date>
            </p>
            <closer>Signed Sealed &amp; delivered <lb/> in presence of } <lb/>
               <signed>H  Tatum</signed>
               <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>signatures and seals of William Taitt, John Gordon, and Andrew Jackson</unclear>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl144d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top ">P.S. It is the intent and meaning of the <gap agent="damage"/> agreement that the said Gordon is only to <gap agent="damage"/> washing &amp; cooking done for him free from  hereby the Negroe woman Nelly mentioned in the first article of the within agreement and no further authority over <choice>
                     <orig>hir</orig>
                     <reg>her</reg>
                  </choice>. witness our hands &amp; seals the day and date within written <add place="left of signatures">Signed Sealed &amp; delivered<lb/> in presence of } <lb/>
                     <name type="person">M Tatum</name>
                  </add>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                        <expan>William</expan>
                     </choice> Taitt</name>
               </add>
            </closer>
            <closer>
               <add place="top ">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>seal</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <lb/>
                  <name type="person">John Gordon</name>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>seal</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <lb/>
                  <name type="person">Andrew Jackson</name>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>seal</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <add place="upside down, bottom of page">
                  <name type="person">John M Crory</name>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>miscellaneous calculations</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <name type="person">J. Hunter</name>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>miscellaneous calculations</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <name type="person">John Garner</name>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>miscellaneous calculations</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <name type="person">Wm Cartalo</name>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>miscellaneous calculations</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
