<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc014">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Resolution] In the House of Delegates, 1800 Jan. 10: a
			 machine-readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Mays</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno>sc014</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50009163</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Resolution] In the House of Delegates, 1800 Jan. 10</title>
               <date when="1800-01-10">January 10, 1800</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This document is a resolution passed by the
				House of Delegates on January 10, 1800. The document summarizes preceding
				congressional acts regarding the cessation of the Southwest Territory from
				North Carolina in 1790, the establishment of "Walker's line" as the boundary of
				North Carolina in 1791, and the creation of the state of Tennessee in 1796. It
				was then resolved that three commissioners be appointed to meet with Tennessee
				commissioners regarding issues concerning the boundary line between the two
				states.</note>
               <note type="Collection">Virginia. General Assembly. House of
				Delegates</note>
               <note type="Box">n/a</note>
               <note type="Folder"> MS-792</note>
               <note type="Document"/>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee </term>
               <term>North Carolina </term>
               <term>Boundaries </term>
               <term>Legal Document </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc014a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>In the House of Delegates</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Friday, 
				  <date when="1800-01-10">January 10th 1800</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>Whereas it is represented to the present General Assembly, that
			 people living between what are called Walker's and Henderson's lines, so far as
			 the same run between the state of 
			 <name type="place">Tennessee</name> and this state, do not consider
			 themselves under either the jurisdiction of that or this state, and therefore
			 refuse the payment of any taxes to either of the said States, or to the
			 collectors of either for the General Government, because the state of 
			 <name type="place">North Carolina</name>, on the 
			 <date when="1790-02-25">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>twenty fifth</orig>
                     <reg>twenty-fifth</reg>
                  </choice>
				day of February 1790</date>, ceded the said State of Tennessee, then called the
			 
			 <name> Southwestern Territory</name>, to the Government of the 
			 <name type="place">United States</name>; and therefore the act
			 entitled "an act concerning the southern boundary of this state," passed on the
			 
			 <date when="1791-12-07">seventh of December 1791</date> , in this
			 legislature to establish the line commonly called Walker's line, as the
			 boundary between 
			 <name type="place">North Carolina</name> and this state, could
			 <add place="bottom right corner">only</add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sc014b.small.jpg"/> only bind the state of
			 North Carolina as far as her territorial limits extended on the line of this
			 state, and could not bind the said southwestern Territory, which had been
			 previously conveyed as aforesaid: And whereas since the said Cession the
			 General Government hath erected the said Southwestern Territory into an
			 <choice>
                  <orig>independant</orig>
                  <reg>independent</reg>
               </choice> state, by their act of 
			 <date when="1796-06-01">June the first 1796</date>, whereby it has
			 become the duty of the said State of Tennessee and of this state to settle all
			 differences between them with respect to the said boundary line.
               </p>
            <p>Resolved therefore, that the Executive be authorized and requested
			 to appoint three Commissioners, whose duty it shall be to meet Commissioners to
			 be appointed by the State of Tennessee to settle and adjust all differences
			 concerning the said boundary line, and to establish the one or the other
			 <add place="bottom right corner">of</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sc014c.small.jpg"/> of the said lines, as
			 the case may be, or to run any other line which may be agreed on for settling
			 the same; and that the Executive be also requested to transmit a copy of this
			 resolution to the Executive Authority of the State of Tennessee.
               </p>
            <p>
               <date when="1800-01-13">January 13th 1800 </date> Agreed to
			 by the Senate</p>
            <closer>
               <add place="left"> a copy </add>
               <signed>Attest 
				<name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm.</abbr>
                        <expan>William</expan>
                     </choice>
				  Wirt</name>
               </signed>
               <signed>Keeper of the Rolls.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
