<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl013"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1821 Aug. 25 [to] Capt[ain] John Donelson / Rachel Jackson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Jackson, Rachel</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl013</idno><idno>OCLC: 50008910</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1821 Aug. 25 [to] Capt[ain] John Donelson / Rachel Jackson</title><author>Jackson, Rachel</author><date value="1825-08-25">August 25, 1821</date><extent> 4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated August 25, 1821 from Mrs. Andrew  Jackson (Rachel) to her brother Captain John Donelson. The letter contains her views on the Seminole Campaign, her husbands troubles, and her grief over the death of her nephew.</note><note type="collection">Tennessee Historical Society</note><note type="box">B-4</note><note type="folder">725</note><note type="document">sl013</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Seminole Indians -- Wars</item><item>Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</item><item>Florida</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><orig reg="Pensecola">Pansacola</orig></addrLine></address><date value="1821-08-25">August 25- 1821</date><add place="under date">Box J1 No. 72 J</add> <salute>My Dear Brother</salute></opener><p>I have often thought I would sit Down &amp; write you a few lines so <orig reg="many">maney</orig> <orig reg="coming">comeing</orig> in to interrupt me and more then all that a mind never at rest, <orig reg="Oh">O</orig> what will our poor old sister say when she <orig reg="hears">hers</orig> the <orig reg="melancholy">mealancholey</orig> Death of her son He has found a grave in this land in this land of  <orig reg="strangers">stangers</orig>, he was<orig reg="perfectly">purfectly</orig> in his <orig reg="senses">sences</orig> to the last his lungs <orig reg="were">wer</orig> much affected&mdash; <name type="person">Dr Bronough</name> was very attentive <orig reg="to him">tehi</orig> Andrew waited on him Day and night indeed all was kind to them&mdash;&mdash; I have <emph>not</emph> enjoyed myself no was contented no health but I hope to see you all <orig reg="again">againe</orig> <orig reg="there ">ther</orig> never was a man more Disappointed than he has been in the first place he has not the power to<orig reg="appoint"> apoint</orig> one of his friends which I thought was in part the reason of his <orig reg="coming">comeing</orig> But far has it Exceeded Every Calculation it has almost taken His life&mdash; <name type="person"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> Call</name> says its <orig reg="equal">equel</orig> to the <orig reg="Seminole Campaign">Simenole Campaine</orig>, well I knew it would be a <orig reg="ruining concern">ruening concerne</orig> I shall not pretend to <orig reg="Describe">Disscribe</orig> the<orig reg="toil"> toile</orig> fatigue &amp; trouble, those Spaniards had as here Dye as give up their Country, he has had <orig reg="terrible">turrible</orig> <orig reg="senses">senes</orig> the <orig reg="governor">governer</orig> has been put in the <orig reg="Calaboose">Callibous</orig> <orig reg="which">wich</orig> a <orig reg="terrible">turrible</orig> thing <orig reg="really">realy</orig> I was <orig reg="afraid">afraide</orig> <orig reg="there">ther</orig> would be a <orig reg="rebellion">rebelion</orig> But the Spanish Troops <orig reg="were">wer</orig> all <orig reg="gone">gon</orig> to the Havannah Several officers remaining Here yet we have a hope of <orig>gitting</orig> out the first<pb n="[2]"/> <orig reg="October">october</orig> for home <name type="person">Little Andrew</name> and <name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo</abbr> Butler</name> has started for <name type="place">Tennessee</name> he was the most anxious creature I ever saw in my life <orig reg="They">Theay</orig> all begin to think with me that Tennessee is the best Country yet <name type="person">Stockley Hutchings</name> <orig reg="widow">widdow</orig> and <orig reg="family">famaly</orig> will return this fall poor thing  She expects her Brother to come for her tell our friends and all I hope to see them <orig reg="again">againe</orig> in our Country and to know it is the best I ever saw what a <orig reg="pity">pitty</orig> that some do not know when <orig reg="they">theay</orig> <orig reg="are">ar</orig> well <orig reg="off">of</orig> in this world <orig reg="they">theay</orig> not only hurt themselves but those that is innocent&mdash;But still all things worketh together for good&mdash; Say to sister Mary I have <orig reg="heard">herd</orig> but one sermon <orig reg="since">sine</orig> I <orig reg="heard">herd</orig> <name type="person">Mr Hoge</name> he promised me to come to this place in June but no he never came I have mourned for Zion my tears has ran down in the night season&mdash; Mr J has been very unwell no wonder my health is delicate&mdash; The Lord is my help in him will I trust &amp; I will praise him with joyful lips remember me to all my Dear friends the young ones <orig reg="oh">O</orig> how I want <add place="supralinear">to</add> hear them tell that Jesus the hope of glory is formed in them tell Brother Sunday I have many things to say to him&mdash; <orig reg="farewell">farwell</orig> my Dear Brother &amp; my you say as pious job I knew that my redeemer <add place="bottom of page">Cap John Donelso<gap reason="document torn" desc="Donelson"/></add> <pb n="[3]"/> liveth </p> <gap desc="page blank between top word and bottom signature"/><closer><signed><name>Rachel Jackson</name></signed><pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine><name><abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> John Donelson</name></addrLine><addrLine>State of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>mail <unclear>unk</unclear></addrLine></address><add place="right of address">Mrs. <emph>Rachel Jackson</emph>(wife of <abbr expan="General Jackson">Genl. J.</abbr>  to her brother <abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> Donelson</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
