<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl043"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1830 Nov. 7, Washington [to] Robert J. Chester, Jackson, [Tennessee] / Andrew Jackson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Jackson, Andrew</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl043</idno><idno>OCLC: 50029644</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1830 Nov. 7, Washington [to] Robert J. Chester, Jackson, [Tennessee] / Andrew Jackson</title><author>Jackson, Andrew</author><date value="1830-11-07">November 7, 1830</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written by Andrew Jackson to Robert J. Chester on November 7, 1830. In the letter, Jackson agrees to sell some of his slaves, one woman named Charlotte and her three children, to Chester for $800.00. Jackson also asks for Chester to send a certificate to him regarding a Colonel S. D. Hays on the matter of his sobriety and abilities as a surveyor. </note><note type="collection">Tennessee Historical Society</note><note type="box">Miscellaneous documents J1</note><note type="folder">44J</note><note type="document">sl043</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Slaveholders</item><item>Surveyors</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Washington</name> <date value="1830-11-07"><abbr expan="November">Novbr</abbr> 7th 1830</date> &mdash;</addrLine></address><salute>My <abbr expan="Dear">Dr</abbr> Sir</salute></opener><p>Your letter of the 25th ultimo has just been <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr> and I hasten to reply to it.</p><p>There are no complaints here against <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> Purdy</name>, nor have we <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr>, any intimation of his intention to resign &mdash; but should the office become vacant you may rest assured your enemy shall not be appointed.</p><p>I <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr> a letter from <name type="person">Mr Steel</name> my overseer informing me that <name type="person">Charlotte</name> had applied to you to purchase her, being discounted where she now is &mdash; I bought her being the wife of <name type="person">Charles</name> at his request, he appears now desirous that she with her children be sold &mdash; I have therefore come to the resolution to part with her. But from the great reduction of hands on my plantation by recent deaths since the first of the year <date value="1829-00-00">1829</date> &mdash; having lost set of my best hands. I was glad to hear that you had said to my overseer, that you would pay me here, so that I can get <name type="person">Andrew</name> to reinstate, Charlotte by purchase here <pb n="[2]"/> in due time to aid in the next years crop I have therefore concluded to let you have them, that is to say Charlotte with her three children for Eight hundred dollars, paid here in all the month of February next, and on your application for them, and <del type="overstrike">sends</del> &caret; <add place="supralinear">handing to Mr Steel</add> on a note payable in this Bank; &caret; <add place="supralinear">to me</add> with <name type="person">Doctor Butler</name> endorser, I have directed her to  to deliver them to you or if it will suit you better, to <orig reg="place">placce</orig> a note in Bank at <name type="place">Nashville</name>, due &amp; payable, by the <date value="0000-02-10">10th of <abbr expan="February">Febry</abbr></date> next, which will enable the cashier to remit a check for the amount to me her by the last of February, it will answer as I wish to send my son out early in March, by whom I would send the purchase in lieu of Charlotte &amp; her children</p><p>I give my overseer $500 per annum &amp; my hands have I decreased so much, that really this year with the bad season I will not clear from my farm what its <unclear>cuther</unclear> has cost me &mdash;</p><p>I think I have placed Charlotte &amp; her  children as low as they could be bought now here, &amp; sent to my farm, but I do it that she may be contented &mdash; let &caret; <add place="supralinear">me</add> hear from you on the receipt of this letter.</p><p>I wish you to say to <name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> S. D. Hays</name>, that he must get, &amp; send on here, as early as he can, testimonials of his sobriety &amp; <pb n="[3]"/> capacity as a surveyor, &mdash; This will be necessary, for so sure as an opportunity offers if one should, to give here a surveyors District, that in order to mortify me <del type="overstrike">that</del> his appointment will be opposed in the Senate &amp; <name type="person">Crockett</name> &amp; <unclear>Desha</unclear>, will represent him as intemperate. Let the recommendations be strong and go to his capacity, and ability to give the necessary <emph>Security, if required</emph>. This must be attended to early to be here by the middle or <date value="0000-12-20">20th of <abbr expan="December">Decbr</abbr></date> past if practicable</p><p>Present &caret; <add place="supralinear">me</add> to <name type="person">Betsy</name> &amp; the children all friends &mdash; to my good old friend <name type="person">Mrs Hays</name>, <unclear>Norcessor</unclear> &mdash; to <name type="person">Daniel J Hays</name> &amp; his sweet little wife, &amp; kiss my namesake for me: to the Doctor &amp; <name type="person">Patsy</name> &amp; Son, to <name type="person">Stockly</name> &amp; <name type="person">Lydia Jane</name> &amp; little Jackson and believe me <abbr expan="your">yr</abbr> friend</p><closer><signed><emph><name type="person">Andrew Jackson</name></emph></signed><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mr. Robert J. Chester</name> &mdash;</addrLine></address><pb n="[4]"/> <address><addrLine><name type="person">Robert J. Chester</name> <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Jackson</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Madison County</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">West Tennessee</name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
