<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl064"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1824 Nov. 27, Gainesboro, [Tennessee] [to] Postmaster General / Sam Smith : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Smith, Sam</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl064</idno><idno>OCLC: 50078664</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1824 Nov. 27, Gainesboro, [Tennessee] [to] Postmaster General / Sam Smith</title><author>Smith, Sam</author><date value="1824-11-27">November 27, 1824</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written by Sam L. Smith to the Postmaster General on November 27, 1824. In the letter, Smith informs the Postmaster General that on the mail route from Sparta, Tennessee to Tompkinsville, Kentucky, one mail carrier's horse died and another became sick and could not continue the route. He is concerned about the mail not continuing on its route to Meigsville and on to Tompkinsville. Sam Smith concludes the letter by asking the Postmaster General the appropriate age for a person to become a mail carrier.</note><note type="collection">Coffee Perkins Papers</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">19</note><note type="document">sl064</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Postal service</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Gainesboro</name> <date value="1824-11-27">27th <abbr expan="November">Nov</abbr> 1824</date></addrLine></address><salute>Sir</salute></opener><p>I have to report to you that a few weeks since the horse belonging to the mail carrier on the <orig reg="route">rout</orig> from  <name type="place">Sparta <abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></name> to <name type="place">Tompkinsville <abbr expan="Kentucky">Ky</abbr></name> died on the road in the <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood</orig> of this office while making a trip and thereby some <del type="overstrike">delay</del> <add place="supralinear">irregularity &amp; <orig reg="delay">dilay</orig></add> was occasioned in completing the trip <del type="overstrike">that it was not on</del> And I have further to report that on last Monday the mail carrier upon the same <unclear>rout reached</unclear> &amp; this office with a foundered horse (sick) and thereby some delay has again been occasioned in completing the Trip &mdash;</p><p>I did not think in either case <del type="overstrike">that it was</del> <orig reg="necessary">nessary</orig> to forward the mail by another person because I did not believe the public good required it &mdash; the mail is a very <orig reg="important">immportant</orig> one and at both times <del type="overstrike">when</del> at which the delay was occasioned there could not have been more than one or two very small packets in it <pb n="[2]"/> so that no injury could result either public or private &mdash;</p><p>I am informed by the carrier of the mail that he has not been able to call at <name type="place">Meigsville</name> for several trips for the want of a ferry boat to cross Cumberland River consequently he is <unclear>compelled</unclear>   to take a <orig reg="different route">diferent rout</orig> to Tompkinsville &mdash;</p><p>It could not be considered an <orig reg="entire">intire</orig> failure at either time not were they such occasioned by such circumstances as the Contractor could have <orig reg="controlled">controled</orig> at the time they <orig reg="occurred">ocured</orig></p><p>If the mail cannot be continued by Meigsville it is  unimportant to continue the <orig reg="balance">ballance</orig> of the <orig reg="route">rout</orig></p><closer><salute>I have the honor to be your <abbr expan="obedient servant">obt servt</abbr></salute><signed><name type="person">Sam L Smith</name></signed><address><addrLine>Post Master General</addrLine></address><add place="below address"><abbr expan="Post Script">PS</abbr> It would afford me some satisfaction to know at what age a person must be to make him competent to carry the mail Sam L. Smith</add> <pb n="[3]"/> Copy of a letter <lb/> to &rcub; <lb/> Postmaster <lb/> General <lb/> <date value="1824-11-27">27 <abbr expan="November">Nov.</abbr> 1824</date> <lb/> <hi rend="different hand, different ink"><emph>From Gainesboro</emph> <lb/> <unclear>Hertoned</unclear> <lb/> Jackson Co. <lb/>1824</hi></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
