<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2><teiHeader id="SL088"><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1833 Feb 15, Pebblehill Academy, Jefferson, Ten[nessee] [to] Mrs. Jane M. Foster, Nashville, Tennessee /   Robert C. Foster, Jr.: a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Foster, Robert C., Jr.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl088</idno><idno>OCLC: 50178265</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1833 Feb 15, Pebblehill Academy, Jefferson, Ten[nessee] [to] Mrs. Jane M. Foster, Nashville, Tennessee /   Robert C. Foster, Jr.</title><author>Foster, Robert C., Jr.</author><date value="1833-02-15">February 15, 1833</date><extent>2p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Robert C. Foster, Jr. to his mother Jane M. Foster, dated February 15, 1833.  The younger Foster writes that he misses his mother and hopes that she will get better as she appears to be suffering from cholera.</note><note type="collection">Foster Family</note><note type="box">Correspondence R. C. Foster</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">sl088</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Comfort letters</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Pebblehill Academy</name> <date value="1833-02-15">February 15th 1833</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Mother,</salute></opener><p>I was very sorry that I did not find a letter in the Post Office from some one of you, but <name type="person">Henry Crabb</name> received a letter from his Mother, and I was very glad to hear, that the Cholera was not as bad as it has been: it was reported that there was a few cases of the Cholera in   <name type="place"><orig reg="Murfreesboro">Murfreesborough</orig></name>, but I believe that it is a mistake.</p><p>I was in <name type="person"><orig reg="Murfreesboro">Murfreesborough</orig></name>on Saturday last and <name type="person">Aunt Peggy Taylor</name>  gave me the stocks which you had the kindness to send me; the velvet one was a great deal too large, but the other one fitted me pretty well.</p><p>Nothing would please me more than to receive a letter from you My Dear Mother, but knowing that you are generally unwell, I do not want you to write when you are unwell, for fear that you would fatigue yourself, but I hope that you will write to me before I return.</p><p>I want to see you all very much in deed, and you in particular, since I left home, I have found out since I have been up here that there's no place like Home; I <orig reg="like">lik</orig><name type="person"> Mr. &amp; Mrs Black</name>very well and I think that they are very fine people and they have treated me very well.</p><p>The session is only five weeks longer. I am very well. Give my love to all the family. Tell <name type="person">Mr. Douglass</name> that <name type="person">Henry </name>and <name type="person">John</name> are well. Tell Father that he must answer my letter,</p><closer><salute>I am your affectionate Son</salute><signed><name type="person">Robert C. Foster Jr.</name></signed><pb n="[2]"/><add place="top left of page" rend="different hand, ink"><address><addrLine><abbr expan="Robert">R.</abbr>C. Foster</addrLine><addrLine>Pebble Hill</addrLine><addrLine>Academy 1833</addrLine></address>  </add><address><addrLine><name type="place">Jefferson <abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="0000-02-16"><abbr expan="February">Feby</abbr> 16th</date></addrLine><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs Jane M. Foster</name></addrLine><addrLine>Care of <name type="person">E. H. Foster <abbr expan="Esquire">Esq</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name></addrLine><addrLine>Tennessee</addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
