<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl106"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1840 April 9, Cornplanter, [PA] [to] Margaret W. Bell,    near Charlotte, Tenn[essee] / Jane Bell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Bell, Jane</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl106</idno><idno>OCLC: 50489416</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1840 April 9, Cornplanter [PA] [to] Margaret W. Bell,    near Charlotte, TN / Jane Bell</title><author>Bell, Jane</author><date value="1840-04-09">April 9, 1840</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This a letter from Jane Bell to her sister Margaret dated April 9, 1840. Jane writes that she misses everyone and that she wishes that one of her family could visit her. She writes a lot about death and that this world does not leave enough time to prepare one's self  and one's soul for the inevitable. She shares in her sister's grief over the loss of their parents and hopes that they will be the better for it. She also worries over her own  husband's ill health.</note><note type="collection">Bell Collection, IV-H-1</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">1</note><note type="document">sl106</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Life change events</item><item>Pennsylvania</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Cornplanter</name><date value="1840-04-09">April 9th 1840</date></addrLine></address> <salute>My dear<name type="person"> Margaret</name>,</salute></opener><p>I know how much your warm affectionate heart must have  felt in your late severe bereavement, but why you should have been ignorant of its approach, when all the family knew it, You will forgive the <abbr expan="Doctor">Dr.</abbr>'s deception when you learn, that he kept <name type="person">Mrs. Hudson</name> in ignorance of her mother's approaching end. My heart is often with you, mingling my tears with yours, over the graves of our lamented parents, the recollection of their many  virtues, and the certainty of never again <unclear>beholding</unclear> them in this world, so completely  overcomes me, that I have frequently to seek a secret place to weep My poor husband has been made to drink  so deep of the cup of affliction, that I do not wish to <orig reg="increase">encrease</orig> his troubles by adding   mine, consequently I assume an air of cheerfulness often when my heart is sad. Your letter <orig reg="increased">encreased</orig> those feelings <pb n="[2]"/> when you spoke of <name type="person"><abbr expan="William's">Wm.'s</abbr></name> ill health. I do not know how you all feel on this subject, but I have always had a trembling anxiety lest he should not be <add place="supralinear">a</add> long time with us. My father's age and infirmities requiring just such a  person as <name type="person"><abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr></name> has always been  necessary to the comfort and happiness of the family. There is nothing could afford me so much pleasure as to hear of his becoming truly pious, and then whether his life be short or long, his surviving friends would have the happiness of   <orig reg="reflecting">refflecting</orig> that death had been his eternal gain. Grief  for our departed friends is certainly commendable, if it lead us to a close imitation of their virtues, and to realize the  uncertainty of life, and living in a constant <add place="supralinear">state of</add> <orig reg="preparation">preperation</orig> for death. Let us endeavour to make this improvement of our dear parents death, that we may have reason to say "it is good for us that  we have been afflicted." Poor <name type="person">Eveline</name> if <unclear>we</unclear> should lose her husband, with her large family she will <add place="supralinear">be</add> entitled to our warmest sympathy. I have not heard from <name type="person">Eliza Smith</name> for some time I frequently wish I had one of you here with me, and did <pb n="[3]"/> it not partake too much of a selfish feeling I would urge one of you to come. I have no inducement to offer, but the satisfaction of knowing that your society would add much to my happiness, as there are no other persons whom I could love with the same affection I have always had for you all, so there are none, whose society would afford me so much pleasure &mdash; Should you ever be <orig reg="separated">seperated</orig> from each other, you will better understand my feelings then you can at present.</p><p><name type="person">Mr. Bell</name> says I think too much <gap reason="document damaged"/> you all, but it has become a part of my nature that I could not love you less if I would. Were you here at present you would most likely take more interest in the improvements which are making then I do&mdash;  I feel that this world takes up too much of our time that should be given to our eternal welfare</p><p>Write soon, there is nothing gives me so much pleasure as a letter from home. <name type="person">Mr. Bell </name>unites with me in love to you all.<name type="person">  Martha</name> and <name type="person">Theodore</name> send theirs.</p><closer><salute>Ever my dear <name type="person">Margaret</name>, Your affectionate</salute><signed>Sister <name type="person">Jane</name></signed><pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine>Free &rcub; J. Bell. <unclear><abbr expan="Post Master">P. M.</abbr></unclear></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Cornplanter</name> <date value="1840-04-10">10 April</date></addrLine><addrLine><name type="person">Miss Margaret W. Bell</name></addrLine><addrLine>Near <name type="place">Charlotte</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
