<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl109"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>   [Letter] 1837 Sept. 18, Clover Dale, TN  [to] Miss Ann Jane Bell, Philadelphia /  C[aroline] D. Bell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Bell, Caroline D.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl109</idno><idno>OCLC: 50499244</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1837 Sept. 18, Clover Dale, TN  [to] Miss Ann Jane Bell, Philadelphia /  C[aroline] D. Bell</title><author>Bell, Caroline</author><date value="1837-09-18">September 18, 1837</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">The following document is a letter dated September 18, 1837, from Caroline D. Bell in Clover Dale, TN, to her sister Ann Jane Bell in Philadelphia.  In the letter, Caroline describes a  church camp meeting she had recently attended , in which 60 people had "professed religion."  Caroline further explains the nascent religious revivalism that had swept over the area and discusses more church revival meetings that were being planned.  </note><note type="collection">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">sl109</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Religious gatherings</item><item>Religious awakening</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Clover Dale</name><date value="1837-09-18"><abbr expan="September">Sept</abbr> 18 1837</date></addrLine></address><salute>My dear sister</salute></opener><p>As you know my aversion to letter writing, I deem it quite unnecessary to apologize for having delayed answering your letter sooner, and I hope you will not be unreasonable as to expect more than two or three from me in the course of a year, Papa is much better he is able to walk about the yard and he has been to the barn field once, he is reduced very much, and this is by far the severest spell he has had since we came to <name type="place">Tennessee</name>, the rest of the family are all very well; I have not been sick but one day since you left here and that was occasioned by eating <orig reg="too">tooo</orig> many of <name type="person">Allens</name> good apples. I wish you were now here to participate in the <orig reg="heartfelt">heart felt</orig> joy of many of our dear friends, who   professed religion last week at the <orig reg="Camp meeting">Campmeeting</orig> on <name type="place"><orig reg="Johnson's">Jhonsons</orig> creek</name> <del type="erasure"><unclear></unclear> with</del> <name type="person">Squire Caldwell</name>   &amp; wife <name type="person">Mary Campbell</name>, <name type="person">Sarah Cruse</name>, <name type="person">Fredonia</name> and <name type="person">Betsey Walker</name>, <name type="person">Eliza</name> and <name type="person">John J Hardwich</name>, <name type="person">Indiania Massie</name>, <name type="person">Tom Richardson</name> a brother of the <name type="person">Dr Prior Smith</name>, and <name type="person">Benjamin Robertson</name>, his wife had professed shortly before. The number of those that professed was estimated at 60, 40 of whom joined that church, I had forgotten to mention <name type="person">Mrs Davies</name>   and <name type="person">Allen Neslick</name> <name type="person">Araminto</name>  and <name type="person">Amanda</name>  were  very much affected, but on account of a promise their father exacted from them Wednesday morning they would not <add place="left margin">you must excuse bad composition, &amp; bad writing too for I cannot get a good pen We all join in best love to brother John &amp;  <abbr expan="Samuel">S.</abbr> &amp;  your <add place="supralinear">self</add> <lb/> yours affectionately <lb/> <name type="person"><abbr expan="Caroline">C</abbr> D. Bell</name>.</add> <pb n="[2]"/> go in to the altar, but <name type="person">Araminto</name> sent for <name type="person">Mr. Guthrie</name> to come to where she was sitting, to talk and to pray with her, <name type="person">Dr. Hudson</name> and <name type="person">Major Bell</name>  shed tears manfully.  When <name type="person">Ben Robertson</name> professed he was very anxious to see <name type="person">Chris Dickson</name>, but he was equally as anxious to avoid him, and although they were both on the same ground they did not meet <orig reg="until">untill</orig> the next day, and those that witnessed it say it was a very affecting scene.  At the close of the meeting, which commenced on the <date value="1837-09-08">8</date> and lasted <orig reg="until">untill</orig> the <date value="1837-09-13">13</date>, <name type="person">Prior Smith</name> stood upon a bench and prayed for and <orig reg="exhorted">exorted</orig> the Preachers &amp; Christians very much and said that it was right they should part to <orig reg="propagate">propogate</orig> religion for they were the salt of the earth, and <name type="person">John James</name>' excellent prayers for <name type="person">Eliza</name>'s conversion astonished them all very much.  <name type="person">Eliza &caret; <add place="supralinear">H</add></name> and <name type="person">Mary C</name> laughed and shouted very much indeed they were affected in the same manner they were when they took <unclear>either</unclear> <name type="person">Eliza</name> said she always thought she would cry when she professed religion but she did not feel like crying now.  There were a great many preachers present among the   <unclear>number</unclear> were <name type="person">Mr Burniep</name> &amp; <name type="person">Mr Ray</name>, the former has improved very much, but I think one of our circuit &caret; <add place="supralinear">riders</add> <name type="person">Mr Pope</name> excels him.  There is to be a three days meeting at <name type="place">New Hope</name> the third week in next month and if the neighbors will camp on the ground there will be  preaching as long as they can do any good or the people will attend The Methodists had an appointment for a two days meeting on <name type="place">White Oak</name> last month and the people appeared so anxious and willing to attend that it continued six days <pb n="[3]"/> and it is said 63 persons professed religion.  <name type="person">Mr Edwards</name> has been here, and we are all very much pleased with him.  <name type="person">Mrs Wade</name>  &amp; <name type="person">James</name>  , <name type="person">Mrs McLaughlin</name> &amp; daughter left here this morning after spending one day and two nights with us,  there has been a revival of religion at <name type="place">Spring Hill</name>.  We expect <name type="person">Mr Wade</name> &amp;<name type="person">Sarah</name>  the last day of this week <name type="person">Mr Mills</name> is gone to <name type="person">Kentucky</name>, <name type="person">Mr Hayes</name> a Presbyterian Preacher of <unclear><name type="place">Nashville</name></unclear> is to preach <name type="person">Mr Farrars</name> and <name type="person">Mrs Napiers</name> funeral at <name type="person">Squire Napiers</name> next month.  <add place="supralinear"><name type="person">Mr <abbr expan="Hays">H</abbr></name> was the person that connected <name type="person">B Robertson</name></add> I declare  you are a strange being and I always thought so, I suppose you could not see <name type="person">Mr Foote</name> &amp; <name type="person">Mr Shamran</name> because they were widowers, but why did you not see <name type="person">Mr Campbell</name>, &amp; <name type="person">Dr. Hill</name>  / if you were confined to your bed it should not be any <del type="overstrike">for</del> excuse for your not seeing a clergyman, particularly  an old acquaintance. I had no doubt but you <del type="erasure"><unclear></unclear></del> <add place="supralinear"><unclear>sorta quality</unclear> </add> would be mightily set up with the attentions of the first quality of <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>, but all <gap reason="document damaged"/> is the pleasure of seeing so many of our relations.  I have been <gap reason="document damaged"/> for an introduction to that celebrated correspondent of yours. <gap reason="document damaged"/> <unclear>24</unclear> <name type="person">Mr Vanbier</name>  returned the day before yesterday, we received the parcel you sent by him, and are very much pleased with the contents of it, I think I can wear one <unclear>pr</unclear> of the gaiter boots but <name type="person">Margaret</name>   cannot, <name type="person">Ellenora</name> will remain in <name type="place">Nashville</name> until the sickly season is over.  <name type="person">William</name>s Cap fits him very well.  There has been a subscription raised in <name type="place">Charlotte</name>  to the amount of 33$ for the purpose of building a shelter at <name type="place">New Hope</name>.   your friend <name type="person">Thee</name> subscribed <unclear></unclear> $.  <name type="person">Squire Caldwell</name> &amp; <name type="person">J  B Walker</name> are building camps on a large scale <name type="person">Mr Wells </name>&amp; <name type="person">Mrs Garret</name>  will commence building this week.  Every  person is going to <orig reg="camp meeting">campmeeting</orig> now for the express purpose of getting religion.  <name type="person">Mr Gould</name> &amp; <name type="person">John</name> are very sick at present <name type="person">Margaret</name> has received your  letter and will answer it after <orig reg="camp meeting">campmeeting</orig>.  The Dahlia has bloomed, it is a great large red thing but  <name type="person">Margaret</name> &amp; <name type="person">Mary</name> pretend to admire it very much.  Your friends desire to be remembered to you.  I have written this letter without <orig reg="copying ">coppying</orig> it so <add rend="different hand" place="left margin">* Not my fault but brothers. <abbr expan="Ann Jane Bell">A J. B.</abbr></add></p> <pb n="[4]"/> <closer><address><addrLine><name type="place">Charlotte <abbr type="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1837-10-07"><abbr expan="October">Oct</abbr> 4th 1837</date>&rcub;</addrLine></address><add place="right">25</add> <address><addrLine><name type="person">Miss Ann Jane Bell</name></addrLine><addrLine>Care of <name type="person">Dr John Bell</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Philadelphia</name></addrLine></address><add place="right of address" rend="different hand">Wrote to my father. <date value="1837-10-25">Oct. 25</date> <lb/> <abbr expan="Ann Jane Bell">A J.  B.</abbr></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
