<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl104"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1837 Dec 6, Cornplanter, [PA],  [to] Mrs. [Anne]  Walter Bell, Dickson county, TN / Jane Bell    : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Bell, Jane</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl104</idno><idno>OCLC: 50489217</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1837 Dec 6, Cornplanter, [PA],  [to] Mrs. [Anne] Walter Bell, Dickson County, TN / Jane Bell    </title><author>Bell, Jane</author><date value="1837-12-06">December 6, 1837</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Jane Bell in Cornplanter, PA, to her mother Anne Bell in Cloverdale, TN, dated December 6, 1837.  Jane has decided to marry Mr. Bell without her parents expressed consent, although she knows they do like him.  She believes she will not make a very good wife because she is sickly. Even though her new family has been very welcoming, she misses her  old family and friends and says that she will always consider Clover Dale her home. She also fears that her family  will not keep in touch as much as she would like.</note><note type="collection"> Bell Collection, IV-H-1</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">1</note><note type="document">sl104</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Marriage</item><item>Iron -- works</item><item>Pennsylvania</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Cornplanter</name> <date value="1837-12-06"><abbr expan="December">Decr.</abbr> 6th 1837</date></addrLine></address><salute>My dear Mother,</salute></opener><p> My brother and <name type="person">Mr Bell</name> have informed you of my being in this place. You no doubt think me to blame for taking such a step without consulting you and my father, indeed, no inducement which could have been offered, would have prevailed, had I been ignorant of your sentiments, but knowing <orig reg="your">you</orig> favorable opinion of <name type="person">Mr Bell</name> I  acceded to his proposals not without regret that you had not been formally consulted. A few weeks since, I had not the least idea of coming here before next spring if then, but all my pleas of  ill health your consent  <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;c</abbr> had no weight with <name type="person">Mr. <abbr expan="Bell">B.</abbr></name> as I told him a sickly wife would be no prize, but this situation is so healthy that he flatters himself with the hopes that my health will be <pb n="[2]"/> good. so long as I am able to talk and laugh he appears satisfied and I have learned not to complain.  We spent 2 days in <name type="place"><orig reg="Pittsburgh">Pittsburg</orig></name> at  <name type="person">Mr. <abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr> Bell's</name> where we saw<name type="person"> Mrs. Anderson</name> though not so pretty as when I last saw her,  is a very fine looking old lady for 65. she and Mr. <add place="supralinear"><abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr></add> Bell's family received me with much affection and there also I saw <name type="person">Mr. Bell's</name> son <name type="person">William</name> and his daughter <name type="person">Martha</name>, the latter is going to school in <orig reg="Pittsburgh">Pittsburg</orig> they both received me with so much cordiality as was quite gratifying, <abbr type="William">Wm</abbr>  lives at a <unclear>furnace</unclear> 3 miles from here but has been at this place since I came here, he says Mother so affectionately and respectfully that even the most fastidious would be pleased. <name type="person"> Wylie</name> is a very intelligent boy, and <name type="person">Theodore</name> is the most interesting one I have known ( The parson always <unclear><orig reg="exerted">exrehted</orig></unclear>)  had I met with him at an acquaintances,    I would have caressed him more than I do here, it shall not be said that I make great  pretensions. If the children would only call me Sister I should feel more at home <name type="person">Miss Gormly</name> has <pb n="[3]"/> lived so long in the family that she feels quite a sisterly regard for Mr. Bell and I dare say thinks herself in duty bound, to pay every attention to his wife, She attends to the domestic concerns, and I sew and knit as I did in <name type="place">Clover Dale</name> and read for Mr. <abbr expan="Mr. Bell">B.</abbr> as <gap reason="hole in document"/> I did for my father.  This is a handsome situation for Iron works, on the <name type="place">river <orig reg="Allegheny">Alleghanny</orig></name> The dwelling house is frame with five rooms, 2 <orig reg="downstairs">down stairs</orig> and 3 above it is not finished and they are building an addition of   4 rooms and when completed, will be quite a comfortable house. Mr. <abbr expan="Bell">B.</abbr> had his furniture brought from <name type="place"><abbr expan="Philadelphia">Phila</abbr></name>, carpets &amp; Piano <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;c</abbr>.  Tell M <gap reason="document damaged"/>  if she will only come out  here she may <gap reason="document damaged"/> on a sofa and read novels, or fancy herself a heroine of romance. I have been quite disappointed in not hearing from her before this, I have <add place="supralinear">been</add> here two weeks without receiving a letter, and find whether <name type="place">Clover Dale</name>, <abbr expan="Philadelphia">Phila</abbr> or Cornplanter,  to hear frequently from my absent friends is necessary to my happiness.  I had intended to have written you a letter instead of this scrawl, but we have had company till a late hour, and I shall have an opportunity of sending this to <name type="place">Franklin</name> early tomorrow morning, but I will write to <name type="person">Caroline</name> next week and as Postage will cost you nothing I wish you would keep a diary <pb n="[4]"/> of all that is passing at <name type="person">Clover Dale</name> and send me weekly. Tell <abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> <name type="person">Wylie</name> and <name type="person">Theodore</name> speak frequently of him, the latter is delighted with the idea of going with me to <name type="place">Tennessee</name> to see him. Mr Bell unites me in much love to every member of your family <add place="rotated 90 degrees CCW in center of page"><address><addrLine> Free &rcub;<name type="person"><abbr expan="Jane">J</abbr> Bell</name> <unclear><abbr expan="Post Master">P M</abbr></unclear></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Cornplanter</name> <date value="0000-12-04">4 <abbr expan="December">Decr</abbr></date></addrLine><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs Walter Bell</name></addrLine><addrLine>Near <name type="place">Charlotte</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Dickson County</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name></addrLine></address></add></p><p>Tell <abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> and all my sisters to write to me&mdash; I feel anxious to hear from home as the last  account of my father's health was not satisfactory. I shall always continue to call <name type="place">Clover Dale</name> home though I have every reason to believe that any exertion will be wanting on the part of this family to make me happy. I am my dear Mother</p> <closer><salute> your affectionate Daughter,</salute><signed> <name type="person"> Jane</name></signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
