<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl119"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1840 March 9, Clover Dale, [TN] [to] Ann Jane Bell, Cornplanter, PA / M[argaret] V. Bell   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Bell, Margaret V.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl119</idno><idno>OCLC: 50504897</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1840 March 9, Clover Dale, [TN] [to] Ann Jane Bell, Cornplanter, PA / M[argaret] V. Bell   :</title><author>Bell, Margaret V.</author><date value="1840-03-09">March 9, 1840</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Margaret Bell to her sister Jane Bell dated March 9, 1840. Margaret writes about her grief over the death of their father, followed unexpectedly by the death of their  mother. She includes notices of other people who have either died or are sick. She also mentions how favorable the weather has been for the crops and peaches. Their brother is giving a speech on temperance that Margaret wishes Jane could attend. She writes that it will be almost impossible for her to visit Jane , and that it is her wish for Jane and their brother Sam to come to Clover Dale for a visit.</note><note type="collection">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">10</note><note type="document">sl119</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>Bereavement</item><item>Temperance and religion</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Clover Dale</name>, <date value="1840-03-09">March 9th</date></addrLine></address><salute>My dear Sister</salute></opener><p> I received your letter the <date value="1840-02-11">11 of  <abbr expan="February">Feb,</abbr></date> last week, little did you think when you wrote it that, the next from <name type="place">Clover Dale</name> would contain such melancholy news we were prepared for the death of our Father, but not for our Mothers  Neither can we reconcile ourselves to the idea that she is gone not to return It was all so sudden, that it appeared at first like a dream, yet now at times we are constrained to believe it is all a reality we <orig reg="daily">dayly</orig> miss them more and more, Oh my dear sister I cannot <orig reg="describe">discribe</orig> my feelings, had I known as the others did that my Mother was dangerous, and was dying all day I think I would be better satisfied but <name type="person">Dr. Hudson</name> deceived me once and I do not think I can trust him again, he told me that the was she was not dangerous, and would <add place="supralinear">be</add> well in a few days, and as she  <orig reg="noticed">notised</orig> more that day than she had any day while she was sick, I thought she was getting better <pb n="[2]"/> <orig reg="until">untill</orig> she was gone, and then at first I thought she had only fainted. But they are both gone and deeply do we feel their loss, Some of our <orig reg="neighbors">neighbours</orig> think we ought not to stay so much at home, but we all think retirement best suited to our feelings we have not been from home, except to our nearest neighbours, <name type="person">Mr. Reynolds</name> who lost a child of 3 years old last week, we set up with it from Thursday night <orig reg="until">untill</orig> Sunday night when it died. it suffered very much and has not been well since it had the scarlet fever which was two years ago, <name type="person">William</name> received a letter from brother yesterday in answer to one he wrote the day <name type="person">Sally</name> wrote to you, we were disappointed in not receiving one from you. <name type="person">Major Bell</name> and family <add place="supralinear">have</add>  returned to the <unclear><name type="person">Narrams</name></unclear>, he has been very sick for some time,  it is thought he will never recover, <name type="person">Mrs. Garret</name>also is very sick, she &caret; <add place="supralinear">is</add> entirely blind at this time. There has been more sickness and sudden deaths in this country than <add place="supralinear">there</add> has been for some years, <name type="person">Squire Hardy</name> is dead, <name type="person">Mrs. Dabney</name> and <name type="person">Ann</name> are well I have not seen them in some time, <name type="person">Mary</name> was here a few weeks since, she has <pb n="[3]"/> grown and improved very much, <name type="person">Mrs. Carter</name> has <orig reg="another">a nother</orig> daughter, she has five, <name type="person">Mr. John Collier</name>has been quite sick for some months, her health is very delicate indeed, <name type="person">Anne West</name> died a few weeks since of the consumption, she was sick for some months, <name type="person">Williams</name> health is not very good this winter, he is subject to bad colds which make him feel very bad, he <orig reg="does">dose</orig> not look as well as usual, though he <add place="supralinear">is</add> busily <orig reg="engaged">ingaged</orig> on the farm, the weather has been so favorable for the last month, that some are almost ready to plant corn, Our peach <orig reg="trees">treas</orig> are in bloom, which is a month earlier than usual, brother is progressing very well <gap reason="document stained"/> his temperance <orig reg="speech">speach</orig>,  I wish very much  you would be here, to hear him on the 4th. Tell <name type="person">Martha</name> she must excuse me I cannot write to a person who I have never seen, but if she will visit us, I will then correspond with her, We wish it was convenient for you and brother <name type="person">Sam</name> to visit us, It appears more impossible now than ever our visiting you, when one or two is gone, the others are very lonesome we miss Mother and Father so much, that I cannot bear the idea of <orig reg="separating">seperating</orig> or leaving this place, which is dearer now than <add place="suparlinear">ever</add> <pb n="[4]"/> Your friends all desire to be remembered to you they are quite anxious to see you We all desire to be remembered to you all with much love,</p><closer><salute>I remain your sincere and affectionate sister</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Margaret">M.</abbr> V. Bell</name></signed><add place="center of page, rotated 90 deg."><address><addrLine><name type="place">Charlotte <abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1840-03-15">March 15th 1840 </date><add place="right of return address">&rcub;</add><add place="right of address">25</add></addrLine><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs. Ann Jane Bell</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Cornplanter</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Venango County</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Pennsylvania">Pa</abbr></name></addrLine></address></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
