<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl115"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1838 Jan 1,  Clover Dale, Ten[nessee] [to] Mrs. Ann  Jane Bell, Oil Creek, Venango Co.,  PA  / Margaret Bell    : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Bell, Margaret</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl115</idno><idno>OCLC: 50504035</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1838 Jan 1,  Clover Dale, Ten[nessee] [to] Mrs. Ann  Jane Bell, Oil Creek, Venango Co.,  PA  / Margaret Bell</title><author>Bell, Margaret</author><date value="1838-01-01">January 1, 1838</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Margaret Bell to her sister Ann Jane Bell dated January 1, 1838. Margaret and their mother are glad that Jane is happy in her new home, and they hope that the fresh country air will speed her recovery in a way that the city could not. She writes there are a great many weddings going on in Clover Dale. One of the grooms is the teacher at the new boy's school. There is also now a girl's school.  They celebrated Christmas differently, with prayer meetings instead of parties. She writes about who has received religion and how they have changed as a result. She also reports the death of a Mrs. Gould in her  post script.</note><note type="collection">Bell Collection  IV-H-1</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">10</note><note type="document">sl115</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Religious gatherings</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Clover Dale</name> <date value="1838-01-01"><abbr expan="January">Jan</abbr> 1st 1838</date></addrLine></address><salute>My dear sister</salute></opener><p>Your letter to Mother we received, which afforded us all much pleasure to  hear that you are pleased with your new home, as you are living in the country the hills, and woods no doubt remind you of  <name type="place">Dickson</name>. we hope the country will restore your health which the city air has failed to do, Mother is very anxious to know how the sabbath is spent at the furnace, and if there is a Church near you she also wishes to know if you have any <orig reg="neighbors">neighbours</orig> and how you are pleased with them. All your friends have expressed a great desire to see you, the first question is when did you hear from <name type="person">Ann Jane</name> and when is she coming to see you? There has been prayer meetings and sunday schools in <name type="place">Charlotte</name> this Christmas in place of balls and parties, There is at present a male and female school in <name type="place">Charlotte</name>, <name type="person">Mr. Lee</name> from <name type="place"><abbr expan="Rhode">R</abbr> Island</name>, a baptist preacher, and <name type="person">Mrs. Cain</name> are the teachers, they have <orig reg="separate">seperate</orig> schools, <name type="person">Mr. Lee</name> is a b<add place="supralinear">e</add>au of  <name type="person">Mrs. Fanons</name>, he is 10 years younger than she is, <name type="person">Sally</name> and myself was at the <unclear></unclear> of <name type="place">Harpeth</name> a few weeks since, and <orig reg="attended">atended</orig> a 2 day meeting, near <name type="person">Mr. Robertsons</name>, <name type="person">Major Evaline</name>  <pb n="[2]"/> <name type="person">Mary Bell</name>. <name type="person">Cornelia Carter</name>. and <name type="person">Mrs. <unclear>Rearveth</unclear></name> who was returning home from <name type="place">Nashville</name>,  accompany us to the meeting, <name type="person">Mary Bell</name> fell from her horse in to the river as we were going, and would have been drowned, but for the timely assistance of the Major. we stayed one night at <name type="person">Mr. Robertsons</name> and was very much pleased with our visit, Mr. <abbr expan="Robertson">R</abbr> is so much alter<add place="supralinear">e</add>d that you could not but  be pleased in his society, as the change for the better has <orig reg="rendered">renderd</orig> him quite sociable and agreeable <name type="person">Caroline</name> has been immersed and the children all <orig reg="christened">christined</orig> the change in her is very perceivable and the Major is an altered man, though he has not professed religion yet, he is anxiously seeking it, the children have grown very much since we saw them last. and have lost all their beauty, I can no longer boast of a pretty <name type="person">Bell</name> though the youngest is quite an interesting child, and is very much like his father. <name type="person">Evaline</name> has become very neat in her dress and house <name type="person">Mrs. Gould</name> is very sick at this time and has been for the last 2 or 3 weeks, they entertain very little hopes of her recovery at this time, it is by far the <add place="supralinear">most</add> severest attack she has ever had in <name type="place">Charlotte</name>,<name type="person">  Mrs. Walters</name> has been staying with her for some weeks, she has broke very much since I saw  her last, We spent our christmas very agreeably part of the time at <name type="person">Squire <orig reg="Caldwell's">Coladwells</orig></name>, and the rest at home with some of the <name type="place">Charlotte</name> gentry, and our country frie<add place="supralinear">n</add>ds <pb n="[3]"/> We have found the <name type="person">Smith</name> family to be quite agreeable particularly <name type="person">Prior</name> since his conversion, he <orig reg="exhorts">exorts</orig> and prays very well, You will be a little surprised to hear that <name type="person">Montgomery Caldwell </name>and <name type="person">Eizabeth Bell</name> are to be married the last of this month, his friends are not so very well pleased with his choice, particularly <name type="person">Mary</name> and <name type="person">Orville</name> they think <name type="person">Montgomerys</name> wife ought to be some what different, or rather superior I should have said, <name type="person">James Gould</name> has been courting <name type="person">Eizabeth</name> for the last 6 months and is very much disappointed to find <abbr expan="Montgomery">M</abbr> has cut him out, there  are several weddings on the carpet, <name type="person"><unclear>Missoura</unclear> Smith</name> and <name type="person">Theo Collier</name>, <name type="person">Mrs. Davis</name> &amp;<name type="person"> John Steel</name>,<name type="person">Mrs. Fanon</name> and <name type="person">Mr. Lee</name>, <name type="person">Dr. Hudson</name> has declined moving and intends farming and practising in this neighborhood, <name type="person">Dr. Carter</name> has just returned from <name type="place"><orig reg="Arkansas">Arkansaw</orig></name> with his negroes and is going to live in <gap reason="ink blot"/> <name type="person">Mr. Cunningham</name> is going to move tomorrow to <name type="place">yellow creek</name> he has purchased a farm in the <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood</orig> of <name type="place">Bolthrops</name>,<name type="person"> Capt. <add place="supralinear">William</add> Reynolds</name> is coming to live at the place he <orig reg="left">lift</orig>,  Dear sister I am a little surprised at you who knows my disposition so well and knowing <orig reg="too">tow</orig> that I am by nature a little inclined to be indolent  to sit me on a sofa to read novels would not do for me, I fear it would be indulging to, the pride in me which I am <orig reg="every">evry</orig> day said to possess to an eminent degree by those who do not know me as well as you do. I received a letter from <name type="person">Sarah Wade</name> they are all well <name type="person">Mr. <abbr expan="Wade">W</abbr></name> says he was acquainted with brother <name type="person">Samuel</name> <pb n="[4]"/> and sisters, that he is like all of the <name type="person">Bells </name>of our connection a very fine man, When you write let us know how brother <name type="person">John</name>and <name type="person">Aunt Williams'</name> family are, We are very anxious to know when you and brother <name type="person">Sam</name> are coming to see us, your friends are all very anxious to see him. all the family join with me in love to you and brother <abbr expan="Samuel">S</abbr> we are all well except bad colds</p>  <closer><salute>Your affectionate sister</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Margaret">M.</abbr> V. Bell</name>.</signed> <add place="center of page, rotated 90 deg. CW"><address><addrLine><name type="place">Charlotte <abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></name> </addrLine><addrLine><date value="1838-01-12"><abbr expan="January">Jany</abbr> 12th 1838</date>&rcub;</addrLine><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs. Ann Jane Bell</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Cornplanter</name> Post Office</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Oil Creek</name>.</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Venango County</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Pennsylvania">Penn.</abbr></name></addrLine></address></add> <name type="person">Mrs. Gould</name> died on the <date value="1838-01-04">4th </date>at halfpast 12 <orig reg="O'clock">Oclock</orig> at night her corpse was taken to <del type="overstrike">F</del> <name type="place"><orig reg="Nashville">Nashvill</orig></name> the next day <name type="person">Sally</name>has been staying with her all week and has not returned home,  yet,  so we do not know the particulars respecting her death, <name type="person">Sally</name> will write soon <signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Margaret V. Bell">MVB</abbr></name></signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
