<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "file:///C|/Program%20Files/SoftQuad/XMetaL%202/rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl116"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title> [Letter] 1838 March 28, Clover Dale, TN [to] Mrs. Ann Jane Bell, Cornplanter, Venango Co., PA / Margaret V. Bell    : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Bell, Margaret V.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl116</idno><idno>OCLC: 50504228</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title> [Letter] 1838 March 28, Clover Dale, TN [to] Mrs. Ann Jane Bell, Cornplanter, Venango Co., PA / Margaret V. Bell    </title><author>Bell, Margaret V.</author><date value="1838-03-28">March 28, 1838</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Margaret V. Bell to her sister Ann Jane Bell dated March 28, 1838.  Margaret writes that many of the weddings mentioned in her last letter did not happen. Mr. Lee has stopped preaching because people have stopped going to hear him. Apparently he did something the community did not approve of. He is still running the school, now with his new wife, Elizabeth Roberts. Margaret thanks Jane for the gifts she sent, especially some monogram thimbles and shields. The family's candidate for circuit court clerk, John C. Collier won the election. The family has been reading Young's Night Thoughts and greatly enjoying it. She writes of improvements to the farm and domestic chores. The family is well except their father who is weak and feeble. She also mentions a girl named Elennora as the belle of Nashville. </note><note type="collection">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">10</note><note type="document">sl116</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Religious thought -- 19th century</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Clover Dale</name><date value="1838-03-28">March 28th 1838</date></addrLine></address><add place="left margin">Give our respects to <name type="person">Miss Gormly</name>, Yours sincerely <name type="person">Margaret. V. Bell</name>.</add><salute>Dear Sister</salute></opener><p>It was not ingratitude in me nor neglect that I did not thank you for those articles, I thought <name type="person">Sally</name> told you how much we were pleased with our merino dresses and scarfs. belts. gloves. <unclear></unclear>. they are the <orig reg="admiration"><emph>miration</emph></orig> of the <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood</orig>, one of the scarfs are I think almost <orig reg="too">to</orig> fine for our present circumstances. As for the thimbles and shields, they fit as well as if you had our fingers to try them on The shields are something so new that some do not know what finger to put them on, or whether they are to go on the fingers or not, when I have mine on I find it so <orig reg="useful">usefull</orig> that I am at a loss to know how I used to do with out one. Our names I think looks very pretty on the thimbles, <name type="person">Caroline</name> tried the contents of the vial, once, but it did not have the desired effect. Those expected weddings which I spoke of in my last letter are all a blank <name type="person">Mr. Roberson</name> would not consent for <name type="person">Martha</name> to marry such a stranger as <name type="person">Mr. Lee</name>was then, his conduct since he has been in <name type="place">Charlotte</name> is not <orig reg="justifiable">justifible</orig> in a preacher, he has declined <pb n="[2]"/> preaching, or rather the people will not go to hear him. He was married last week to <name type="person">Elizabeth Roberts</name> <orig reg="niece">nice</orig> of <name type="person">Dr. Roberts</name>.<name type="person">Mrs. Lee</name> is to assist him in his school, she is to take charge of the female department <name type="person">Letticia <unclear>Trier</unclear></name> was married last week to <name type="person">John Ragan</name>, <name type="person">Sally Hundles</name> old beau, <name type="person">Squire Caldwell</name> gave them a dinner the next day, we were not  there, none but those in the immediate neighbourhood were invited, <name type="person">Mary C</name> has not  returned from <name type="place">Shelbyville</name>, <name type="person">Mrs. Hudson</name> has a daughter, A sister of <name type="person">Dr. Hudsons</name> is on a <orig reg="visit">visite</orig> there at present, she is not very young nor very pretty, but quite agreeable, And to use  the common phrase a very good ev<add place="supralinear">e</add>ry day sort  of a girl. <name type="person">Sally Adams</name> has lost a fine son, the Old Lady and <name type="person">Sam</name> was very much distressed because it was so <emph>pretty</emph>. Our new <orig reg="neighbors">neighbours</orig> are equally as good as <name type="person">Mr. Cunningham</name>. <name type="person">Mr. Collier</name> starts for the city in a few days; We have as usual at this season of the year been <orig reg="fitting">fiting</orig> fine all week There has been a great excitement for 2 months past respecting the candidates for the <orig reg="clerk">clirk</orig> of the circuit court. <name type="person">John C Collier</name> and <name type="person">Mr. James</name> were the candidates, but as might be expected <name type="person">John <abbr expan="Collier">C</abbr></name> was elected All we the friends of  <name type="person">Mr. <abbr expan="Collier">C.</abbr></name> left nothing  unt<add place="supralinear">r</add>ied which would promote his interest, Mother even went so far as to tell some if they did not vote for him never to come here again.</p><pb n="[3]"/><p><name type="person">Mr. Scott</name> is here <orig reg="occasionally">occasionly</orig> and is highly entertaining giving us quotations from <name type="person">Shakespeere</name> <name type="person">Milton</name> and <name type="person">Young</name>, he gave <name type="person">Sally</name> <name type="person">Youngs</name> Night Thoughts, we are all very much pleased with it, it is for who will give the most quotations from it, I am very much pleased with the Young Lady's Friend. <name type="person">Mary C.</name> thinks it is to strict, I have learned from it how to prevent the holes in the heels of my fine stockings, by lining them with the tops of old ones, We have just taken 40 yards of plain cloth out of the looms for sheeting  shirting and some very pretty corded skirts, Mother is drying blue. green. <add place="supralinear">and</add> copperas for our frocks, which we will put in the loom in a fen<gap reason="hole in document"/> is making a great many improvements <gap reason="hole in document"/> farm,  he has fenced  in the orchards and <gap reason="hole in document"/> back of the garden, including the <orig reg="corn lot">cornlot</orig> meadow and barn field all of which he intends <orig reg="putting">puting</orig> in corn, we have 3 new gates, which improves the looks of the place very much, one at the garden one at the draw bars , and the other at the new <orig reg="lane">lain</orig> between the garden and the orchard <name type="person">Will</name>, is the <orig reg="steadiest">steadyest</orig> and most industrious farmer in the county, he is also very economical he will not purchase an article in <name type="place">Charlotte</name> without paying for it, by selling corn and pork he has payed all of Fathers debts except <name type="person">Mr. Collier</name> I know you will rejoice  with us to hear he has a clear receipt from <name type="person">Henry Napier</name>, his account amounted to $149. <pb n="[4]"/> <name type="person">William</name> has not been in town for 2 weeks, we were then disappointed in not receiving a letter from you as we have not heard from you in some time. <name type="person">Will</name>, does not go to town only when he has very particular business, therefore you must not expect a letter <orig reg="every mail">evry male</orig>, We are all well, Fathers health is as good as usual, though he is weak and feeble, <add place="in center of page, rotated 90 deg. CW"><address><addrLine><name type="place">Charlotte <abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1838-03-30"><abbr expan="March">Mar</abbr> 30. 1838</date> &rcub; <add place="right of address">25</add></addrLine><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs. Ann Jane Bell</name>.</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Cornplanter</name>.</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Venango County</name>.</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Pennsylvania">Pa</abbr></name>.</addrLine></address></add> <name type="person">Elennora</name> is the belle of <name type="place">Nashville</name>, she dresses in the very extreme of the fashion, and coquets with every gentleman of her acquaintance, Your friends all desire to be remembered to you We all join in love to you and brother <name type="person">Sam</name>,</p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
