<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl124"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1839 Aug. 7, Clover Dale, TN [to] Mrs. Ann Jane Bell,  Cornplanter, PA / Sarah B.  Bell   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Bell, Sarah B.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl124</idno><idno>OCLC: 50591409</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1839 Aug. 7, Clover Dale, TN [to] Mrs. Ann Jane Bell,  Cornplanter, PA / Sarah B.  Bell</title><author>Bell, Sarah B.</author><date value="1839-08-07">August 7, 1839</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Sarah Bell to her sister Ann Jane Bell, dated August 7, 1839. Jane's infant has died and Sarah offers her condolences. She explains that though she wants to visit Jane, she cannot due to their father's illness.  She mentions a local election, the books the family has been reading, and the state of their horses. She writes about the illness of their brother William, and other illnesses and deaths in the community.</note><note type="collection">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note><note type="box">B:1</note><note type="folder">F:11</note><note type="document">sl124</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Comfort letters</item><item>Bereavement</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Clover Dale</name>. <date value="1839-08-07">August 7th 1839</date>.</addrLine></address><salute>My Dear Sister</salute></opener><p>It was with pleasure we received your letter to Margaret yesterday, having only received a few lines from brother Sam and that only stating the death of your child. we were in <orig reg="suspense">suspence</orig> and anxiously looked for one from you, knowing how easily Mother is alarmed you ought to have wrote two or three lines at least saying you were well. We all deeply sympathize, with you in your <orig reg="loss">looss</orig>, it would have given us much pleasure to have &caret; <add place="supralinear">seen</add> the dear little creature, Yet my dear sister why should you grieve so much now when it is taken away, as I hope there is no doubt on your mind but that it is happy, when our friends are taken away from us by the hand of death and we have doubts as to their situation in another world, then it is the human heart must <orig reg="bleed">blead</orig>, but when <del type="overstrike">the</del> our loss is their gain why should we <orig reg="grieve">greive</orig>. You say the company of one of us would do you good, with pleasure would I resign the good society and preaching which I now enjoy to be with you, if it would add to your happiness. yet my Fathers health would not at this time admit of it, I do not think it would be right for me to leave him at this time were it ever so convenient I do not feel satisfied to leave home one night at a time which I have seldom done for the last six <unclear>month</unclear> <add place="up left side of page and upper left hand corner"><abbr expan="Margaret">Mag</abbr> and I are going to <name type="person">Dr. Carters</name> <orig reg="tomorrow">to morrow</orig> to see <name type="person">Mrs Dabney</name>. My Fathers health has been much better this week than usual <abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr>  has been working near the house this week and he goes often to see him. The next time you write you must say when you are <orig reg="coming">comeing</orig>. The family all join me in love to you all. Ever your affectionate Sister<name type="person"> Sarah B. Bell</name>.</add><pb n="[2]"/> <name type="person">Miss Sally Walkers</name> little nephew<name type="person"> Mr. Gilberts</name> youngest child died last week, it went hard with Sally to give it up it had been a great deal of trouble to her, yet she said all she had done for it was a pleasure to her, I am truly sorry for her I can not look at her with out <orig reg="shedding">sheding</orig> tears it was a <orig reg="lovely">lovly</orig> little corpse, when I was laying it in the coffin I thought of yours. <name type="person">John James Hardwick</name> is also dead he died the fourth of July of a <orig reg="fever">feever</orig> in <name type="place">Mississippi</name>. I hope <orig reg="politics">politicks</orig> does not run so high in your <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood</orig> as it does here we have heard nothing else for the last three months the election took place last week, the Democrat party beat in this county, Your friend <name type="person">John C. Collier</name> and brothers have injured themselves by interfering in the election to much they belong to the whig party. Last winter I spoke of reading a new <gap reason="document damaged"/> novel the homeward bound which we all thought <gap reason="document damaged"/> very interesting, it had a sequel called the <gap reason="document damaged"/>ame as found, which we were anxious to see <gap reason="document damaged"/> <name type="person">Chambers</name> sent it up to us this evening I think <gap reason="document damaged"/>  like it as I see it ends just as I wished it. <gap reason="document damaged"/> have had a very good season here this summer <gap reason="document damaged"/> and every thing looks well, we are getting well off <gap reason="document damaged"/> the horse way, we have 4 good riding horses and  three colts, one will be large enough to ride next year. If you know how to make tomato catsup I wish you give me a receipt for making it, I  made some last week but it is not good. I made a mistake in writing this letter, but you must turn it till it comes night , it has been wrote a week but <abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr> could not go to town before this evening. <pb n="[3]"/> I do not think he gets any better, his cough is <orig reg="worse">wors</orig> than it has been for the last few weeks, he is scarcely able to walk a cross the yard without assistance, he lays in bed nearly half the day and is asleep most of the time, he is much changed since you left home. After reading your letter last evening, we all concluded it would do you good to visit us this fall, it would improve your health and add to your happiness, yet one thing we are certain of, that a visit from you and brother Sam would do our Father much &caret; <add place="supralinear">good</add> he often speaks of you and him, we are in earnest and think you ought to come as it may be the last time you will see my Father in this world which I think very likely, therefore I think you <orig reg="might">migh</orig> come. <name type="person">Mrs. Mills</name> says she wants to  hear of you coming to <name type="place">Dickson</name> if you knew how many were anxious to see you I think you would come. Caroline, Margaret, and William went to the campmeeting on <name type="place">yellow creek</name>, where they had some good preaching. <name type="person">Dr. Marable</name>was drinking which kept his family uneasy all the time, he told  the girls they had grown so pretty he did not know them at first, <name type="person">Mrs. Dabney</name> sent her love to you, and says when you come to Dickson she is coming to see you <name type="person">Mrs. Shed Bell</name>died two weeks since, it is a distressed family, I <orig reg="pity">pitty</orig> the old man as I heard he took it very hard, being blind he is very fretful and peevish, and though he has two daughters at home, they are too fond of visiting to confine themselves at home, but Mrs. Bell was always there</p>  <pb n="[4]"/><closer><add place="top, right of address">25</add><address><addrLine><name type="place">Charlotte <abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1839-08-11">Aug 11th 1839</date> <add place="right of return address">&rcub;</add></addrLine><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs. Ann Jane Bell</name>. </addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Cornplanter</name>.</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Venango County</name>.</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Pennsylvania">Pa.</abbr></name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
