<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl135"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1813 Sep. 30, Highwassee [i.e., Hiwassee] Garrison [to] Major General John Cocke / Return J. Meigs    : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Meigs, Return J.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl135</idno><idno>OCLC: 50548171</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1813 Sep. 30, Highwassee [i.e., Hiwassee] Garrison [to] Major General John Cocke / Return J. Meigs</title><author>Meigs, Return J. </author><date value="1813-09-30">September 30, 1813</date><extent>2p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Return J. Meigs, agent to the Cherokee Nation, to Major General John Cocke, dated September 3, 1813. Meigs writes that he thinks that  the Cherokee  who had volunteered to fight against the Creek should be put together and supervised by another Cherokee. The whole group should then come under the command of a United States citizen who is familiar with Cherokee fighting. He agrees with Governor Blount that the Cherokee expedition should be lead by Judge Cocke. </note><note type="collection">John Cocke Papers V-J-3</note><note type="box">n/a</note><note type="folder">8</note><note type="document">sl135</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Indian agents</item><item>Cherokee Indians -- Government relations</item><item>Creek Indians -- Wars</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place"><orig reg="Hiwassee">Highwassee</orig> Garrison</name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1813-09-30">30th September 1813</date></addrLine></address></opener><salute>Sir</salute><p>It was contemplated by me in <del type="overstrike"><unclear></unclear></del> the <orig reg="organization">orgenization</orig> of the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> who <orig reg="volunteer their">volantier there</orig>  service against the <name type="person">Creeks</name> to have them formed to Companies &amp; <orig reg="Battalion">Battallions</orig> property Officers by their own people <del type="overstrike"><unclear></unclear></del> in all the grades of Officers, so far as to <unclear>enclude</unclear> that of majors and that then the whole should be commanded &amp; lead by a  Citizen of the <name type="place">United States</name> whose experience in Indian warfare would qualify him for such a Command. Such Character I presumed might be formed without having any one individual in my mind. The above arrangement I <orig reg="previously">preeviously</orig> stated to the secretary of war who in answer to my letter made no observation relating to such an organization.  I concluded that he could not do otherwise than approve of it &mdash;</p><p>The proposition of the Governor in favor of <name type="person">Judge Cocke</name> to lead the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> in the expedition now beginning its movement is perfectly agreeable to me &mdash; and I will endeavor to make it agreeable to the Young Cherokee Officers who will bring forward their young men for the Campaign.</p><p>I have the honor to be with great respect</p><closer><salute><abbr expan="your obedient">yr. obt.</abbr> Servant</salute><signed><name type="person">Return J. Meigs</name></signed> <address><addrLine><name type="person">General Cocke</name></addrLine></address><pb n="[2]"/><address><addrLine><name type="person">Major General John Cocke</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Garrison <orig reg="Hiwassee">Highwassee</orig></name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
