<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl139"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>   [Letter] 1813 Nov. 7, Camp near Turkey Town [to] Major Gen[era]l John Cocke  / James White : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>White, James</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl139</idno><idno>OCLC: 50555389</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>   [Letter] 1813 Nov. 7, Camp near Turkey Town [to] Major Gen[era]l John Cocke  / James White</title><author>White, James </author><date value="1813-11-07">November 7, 1813</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">The following document consists of two letters sent to Major General John Cocke from James White.  The first is a letter White writes from a military camp near Turkey Town, dated November 7, 1813.  White discusses General Andrew Jackson's advancements at the present stage of the War of 1812.  The second letter is a copy of a letter written from General Jackson to White, four days earlier on November 4.  In that letter, Jackson describes his  army's advancement to Ten Island, as well as a very brief description of a battle between General Coffee and  Native Americans, in which all of the Native Amer. men were killed and the women and children taken prisoner.      </note><note type="collection">John Cocke Papers V-J-3</note><note type="box">3</note><note type="folder">8</note><note type="document">sl139</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Military supplies</item><item>United States -- History -- War of 1812</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>Creek Indians -- Wars</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine>Camp near <name type="place">Turkey Town</name> <date value="1813-11-07"><abbr expan="November">Novr.</abbr> 7th 1813</date></addrLine></address><salute><name type="person">Major <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> John <orig reg="Cocke">Cock</orig></name></salute></opener><p><name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Gen</abbr> Jackson</name> is <orig reg="encamped">encampt</orig> as You will see by his letter at the <name type="place">ten Island</name> and not crossed with his Army Only that detachment <orig reg="Believed">Beleived</orig> when I crossed the River that <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Jackson was Over and Advancing and that I could Junction with him Sooner by this <orig reg="Route">Rout</orig></p><p>I shall advance this Morning by forced marches to Join the <abbr expan="General">Gen</abbr> at the Ten  Islands say thirty Miles</p><p>I crossed the <orig reg="Wagons">Waggons</orig> on Canoes but Yours I expect is deeper loaded and it is a <unclear>bad place</unclear> it is said to be twelve miles from Turkey Town to <name type="place">Ratelifs</name>  which is on <abbr expan="General">Gen</abbr> Jacksons <unclear>trace</unclear> this is all I can say on this Subject Should you find good crossing where you are perhaps it would be the shortest <orig reg="Route">Rout</orig> for the Ten Island I sent an Order to <name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> <unclear>Weare</unclear></name> to March and Join me as I am in the Most exposed part of <orig reg="Route">Rout</orig> the delay I suppose he can account for Your presence renders it <orig reg="unnecessary">unessary</orig> and improper to give Any <del type="overstrike">and</del> Orders to troops with &caret; <add place="supralinear">You</add> back I hope you will <gap reason="hole in document"/>th <orig reg="pursue">persue</orig> me with force and add to it your presence speedily I am <orig reg="really">realy</orig> presenting a strange spectacle&mdash; advancing in an enemy country and so much of my effective force staying back the Indian force with no <unclear>Order</unclear> 400 &mdash; who are  <unclear><orig reg="attrocious">atrisious</orig></unclear> to go on</p><closer><salute>I am your Ever <abbr expan="Obedient Servant">Obd st</abbr></salute><signed><name type="person">James White</name></signed></closer></div1><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[2]"/><opener><address><addrLine>Copy Camp to <name type="place">ten Islands</name> <date value="1813-11-04">4 <abbr expan="November">Nov</abbr> 1813</date></addrLine><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> James White</name></addrLine></address><salute>Sir</salute></opener><p>Your letter of the 1st Instant was handed me last night by <name type="person">Mr. Rice</name> <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Coffee</name>  had just returned from the destruction of <name type="place"><unclear>Talleestatehee</unclear></name> I had detached him for the purpose with a part of his Brigade on the 2nd and on the Morning of the 3rd he Accomplished the Object <orig reg="completely">compleatly</orig>. &mdash; the Enemy fought with desperate Valor but <orig reg="were">where</orig> not  Able to &caret; <add place="supralinear">with</add> stand the coolness and intrepidity with which Assailed 186 <orig reg="were">where</orig> found dead on the field and about 80 taken prisoners the latter con<gap reason="document torn"/> wholly of women &amp; children it is believed none <gap reason="document torn"/> <orig reg="their">theire</orig> <unclear>warriors?</unclear> <orig reg="escaped">excaped</orig></p><p>I shall remain at this place of few days for the <gap reason="document torn" desc="purpose"/> of establishing a depot for <orig reg="provision">provission</orig> and here I shall expect to be United with by You My Ultimate Object You are <orig reg="Advised">Avised</orig> of &mdash; I am Very sorry to hear your <unclear>prod</unclear> is growing <unclear>scarce</unclear> particularly as I had en<gap reason="hole in document"/> a hope that you would be to bring on some supplies for me let me repeat my entreaties that you take every Measures in your power in cash Tennessee <orig reg="plentiful">plentifull</orig> supplies of all that an Army stands in Need of we are almost entirely destitute</p><closer><salute>(Signed)</salute><signed><name type="person">Andrew Jackson</name></signed><pb n="[3]"/> <address><addrLine>Major <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> John Cocke</addrLine></address><add>pr. Express <lb/> <name type="person">Mr. <unclear>Canrik</unclear></name></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
