<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl151"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1835, Jul. 22, Frederick[s]burg, [VA]   [to] Dr. J. Beckwith, Florence, Ala[bama] / Andrew B. B[eckwith] : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Beckwith, Andrew B.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl151</idno><idno>OCLC: 50563940</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1835, Jul. 22, Frederick[s]burg, [VA]   [to] Dr. J. Beckwith, Florence, Ala[bama] / Andrew B. B[eckwith] </title><author>Beckwith, Andrew B.</author><date value="1835-07-22">July 22, 1835</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Andrew B. Beckwith in Fredericksburg, VA to his brother Dr. J. Beckwith in Florence, AL, dated July 22, 1835. Andrew is updating his brother on the new of his friends and family, especially of the family's embarrassment caused by the behavior of their brother Butler.</note><note type="collection">Woods Family</note><note type="box">Abeel- Campbell</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">sl151</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Southern States</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place"><orig reg="Fredericksburg">Frederickburg</orig></name>, <date value="1835-07-22">July 22, 1835</date> &mdash;</addrLine></address><salute>Dear Brother:</salute></opener><p>I am happy to inform you that I arrived here on the evening of the 4th  July without accident to myself or horse, and  without the least inconvenience or sickness to myself or horse. I found <name type="person">Adelaide</name> and the children in perfect health, and the girls also. They have grown very much, you would not know the girls. I wrote <name type="person">Butler</name> on my arrival here, and awaited for him one week, <orig reg="when">whin</orig>  I became somewhat impatient,  I then went in search of him, and after two days hard riding I found him. He had met with an accident which had prevented him from attending to business for  some months and had two weeks prior to my arrival, engaged with a gentleman by the month. I told him and the gentleman that it was actually necessary for him to leave in a few days, &mdash; he told me he would try so to do on monday that was on Thursday, and that he would be up on Monday  the same day, in the Steamboat, but here it is near that day week and I have not seen or heard from him since. He seems to be anxious to go out, and says <name type="person">James</name> is determined to leave <name type="place">Virginia</name> this fall. I wrote <name type="person">Richard</name> to come up with <name type="person">Mary</name> as soon as possible, so I could fix her, by the time Butler was ready but I have not as yet heard of or seen  him. Our family are the most stupid and tardy species of  creation  His conduct here was of &caret; <add place="supralinear">the</add> cast you and myself judged it be. We were not mistaken in our suspicions, if <name type="person">Laura</name> and <name type="person">Rebecca</name> are to be believed. Adelaide says she thinks so too, but says the lowest and most vulgar were his associates &mdash;  He <pb n="[2]"/> came to her on Sunday to fix his clothes after <orig reg="idling">idleing</orig> all the week off which, she refused, as it was not of much consequence,   &mdash; She had done all the day before, as she thought. She sent for him and talked to him about conducting himself in the manner he did. He was driving a butchers cart about the town, and she was told of it, and sent for him and told him that he was disgracing his sisters, after which he left  &mdash; Driving a cart with meat to every one's door, without intending to learn the business. Watch him, he can do right if he wants &mdash; He thinks hard of Adelaide, Laura, and <orig reg="Rebecca">Rebeca</orig> because they would talk to him. <abbr expan="Laura">L.</abbr> and <abbr expan="Rebecca">R.</abbr> says he was very <orig reg="dissipated">dissepated</orig>. Adelaide got her cousin young <name type="person">Edwards</name> to see him start, and told him never to show his <emph>face</emph> in that <emph>place again</emph>!!!</p><p>Richard intends this fall to move South,  I  will see him, and talk to him. <name type="person">Dr. Buchanan</name> is very uneasy here, he told me in the street that he had to sell a negro or two a year to live.</p><p>Our conversation relative to my coming out there next spring meets Adelaide's wishes in every particular, her Brother has got his business in such a fix that he could not settle it up sooner than two years, though he intends to move to <name type="place">Alabama</name>, after he can settle his business. If you can purchase me a lot in that town below the <name type="place"><orig reg="Muscle">Mussel</orig> Shoals</name>or the other side of the River,  <del><unclear></unclear></del> <add place="supralinear">which</add> is to be sold in August, I think it would be desirable; It might be got cheap I think,&mdash; though you must judge whether lots purchased at the sale then will be an object hereafter. I only wish to <orig reg="remind">rimind</orig> you of it, and for you to act accordingly, for I should not like to improve others Lots. <pb n="[3]"/> I should not have known my children if they had not been with their mother. <name type="person">Richard</name> is the finest Boy in the State, &mdash; has more natural sense than any child I ever saw at his age &mdash; <name type="person">Virginia</name> equally as much so. <name type="person">Roger</name> left me about 60 miles the other side of <name type="place">Knoxville</name>, I had no company the rest of the way, nor I did not want any for I would have had to break my <unclear>mode</unclear> of travelling had I travelled with others. He is quite a fine fellow I think, &mdash; give my respects to him. &mdash; Adelaide sends her love to Sister and you and the children. Tell <name type="person">Clay</name> that Virginia is nearly as large as he is. Remember me to Sister and the Children, Hugs, <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;C</abbr> &mdash;</p><closer><salute>And believe me your Brother</salute><signed><emph><name type="person">Andrew B. <gap desc="Beckwith" reason="document damaged"/></name></emph> </signed><add place="post script"><name type="person">Dr. Fitzburgh</name> asked after you, and <name type="person">Mrs. Buchanan</name>. <unclear>Huch</unclear> tells a lie about Dr. Buchanan, the girls says he treats them as well as they would deserve. &mdash; Also she, <name>Mrs. <abbr expan="Buchanan">B.</abbr></name> <name><abbr expan="Andrew B. Beckwith"> A. B. B.</abbr></name></add><pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine><name type="person">Dr. J. Beckwith</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Florence</name>.</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Alabama">Ala.</abbr></name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
