<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl159"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1843 Jun. 28, Nashville, [TN] [to] Sarah B. Woods, Philadelphia, Penn[sylvania] / J[ane] W[oods]   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Woods, Jane</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl159</idno><idno>OCLC: 50565050</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1843 Jun. 28, Nashville, [TN] [to] Sarah B. Woods, Philadelphia, Penn[sylvania] / J[ane] W[oods]</title><author>Woods, Jane</author><date value="1843-06-28">June 28, 1843</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter to Sarah Woods from her sister Jane, dated June 28, 1843. Most of the letter is updating Sarah on the activities of the townspeople. Jane also tells Sarah that there is some question as to where Joseph will be spending the fall, if he will be sent away to school, stay with Maria Price, or stay home at Westwood. The death of Henry Stephens is reported. Jane also mentions that people are trying to build a Second Presbyterian Church.</note><note type="collection">Wood Family</note><note type="box">Foster-West</note><note type="document">sl159</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Religious facilities</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name> <date value="1843-06-28"><abbr expan="June">Jun</abbr> 28th 1843</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear <name type="person">Sally</name>,</salute></opener><p>We have only <orig reg="heard">herd</orig> once from you since you left, and that was from <name type="place"><orig reg=" Cincinnati">Cincinati</orig></name>, and I was <orig reg="thankful">thankfull</orig> to know you had got that far safe, after having had some alarms on the way I have been out to, <name type="place">Westwood</name>, several times since you left, they seem to be going on very <orig reg="smoothly">smoothely</orig> there, Aunt,<name type="person"> Jenny</name> is about looks very well and is attending to matters, and things, <name type="person">Adine</name> was in town all last week and staid with <name type="person">Agness <unclear>Trabue</unclear></name>, but both her children took bad colds and she feared they might have the croup,<name type="person"> Mr Courtney</name> was away and she was very unwell herself,; <orig reg="however">howeve</orig> on Sunday morning, he returned, and at noon, they all went out to Westwood, I went out the next day, and found, Adine taking <orig reg="medicine">medicin</orig>, <name type="person">Leize</name> had a high fever all the night before and was very <orig reg="fretful">fretfull</orig>, <name type="person">Josephin</name> was better, <name type="person">James</name> goes over to his place every day he has sent Aunt, <name type="person">Sarah</name>, and <name type="person">Maria</name>, over to clean the house, Maria took all the children, but <name type="person">Celia</name>, and <name type="person">Josephine</name> brought her to town to nurse the baby about the house <name type="person">Jo</name>, and <name type="person">Mr Branch</name> are going on tomorrow to, <name type="place">Sumner</name>, and  expect to be away two weeks or more her, little <name type="person">Theora</name>, has been very good   lately, I persuaded her to feed it, for I have thought for some &caret; <add place="supralinear">time</add> that she did not give milk enough for her, and ever since <pb n="[2]"/> she began to feed her she is better, and is thriving Jo &mdash; was at a party, here that we gave to <name type="person">Mr, Carry</name>, and at <name type="person">Mr, Nichols</name>, and <orig reg="stayed till">staid tell</orig> twelve <orig reg="o'clock">oclock</orig> and the babe slept all the time, last night it had a crying spell, and this morning she gave her some oil, which griped it <name type="person">Sarah</name>, was there and she said it <orig reg="cried">cryed</orig> very much, but I hope it will be better after the oil, <name type="person">Adin</name> and I drank tea with <name type="person">Maria Price</name> while she was in town, and she told me how much opposed you were to <name type="person">Josephs</name> going to, <name type="place">North, Carolina</name>, <name type="person">Mr. Woods</name> was exceedingly sorry that you did not talk to him on that subject before you left, as he was several times told you his plans, and beside he had made every arrangement <orig reg="arrangement for ">fer</orig> his going, and was in correspondence with some of the teachers, he has however, concluded, <emph>only</emph> on <emph>your</emph> account, to send him <emph>one</emph> session to, <name type="person">Mr, Hume</name> as he has several vacancies the next term, if he <orig reg="does">dose</orig> well, he may continue him longer, but I fear, he has  been so in the habit of <emph>not</emph> going to school half his time, that it will difficult for him to confine himself as he will have to do, with, Mr, Hume, for he tells Mr, Woods, that he gives an account of every day he is not there, and every bad  lesson he has, you had better write to Jo, and tell him, that his, Uncle, <orig reg="will">well</orig> be compelled to send him away, if he will not learn at home, Maria Price intends taking him to live with her, and I have no doubt, will do by him all you could wish, if he will submit to her <unclear>desire</unclear> and council, <name type="person">Mrs McCay</name>, is here from, <name type="place">St, Louis</name> is rather <pb n="[3]"/> out of health, and has come to see her brother, <name type="person">Dr, Jennings</name> the girls are going to see her this afternoon, Sarah and I will go some other time, poor, <name type="person">Henry, Stephens</name>, is dead he was buried on monday, there is a subscription going around for building a second, Presbyterian Church, <name type="person">Mr, Vancourt</name>, has been preaching the last two sundays a the place where they have a sunday school, <name type="person">Mr Louis Ervin</name> , was there on sunday last, and says that a church could soon be filled, and that their school is very large. Mr Woods and I intend riding out to <name type="place">White Creek Spring</name> this week, I am told that the accommodations <orig reg="are">or</orig>  so <orig reg="elegant">elligant</orig> that I am anxious to see it, and if  Mr Courtney likes it we will go there as soon as the weather is warm enough, the day you left is  the warmest  we have had since, I hope, <unclear><name type="person">Molena</name></unclear> , will remember her promise to me of writing for I shall be anxious to hear from you every week or two, give my kind compliment to <name type="person">Mr, Handy</name>, and do let me  know how, <name type="person">Isac</name>, is and whether he has gone home, and if <name type="person">Mr Morten</name> is confined, Sarah and the girls  join me in love to you all, little <name type="person">Joseph</name>, grows every day and is good as ever, we are all looking every day to hear of your safe arrival in, <name type="place"><orig reg="Philadelphia">Philadelph</orig></name> , should you see the, <unclear>Tajert</unclear>, tell them how much I long to <orig reg="see">se</orig> them wishing you every happiness and a safe return home </p><closer><salute>I remain affectionately your Sister</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="James Woods">J W</abbr></name></signed><add place="under signature"><unclear></unclear></add> <pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs Sarah B. Woods</name></addrLine><addrLine>138 Walnut <abbr expan="Street">St</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Philadelphia</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Pennsylvania">Penn</abbr></name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
