<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl153"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>   [Letter] 1818 Jun. 11, Lexington, [KY] [to] Mrs. Sarah B. Woods, Nashville, [TN] / C C : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>CC?</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl153</idno><idno>OCLC: 51106235</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>   [Letter] 1818 Jun. 11, Lexington, [KY] [to] Mrs. Sarah B. Woods, Nashville, [TN] / C C</title><author>CC </author><date value="1818-06-11">June 11, 1818</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated June 11, 1818 to Mrs. Sarah B. Woods from her sister who only signed the letter CC.  The letter from CC consists of numerous complaints about her health and finances.</note><note type="collection">Woods Family</note><note type="box">Abeel-Campbell</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">sl153</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Finance, personal</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Lexington</name> <date value="1818-06-11">June the 11 1818</date></addrLine></address><salute>Sister Sally,</salute></opener><p>Since you have been <orig reg="married">maried</orig> you abound in so much happiness that you hardly bestow a thought on <orig reg="anybody">any boddy</orig> else but Brother <name type="person">Robert</name>.  I have at length disposed of <name type="person"><abbr expan="Doctor">Doct</abbr> Campbell</name> to the <unclear>best</unclear> advantage but it has cost me many a painful thought.  I am now entirely destitute of a <orig reg="protector">protecter</orig>. <sic corr="it's">its</sic> true he was but a <orig reg="very">verry</orig> indifferent one but he <unclear>love the name</unclear>, I expect this year will just about break me I have taken a large house and give three hundred and fifty dollars for it. and have not many Boarders <name type="person">Tandy</name> and <name type="person">Bow <add place="supralinear">man</add></name> persuaded me to take it that the situation was such that I would get more Boarders than I could accomodated but I have not got them nor had the offer its the house that <name type="person">Margaret Mershen</name> lived <del type="overstrike">at</del>&caret;<add>in</add> my eyes are unusually bad this spring the doctor advise me to go to the blue licks but I <del type="overstrike"></del> have not the means to spare <name type="person">Dudly</name> advises me not to eat any meat drink no tea nor coffee nor smoke no <orig reg="cigars">segars</orig> them are things that I am particularly fond of  I have not tasted any of them for a week that and other things keeps me half my time with the<unclear> hypo,</unclear> <name type="person">Hannah</name> writes you had such a nice wedding her letter is filled with <unclear>premises</unclear> of Brother <unclear>Robert</unclear> and says he made her so many nice presents that she <pb n="[2]"/> could not name them tell her all she cannot find a name for to send to me and I will call them <unclear>pud</unclear> you must give a great deal of love to <name type="person">Jane</name> west tell her that I will write to her one of these days was any of you placed in a more unhappy situation than myself I think I could write <orig reg="very">verry</orig> <orig reg="cosolatory">consolatary</orig> and <sic corr="and">and and</sic> <orig reg="cheerful">chereful</orig> but knowing that <add place="supralinear">I am</add> <orig reg="worse">werse</orig> situated and in my own opinion as little deserving of it as any of you prevents my writing often &mdash; there is perhaps nine of you that pities me and says as <name type="person">Jenny Little</name> used to <unclear>no adds</unclear> I might of had better luck I am at times very unhappy but never murmur I have even thought Heavens punishment was <orig reg="just">gust</orig> but severe. I have <name type="person">Aunt Judy</name> young with me at present and she is to stay <orig reg="until">untill</orig> fall if I cannot get to the springs I want to get as far as <unclear>Parris</unclear> the stage is a very convenient way of going and very nice give my love to <name type="person">Hannah</name> <name type="person">Jack</name> and <name type="person">Franlin</name> and particular love to Brother Robert and <name type="person">Moses</name> I wish much to see you and <name type="person">Bob</name>. I suppose in October I &caret; <add place="supralinear">will</add> have  another long legged Brother but he will be the largest of any but he is much of a gentleman I assure you and quite handsome he will get <sic>the</sic> the worst of the bargain for you know she <add place="supralinear">Eliza</add> is lazy and trifling <pb n="[3]"/> do write soon and tell the girls to write we are all health except <name type="person">Norvel Woods</name> and myself <name type="person">Doctor Pindel</name> said I must take him with me to the spring he has a dreadful cough and fever as its not in power we will have to abide by the consequence</p><closer><signed><name>C. C.</name></signed><pb n="[4]"/> <add>Postmark 18</add><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs Sarah B. Woods</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
