<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl179"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1850 Feb. 4, Jackson, [MS] [to] Col[onel] Joseph Brown, Maury County, Tennessee / James Brown   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Brown, James</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl179</idno><idno>OCLC: 51173299</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1850 Feb. 4, Jackson, [MS] [to] Col[onel] Joseph Brown, Maury County, Tennessee / James Brown</title><author>Brown, James </author><date value="1850-02-04">February 4, 1850</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from James Brown to his father Joseph Brown dated February 4, 1850. James advises Joseph to stop helping his brother Randolph, and to tell him to  get a job, possibly as someone's apprentice. He informs Joseph that he will be loaning money to Mr. Love. James  also updates him on local politics and correspondences he has had with other people.</note><note type="collection">Joseph Brown Papers</note><note type="box">THS-JB</note><note type="folder">171-180</note><note type="document">sl179</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communications in the family</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><name type="place">Jackson</name> <date value="1850-02-04">4th <abbr expan="February">Feb</abbr> 1850</date> <salute>Dear Father</salute></opener><p>your <orig reg="favor">favour</orig> of 17th <abbr expan="ultimo">ult</abbr> was <orig reg="received">receved</orig> last night and in reply as to Randolph I would say that the best thing that can be done for him is to send him off, to seek his own fortune upon his own exertions, tell him to go to work, learn a trade or whatever else he may desire, that he need not expect any further aid from any quarter, other than his own exertion  It is useless to <orig reg="throw">thow</orig> pearls before swine, I would say to Mr. L<gap reason="document damaged"/> that I regret he has given himself and family <gap reason="document damaged"/> much trouble about him especially as he <gap reason="document damaged" desc="has"/> proved <gap desc="u" reason="document damaged"/> nworthy of the pains that <gap reason="hole in document"/> taken with him I hope he will <gap reason="hole in document "/> off <orig reg="immediately">immedialety</orig> to rely upon his <gap reason="hole in document"/></p><p> I had a conversation <gap reason="document damaged"/> <name type="person">Mrs McGehee</name>  on the subject of the money <gap reason="document damaged"/> Mr Love , it was then understood that along in January a draft would be sent to <name type="person">Mr Love</name> , but I do not know whether or not it has been done, I have written to Mr McGehee ( as he is not at home) on the subject <pb n="[2]"/> I shall see them pretty soon now and if the draft has not been sent I will endeavour to have it done We are progressing slowly in Legislature business in which the country at large is interested we have passed a <unclear>civil</unclear> law for <name type="place">Bolivar County</name>, and hope to get some aid from the state by way of taxes on his landed interest for all the Counties where <unclear>Laws</unclear> are necessary, we have a great many more friends for that scheme and the improvement of the navigation of our rivers than we had two years ago I met with <name type="person">Mr Murdock</name> here who informs me that sister nancy had sold some 6 or 8 negros, and hired out the <orig reg="balance until">ballance untill</orig> fall when she expects to move to <name type="place">texas</name>, she is living near <name type="place">Black Hawk</name> in <name type="place">Carroll County</name> for the present, I do not know whether Joseph is gone to texas or not </p><p>I had a letter from William a few days since saying the <gap reason="hole in document" desc="Miss"/> River was rising very fast , and <gap reason="hole in document "/> it would get up before all the <gap reason="hole in document" desc="c"/>  ould be finished, but they could <gap reason="hole in document "/> what was done all will when I <gap reason="hole in document "/> from home</p><closer><salute>yours <gap reason="hole in document" desc="tr"/>uly</salute><signed><name type="person">James Brown</name></signed><pb n="[3]"/><address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Joseph Brown</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Cave Spring</name> <abbr expan="Post Office">P. O.</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Maury County</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine></address><add place="upside down at bottom of page" cert="different hand, ink"><name type="person">Randolph Porter</name></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
