<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "file:///C|/Program%20Files/SoftQuad/XMetaL%202/rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl206"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1850, Feb. 25, Russellville, [KY] [to] Mary House, Nashville, Tenn[essee] / J. P. Ewing   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Ewing, J. P.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl206</idno><idno>OCLC: 51206272</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1850, Feb.25, Russellville, [KY] [to] Mary House, Nashville, Tenn[essee] / J. P. Ewing</title><author>Ewing, J. P. </author><date value="1850-02-25">February 25, 1850</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated February 25, 1850, from J. P. Ewing to Mary House in Nashville. Ewing mostly writes of the local news and personal announcements. He mentions the controversy over the newly proposed  Kentucky constitution, in relation to the Democrats, Whigs, and the slavery debate.</note><note type="collection">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note><note type="box">2</note><note type="folder">6</note><note type="document">sl206</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Kentucky -- Politics and government</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><unclear><name type="place">Russellville</name></unclear> <date value="1850-02-25"><abbr expan="February">Feb</abbr> 25th 1850</date></addrLine></address><salute>My Dear <name type="person">Mary</name> </salute></opener><p>On my return this fall, I found so many things pressing on me, that I <orig reg="deferred">defered</orig> writing till I could adjust matters, unless something <orig reg="compelled">compeled</orig> me to write &amp; promised myself to make amends after <orig reg="Christmas">Christmass</orig>.</p><p>But I have suffered much with pain in my head &amp; eyes since that time, &amp; am now just recovering from an attack until I am almost as bad a correspondent as yourself &amp; your mother, Indeed if it were not for the <abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> I should never write to either of you with any certain prospect of hearing from you.</p><p>But now the time has been so long since we heard, &amp; every now &amp; then I am <orig reg="interrogated">interogated</orig> about when I heard from you &amp; it is time I should respond &mdash; Very recently I wish I had something interesting to write you, but what could I have &mdash; This certainly has been the dullest winter for ma<add place="supralinear">n</add>y <name type="person">Presley</name> has been absent , &amp; Mr E &amp; <name type="person">Henry</name> has been a <orig reg="good deal">goodeal</orig> from home &mdash; They are winding up the store at <name type="place">Adairville</name> <pb n="[2]"/> <name type="person">Sophronia</name> <orig reg="stayed">staid</orig> with me two weeks of the time but she was somewhat gloomy &mdash; Her last child is married &mdash; Her baby, &amp; &caret; <add place="supralinear">he</add> just going to house keeping &amp; <name type="person">James</name>started to <name type="place">Arkansas</name> &caret; <add place="supralinear">this winter</add> with his family &amp; on his way he lost three negroes with Cholera &amp; he &amp; Lue were just recovering from an attack of the same, James &amp; <name type="person">Frank Snoden</name> located them in the fall, but did not take all their servants until James &amp; family went  down, &mdash; Frank lost several also &mdash; Some thirty had died on the boat before <abbr expan="James">J.</abbr> left it &mdash;</p><p>So your mother can see how she is blessed in having all, or nearly all of her children settled around her, &amp; doing well &mdash; We are all moving on much as usual &mdash; <name type="person">Mr J. B. Bihh</name> &amp; wife talks of going to <name type="place">New Orleans</name> shortly, If the Cholera does not deter them &mdash; <name type="person">Mrs. R. Bihh</name> is in usual health this winter &mdash; O we have had a wedding this winter, but a very still one, <name type="place"> Mrs. &caret; <add place="supralinear">J</add> Davidson</name> to <name type="person">George Grey</name> &mdash; I suppose you would like to hear something from <name type="person">Mrs <unclear>Mauy</unclear></name> &mdash; She is living at <name type="person">Mr Skyles</name> His last daughter was married this winter, &amp; they were anxious to have Mrs <abbr expan="Mauy">M</abbr> 's society  in <orig reg="their">thier</orig> loneliness &mdash; I think I have given you all the news that I am in possession of &mdash; Now let me entreat you to do the same &mdash; One thing however for the Capt &mdash; Our state as he will have seen <pb n="[3]"/> is in a perfect Commotion relative to this new constitution, Mr. E. was called out to address the people to day &caret; <add place="supralinear">against it</add> (being County Court day) &amp; it is thought from the signs of the times that <name type="place">Logan</name> will reject it by a large majority. How the state will go is yet doubtful, but the thing is very odious to many, &amp; the whigs particularly &mdash; They laid down thier arms &amp; made a truce with the democrats, &amp; united in this perplexing Slavery question, by which they got a majority of democrats in Convention, &amp; they have made a Constitution as they think for them selves but it suits no body well, for it is perfectly uninteligible that &caret; <add place="supralinear">is</add> many Clauses, &amp; they differ among themselves as to the constitution But its a model for schools in its grammatical structure, or arrangement, to be handed down to our childrens children as a specimen of our literature &mdash; But enough, we are already sick of it, &amp; God <orig reg="forbid">firbid</orig> the people may not be sicker</p><p>My paper runs short but permit me to ask the <orig reg="favor">favour</orig> of you to get the <orig reg="receipt">reciept</orig> for the rough &amp; ready cake, &amp; enclose it &mdash; I lost the one I had &mdash; Also ask your mother about the Peas she gave me, what they are good for, How to grow them, &amp; who the four papers were for?</p><p>Please remember me kindly to all, &amp; particularly to Sally &mdash; Are you not coming over soon ? Will not <name type="person">Mary Bostic </name>come with you? <pb n="[4]"/> Remember, you nor mother are to come without Sally &mdash; Make our ackowledgements to our friends <orig reg="generally">generly</orig> for thier kind attentions to us, while there, &amp; to Mr. Bostic's family particularly</p><closer><salute>Yours as Ever</salute><signed><name type="person">J. P. Ewing</name></signed><add place="center of page, rotated"><address><addrLine> <name type="person">Mrs Mary House</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name></addrLine></address></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
