<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl203"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1830 Oct. 24, Louisville [KY] [to] John Overton, Nashville, Tennessee / Fort[unatus] Cosby Sr.   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Cosby, Fortunatus</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl203</idno><idno>OCLC: 51196840</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1830 Oct. 24, Louisville [KY] [to] John Overton, Nashville, Tennessee / Fort[unatus] Cosby Sr.</title><author>Cosby, Fortunatus </author><date value="1830-10-24">October 24, 1830</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated October 24, 1830, from Fortunatus Cosby Sr. to his friend John Overton. Cosby is asking Overton to help his son William gain entrance to West Point. He is also requesting that Overton help his grandson Robert get into the navy.</note><note type="collection">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note><note type="box">2</note><note type="folder">5</note><note type="document">sl203</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>United States Military Academy</item><item>United States</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Louisville</name> <date value="1830-10-24"><abbr expan="October">Oct.</abbr> 24th 1830</date></addrLine></address><salute>My Friend</salute></opener><p>I wrote you not many days past giving you such information respecting the nature of the claim of the City of <name type="place">Cincinnati</name> to the public wharf  &amp; ferry. as you desired a confirmation of which, I have Just received </p><p>Should you desire more specific information write me and it shall be obtained &mdash;</p><p> I believe You made some acquaintance with my third Son <name type="person"><abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> Vernon Cosby</name> who was 17 years old the 22d day of this month, and I believe I expressed to you my opinions, my views &amp; hopes respecting him, he possesses very fine talents, is an uncommonly laborious student and his conduct in every respect Just as we could desire it, he is a good Classic Scholar, &amp; is now Studying <orig reg="Mathematics">Mathematicks</orig> Astronomy <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;c</abbr> in which he is making great progress &amp; possesses as his Teacher informs me uncommon taste &amp; talent for those Studies &mdash; When you were here I informed that I had <pb n="[2]"/> intended to put him in a Counting house but his friends &amp; particularly his Tutor <orig reg="oppose">oppos</orig> it they are of opinion that could he finish his education at <name type="place">West Point</name> that he might and would become a &caret; <add place="supralinear">more</add> valuable member of Society. under these impression and his own desires &mdash; I have again to trespass on Your goodness, in most earnestly requesting you to endeavor to get him admission to West Point &mdash; The Secretary of War is yet in your <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood</orig>  I believe Should you succeed, I entertain no doubt but that he will reflect credit on your friendship &mdash;  I believe I informd you that my Grandson <name type="person"><abbr expan="Robert">Robt</abbr> Todd</name> was 12 years old; I incline to believe that his genius is best suited to the Navy, where you have promised your aid to get him admitted should it be desired &mdash; which I hope you will be enabled to do, unless you should believe that I am drawing to largely on your goodness &amp; the patronage of the <pb n="[3]"/> Government &mdash; Write me as soon as convenient</p><closer><salute><abbr expan="Your">Yr.</abbr> Friend </salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Fortunatus">Fort.</abbr> Cosby</name><abbr expan="Senior">Sr</abbr></signed><pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine><name type="person">John Overton </name><abbr expan="Esquire">Esq</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><abbr expan="attorney">att</abbr> at Law</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine></address><add place="up left margin">Fortunatus Cosby <lb/> Oct 24th 1830</add> <add place="down right margin ">(miscellaneous notes)</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
