<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl209"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1842 Nov. 29, Nashville [TN] [to] S[ally] B. Hamilton, Russelville, Kentucky / Jos[eph] D. Hamilton, Jr.   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Hamilton, Joseph Jr.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl209</idno><idno>OCLC: 51206646</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1842 Nov. 29, Nashville [TN] [to] S[ally] B. Hamilton, Russelville, Kentucky / Jos[eph] D. Hamilton, Jr.</title><author>Hamilton, Joseph Jr. </author><date value="1842-11-29">November 29, 1842</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is  a letter from Joseph D. Hamilton to his mother Sally B. Hamilton, dated November 29, 1842. He writes that he has been busy with his studies. He writes that at school, one should study not only the books, but also how virtue is connected to them. Joseph updates his mother about the local news. He mentions that a count from Poland has been lecturing about  the life of Emperor Bonaparte, whom he has fought alongside.</note><note type="collection">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note><note type="box">2</note><note type="folder">9</note><note type="document">sl209</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Kentucky</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><name type="place">Nashville</name> (Meris School House)<date value="1842-11-29"><abbr expan="November"> Nov</abbr> 29 1842</date><salute>My Dear Mother</salute></opener><p>I have been procrastinating for some time and if excuses were not so common, I should <orig reg="attempt">attemp</orig> to give one; but you know a school boy who has <orig reg="studies">studdies</orig> to attend to, has not much time to Spare otherwise than at his studdies. All persons when grown up to the age of maturity regret that they did not devote more of their time to study. Therefore it is eventually requisite that we should study <orig reg="while">whyle</orig> we have an opportunity and whyle we are at it we should not only study the <orig reg="contents">contense</orig> of school books, but we should <del type="overstirke">we</del> connect virtue with it and make that the principle part of our <orig reg="studies">studys</orig> for unless virtue is well studied and fully practiced, we are apt to be led astray; for you know the many vices and evils connected with the habit and dispositions of the &caret; <add place="supralinear">youth</add> of the <orig reg="present">pressent</orig> age that it is almost impossible to escape.</p><p>But virtue ever simple and credulous; conscious of new designs of itself it <unclear>suspits</unclear> none in others; it wears no guards before its breast; <orig reg="every">evry</orig> door and portal and avenue of the heart is thrown open and all who choose it enter. One of the most vicious and poisonous &caret; <add place="supralinear">enemies to virtue</add> and one whose fang enters deeper in the heart than any other, is the craving appetite <del type="overstrike">for</del> for wealth: and we too frequently &caret; <add place="supralinear">stop to</add> look upon the many splendid objects which it presents to our mind; and then it is that we are allured from the path <sic corr="of">of of</sic> virtue, into the dark and <orig reg="merciless">mercyless</orig> ways of vice, without one bright <del type="overstrike">ry</del> ray of hope to cheer us on our way. Knowledge is <pb n="[2]"/> standard and virtue is my guide</p><p>I frequently think of Old Rock Cave and the many <orig reg="happy">hapy</orig> hours that I have spent there; but those happy hours have &caret; <add place="supralinear">passed</add> never more to return and when I &caret; <add place="supralinear">think</add> that I shall never enjoy them again, it produces quite melancholy feeling</p><p>We are all getting <orig reg="along">a long</orig> finely for the hard times: lots of weddings and as the saying is parties till you cant rest. The <abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> says that he believes he will sit out as a widower: and I <del type="overstrike"></del> believe there is something <del type="overstrike">it</del> in it, for the <orig reg="topic">topick</orig> of his conversation is women, and he thinks about them, talks about them, goes to see them, and is so much taken with them, that he even goes so far as to dream about them and Ill tell you what? he is just about the greatest ladies man you ever heard of Tell sister if he does not get see her very soon, my opinion is that she will be a grass widow. Since all this marrying and party business has commenced <del type="overstike">I am</del> I have got in the notion myself, so you must not be <orig reg="surprised">supprised</orig> if I bring <name type="person">Mrs Hamilton</name> over next <orig reg="Christmas">Christmast</orig> I have become quite a gallant since you left here; I go to see the girls very frequently and if you were to see me gallant them up Church street, you would not know me.</p><p>I was down to see Miss <name type="person">Mary Craighead</name> the other evening and she desired to be remembered to you and sister. Bob and Kitty are as <orig reg="loving">loveing</orig> as ever and I rather believe if he <del type="overstrike">were</del> <add place="supralinear">were</add> in <del type="overstrike"></del> <orig reg="business">buisness</orig>, that we would have a wedding <name type="person">Mr Pillar</name> was down to see Susan the other day; the <name type="person">Hill</name> family seem to be very much pleased with him and I think if he would say the word, we would have a match</p><p><name type="person">Count <unclear>Lemonovske</unclear></name> (from <name type="place">Poland</name>) has been lecturing <pb n="[3]"/> upon the life of <name type="person"><orig reg="Bonaparte">Bonepart</orig></name>, he is said to have been with him in all his battles</p><p>I shall <orig reg="endeavor">endeavour</orig> to come over there <abbr expan="Christmas">Ct</abbr> &mdash; as I suppose you will want some help about <orig reg="moving">moveing</orig>: <orig reg="and">an</orig> I do assure you that it will give me great pleasure to render you any assistance that may be in my power for I know a child can never pay the debt that is due a parent. I will feel <orig reg="thankful">thanful</orig> that I have it my power to render you assistance</p><p>Tell sister that she must comply with <orig reg="her">hir</orig> promise to write to me. I do want to see you all, and especially little jimy; I expect he has forgot me but you must talk to him about me, that he may <gap reason="hole in document"/> Little Mary an Lenora are very fat and plu<gap reason="hole in document"/> the <orig reg="healthiest">healthyest</orig> children you ever saw</p><p>Say to Tom an <gap reason="hole in document"/> that they must write to <gap reason="hole in document"/> (both of them) Will promised to <orig reg="favor">favour</orig> me with a <orig reg="correspondence">corespondence</orig> <gap reason="hole in document"/> I was over there last summer The arrangement <gap reason="hole in document"/> he was to write the first letter which I have <gap reason="hole in document"/> received. Tell him that it is high ti<gap reason="hole in documennt"/> as writing <gap reason="document damaged"/> fail to answer this <gap reason="document damaged"/></p><p>Sister Emeline wishes you to get her some Eggs and send over before Ct . It is <orig reg="getting">geting</orig> late and I must stop. All of our family send their love to you and sister give my love to all of our relations. give my respects to <name type="person">Mr &amp; Miss Dawson</name> <del type="overstrike">Harriette</del> and all the <orig reg="balance">ballance</orig> of the family also to <name type="person">Mr &amp; Mrs Freman</name> <pb n="[4]"/> and all other enquiring friends. Give a thousand bushels of love to sister and jimmy. kiss jimmy a hundred times for me. <orig reg="Accept">Except</orig> &caret; <add place="supralinear">for your self</add> all the love that a loveing son is able to bestow</p><closer><salute>Your affectionate Son</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Joseph">Jos.</abbr> D.  Hamilton Jr</name></signed><add place="middle of page, rotated"><address><addrLine>Mrs <name type="person"><abbr expan="Sally">S</abbr> B Hamilton</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Russellville</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Kentucky</name></addrLine></address></add></closer></div1></body></text> </TEI.2>
