<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl219"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1844 Jul. 17 Nashville [TN] [to] Mary House, Louisville, Alaba[ma] / Geo[rge] W. House   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author> House, Geo[rge] W.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl219</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1844 Jul. 17 Nashville [TN] [to] Mary House, Louisville, Alaba[ma] / Geo[rge] W. House</title><author>House, Geo[rge] W.</author><date value="1844-07-17">July 17, 1844</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from George W. House to his wife Mary House, dated July 17,1844. He sends updates on friends and family events. He informs her that some people want to buy her guitar. He complains of being lonely. He writes about a recent parade and public speech that he enjoyed. He mentions the passing of  resolutions in Laurence County on the Texas Question. He also mentions the Philadelphia riots involving the Nativists and Irish Catholic immigrants.</note><note type="collection">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note><note type="box">3</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">sl219</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name> <date value="1844-07-17">July 17 1844</date></addrLine></address><salute>My dear Wife</salute></opener><p>I received yours of the 9th <abbr expan="instant">inst</abbr> on the 13th &mdash; it was not mailed until the 11th which accounts for the delay of two days &mdash; Your trip must have been most exceedingly tiresome, but am glad that you and our jewels arrived safely and that the children behaved so well &mdash; I am anxious to hear from you; now &caret; <add place="supralinear">that</add> you are once more upon the land of my youth &mdash; The place of  Many bright and happy associations, and to Know that you and our little pledges are well &mdash;</p><p>The next Morning after you left Lousa addressed you a note, asking for the receipt book &mdash; I <orig reg="answered">answerd</orig> it, and stated you Were half Way to <name type="place"><abbr expan="Alabama">Alaba</abbr></name> James, says she abused you not a little for going off Without sending her Word of it &mdash; I told James, you had requested Horace, on saturday before, to let her Know your intention of leaving when you did &mdash; I cut out all my receipts and sent her the book &mdash;</p><p>We have a great crowd at the Academy &mdash; <name type="person">Julia <unclear> Davis</unclear></name> left last week, and is boarding at Stones &mdash; I walked home with her on Sabbath evening last, and remained until Church hour &mdash; If the Crowd should Continue to increase <pb n="[2]"/> I shall have to decamp myself &mdash; Julia will take the Wardrobe, at 12&dollar; I spoken to Workman for another larger to cost 14&dollar; &mdash;</p><p><name type="person">Messy Elliot</name> &amp; Sapsey want to buy your Guitar &mdash; write to me, and say whether or not you will sell it &mdash; Nick waits on me, and We get along better then I at first anticipated &mdash; I need not tell you, I am very lonesome <name type="person">Mr Scorel</name> expects to leave about the last of the Month &mdash; for his Wife &mdash; Mother is going to send by him a power of attorney to receive the legacy Coming to her in <unclear>Va</unclear> Mr Scorel says he will attend to it with pleasure &mdash; His (<abbr expan="Scorel">S</abbr>'s) wife has Written to him to Come on as soon as Possible she is anxious to get back &mdash; We had a <unclear>grand</unclear> parade on Saturday last, and a speech from <unclear><name type="person">Missy Foster</name> &amp; Jones</unclear> , there was a large crowd, and a great many ladies in attendance, some <unclear>with</unclear> "Coon tails" in their <unclear>bonnets</unclear> &mdash; <name type="person">William Forte</name> left for <name type="place">Clarksville</name> on Monday &mdash; Kitty is at <name type="place">Tyres Springs</name> with her <name type="person">Aunt McNairy</name> &mdash; She requested Forte to Write to her while he was gone to <name type="place"><abbr expan="Kentucky">Ky</abbr></name> &mdash; and told him She Would answer his letters &mdash; So you See how things are likely to turn out &mdash; <name type="person">Gus Forte</name> and his sister Elizabeth, have been here a week Elizabeth graduated at the "Columbia Institute" &mdash; <pb n="[3]"/> and has grown Considerably She is quite tall &mdash; and a very good looking brunette &mdash; Gus, health is rather delicate, and he speaks of spending a month or two here and at the different watering places in this state &mdash; You must enquire for papers, as I shall send you one or more every Week &mdash; In <name type="person">Mr John J <unclear>Crittenden's</unclear></name>  letter to the ladies who petitioned him to be here on the <date value="1844-08-21">21st <abbr expan="August">Augst</abbr></date> he stated their Wish to be his pleasure, he says that the despotism of the ladies, is the only despotism he acknowledges he is  a very gallant gentleman &mdash;</p><p><name type="person">Mr Elliott</name> Will Most Certainly vote for <name type="person">Mr Clay</name> &mdash; The resolutions passed at a meeting in <name type="place">Laurence County</name> <abbr expan="Alabama">Alaba</abbr> on the subject of <name type="place">Texas</name> and <unclear>disunion</unclear> , has Completely Killed off these humbugs with him &mdash; and Will do it With every honest man Who loves his country and her institutions &mdash;</p><p>We have nothing new &mdash; The riots have commenced again in <name type="place"><abbr expan="Philadelphia">Philda</abbr></name> in a shocking Manner</p><p>We are all well &mdash; Make my love to all my relatives Kiss James &amp; Sally for me, tell James he must be good boy, mind his Ma, and Grandma and not fight the little negroes, tell all the negroes howdy for me</p><closer><salute>With My prayers for Your health and happiness I remain affectionately Your husband</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="George Washington">Geo, W,</abbr> House</name></signed><add place="under salute"><unclear>Tell</unclear> sister; Ann is nearly crazy for a letter</add> <add place="up left margin">Remember me affectionately to all the children &mdash;</add> <pb n="[4]"/> <abbr expan="Post Script">P. S.</abbr> Mother desires her love to You the little ones, and to my mother &mdash; when You wish to get home again Write to me &mdash; I will try and come for You &mdash;<orig reg="although">altho</orig> not very active &mdash; I will be a protection &mdash; <salute>Yours ever</salute><signed><abbr expan="George">G</abbr></signed><add place="center of page, rotated"><address><addrLine>Mrs<name type="person"> Mary House</name></addrLine><addrLine>Care of <name type="person"><abbr expan="Samuel John">Saml J</abbr> House</name> <abbr expan="Esquire">Esq</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><orig reg="Louisville">Loueville</orig></name></addrLine><addrLine>Near <name type="place">Huntsville</name></addrLine><addrLine>Alaba</addrLine></address></add> Should You be trouble with the Piles send to <name type="place">Mr Coltach</name> in Huntsville for a Bit of ointment and tell him to charge it to me &mdash; <signed><abbr expan="House">H</abbr></signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
