<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl228"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>1850 Jun. 8, Athens [to] Mary House, Nashville, Tenn[essee] / George [House]   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>House, George</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl228</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1850 Jun. 8, Athens [to] Mary House, Nashville, Tenn[essee] / George [House]</title><author>House, George</author><date value="1850-06-08">June 8, 1850</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated June 8, 1850, from George House to his wife Mary in Nashville. He is on a business trip selling medicines. Most of the letter is naming the places he is going, which are probably in Alabama, but may be in Tennessee. He writes that the towns he is visiting are very small and that it will be difficult to sell out because of that. He misses her so much that he is dreaming of her. He sends love to the family in Nashville.</note><note type="collection">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note><note type="box">3</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">sl228</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Tennessee -- Travel and description</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Athens</name> <date value="1850-06-08">June 8 1850</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Mary</salute></opener><p>I am here Well&mdash; and less fatigued than when I wrote to you Yesterday from <name type="place">Pulaski</name> "Tom" has gotten over his attack of sore feet produced by the line on the Turnpike I <orig reg="stayed">staid</orig> last night 16 miles from here at <name type="place">Prices Springs</name> within a mile of  the house in which we took our breakfast, the morning we left <name type="place">Elkton</name> on our way to <name type="place">Huntsville</name> &mdash; I intend leaving this for <name type="place">Triana</name> and shall endeavor to spend tomorrow with <name type="person">Mr Charles Collier</name> (Amy's uncle &mdash; Such an event, will be of  very pleasant circumstance&mdash;</p><p>This place, like all the other small places &caret; <add place="supralinear">have</add>  I  <orig reg="stopped">stoped</orig> at &mdash; is dull &caret; scarcely anything doing at all &mdash; which makes it a difficult Matter to do anything towards selling, I am afraid I shall meet with but little success in selling out, as every one can get as much &caret; <add place="supralinear">medicine</add> as they wish on Commission</p><p>I dreamed of you last night &mdash; (and you looked as lovely as ever)&mdash; it was a very pleasant dream I can assure You &mdash; and hope I may have as pleasant a one to night &mdash;</p><p>I have had some amusing questions asked me on the way side, and have given some in return &mdash; I shall not remit any money from this, but shall wait until I get to <name type="place">Courtland</name>, <name type="place">Tuscumbia</name> or <name type="place">Florence</name>, which will be (without accident) in a few days &mdash; I shall not travel on tomorrow if I can possibly avoid it &mdash; Tell Sallie, I think of her whenever I see a little girl about her size &mdash; I hope she <pb n="[2]"/> Will be very Kind to her Ma, and grand Ma while her Pa, is away &mdash;</p><p>I should feel so much better if I had You along with me &mdash; I must try and bear it the very best I can however for a few months &mdash; Make My love to all Kiss "Sallie" Lou, and "Honnie" and Eliza if she has returned &mdash; I shall not write again to You until I reach Tuscumbia</p><closer><salute>With my prayers and love I am Your own dear</salute><signed>George</signed><pb n="[3]"/><address><addrLine>Mrs <name type="person">Mary House</name></addrLine><addrLine>Care of <name type="person"><abbr expan="George Washington">Geo W</abbr> House</name> </addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennesee">Tenn</abbr></name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
