<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl223"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1847 Oct. 14, Nashville [to] Sarah B. Hamilton / George W. House   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>House, George W.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl223</idno><idno>OCLC: 51217428</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1847 Oct. 14, Nashville [to] Sarah B. Hamilton / George W. House   </title><author>House, George W. </author><date value="1847-10-14">October 14, 1847</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated October 14, 1847 from George House to his mother-in-law Sarah B. Hamilton. George writes a lengthy letter about a magazine explosion that occurred in Nashville. The explosion killed six people, wounded dozens, and destroyed numerous homes and businesses.</note><note type="collection">Orr Collection-IV-J-2</note><note type="box">3</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">sl223</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Explosions</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name><date value="1847-10-14"><abbr expan="October">Oct</abbr> 14th 1847</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Mother</salute></opener><p>I received a letter yesterday from <name type="person">William H. Morgan</name> saying you had returned to Russellville &mdash; Therefore you must have received my several letters together with <name type="person">Mr Pope's</name>. <name type="person">Mr. Masons</name> wagon has not yet been over &mdash;</p><p>You will probably hear something of the awful calamity which befell our city on last Monday evening the 12th <abbr expan="instant">inst</abbr> &mdash; During a thunder storm at about &frac12; past 4 PM &mdash; The magazine below Capitol Hill (and on a direct line with the female academy) was struck with lightening with over six hundred kegs of powder in it &mdash; the concussional was <orig reg="awful">awfull</orig> and about fifty house were entirely demolished or rendered useless in the immediate vicinity and a great many others' badly damaged and not one in city that did not receive some hurt &mdash; There were four persons killed and many seriously injured, how many I do not know &mdash; It seems a miracle that hundreds were not instantly killed &frac12; and had it happened when people were out of their house's, no doubt the destruction to life would have been great &mdash; The Female Academy was badly riddled and no one seriously hurt &mdash; All the partitions that were made of laths and plastering were thrown down and I suppose every window in the house &mdash; broken to pieces <pb n="[2]"/> Our house suffered very much also &mdash; every window in the end next towards the Academy &mdash; Kitchen included were smashed all to pieces and all the others but one had glass broken out &mdash; The transom over the front door, and the pieces at each side of the doors were blown out but not broken &mdash; the <orig reg="staples">steeples</orig> that fastened the bell wire were all forced out &mdash; Some of the plastering in Amy's room fell down &mdash; all the doors in the house were forced open and some split &mdash; the rafters where they were joined at the top of the ell of the house were riven <orig reg="asunder">assunder</orig> at least three inches <name type="person">Jane Smiths</name> Band box had the lid thrown off and her bonnet thrown out &mdash; Some of the broken glass was so finely powdered that it looked like it had been pulverized in a mortar &mdash; Rose received several cuts by the glass on one arm hand and shoulder &mdash; Mary had her comb broken which saved her head, and received a few scratches in her left hand &mdash; Sally was in the kitchen under the table which saved her and was the only one about the house  who screamed &mdash; As soon as her Mother reached her she immediately asked "Ma is God in the house I don't want him to thunder any more" So it is we should be very thankful for our preservation amid so much danger &caret; <add place="supralinear">and destruction</add> Little <name type="person">Mary Hamilton</name> was with us was very much alarmed but not hurt &mdash; I was <pb n="[3]"/> <sic>was</sic> at the <name type="place">Nashville Inn</name> in the parlor conversing with Mr &amp; Mrs <name type="person">Donegan</name> of <name type="place">Huntsville</name> and we thought the Inn was struck with lightning and so did every one else think of their house &mdash; It is impossible for me to give you anything like a <orig reg="description">discription</orig> of the extent of damage done &mdash; I enclose you the description by the "Whig"</p><p>We are all well and Mary joins me in love to you, and regards to all of our <name type="place">Russellville</name> friends &mdash; Write to us, and say when you are coming home &mdash; Mrs. <name type="person">Gustavus Henry</name> of <del type="overstrike">at</del> <name type="place">Clarksville</name> is at <name type="person"><abbr expan="John">Jno</abbr> P Erwins</name> Mary and myself are going out to see her this evening at three Oclock.</p><p><name type="person">Mrs Pope</name> Amy &amp; Jane wish to be remembered to you Sally says you must bring her a doll and says she does not want to hear any more thunder to tear down our house &mdash; Since writing the above I have understood that two persons who were wounded have died; making the number six &mdash;</p><p>Mr <name type="person">Shanklands</name> house was completely torn to pieces by timbers and stones, the furniture broken to pieces, and not one hurt. So soon as I learn it was the magazine I left my company at the Inn and went home in the rain in a hurry and was greatly relieved when I found no one killed or maimed &mdash; I write in a hurry <pb n="[4]"/> </p><closer><add place="down left margin ">Wish you good health and hoping we may see you soon &mdash; I am affectionately your son George</add><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs. Sally B. Hamilton</name></addrLine><addrLine>care of <name type="person">P. N.  Ewing</name> <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr</abbr></addrLine><addrLine>Russellville</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Kentucky</name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
