<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl220"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1844 Jul 31, Nashville [TN] [to] Mary House, Louisville, Alabama  / George House   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>House, George</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl220</idno><idno>OCLC: 51217206</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1844 Jul 31, Nashville [TN] [to] Mary House, Louisville, Alabama  / George House</title><author>House, George </author><date value="1844-07-31">July 31, 1844</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated July 31, 1844 to Mary House from her husband, George House. He writes quite a bit about how much he misses her. He even stares out his window at night in the direction she lives. He gives the news of his friends, and their family.  He also describes in detail a recent Whig rally and looks forward to their convention. He gives the news of their family, and the people that want her to write to them. He also advises her to take boneset tea if she gets another cough.</note><note type="collection">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note><note type="box">3</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">sl220</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name> <date value="1844-07-31">July 31 1844</date></addrLine></address><salute>My dearest Mary</salute></opener><p>I received yours of 15th on the 27th inst, after it had been Written 12 days &mdash; it was a very Welcome epistle &mdash; <orig reg="though">tho</orig> long delayed &mdash; It was post Marked on the 24th &mdash; Nine days after it Was Written a delay quite unaccountable &mdash; such as one I hope Will not occur again</p> <p>The good News, that yourself and the children Were so Well &mdash; served as a bright ray, to illumine the cheerless feelings of My heart I am in deed very lonesome Mary &mdash; particularly at night, in a large room alone with here and there a symbol to remind me, all I love are faraway &mdash; Why is it so &mdash; has life not enough of woe &amp; sorrow, without adding this &mdash; Ah Mary &mdash; your husband though not old has already drunk deep of the waters of "Mara" and what is yet in store for me, is hidden in the Mysteries of the future &mdash; You have seen part of my sufferings &mdash; but You have never felt <unclear>them</unclear> &mdash; For several nights I sat up until eleven and after &mdash;  and before retiring would go to the Window, and look out towards <name type="place">Alabama</name>, in the direction of your whereabouts &mdash; and think that You with our two loved ones Were Wrapped in the gentle slumbers of &caret; <add place="supralinear">sweet</add> sleep &mdash; while I alone &mdash; looking out upon the silence of night with all the feelings of husband and parent pressing up and going out in  <pb n="[2]"/> fervent prayer to the God of all Mercies to protect You from all danger and to restore You soon to my bosom &mdash; Mine is an affection that lies deep within the recesses of the heart and there burns with a flame as <unclear>ardent</unclear> as sacred &mdash; which is only Known to myself &mdash; Mary I have frequently thought that within the last two years You did not fully appreciate my love for You &mdash; Those demonstrations of Kindness &mdash; My heart so fondly anticipated and looked for &mdash; Were not realized &mdash; But to the News &mdash; <name type="person">Mrs Shankland</name> has a fine son &mdash; More than a week old &mdash; <name type="person">Mrs Willoughby Williams</name> and <name type="person">Mr Edwin Ewing</name> are both numbered with the dead &mdash; A letter from <name type="person">Mr Forte</name> to Mother states that <name type="person">Mrs. Ewing</name> still Continues to improve and is getting Well &mdash; I took tea night before last With Cousin <name type="person">Letitia Brown</name> &mdash; they Were Very glad to see me, and inquired particularly about You and the children &mdash; after supper Jane, had a beau who went with her to church &mdash; The Whigs had a grand rally at <name type="place">Russellville</name> on the 26th &mdash; The straightouts the Harrison Guards and Clay Dragoons <unclear>west from here</unclear> the Number present in Conventions were from ten to 15 thousand &mdash; Four <orig reg="Young">Yung</orig> ladies from <name type="place">Hopkensville</name> Chartered a New Coach With four horses &mdash; placed a flag at each Corner of the Coach and one upon each of the horses &mdash; The two front flags had upon them "Whig or no husband" &mdash; the other two &mdash; "We Will do our duty" and upon the horses flags &mdash; "<name type="person">Clay</name> &amp; <name type="person">Frelenghuysen</name>" <pb n="[3]"/> they were also badges &mdash; upon which was inscribed Members of the ladies Clay Club of Hopkensville" &mdash; and <orig reg="honorary">honory</orig> members of the ashland <unclear>straitouts</unclear> " &mdash; two of  the banners &mdash; "Whig or no husband", Were <unclear>brot</unclear> home by the Companies that Went from here &mdash; We shall have a rousing Convention here on the 21st of next month, The Democrats are making great preparations for theirs on the 15th &mdash; <name type="person">Mr <unclear>Crittenden</unclear></name> was at Russellville and will be here, so will Prentiss &mdash; I almost Wish You Could be here &mdash; Tell Jimmy his grand ma says he shall have a saddle and that his Papa looked at <unclear>two</unclear> to day &mdash; which will cost out and out, about 8$ &mdash; and if an oppurtunity occurs it shall be sent also Your flannel <unclear>peticoat shawl and the babies wrapper</unclear> &mdash; which Mother says You left &mdash; You Will also Want Something for Jims winter Clothes &mdash; however it will be time enough when I Come out &mdash; You did not say how mothers spectacles suited her &mdash; <name type="person">Mother Hamilton</name> says You must Write all the news &mdash; particularly about the children and what Jim, talks about &mdash; Em says if You Will Write to her she will answer Your letter and that she is making preparation for a Wedding to morrow night &mdash; Miss Fanny and a <name type="person">Mr Kingsly</name> We are  all Well &mdash; Mother and Ann joins me in love to You and all our relatives &mdash; Ann had <add place="up left margin">Mother says You must write how you enjoy Your self &mdash; and You had better write the letter to her as she will be much pleased to receive one from you Farewell <abbr expan="George">G</abbr></add> <pb n="[4]"/> a tooth drawn this morning &mdash; it had the largest prongs I ever saw &mdash; Louse and Jimmy Called to see us last week Louisa is almost as large as Mother &mdash; she looks like she would have four &mdash; she desired me to give her love to  You &mdash; You must remember me very affectionately to Mother, sister Nancy, Brother <abbr expan="and etcetera">&amp;c</abbr> &mdash; I will try and write papers <orig reg="occasionally">occassionally</orig> &mdash; Young Williams the <add place="center of page, rotated"><address><addrLine>Mrs <name type="person">Mary House</name></addrLine><addrLine>Care of <name type="person"><abbr expan="Samuel John Cotten">Saml J C</abbr> House</name> <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><orig reg="Louisville">Loueville</orig></name></addrLine><addrLine>Near <name type="place">Huntsville</name></addrLine><addrLine>Alabama</addrLine></address></add> lawyer is married to a rich girl &mdash; Mother says tell Mary <name type="person">Mrs Elliott</name> is a great <unclear>run</unclear> about &mdash; Mrs Elliott sends her love to You &mdash; <name type="person">Mary Baber</name> as one home, her father is dead, died about a week ago &mdash; just after Mary got home &mdash; <name type="person">Julia Davis</name> is well &mdash; and says she will write, sends her love &mdash; Kiss the children for me and take good Care of them, and Yourself &mdash; tell Mother <add place="up left margin of page 1">to give you some Boneset tea, if you should get another cough &mdash; and now my dear Mary may <unclear>heavens</unclear> bless You and our little ones &mdash; in the prayer of <unclear>the</unclear> lonely one George</add></p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
