<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl272"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Legal Document] 1849 Mar. 15, Davidson County, Tennessee, [to]  Washington Institute Trustees / John R. Wilson   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Wilson, John R.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl272</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Legal document] 1849 Mar. 15, Davidson County, Tennessee, [to]  Washington Institute Trustees / John R. Wilson</title><author>Wilson, John R.</author><date value="1849-03-15">March 15, 1849</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a legal document dated March 15, 1849, in which John R. Wilson is donating some land to be used for a school and church, named the Washington Institute. He adds the condition that he be allowed water access for his livestock and that he be given free tuition for one student each session.  He also adds another stipulation--that he be able to appoint his successor to the board of trustees.</note><note type="collection">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note><note type="box">5</note><note type="folder">14</note><note type="document">sl272</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Legal documents</item><item>Real property</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="legal document"><pb n="[1]"/><p>Know all by these present, that I <name type="person">John R. Wilson</name> of the <name type="place">county of Davidson</name>, <name type="place">State of Tennessee</name>, moved by a desire to promote the cause of education, and furnish means for religious worship, do hereby donate a certain site, to embrace all that part of a site formerly <del type="overstrike">devoted</del> <add place="supralinear">leased</add> by <name type="person">William Vaulx</name> for the use of <name type="place">Pleasant Grove Seminary</name>  West of a fence made by me, East of said site, and to continue South to the <name type="place">Nashville</name> &amp; <name type="place"><orig reg="Murfreesboro">Murfreesborough</orig></name> Turnpike Road, then West with said Road to the line or alley leading North between <name type="person">Thomas. S. King</name> &amp; <name type="person">Margaret Williams</name> &amp; myself, then North to the fence made by me; as the North boundary of said tract, so as to include all the land, set apart by me at the South West part of the tract on which I now live, in said County and State, aforesaid, to <abbr expan="Messieurs">Messrs</abbr> <name type="person">J.J.B. Southall</name>, <name type="person">Robert Buchanan</name>, <name type="person">William H. McLaughlin</name>, <name type="person">W.H. Rains</name> , <name type="person">Hays Blackman</name>, <name type="person">Robert Davis</name>, <name type="person">John. R. Wilson</name>, <name type="person">John Overton</name> &amp; <name type="person">Phos S King</name> &mdash; the present board of Trustees, and their successors, for the purpose of erecting a suitable edifice for on Institution of learning and place of public worship, free to all denominations and clergy of good standing, and I bind myself, My Heirs <abbr expan="and etcetera">&amp;c</abbr>, to convey by Deed to the above trustees or their successors a full right to the ground <orig reg="above">abov</orig> specified, so soon as the proposed building is erected &mdash; Provided always, I have the right of way to water for stock and free tuition for one student, each <del type="overstrike">alternate</del> Session, If the abov ground be not applied to the purposes, above <pb n="[2]"/> specified, this bond shall be null and void,&mdash;</p><p>Given under my hand and seal&mdash; <lb/>  this <date value="1849-03-14">14th day of March 1849</date></p><p>The above <orig reg="although">altho</orig> not precisely as I would like to have it is substantially what I have designed</p><closer><signed>John R. Wilson</signed><date value="1849-03-15">March 15. 1849</date><add place="left of signature">Test <lb/> <name type="person">G A G McEwen</name></add> <add place="under signature" cert="different hand, ink">March 15th 1849 In addition to the above provisions I. <name type="person"> J. R. Wilson</name> do reserve to myself my heirs or executors the right to appoint my successor as trustee in the washington Institute. John R. Wilson <lb/> witness <lb/> <name type="person">J. Smith Fowler</name></add><pb n="[3]"/> Bond of <abbr expan="Doctored">Doct</abbr> J. R. Wilson for site of Washington <abbr expan="Institute">I</abbr> <add cert="different hand, ink">Lease inserted for donated Each session that Dr Wilson and his heirs &caret; <add place="supralinear">and executors</add> shall have the right of appointing his successors as trustee.</add> <add place="upside down at bottom of page"><figure><figDesc>misc. math problems</figDesc></figure></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
