<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl284"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>   [Letter] 1834 May 16, Balt[im]o[re] [to] Major A[ndrew] J[ackson] Donaldson [i.e., Donelson], Washington / Jno [i.e., John] Patrick : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Patrick, John</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl284</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>   [Letter] 1834 May 16, Balt[im]o[re] [to] Major A[ndrew] J[ackson] Donaldson [i.e., Donelson], Washington / Jno [i.e., John] Patrick</title><author>Patrick, John</author><date value="1834-05-16">May 16, 1834</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated May 16, 1834, from John Patrick of Baltimore to Andrew Jackson Donelson, confidential secretary to President Andrew Jackson.  Patrick writes on behalf of two hat makers who wish to make the President a hat as a show of support for the recent decision to destroy the Bank of the United States. Patrick seeks to find out the size and description of a hat that would   please the President.</note><note type="collection">A. J. Donelson Papers</note><note type="box">I-D-3</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">sl284</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</item><item>Hat trade</item><item>Southern States</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><salute>My Dear Sir,</salute></opener><p><abbr expan="Messiers">Messrs</abbr> <name type="person">James McGrath</name> and <name type="person">Solomon M. Sandborn</name>, two young operative hatters of this City, are desirous of <orig reg="evincing">evinceing</orig> to our much loved President, their gratitude, for the firm and energetic  course <orig reg="pursued">persued</orig> in all his public acts; and more partic<add place="supralinear">u</add>larly in the Constitutional methods adopted to destroy, that Hydra of Corruption, the Bank of the <name type="place"><abbr expan="United">U.</abbr> States</name>.</p><p>I am requested by those Gentlemen, to obtain through some known Source, the Size as well as the minute description of a hat, such as would be most acceptable to the President:  &mdash; In asking this information, they are actuated by an honest ambition to testify their firm devotion to the cause of, "Jackson  and Democracy." &mdash;</p><p>Will Major <abbr expan="Donelson">D.</abbr> be good enough to present to the General, assurance of the warm <pb n="[2]"/> attachment entertained for him by the humble writer of this, and my firm belief that he will continue to be sustained, by an increased majority of the citizens of this City?&mdash; I have the honor to be, </p><closer><salute>Sir, Your <abbr expan="Obedient Servant">Obd. Servt.</abbr></salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="John">Jno.</abbr> Patrick</name></signed><address><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Baltimore">Balto.</abbr></name>  <date value="1834-05-16">16th May 1834</date>.</addrLine></address> <add place="below address" cert="different hand, ink">&equals; If a green rim would be preferred please signify it.&mdash; &equals;</add> <pb n="[3]"/> <address><addrLine>To. <name type="person">Major <abbr expan="Andrew Jackson">A. J.</abbr> <orig reg="Donelson">Donaldson</orig></name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Washington</name></addrLine></address><add place="below address, upside down" cert="different hand">Jno Patrick of Baltimore &mdash; wishes to present a hat to the President.</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
