<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "file:///C|/Program%20Files/SoftQuad/XMetaL%202/rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl294"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1836 Apr. 27, Long Creek, Sumner C[oun]ty, Tennessee [to] A. Fergusson, Holly Springs, Tennessee   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>[unknown]</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl294</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1836 Apr. 27, Long Creek, Sumner C[oun]ty, Tennessee [to] A. Fergusson, Holly Springs, Tennessee</title><author>[unknown]</author><date value="1836-01-27">April 27, 1836</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter to A. Fergusson dated April 27, 1836. The unknown author writes about school, particularly about learning arithmetic. The author also gives the results of local elections.</note><note type="collection">Fergusson Papers IV-G-1</note><note type="box">2</note><note type="folder">6</note><note type="document">sl294</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee --Politics and government -- To 1865</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine> <date value="1836-04-27">April 27th 1836</date> <name type="place">Simpson Stone</name> <name type="place">Sumner <abbr expan="County">Cty</abbr></name> <name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine>Long Creek</addrLine></address><salute>Dear Friends</salute></opener><p>I now  embrace this <orig reg="opportunity">oportunity</orig> of Writing unto you to let you know that my fathers family and myself are all well at present and also all of your <unclear>Connexion</unclear> is well So far as I know we received your letter about Six weeks ago which Gave us Great pleasure to hear that you were all well and Satisfied with the Country and wishing you health and prosperity through life I will tell <orig reg="you">yo</orig> Some thing what I have been Doing Since you left this Country _ I have been Going to school about five months and have acquired a Good knowledge of the <orig reg="arithmetic">arithmetick</orig> as my Master Says _ I have been through the Arithmeticks known by <name type="person">Smileys</name> <unclear>Pikes</unclear> <name type="person">Crookshanks</name> and <name type="person">Smiths</name> <unclear>also</unclear> I have <unclear>Shrdred</unclear> Book keeping after the plan of those Arithmeticks _ on monday last I Commenced keeping Store for <name type="person">mrs <abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> Robert Simpson</name> and Son on long Creek near  <unclear>Lawnnes mill</unclear>  and expect Continuing with them until about Christmas next at the moderate price of $5 per month they find me my boarding at <unclear>Mark</unclear> Woodcocks also my washing and mending and at that rate I cannot be making much in this country but at the expiration of that time <gap reason="document torn"/> from 20 to 30 $ per month <gap reason="document torn"/> Glad to See you and family and <gap reason="document torn"/> Soon as Circumstances will per <gap reason="document torn"/> often talks about <gap reason="document torn"/> you and family <gap reason="document torn"/> you all too you <gap reason="document torn"/> come this fall <pb n="[2]"/> corn crops in the <gap reason="document torn"/> Generally planted and some has plowed their corn but not many &mdash;</p><p> I want you to write on the receipt of this letter Some Rules and Directions for Epistolary Writing &amp; and I want you to Excuse this Sorry writing as I do it by Intervals and then in a Great <unclear>hury</unclear> _</p><p> I want you to Write the price of a book keeper a year or month in <name type="place">Mississippi</name> </p><p>we have had Some warm Elections this Spring for Esquire and military officers my father was elected Esquire and Also Uncle <name type="person">Patrick William Raglan</name> was elected Colonel Commandant of the 53d <abbr expan="Regiment">Regt</abbr> in opposition to <name type="person">Jacob Jonston</name> <name type="person">Mayor McMury</name> was elected <abbr expan="Lieutenant Colonel">Lieut Col</abbr> in opposition to <name type="person">Joseph Carter</name> and Madison <unclear>Donohood</unclear> major in the <unclear><?xm-replace_text {unclear}?></unclear> without opposition &mdash; Mr <del type="overstrike">Dapid</del> <name type="person">David Fergusen</name> was a Candidate for Sheriff but missed it by a long gap <name type="person">Mr Howard</name> was reelected by Double all his Competitors which was <name type="person">Ballie Fergusen</name> and <name type="person">Baly Young</name> <name type="person">mr Burnett</name> was elected Clerk in opposition to <name type="person">Joseph Hibbans</name> and mr &caret;<name type="person"><add place="supralinear ">John</add> Bransford</name> elected Registrar of middle Tennessee by the Legislature So I must <unclear>gent</unclear> my vehement way of Writing but not without letting you first that <gap reason="document torn"/></p><closer><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mr A Fergusson</name> and Family</addrLine></address><pb n="[3]"/><address><addrLine>A Fergusson <abbr expan="esquire">esqr</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Holly Springs</name></addrLine><addrLine>Tennessee</addrLine></address><add place="under address"><abbr expan="Deliver">Dr</abbr> Mail in haste <lb/> Single</add> <add place="right margin">Bratton's <lb/>  <unclear>Mayest</unclear>&rcub;</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
