<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl331"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1840 Dec. 16, Nashville [Tennessee] [to] A. Fergusson, Carthage, Tenn[essee] / Geo. Harris   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Harris, George</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl331</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1840 Dec. 16, Nashville [Tennessee] [to] A. Fergusson, Carthage, Tenn[essee] / Geo. Harris</title><author>Harris, George</author><date value="1840-12-16">December 16, 1840</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from George Harris to Adam Fergusson, dated December 16, 1840. Harris thanks Fergusson for extending the circulation of the newspaper The Union. Harris plans to use the paper to promote Republican doctrine. He mentions some political opinions.</note><note type="collection">Fergusson Papers</note><note type="box"> IV-G-2 b4</note><note type="folder">1</note><note type="document">sl331</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee -- Politics and government</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name> <date value="1840-12-16"><abbr expan="December">Dec</abbr> 16. 1840</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>Your letter of the 14th is at hand, <unclear>per politeness</unclear> of <name type="person">Mr. Stephens</name> I thank you for the interest you express in extending the circulation of the Union. I can only say that so long as I can <unclear>wag</unclear> my pen I shall be untiring in my efforts to give forth true information and sound republican doctrine through the columns of my paper__striving to advise the people of the course and conduct of <add place="supralinear">the</add> associated factions that have by pipelaying and money succeeded in a <orig reg="temporary">temperary</orig> overthrow  of the old Republican party. They must and will quarrel among themselves__ and expire from spontaneous <orig reg="combustion">conbustion</orig> as did old Mrs. <unclear>Frithful</unclear> Already <name type="person">Clay</name> &amp; <name type="person">Webster</name> are falling out. Meantime let us take advantage of their difficulties and <orig reg="organize">organise</orig> thoroughly for action next August. Let every precinct be organised, so that the committees of <gap reason="hole in document "/> may cause documents and papers to be <gap reason="hole in document"/> people's houses, and Know exactly how many <gap reason="hole in document"/> can be cast on the day of election. If we <gap reason="hole in document"/> re-elect <name type="person"><abbr expan="Govenor">Gov.</abbr> Polk</name> __ if we do not work thro<gap reason="hole in document"/> we may be defeated. We are organised in <gap reason="hole in document"/> in <name type="place">Maury</name> ; and the good <pb n="[2]"/> work seems to be going on throughout the state. I will make the Union useful in the state __ and if my <orig reg="friends">freinds</orig> will only take the interest that you kindly manifest, in circulating it &mdash; its effect must be seen and felt.</p><p>I intend to publish a prospectus in a day or two. But there is no necessity for one. Any subscribers that you or your freinds may obtain can be sent in a letter through the <abbr expan="Post Office">P. O.</abbr> The <unclear>rules</unclear> of the P. O.<abbr expan="Department"> Dept</abbr> allow Post Masters to send money <abbr expan="and etcetera">&amp;c</abbr> in letters to editors for papers, free of postage when the letters are written by the <abbr expan="Post Master">P. M.</abbr> himself &mdash; so no expense need be <orig reg="incurred">encurred</orig> by <unclear>transmission</unclear></p><p>I shall be ready to make and reasonable allowance in the way of commissions for subscribers obtained.</p><closer><salute>I am sir very respectfully <lb/> <abbr expan="Your Obedient Servant">Yr obt servt</abbr></salute><signed><name type="person">Geo Harris</name></signed><add place="bottom left corner">for/ <name type="person"><abbr expan="Adam">A</abbr> Fergusson</name></add> <pb n="[3]"/><address><addrLine>A. Fergusson <abbr expan="Esquire">Esq</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Carthage</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name></addrLine></address><add place="left of address">Favored by <lb/> Mr. Stephens &rcub;</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
