<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl332"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1842 Mar. 17, South Harpeth, Tennessee [to] A. Fergusson, Carthage, Tennessee / Ezra Holstead   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Holstead, Ezra</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl332</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1842 Mar. 17, South Harpeth, Tennessee [to] A. Fergusson, Carthage, Tennessee / Ezra Holstead</title><author>Holstead, Ezra</author><date value="1842-03-17">March 17, 1842</date><extent>2p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Ezra Holstead to Adam Fergusson, dated March 17, 1840. He writes responses to his last letter about her property. Holstead also requests that  Fergusson  visit him when he comes through the area on his way to Charlotte.</note><note type="collection">Fergusson Papers </note><note type="box">IV-G-1 b4</note><note type="folder">2</note><note type="document">sl332</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Business enterprises</item><item>Real property</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>Arkansas</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">South Harpeth</name> <name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1842-03-17">March 17th 1842</date></addrLine><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Adam">A.</abbr> Fergusson</name><abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr</abbr></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>your <orig reg="favor">favour</orig> of the <date value="1842-03-11">11th <abbr expan="Instant">Inst.</abbr></date> came to hand yesterday, and I now embrace the opportunity of responding to your enquiries__ I do not know of but one man in <name type="place">Dickson County</name> by the name of Walker and his name is <name type="person">Nelson Walker</name>, formerly of your County, he lives some 8 or ten miles from this__ I have not sold my claims in <name type="place">Arkansas</name>__ I have two__ I have also two Lots in the town of <name type="place">Carmi</name> <name type="place">White County</name><name type="place"><abbr expan="Illinois">Ill.</abbr></name> and there are two persons in this <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood</orig> having each a claim of 160 acres in <name type="place">Illinois</name> __ As you have business in Dickson County when you come to <name type="place">Nashville</name> come and stay with me all night, as I am anxious of having a long conversation with you__ I keep school in sight of <name type="place">Allisons Mill </name> on South Harpeth _ A visit here might ultimately prove beneficial to you and it is not much out of your direct route to <name type="place">Charlotte</name> (say 3 miles) _ Should it so occur that you cannot <del type="overstrike">you</del> come here before you go to Arkansas and Illinois. apprise me of the same, as I want you to attend to my claims: but if possible fail not to come</p><closer><salute>Respectfully <lb/> Your <abbr expan="Obedient servant">Obt servt.</abbr></salute><signed><name type="person">Ezra Holstead</name></signed><pb n="[2]"/><address><addrLine>A. Fergusson <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Carthage</name></addrLine><addrLine>Tennessee</addrLine></address><add place="upper right corner" cert="different hand, ink">South Harpeth <lb/> <date value="1842-03-18">March 18</date></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
