<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl422"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1843 Nov. 15, Franklin, Tennessee [to] Hester Ann Fergusson, Carthage, Tennessee / A[dam] Fergusson: a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Fergusson, A.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sl422</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1843 Nov. 15, Franklin, Tennessee [to] Hester Ann Fergusson, Carthage, Tennessee / A[dam] Fergusson</title><author>Fergusson, A.</author><date value="1843-11-15">November 15th 1843</date><extent>2p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Adam Fergusson to his wife Hester Ann, dated November 15, 1843. Fergusson is on his way to Nashville and is writing to update Hester on his progress. He writes of some of the people he has encountered so far.</note><note type="collection">Fergusson Papers</note><note type="box">IV-G-1, B6</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">sl422</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee</item><item>Communications in the family</item><item>Travel</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name>Franklin</name> <name>Tennessee</name></addrLine><addrLine>15th November 1843</addrLine></address><salute>Dear <gap desc="Hester"/> Ann</salute></opener><p>I am this far only on my way yet as I could get along no faster. I saw Ann E. at <name>Gallatin</name> on monday She was well but had a bad cold indeed I do not know what She is to look like she has fattened and puffed up so but when she comes home I hope she will take more <orig reg="exercise">excercise</orig> and not get So fat she <gap/> anxious to get home so is <gap/> I have <orig reg="succeed">Suceeded</orig> tolerably well So fa <gap/> <orig reg="business">buisiness</orig> . I Shall in two more days g <gap/> county and Stay there one day and <gap/> turn home I expect to be at <name>Nashville</name> on the <gap/> ady to be at the convention on the <gap/> I ha <gap/> no money as I do not expect there will <gap/>need of doing so until I come home but <gap/> there be a necessity for it you can apply to <name>McClain</name> who will furnish it as I told him to do So to the amount of thirty or thirty five dollars while will be sufficient I am here with the old man <name>Robinson</name> tavern keeper he is Just married to a young wife. he is 50 and she is 26. I have listened to him telling me what a fine woman She is until I am <orig reg="quite">quit</orig> sick and ready to puke up my Supper So I called for a room and fire and am now seated writing to you I will tell you what <orig reg="funny">funy</orig> things he has told me when I came home I have bought a Sack of coffee at C Conus but did not pay for it So I expect it will not go up until I return. I shall buy Some Sugar <gap/> I have also made enquiry about Mrs Da<gap/> and will find out whether she <gap/> Academy You must take care of y <gap/> dun</p><closer><signed><name><abbr expan="Adam">A</abbr> Fergusson</name></signed> <pb n="[2]"/> <address><addrLine>Mrs <name>Hester Ann Fergusson</name></addrLine><addrLine><name>Carthage</name></addrLine><addrLine><name>Tennessee</name></addrLine></address><add><figure><figDesc>postage Franklin <abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr> <date><abbr expan="November">Nov</abbr> 16</date></figDesc></figure></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
