<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl447"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1815 Jan. 30, Sugar Hill [to] Peter Hardeman, Camp Jackson, New Orleans / Thomas. Hardeman   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Hardeman, Thomas</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name><name>Bobby Holt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sl447</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1815 Jan. 30, Sugar Hill [to] Peter Hardeman, Camp Jackson, New Orleans / Thomas. Hardeman</title><author>Hardeman, Thomas</author><date value="1815-01-30">January 30, 1815</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated January 30, 1815 from Thomas Hardeman to his son Peter Hardeman near New Orleans.  In the letter, Thomas  expresses grief and regret that two of his sons had been captured as prisoners of war by the British in New Orleans; he is optimistic that they will return home safely. </note><note type="collection">Hardeman Family Papers</note><note type="box">Correspondence</note><note type="folder">9</note><note type="document">sl447</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee -- History</item><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine>Sugar hill</addrLine></address>  <date>January 30th 1815</date> <salute>Dear Son</salute></opener><p>yours of the 11th <abbr expan="instant">inst</abbr>. came safe to hand, in which I learn that two of my sons Glen &amp; <abbr expan="Thomas">Thos</abbr> are prisoners with the British, they will suffer no doubt in the hands of such a savage force but there is still a hope of their being exchanged for and return again to their friends, am glad it is no worse their wives had been informed they were both killed But your letter coming has revived all our hopes of their returning to us again.  Our commanding general will no doubt try to bring <orig reg="about">a bout</orig> an exchange of prisoners, as soon as time will permit him to attend to it my wife has been sick ever since you left us, and very quite useless ever since the 10 December last.   &amp; I myself have been afflicted with <orig reg="rheumatoid">rumatoid</orig> pains. <gap reason="hole in document"/> must have suffered considerably if your Brother <name>John Hardeman</name> had not sent Billey to cut fire wood those <orig reg="circumstances">surcomstances</orig> have prevented me from seeing your wife nor should I have seen <abbr expan="Thomas">Thos</abbr> J. Hardemans wife if she had not come herself.  She has a fine boy.  The Tennesseans Both officers &amp; men I am told have distinguished their <orig reg="patriotic">patriotick</orig> bravery <gap reason="hole in document"/> that have been <orig reg="fought">faught</orig>.  They <gap reason="hole in document"/> a <orig reg="pattern">pattron</orig> for our sister states to follow, and teach our common enemy how to tower their high sounding sine qua non.  It appears <add>however that</add> our British enemy is determined to fight us into <orig reg="conquerors">conquerers</orig>, or <orig reg="nonexistence">nonexistance</orig>, and feel <orig reg="very">verry</orig> much <gap reason="document is torn"/>  to meet them on that ground. <pb n="[2]"/> <orig reg="you'll">youl</orig> please inform me every mail, how the army <orig reg="progresses">progreses</orig> what is done &amp; still doing. and also of your own health and if any tidings from your Brothers prisoners, If <orig reg="there">thare</orig> be any prospects of their being soon exchanged for.  we wish to know if any our <orig reg="neighbors">neighbours</orig> are killed and who they are.  Green <gap reason="hole in document"/> has no connection in camp but your self that I know of now, let us know what has become of him.  Your Brother <name>John Hardeman</name> has salted your pork hear, your corn is well cribed at home. when the situation of enemy will admit of your absence <orig reg="you'll">youl</orig> please see <name>seth Lewis</name> and settle my Business with him <orig reg="in full">infull</orig>, as I <orig reg="do not">donot</orig> wish one <orig reg="dollar">doller</orig> left <orig reg="unsettled">unsetled</orig>, I have experienced what I could not have believed with out it.  and that is <name>Seth Lewis</name> would not pay me according to <orig reg="bargain">beargain</orig>, nor return the property he got, when he knew I was offering for want of it.  there is no <orig reg="shuffling">shufling</orig> in <orig reg="their">there</orig> ranks, the thing is plain, he could have paid, or returned the negroes, one or the other he would have done, ought to have done <gap reason="hole in document"/> I would choose the money If to get <gap reason="hole in document"/> to any thing else, you know <orig reg="enough">a nough</orig> of the business yourself, still it the best way you can for I am tired of <gap reason="hole in document"/>  but if <orig reg="possible">possable</orig>  <add>have</add>  it fully <orig reg="settled">setled</orig>, as I wish never to think of it again, I still wish the family well. but no more dealings my wife joins me in love to you &amp; all <orig reg="friend">frind</orig> in camp.  </p> <closer>Your affectionate Father <signed><abbr expan="Thomas">Thos</abbr> Hardeman</signed> <pb n="[3]"/> <address><addrLine>Franklin</addrLine></address> <date>3rd <abbr expan="January">Januy</abbr> 1815</date> <add>Paid 25</add> <address><addrLine><abbr expan="Lieutenant">Lieut</abbr>, Peter Hardeman Camp Jackson Below New Orleans</addrLine></address> <add>Mail</add> <add>miscellaneous calculations</add> <add>17</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>

