<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl454"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>   [Letter] 1838 May 28 [to] R. H. McEwen / W. B. Robinson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Robinson, W. B.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sl454</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1838 May 28 [to] R. H. McEwen / W. B. Robinson</title><author>Robinson, W. B.</author><date value="1838-05-28">May 28, 1838</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter to R. H. McEwen from W. B. Robinson, dated May 28, 1838. Robinson writes about his recent endeavors to sell his cotton. He also writes about his attempts to insure his cotton for market.</note><note type="collection">McEwen Papers</note><note type="folder">7</note><note type="document">sl454</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee</item><item>Cotton</item><item>Financial, Personal</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name><unclear>Cold Water</unclear></name> <date>May 28th 1838</date></addrLine><addrLine><abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> <name>R H McEwen</name> Dr__</addrLine></address></opener><p>Your Favor of the 10th <abbr expan="Instant">Inst</abbr> came to Hand in due time and its contents was duly Considered in which you say <name>Messrs R Pattersen</name> &amp; <abbr expan="Company">Co</abbr> of <abbr expan="Philadelphia">Phila</abbr> had sent out a Draft for $56 10 which will be due the <date>23rd June</date> It shall be attended to</p><p>I got all my Cotton out of <name>Elk River</name> last week with the Exception of a small Lot that was not Ready say 8 or 10 Bales which I hope will go Safe with out damage or delay</p><p>I Forwarded a Bill to <name>White</name> and Instructed him to Insure at Forty <abbr expan="dollars per">dolls pr</abbr> Bale and he wrote me word that he could not effect Insurance on my Bill higher than 27$ and may answer to him was that the cotton might go to Hell before I would <add>Insure</add> at $27 and other Houses in this Country Insuring at $50 pr Bale <pb n="[2]"/> But to Insure at thirty five dollars If he could and if not to let me Hear from him by the Return Mail Express these are all the Particulars concerning my Ill fated Produce from the Recent Transactions I am Induced to <orig reg="Believe">Beleve</orig> that White Is not a Gentleman and he has the last consignment he Ever will have from me and  my Present Feelings are that I never will have an other Bale of Cotton a float on the <name>Mississippi River</name></p><closer><salute>Your <orig reg="Friend">Freind</orig></salute><signed><name>WB Robinson</name></signed><pb n="[3]"/><address><addrLine>Robinson <unclear>Store</unclear></addrLine><addrLine>28th May <abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></addrLine></address><address><addrLine>Robinson PM</addrLine></address><address><addrLine>Col R H McEwen</addrLine><addrLine><name>Nashville</name></addrLine><addrLine>Tenn</addrLine></address><address><addrLine>Col W B Robinson</addrLine><addrLine>28 May 1838</addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
