<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl497"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1801 Dec. 14, Tennessee Ridge [to] James Winchester, Cragfont, Tennessee / Captain Butler: a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Butler, Captain</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sl497</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1801 Dec. 14, Tennessee Ridge [to] James Winchester, Cragfont, Tennessee / Captain Butler</title><author>Butler, Captain</author><date value="1801-12-14">December 14, 1801</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Captain Butler to General James Winchester, dated December 14, 1801. Butler wants to order some flour for his troop. He also requests a rifle. Butler asks that his regards be sent to Colonel William Martin.</note><note type="collection">James Winchester Papers</note><note type="box">2</note><note type="folder">5</note><note type="document">sl497</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee</item><item>Winchester, James, 1752-1826</item><item>Military supplies</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine>Camp Near <name>Tennessee Ridge</name> <date>14th <abbr expan="December">Decr</abbr> 1801</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>The season now appearing <add>as</add> if you might soon get your Mill under way I have sent <name>Sergeant Hunter</name> to inform you that my self and the officers wish to contract for 25 <abbr expan="Barrels">Blls</abbr> Flour of the best quality you <gap/> to be delivered the soonest possible at Nash <gap/> you be pleased to let me know  by the bear <gap/> you will make such a contract what will be the price and the probable time of delivery and I will write you immediately if it will be accepted and where the Flour will be received and how you are to receive the money - we are preparing to commence road <unclear>citing</unclear> and, I believe, have established where it will cross the ridge- in the execution of this business, a good Rifle would be of great use to me. If you will dispose of  yours I will be glad to have it and should you not wish to dispose of it, be so good as Send it me a while and will be <gap/> careful of it and much obliged <gap/> I had wished to pay you a visit, but ca <gap/> will leave my little family- my <unclear>son</unclear> has been sick ever since we reached <name>wilkinsonville</name>- <name>Mrs Butler</name> and <unclear>Eliza</unclear> are in health and sends their best Respects to you- Should you have an opportunity- make my best <sic corr="Respects">Respects <pb n="[2]"/> Respects</sic> acceptable to <name><abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Martin</name> and others my friends who beat the bush with us last <orig reg="fall">faul</orig> __ I have seen <name>Reed</name>, who we employed last season to bring up the steers which were lost and from the manner in which he equivocated and contradicted himself <gap/> believe he made away with them</p><closer><salute>I am, Dear Sir, <lb/> Your Sincere friend <lb/> &amp; <abbr expan="obedient servant">obt sevt</abbr></salute><signed><unclear>JMS</unclear> Butler</signed><add><abbr expan="Post Script">PS</abbr>_ I am much in want of my Chain he so kind as send it-</add><address><addrLine><abbr expan="General James">Genl  J </abbr> Winchester</addrLine></address> <pb n="[3]"/> <address><addrLine>General James Winchester</addrLine><addrLine><name>Crag Font</name></addrLine></address><add>Sergeant Hunter</add> <add><abbr expan="Captain">Cap</abbr> E Butler <lb/> 14th Dec 1801 <lb/> to <abbr expan="James Winchester">JW</abbr></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
