<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl552"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1815 Jan. 20, Choctaw Agency [to] James Winchester / John McKee   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>McKee, John</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sl552</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1815 Jan. 20, Choctaw Agency [to] James Winchester / John McKee</title><author>McKee, John</author><date value="1815-01-20">January 20, 1815</date><extent>2p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated January 20, 1815 from John McKee to General James Winchester.  McKee reports on the business of recruitment service, specifically, that  during the winter season most Choctaw gun-owners are currently engaged in hunting food for their families, and therefore, that his quarter should not be relied upon until their return.  He also mentions the recent  victory of General Andrew Jackson  at the Battle of New Orleans against the British, and as a result, the Choctaw Indians will probably not be needed there.</note><note type="collection">James Winchester Papers</note><note type="box">3</note><note type="folder">5</note><note type="document">sl552</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee -- History</item><item>Letters</item><item>Choctaw Agency (U.S.)</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine>Choctaw Agency</addrLine></address> <date><abbr expan="January">Jany</abbr> 20 1815</date> <salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>I have the honor to receive your letter of the 6 instant</p><p>Before this can reach you, you will have been advised by <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Dinssnoor of the prospect of auxiliaries from the District of the <name>Choctaws</name> where he is stationed.  At this season almost every man that has a gun is in the woods providing for the wants of his family, it will therefore be improper that you should rely on any efficient aid from this quarter until the hunters return.  The few I have found at home seem perfectly disposed to do whatever may be required of them.</p><p>The late glorious news from <name><abbr expan="New">N</abbr>. Orleans</name> will I expect render it unnecessary for the Choctaws to go there and I expect by next mail <name><abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr>. Jacksons</name> instruction as to their destination.</p><p>I have every man of influence engaged in the recruiting service and will occasionally report progress to you</p><closer>I have the honor to be with great respect &amp; esteem Your <abbr expan="Obedient">Obt</abbr> Servant <signed>John McKee</signed><add><abbr expan="Brigadier">B</abbr>. Genl James Winchester <unclear>con. E Sec. 7 Mr Dnr</unclear> </add> <pb n="[2]"/> <add><address><addrLine><abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> John McKee Choctaw agency </addrLine></address><date>20 <abbr expan="January">Janny</abbr> 1815</date></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
