<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl580"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1825 Oct. 1, Nashville [Tennessee, to] James Winchester, Cairo [Tennessee] / J[ohn] W. Overton   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Overton, J[ohn] W.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sl580</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1825 Oct. 1, Nashville [Tennessee, to] James Winchester, Cairo [Tennessee] / J[ohn] W. Overton</title><author>Overton, J[ohn] W.</author><date value="1825-10-01">October 1, 1825</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Judge John Overton to General James Winchester, dated October 1, 1825. Overton writes about a recent trip he took with General and Mrs. Jackson. He writes about some law suits that he and Winchester are working on. Overton also wants to know if Winchester received a deed he sent him.</note><note type="collection">James Winchester Papers</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">9</note><note type="document">sl580</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee</item><item>Overton, John, 1766-1833</item><item>Working life</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name>Nashville</name> <date>October 1st 1825</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>Last night I returned to this place from the western Districts, to which place I went in company with <name><abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> Jackson</name> &amp; his lady. <name>Mrs Jackson</name> went to the <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood</orig> of Jackson in <unclear><name>Madison County</name>  , to visit</unclear>  her only two surviving sisters</p><p>The Genl was invited to partake of a public dinner at <name>Paris</name> in <name>Henry County</name>, which detained us a week longer than I expected, and kept me from <unclear>leaving</unclear> here on the 29th as I expected you will therefore have to give <name>Mr Bledsoe</name> another notice, so that I may attend which I will do on being informed of the time</p><p>I could very much wish <pb n="[2]"/> that you could spend a day at my house__ or a week if convenient, in order that we may talk over your law business particularly the suit with <name>Walton</name></p><p>The <name>Donelson</name> suit I am master of__ I am not sure that I am of the other At all events it would be of great service to the cause to talk it over, examining each point critically__ This is the universal practise with Lawyers &amp; their clients __ Writing is not sufficient At all times you Know me well enough to be <orig reg="convinced">convincd</orig> that every exertion will be made on my part</p><p>I transmitted you a deed for your interest in the <name>Ramsey</name> <unclear>tract</unclear> Have you received it if so please acknowledge the receipt <pb n="[3]"/> of it by letter_ and as the deed discharges the obligation  <unclear>you hold</unclear> of mine, it is nothing but right that you should deliver up that obligation to me, sending it by mail or safe private conveyance as soon as you can. Being in years less uncertain, it is my wish that no obligations should lie out, <gap/> case of death__ I presume you omitted to send it <unclear>by when</unclear> you last wrote to me. I therefore expect to hear from you on this subject, being the only obligation I have out in the world</p><p>Present me to <name>Mr &amp; Mrs Breedlove</name>, of whose polite attention when at <name><orig reg="new orleans">orleans</orig> I retain a dull</name> sense</p><closer><salute>As usual <lb/> <abbr expan="yours respectfully">yos Resply</abbr></salute><signed><name><abbr expan="John">J</abbr>W Overton</name></signed><address><addrLine><abbr expan="General James">Gen J</abbr> Winchester &rcub;</addrLine></address><pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine>Genl <name>James Winchester</name></addrLine><addrLine><name>Cairo</name></addrLine></address><add>The <orig reg="honorable">honorabe</orig> <lb/> Judge Overton <lb/> 1st <abbr expan="October">Oct</abbr> 1825</add> <add>Replied to <date>5th Oct <lb/> 1825</date> <lb/> concerning taking <lb/> deposition <abbr expan="etcetera">&amp;c</abbr> <lb/> Walton Case</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
