<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../Rules/teixlite_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl681">
  <teiHeader>
	 <fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
		  <title>[Letter] 1848 Dec. 18, Portersville, Tipton City, Tennessee [to] Neill Brown, Nashville, Tennessee / Henry Adkins : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
		  <author> Adkins, Henry</author>
		  <respStmt>
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
			 <name>Debra Roney</name>
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name>
		  </respStmt>
		</titleStmt>
		<publicationStmt>
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
		  <address>
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
		  </address>
		  <date>2003
		  </date>
		  <idno type="SPCID">sl681</idno>
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
		  <availability>
			 <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
		  </availability>
		</publicationStmt>
		<sourceDesc>
		  <bibl>
			 <title> [Letter] 1848 Dec. 18, Portersville, Tipton City, Tennessee [to] Neill Brown, Nashville, Tennessee / Henry Adkins</title>
			 <author>  Adkins, Henry</author>
			 <date value="1848-12-18"> 
			 December 18, 1848</date>
			 <extent>3p</extent>
			 <note type="summary">This document is a letter from Henry Adkins to Tennessee governor Neill S. Brown in Nashville.  Adkin's purpose in writing the letter is to request that a good set of wagon wheels be made for him in the state penitentiary, where he has heard that the  quality and craftsmanship is said to be very highly regarded.</note>
			 <note type="collection">Governor Neill S. Brown Papers</note>
			 <note type="box">1</note>
			 <note type="folder">3</note>
			 <note type="document"> sl681</note>
		  </bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	 </fileDesc>
	 <encodingDesc>
		<projectDesc>
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
		</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="4">
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
		</editorialDecl>
		<refsDecl>
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
		</refsDecl>
		<classDecl>
		  <taxonomy>
			 <bibl>
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
			 </bibl>
		  </taxonomy>
		</classDecl>
	 </encodingDesc>
	 <profileDesc>
		<textClass>
		  <keywords>
			 <list>
				<item>Tennessee -- History</item><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</item>
			 </list>
		  </keywords>
		</textClass>
	 </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
	 <body>
		<div1 type="Letter"><pb n="1"/>
		  <opener><address><addrLine>Portersville Tipton <abbr expan="City">Cty</abbr> Tenn</addrLine></address><date><abbr expan="December">Decr</abbr>. the 18th 1848</date><add>His <orig reg="Excellency">Exceleancy</orig> <name><abbr expan="Neill">N</abbr>.S. Brown</name> governor of the State of <name><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name>__</add><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>I hope you will excuse your old <add>friend</add> if he has taken too great liberty in asking you to do him a small favor governors can  sometimes do a friend a small favor without any great trouble.  Sir as I know no one else in <name>Nashville</name> but yourself I have concluded to ask you to do the favor &amp; if you do not wish to do it I hope there will be no great harm done.  Sir as both our timber &amp; workmen are both very indifferent &amp; I want a good set of strong <orig reg="wagon">waggon</orig> wheels and am told they make first rate in the <orig reg="Penitentiary">Peniteniary</orig> can or will you be so good <add>as</add> to get me a set made &amp; Shipped to <name>Randolph</name>  please have them two inches on the head the toe 3/4 of inch thick with good bones I do not wish them painted or <orig reg="tared">tard</orig> I wish them just as they are finished by the workman I want the very Strongest kind that can be made. Now for the pay you will please be so good as to inform me what the price is &amp; how I shall get the money to Nashville  &amp; I could pay it to any agent in <name>Memphis</name> or else where that will suit or enclose it by mail just as will be most convenient please write me so soon as you know; the reason I only want the <orig reg="wheels">whells</orig> alone is I can have the  other work done &amp; not have to pay out money which is <orig reg="desirable">disierable</orig> these hard times If it is not in your power to attend to it will be so good as to get some friend to do so please send them to <name>Henry M Daniels</name> &amp;<name> Merot Randolph</name> your compliance will very much oblige your old whig friend</p>
		<closer><signed><name>Henry Adkins</name></signed><pb n="[2]"/>   <add><abbr expan="Note bene">N.B</abbr>. The money shall be as sure as my Prophecy was when you &amp; <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Bell was at my house that you was to be governor before long that was in 1844 but alas we lost old <name>Henry Clay</name> god has never made the man that I would prefer to him I am like in <abbr expan="governor">govrn</abbr> Jones I hated to give him up but must yield Health &amp; <orig reg="prosperity">prosperty</orig> &amp; a long life to your Honor is the wish of your old whig friend hoping I may live to vote for you again &amp; again if necessary Your <abbr expan="respectful obedient servant">respf   obt Svt</abbr> H Adkins</add><pb n="[3]"/> <add><address><addrLine>Portersville Ten</addrLine></address><date>Decr 19</date><address><addrLine>His <abbr expan="honorable">honbr</abbr> N.S. Brown Governor State of </addrLine><addrLine><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr> Nashville</addrLine></address></add></closer></div1>
	 </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
