<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../Rules/teixlite_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl696">
  <teiHeader>
	 <fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
		  <title>[Letter] 1829 May 28, Campbell Station, Tennessee [to] unnamed / Samuel Martin   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
		  <author> Martin, Samuel</author>
		  <respStmt>
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
			 <name>Debra Roney</name>
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name>
		  </respStmt>
		</titleStmt>
		<publicationStmt>
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
		  <address>
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
		  </address>
		  <date>2003
		  </date>
		  <idno type="SPCID">sl696</idno>
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
		  <availability>
			 <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
		  </availability>
		</publicationStmt>
		<sourceDesc>
		  <bibl>
			 <title>[Letter] 1829 May 28, Campbell Station, Tennessee [to] unnamed / Samuel Martin </title>
			 <author> Martin, Samuel </author>
			 <date value="1829-05-28"> 
			 May 28, 1829</date>
			 <extent>1p</extent>
			 <note type="summary">This document is a portion of a letter dated May 28, 1829 from Samuel Martin to an unnamed person.  In the short letter, Martin expresses disappointment that governor Sam Houston has not collected information from other states concerning their laws and regulations of their schools.  He goes on to convey how important a service would be, when given to the state legislature.</note>
			 <note type="collection">Governor Sam Houston Papers</note>
			 <note type="box">1</note>
			 <note type="folder">4</note>
			 <note type="document"> sl696</note>
		  </bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	 </fileDesc>
	 <encodingDesc>
		<projectDesc>
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
		</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="4">
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
		</editorialDecl>
		<refsDecl>
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
		</refsDecl>
		<classDecl>
		  <taxonomy>
			 <bibl>
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
			 </bibl>
		  </taxonomy>
		</classDecl>
	 </encodingDesc>
	 <profileDesc>
		<textClass>
		  <keywords>
			 <list>
				<item>Tennessee -- History</item><item>Houston, Sam, 1793-1863.</item><item>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</item>
			 </list>
		  </keywords>
		</textClass>
	 </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
	 <body>
		<div1 type="[Letter]"><pb n="1"/>
		  <opener><address><addrLine>Campbell station</addrLine></address>  <date>28 may 1829</date><salute>Sir</salute></opener><p>there is much disappointment caused, by being that governor <orig reg="Houston">Huston</orig>         has not as (Expected he would) anything, toward collecting information, from the different states, of their laws &amp; regulations about their schools look at general <orig reg="Howard's">Howards</orig>, Circular, printed in the  Republican, a few <del>week</del> weeks ago, if you would take the trouble to collect this information, &amp; lay it before the Legislature, you would do for the people, what no other governor <add>of Tennessee</add> has yet done what these will do, who is to be, I cannot say but were these whose situation admits of it, to <unclear>them</unclear> themselves more worthy I think the people <gap reason="document is torn"/> them as their works deserved</p>
		  <closer><name>Samuel Martin</name></closer></div1>
	 </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
