<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc096">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1838 Jan. 29, Washington City [to] James Park, Knoxville,  Tennessee / Luke Lea :a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Lea, Luke</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc096</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1838 Jan. 29, Washington City [to] James Park, Knoxville, Tennessee / Luke Lea</title>
               <author>Lea, Luke</author>
               <date when="1838-01-29">January 29, 1838</date>
               <extent> 3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated January 29, 1838 from Luke Lea to James Park in Knoxville Tennessee.  The letter concerns a matter involving testimony in an unnamed committee of investigation.  Lea compares the proceedings of the investigation to the Spanish Inquisition.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Parks Family</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-538 b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc096</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>United States. Congress</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007155840"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Lea, Luke, 1783-1851</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc096a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Washington City</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date when="1837-01-29">January 29th 1837</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute> ,</opener>
            <p>By the last mail I had the pleasure of receiving your <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice> of the 11th. <choice>
                  <abbr>inst</abbr>
                  <expan>instant</expan>
               </choice>. being the first and only one <choice>
                  <orig>recieved</orig>
                  <reg>received</reg>
               </choice> from you during this winter.-</p>
            <p>I congratulate you upon the marriage of your daughter Eliza.  She has in my humble opinion made choice of a very worthy man for his companion.</p>
            <p>You say that you discover by the papers that we are like to have warm work in both houses-Your predictions are likely to be verified-It has already commenced in the Committees of investigation and will worm its way in to the House of necessity- Several members of the House, among whom is <choice>
                  <abbr>Coln</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Bell, have been summoned and examined on both sides-and I am informed that Judge White Balie Peyton, Pickman and Calhoun of <name>South Carolina</name> and some others are now under subpoena- and I should not be surprised if the President himself should be summoned- But I presume that if he should be, he will not attend, as he has already addressed addressed a letter to Wise, as Chairman of one of the select Committees, denying the right of the Committee to call on the heads of departments to testify, and saying that unless specific charges are made and, that they shall not leave their public duties <pb n="2" facs="sc096b.small.jpg"/> for any such purposes.  He says the committee is nothing better than a <name>spanish</name>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Inquision</orig>
                  <reg>Inquisition</reg>
               </choice>, and expresses his astonishment that the House should ever <add>have</add> raised any such body.  In this letter to Wise, he takes occasion to abuse the committee, &amp; Congress for appointing it and Wise personally, both for his conduct on the committee and for his speeches in the House.  But as this whole business will ultimately come before the public eye, I will for the present, desist from giving you any farther account of the matter, as the space of a letter would not be, at all, equal, to a full development of all the <choice>
                  <orig>villany</orig>
                  <reg>villainy</reg>
               </choice> that is now, here carrying on-</p>
            <p>It is not known, except by a few who is to compare the New Cabinet- In fact there is less said about it than you would suppose-</p>
            <p>I will buy and procure you some beat seed- there is none in this place- Present my respects to <choice>
                  <abbr>Mrs</abbr>
                  <expan>Misses</expan>
               </choice>. Park.  <choice>
                  <abbr>Mrs</abbr>
                  <expan>Misses</expan>
               </choice>. White returned a few days ago from <name>Philadelphia</name> and joined the mess, which we all consider as a great <choice>
                  <orig>acquision</orig>
                  <reg>acquistion</reg>
               </choice>.</p>
            <closer>I am very respectfully Yours. <signed>Luke Lea</signed>
               <add>
                  <name>James Parks <choice>
                        <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>.</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sc096c.small.jpg"/> Free <name>Luke Lea</name>
               <add>congratulation on marriage of daughter Eliza to Chas Coffier</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>James Park Esquire Knoxville <choice>
                        <abbr>E</abbr>
                        <expan>East</expan>
                     </choice>. Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Ella Coffeir</add>
               <add>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>
                        <choice>
                           <sic>30</sic>
                           <orig>30</orig>
                        </choice>
                     </figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <add>
                  <unclear>out</unclear> on the <unclear>9</unclear>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
