<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl053">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Speeches, Addresses, etc.] 1813 Feb. 27, Washington / John Sevier : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Sevier, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl053</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50030646</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Speeches, Addresses, etc.] 1813 Feb. 27, Washington / John Sevier</title>
               <author>Sevier, John</author>
               <date when="1813-02-27">February 27, 1813</date>
               <extent> 1p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is an address written by John Sevier on February 27, 1813. Sevier discusses the topics and events that have taken place in Washington during the last government session. In the address, Sevier states that more money and manpower will be given to the army and navy in order to fight the British. The navy at this time is strong, while the army's land battles have not been very successful. In fighting the British, many American soldiers have been taken as prisoners in Canada. Sevier worries that with the southern soldiers joining the northern troops near the Canadian border, that the Cherokee and whites remaining in the south will be at war over land and rights. Sevier states that Congress has reported using $21 million in expenditures and proposes a further $20 million be used for merchant bonds. Congress also rejected a bill requiring a 25 cent per gallon tax on the sale of whiskey. Sevier concludes the address by mentioning events and disputes in Europe between England, Spain, France, and Russia.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true"> Tennessee Historical Society</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">Correspondence by Author, 1809 b2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl053</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>United States -- Politics and government -- 1789-1815</term>
               <term>Speeches, addresses, etc.</term>
               <term>United States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr89016779"
                        role="Creator http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/cre">Sevier, John, 1745-1815</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl053a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">WASHINGTON</name>,<date when="1813-02-27">27th February, 1813.</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE period in a few days will arrive which will close the present session. To give you a full detail of all the national occurrences would far exceed the bounds of a letter--Let it therefore suffice to make such communication as most materially concerns our immediate interest. Permit me first to state, that every reasonable, just and honorable proposition has been held out by the administration for the purpose of inducing an accommodation and to prevent the further effusion of human blood. Nevertheless, no proposition has, or in my opinion will be acceded to by that haughty, tyrannical, and malicious government, until she again measures her strength in endeavoring by every foul art in her power to subjugate our free and independent nation, and hang round our necks the iron and despotic yoke of the British government.</p>
            <p>Knowing as I do that the free and enlightened sons of <name type="place">Tennessee</name> (and I hope of the nation) are among the last that will submit to such degraded slavery, I have deemed it a duty in every instance, so far as my weak judgment enabled me, to guard against the diabolical machinations of the malignant and embittered nation with whom we are at war. We have passed laws for the better organization of the army, and an additional force of twenty regiments. It has also been found indispensably necessary to augment and increase considerably the navy. Imperious circumstances have demanded these preparations — The safety of our insulted and grossly injured country has required it to be done. Laws are passed for obtaining on loan sixteen millions, and to issue treasury notes for five millions more; which is expected, with other resources, to be amply sufficient to meet the expenditures of the present year.</p>
            <p>Much has been said respecting merchants' bonds, which they had given on their own goods, to an amount of twenty millions; and various opinions were entertained on the propriety of the forfeiture of those obligations — and could there have been a correct discrimination, no doubt there were many in that class of importers who ought to have been so dealt with; but it was found that among this description of people, many friendly and well disposed towards the government, and many of whom had actually been encouraged by our consul to ship goods, who was all the time in <name type="place">London</name>. I did not vote on the ultimate passage of the bill for the exoneration, being at that time much engaged on other business, but am decidedly of opinion it was more consistent with the real principles of justice to let some guilty escape rather than to ruin and confound many innocent and well intending with them — At the same time many of the goods were much wanting for the use of the army, and could not have been procured elsewhere. On these goods a revenue to the amount of five millions will be collected, and had the bonds been adjudged forfeited, it is very much to be questioned whether or not the public would have been benefitted. On the whole, I am of opinion it was the safest way to be contented with the double duties, and not inevitably ruin and drag into poverty many good and worthy families. The war, which is most interesting, has not been conducted in that successful way by any means that we had a just right to expect. The army of brave and gallant heroes at <name type="place">Detroit</name> was shamefully and cowardly surrendered to an enemy with about one half of its own force, without resistance: and at the same time well supplied with arms of all kinds, and all the necessary munitions of war, and in a strong and well fortified garrison!!! The small detachment which engaged the enemy at <name type="place">Queenstown</name>, though not victorious, made them pay very dear for all the laurels they won. The unfortunate defeat of <choice>
                  <abbr>gen.</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Winchester's army, no doubt  you have long since had the particulars — it is much to be lamented that a gallant &amp; brave set of men have been lost in the action, and long will <name type="place">Kentucky</name> have occasion to mourn the loss of many of her best sons. We are not as yet in possession of the true causes that have led to this fatal calamity; but so far as information is not going, it appears that the army was surprised with superior force — <name type="person">General Winchester</name>, with about four hundred and eighty officers and privates, are prisoners in <name type="place">Canada</name>. Great barbarities and cruelties were exercised on the unfortunate wounded by the savages, after the surrender, in the presence of the British who did not interfere! Our infant navy has and is daily performing wonders; their skill, valor and intrepidity astonish the whole world. The enemy has made a number of fruitless attacks on our vessels of war, and sometimes with superior force; in all of which they have been shamefully beaten, and in several engagements their vessels were so crippled and torn to pieces, that it was with difficulty they could be held above water until the prisoners and cargoes could be removed. The frigate Constitution has in two instances handled some of the best frigates in the British navy in this manner.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding our ill successes on land, I have no doubt our troops will shortly begin to repay the enemy with redoubled interest. Our officers and soldiers will daily become more experienced and better disciplined — The arts of war will be more familiar and better understood.</p>
            <p>The frequent successes of the northern tribes, I fear will excite our southern neighbors to be less disposed to continue tranquil, and on this point particularly, I hope my fellow citizens will be cautiously guarded, to neither suffer themselves to be surprised or give any cause of complaint to the Indians. Whilever the Cherokees remain pacific, so long they will afford a good barrier to your southern frontier; and any part of their hunting ground, their claim to which is not yet extinguished, can at any time be easily procured so far as the limits of <name type="place">Tennessee</name> extend,  without war and without the effusion of blood.</p>
            <p>A law has passed both houses for congress to convene again on the fourth Monday in May next. Some particular causes are assigned for this extra session — but there are many , and would not be interesting were they detailed; it is expected the session will be short, and commences so soon, that I shall have but barely time to ride home and return, should I be re-elected.</p>
            <p>A bill was lately introduced in the House of Representatives for laying  a tax of twenty-five cents on each gallon of whiskey distilled within the <name type="place">United States</name> — This bill was rejected by a large majority. It is thought by many that if the non-intercourse law was wholly repealed, that a free trade would then be sufficient to raise a revenue competent to the support of the war in which we are not engaged; on which subject I would be glad to have the opinions of my fellow citizens should they think proper to honor me with their confidence.</p>
            <p>As to European accounts, we have had none of very recent date; it seems that the French have desolated a large part of the Russian empire, and have destroyed a number of the finest cities in that or perhaps any other country. — The Russians have defended themselves with great spirit and bravery, and the damage done on each side is very great and incalculable. As to the affairs in <name type="place">Spain</name> little has been done since autumn — the British are in a fair way to be driven out of the peninsula, and are almost as much despised by the Spanish patriots as they are by the French. There is little doubt but the patriots of Spain will be shortly left to contend against the French alone.</p>
            <p>For further particulars I beg leave to refer you to the documents and papers I have during the session forwarded to Tennessee.</p>
            <p>Before I conclude, permit me to say that in my opinion every necessary preparation has been made for the prosecutions of the war, and to which I have deemed it right to give my support. You will be pleased, so far as may be convenient, to communicate the contents of this letter to the citizens of your county.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have the honor to be, your friend and humble servant,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">JOHN SEVIER</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
