<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl596">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1846 Nov. 18, Knoxville, Tennessee [to] Aaron Brown, Nashville, Tennessee / Isaac Lewis   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Lewis, Isaac</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl596</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1846 Nov. 18, Knoxville, Tennessee [to] Aaron Brown, Nashville, Tennessee / Isaac Lewis</title>
               <author>Lewis, Isaac</author>
               <date when="1846-11-18">November 18, 1846</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated November 18, 1846 from Isaac Lewis in Knoxville, Tennessee to Governor Aaron V. Brown in Nashville.  In the letter, Lewis discusses the completion of the Hiwassee Rail Road, and the hopes and prospects that East Tennesseans hold for it.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Aaron V. Brown Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl596</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Hiwassee Railroad Company</term>
               <term>Brown, Aaron V. (Aaron Venable), 1795-1859</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Lewis, Isaac</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl596a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Knoxville</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Nov</abbr>
                     <expan>November</expan>
                  </choice>. 18th 1846</date>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                     <expan>Dear</expan>
                  </choice>. Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>There is, at this time, strong hope of the completion of the <name>Hiwassee Rail Road</name>, and nearly, if not quite all <choice>
                  <abbr>E. Ten</abbr>
                  <expan>East Tennessee</expan>
               </choice>. is rejoiced at the prospect, as the only means of redeeming this portion of the State__ And while the people are trying to devise the best possible mode of prosecuting the work, the company are likewise endeavoring to adopt the best means to disenthral the Road, and place it in the hands of solvent and additional stockholders of <name>East Tennessee</name>.  There is some anxiety on the part of the others, that the whole matter should be <unclear>thrown</unclear> , or let fall into the hands of Southern men, who, it is believed would readily embrace it.  The whole community, therefore, are content whether it is made by citizens or a company in the south, as to the benefits that will result to E. Ten. But there are fears that if the management of the road is retained in the hands of the same individuals, and at the same place, to wit <name>Athens</name>, as heretofore, there will remain a suspicion in the community, or a want of confidence rather, in the success of the measure.  Therefore, it is thought that a great portion of this stumbling block can be removed by your <unclear>action</unclear> ; and after looking into the premises, you will be able to act deliberately, and that action will not prejudice the company, or any individuals of it.  That is, to appoint men, directors, on the part of the State, at Knoxville and vicinity, and make Knoxville the head quarters or place of the company's operations.  This may seem, <pb n="2" facs="sl596b.small.jpg"/> at first view, like seeking business, but the idea has, in part, been suggested by one or two of the leading men at Athens.</p>
            <p>If the subject strikes your mind in this light, and <add>if</add> you will write me, I will, by the assistance of several others, suggest a number of gentlemen, <unclear>out</unclear> of whom you can get an energetic and reliable board, so far as the State is concerned.</p>
            <p>There is no work that could be named that would do E. Ten. so much good as the completion of this road, and if it falls back now we are hid in the sand for at least an age.</p>
            <p>Already our citizens, below here, are exchanging cornmeal for Liverpool salt, bushel for bushel, which of itself will be a saving to us of thousands of dollars per annum.</p>
            <closer>Your friend <signed>Isaac Lewis</signed>
               <add>His Excellency <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>A.V</abbr>
                        <expan>Aaron Venable</expan>
                     </choice>. Brown</name>
                  <name>Nashville</name>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>
               </add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl596c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>His Excellency <choice>
                           <abbr>Gov. A.V</abbr>
                           <expan>Governor Aaron Venable</expan>
                        </choice>. Brown Nashville <choice>
                           <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>.</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
