<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl440">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1822 Jan. 27, Knoxville, T[ennessee] [to] John Overton, Nashville, T[ennessee] / P.M. Miller   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Miller, P.M.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl440</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1822 Jan. 27, Knoxville, T[ennessee] [to] John Overton, Nashville, T[ennessee] / P.M. Miller</title>
               <author>Miller, P.M.</author>
               <date when="1822-01-27">January 27, 1822</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from P.M. Miller to John Overton, dated January 27, 1822. Miller gives a list of several topics that he wants Overton to consider. He wonders if there is someone other than Andrew Jackson to run for governor of Tennessee. Miller intimates that Jackson may be groomed for President if elected governor. He mentions the penitentiary house and that another may be built if needed. Miller writes about the question of slavery's effect on the presidential election. He thinks there will be  many candidates running for president.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Overton Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">Correspondence</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">12</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl440</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Local government</term>
               <term>Slavery Political aspects United States History 19th century</term>
               <term>Presidential elections</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Miller, P. M.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl440a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Knoxville</name>
                     <date>January 17th 1822</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>D</abbr>
                     <expan>Dear</expan>
                  </choice> Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>the following <del type="overstrike">[unclear]</del> considerations are offered, 1st is there any man whose personal popularity is so likely to assist in <unclear>fixing</unclear> the seat  of government permanently at any given point as <name>Andrew Jackson</name>, if so why should he not be our next governor, or why should this not be wished <add>for</add> by those who desire this result___</p>
            <p>I am satisfied that this cannot be done with the present legislature. I presume some of them may be <choice>
                  <orig>commited</orig>
                  <reg>committed</reg>
               </choice> &amp; if the legislature should <add>be</add> called, for the doing of which there is not the slightest precept__ what is there to work on__ literally nothing in the fall of 1823__ there is of necessity a Senator to make__ south of <unclear>Th B</unclear> the monies due from the <name>High wassee</name>District will have become due, a great many things will be wanting in the <name>chickasaw</name> country___ I am not sure how <name>Bedford</name> will be represented__ the parties for the next President will be developed___ the <choice>
                  <orig>Pennitentiary</orig>
                  <reg>Penitentiary</reg>
               </choice> may be <unclear>received &amp;    fixed</unclear> some where in the east if necessary <unclear>&amp; the</unclear> seal of government in the west_ this will buy the ground for another penitentiary house in the west if I should be necessary_ the Judiciary may be <unclear>revived</unclear> ,  ma <add>n</add> y alterations might be made to suit, particular ends, when the <choice>
                  <orig>publick</orig>
                  <reg>public</reg>
               </choice> sentiment <choice>
                  <orig>favoured</orig>
                  <reg>favored</reg>
               </choice> those ends &amp; it was otherwise just &amp; proper__  I am very sure that no one thing ought to be done, at the present session <pb n="2" facs="sl440b.small.jpg"/> if this should be a call that can be left undone__</p>
            <p>the District for members will be attended to__ in 1823 I shall be able to point out persons, who will be prepared to act, as I hope my friends always well, a fair open &amp; honest part_ I believe you have lived long enough to know that all men do not do this__ I know that Jackson has been solicited to become a candidate for a very high office, if he should be elected governor &amp; they are sincere in these views it will give strength <unclear>&amp;c</unclear> your to those <unclear>pretences</unclear> I read a private letter from the west stating that <name>Grundy</name> had abounded the head of department at <name>Nashville</name>&amp; said that he would speak to me__ this I believe in part but I <choice>
                  <orig>immagine</orig>
                  <reg>imagine</reg>
               </choice> I understand this matter___ the publications at the <name>Shelbyville</name> &amp; the appointment of the author to office does look a little contemptuous it must be allowed__ how do you do <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Crab</name> which way is <name>Col E. H. Foster</name> &amp; <name>General Gibbs</name> while looking over the political Hemisphere, I should expect that it is not <choice>
                  <orig>wholy</orig>
                  <reg>wholly</reg>
               </choice> improbable, that most of the states individually will set up a candidate for President this will prevent a caucus beyond all doubt &amp; congress will have to select one <del type="overstrike">beyond all doubt</del>
               <add>as a consequence</add> the two great states <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Pennsyl.</abbr>
                     <expan>Pennsylvania</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> &amp; <name>New York</name> will doubtlessly understand Each other that &amp; the slave question will probably give to East the President___ but whether it will be from either of those states is doubtful, the smaller states will join the south if they can have the President___ <pb n="3" facs="sl440c.small.jpg"/> so that the smaller states will probably make the President___ will you take time to consider of there matters so far as they concern our Local affairs_ &amp; <choice>
                  <orig>assertain</orig>
                  <reg>ascertain</reg>
               </choice> how far certain persons will act on them, I know that grundy had different views at the called session, &amp; I as well know he was wrong, I know that if you fall in with my notions that you know how to act, I shall see you in the latter end of march I expect when we can converse more freely</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am D Sir</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>PM Millers</name>
               </signed>
               <add>this letter is nothing more than notes for your comment___</add>
               <add>Private</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl440d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Knoxville <choice>
                        <abbr>T</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>30 <choice>
                           <abbr>Jany</abbr>
                           <expan>January</expan>
                        </choice> 1822</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Paid 187</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>John Overton</name> Esquire</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Nashville</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>P M Miller <lb/> 27th Jany 1822</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
