<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl423">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1844 Jun. 8, Carthage [Tennessee, to unknown recipient] / [Adam Fergusson] : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>[Fergusson, Adam]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl423</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1844 Jun. 8, Carthage [Tennessee, to unknown recipient] / [Adam Fergusson]</title>
               <author>[Fergusson, Adam]</author>
               <date when="1844-06-08">June 8, 1844</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to an unknown recipient dated June 8, 1844. The author is most likely Adam Fergusson. Fergusson is writing to announce the nomination of James K. Polk for president. He describes the convention party in Carthage. According to Fergusson the citizens celebrated with great enthusiasm. Fergusson also writes about people's reactions to the nomination.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">IV-G-1, B6</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl423</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Polk, James K., 1795-1849</term>
               <term>Politics</term>
               <term>Political conventions</term>
               <term>
                  <name>[Fergusson, Adam]</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl423a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Carthage</name> 8th June 1844</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <orig>I</orig>
                  <reg>It</reg>
               </choice> is with feelings of delight I give you the particulars of what took place here on the reception of the news of the nomination of <name>James K Polk</name> for President and <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Geo</abbr>
                     <expan>George</expan>
                  </choice> W Dallas</name> for Vice President. on wednesday evening last a slip  from <name>Gallatin</name> informed us barely of the nomination and that of <name>Silas Wright</name>
               <unclear>for</unclear>
               <del type="overstrike">the</del> vice President. We were not certain until the union of Thursday until then our Democratic friends Seemed to hesitate about the certainty of the news but when all doubt was reserved the unanimity of feeling was all powerful no <choice>
                  <orig>disenting</orig>
                  <reg>dissenting</reg>
               </choice> voice among the Democracy. But among the whigs nothing but dejection and murmurs in <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice> of <name>van Buren</name> were heard Some few of the whigs felt not a little of State Pride which Showed itself in their conversations although they tried to suppress it as much as Possible. a few of us proposed an <choice>
                  <orig>ilumination</orig>
                  <reg>illumination</reg>
               </choice> ; it was <choice>
                  <orig>nearely</orig>
                  <reg>nearly</reg>
               </choice> dark when the proposition was made Divine Service was about to be performed in the court House- Candles  and fireworks were <del type="overstrike">performed</del>
               <add>prepared</add> by some while others attended <del type="overstrike">down</del> so preaching no noise or bellowing was permitted all was perfect Silence until the last Hymn was chanted then as if by magic the <choice>
                  <orig>Squre</orig>
                  <reg>Square</reg>
               </choice>  was <del type="overstrike">let</del> lighted up in the most brilliant manner. And the congregation who <del type="overstrike">had</del>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl423b.small.jpg"/> were in the House and knew nothing of what was going <add>with</add> -out were more than <choice>
                  <orig>agreable</orig>
                  <reg>agreeable</reg>
               </choice> surprised to find that every avenue to their House was as bright as day <choice>
                  <orig>Their</orig>
                  <reg>They're</reg>
               </choice> convinced a species of fire works which <unclear>aded</unclear> greatly to the <choice>
                  <orig>briliancy</orig>
                  <reg>brilliancy</reg>
               </choice> of the night. Democrat and whig Joined together Some whigs <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear>hugged</unclear>
               </del> crying out Huyya a for Polk while others cried Huyya for <name>Clay</name> never was there such an excitement and good feeling in Carthage or such an <choice>
                  <orig>ocasion</orig>
                  <reg>occasion</reg>
               </choice> before The Democrats had a glorious time of it. About 10 'clock the lights were all extinguished and the Democrats having <add>most of them</add>
               <del type="overstrike">all</del> returned to their homes Some eight or ten whigs and as many boys and negroes endeavoured to make a Show and paraded the Streets with a Drum and fiddle <add>Shouting for clay</add> and annoyed most of the houses in town until daylight at which time many of them as I am informed were intoxicated with the nights revel whatever may be the result the slips taken here has had thee most powerful effect</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
