<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch038">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter, 1818 July 15, Washington to John C. Calhoun, Sec[retar]y of War / Jeremiah Evarts [and] Elias Cornelius : a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Evarts, Jeremiah, 1781-1831</author>
            <author>Cornelius, Elias, 1794-1832</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch038</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44837330</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Letter, 1818 July 15, Washington to John C. Calhoun, Sec[retar]y of War / Jeremiah Evarts [and] Elias Cornelius</title>
               <author>Evarts, Jeremiah, 1781-1831</author>
               <author>Cornelius, Elias, 1794-1832</author>
               <date when="1818-07-15">July 15, 1818</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">Copy of a letter dated July 15, 1818 from Jeremiah Evarts and Elias Cornelius, agents for the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, to John C. Calhoun, Secretary of War describing the fundamental goals of their society and requesting aid for several of their Cherokee mission projects.</note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">29</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch038</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Indian agents</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Missions</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="https://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n87802039"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Cornelius, Elias, 1794-1832</name>
               </term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n81114178"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Evarts, Jeremiah, 1781-1831</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch038a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>
               <add place="top">C.</add>
               <lb/>Letter from <name type="person">Jeremiah Evarts</name> Esq.  <name type="person">Rev. Elias Cornelius</name> to the <choice>
                  <abbr>Hon.</abbr>
                  <expan>Honorable</expan>
               </choice>
               <name type="person">John C. Calhoun</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Secy.</abbr>
                  <expan>Secretary</expan>
               </choice> of War dated
               </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Washington</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <date when="1818-07-15">July 15 1818</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>As agents for the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions we beg leave to offer the following suggestions  enquiries.  We need not trouble you with a long introduction, as there are several documents in your <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear/>
               </del> department relative to the general subject of this communication.</p>
            <p>Permit us to observe, however, that the society in whose behalf we speak, entertains the most large  liberal designs; that its members reside in seven states of the union,  the only reason why they are not found in every state is the impracticability of their meeting to transact business, if so widely dispersed; that it has patrons  friends in all the states of the union; that its members are not confined to any religious denomination; that it disowns <add place="supralinear">all</add> narrow, local or party views,  seeks to do good by aiding in the moral improvement of our fellow-men, whereever accessible, who have not yet enjoyed the blessings of civilization  christianity; that it regards with peculiar interest the wants of the Aborigines within our own borders; that it acknowledges with gratitude the favorable regards  the important aid of government;  that it will not solicit the patronage of government for any object, to which the members of the society are not ready to contribute their property, their time  their <choice>
                  <orig>labour</orig>
                  <reg>labor</reg>
               </choice>.<pb n="2" facs="ch038b.small.jpg"/>Permit us to add, that <add place="supralinear">as</add> the various concerns of the board are becoming weighty both on account of the expense  responsibility attached to them,  as prudence, circumspection  economy are highly necessary the committee  other agents of the board will not make any communications to government without great care and deliberation.
               </p>
            <p>After these remarks we would respectfully enquire <hi>1st</hi> whether the government may not with propriety give further assurances, that, in case the Indian title to the land on which our schools are  shall be established, should, hereafter, be extinguished, the Board shall enjoy the land occupied  improved by them, it being understood, that all the avails  profits of such tenements shall be applied solely to the benevolent objects for which the board was formed?  It is proper to state here, that it is a favorite plan of the Committee to exhibit a favorable  thorough specimen of agriculture before the eyes of the Indians, and to cultivate all the grains, grasses  fruits which are suited to the various climates of our stations.  For these purposes,  to prevent annoyance from near <choice>
                  <orig>neighbours</orig>
                  <reg>neighbors</reg>
               </choice>, probably no man would think a mile square too great a reservation.  This enquiry will be deemed proper when it is considered, that great expense has been already incurred in improving the farm among the <name type="person">Cherokees</name>  similar expenses are contemplated at other stations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>2dly</abbr>
                     <expan>2ndly</expan>
                  </choice>
               </hi> Will <add place="supralinear">not</add> the government supply a greater number of implements of husbandry  of domestic manufacture, than have as yet been promised?</p>
            <p>At the school among the <name type="person">cherokees</name>, there are already<pb n="3" facs="ch038c.small.jpg"/>more than twenty boys, who can handle the hoe  the axe, very dexterously.
               </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>3dly</abbr>
                     <expan>3rdly</expan>
                  </choice>
               </hi> As it is found desirable to give some promising Indian youths a more thorough education, than they can receive in their own tribes,  to give them a fair  full view of the benefits of civilized society, will not the government bear a moderate part of the expense of their journey  residence for this purpose?</p>
            <p>Four youths of this description are now under our care in this city, on their way to an excellent school, designed gratuitously for their benefit  the benefit of others in similar circumstances.  <add place="bottom">As a particular amount of these youths, has already been given to this Department by one of us, it is not necessary to repeat the account here.</add>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>4thly</hi>  Will not the government assist in the erection a a corn mill near each station, provided it can be done at a moderate expense, with the approbation of the public agent,  with a prospect of success?</p>
            <p>So important is a Mill to the comfort of the family and schools, that the Board have already expended five hundred dollars in building one among the <name type="person">cherokees</name>.  It was not quite completed on the <date when="--06-01">1st of June last</date>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>5thly</hi> Should the board feel able to comply with the earnest  desire of the emigrants to the <name type="place">Arkansas</name>  send a Mission  family  school master thither, as soon as possible, will not the government afford some extraordinary aid, particularly as the </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="ch038d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>distance is great, the passage circuitous  expensive,  the obtaining of supplies difficult?</p>
            <p>Expressing a confident opinion that the civil  moral improvement of the Indians will promote the true policy, the interest, and the dignity of the <name type="place">United States</name>,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>we are Sir, With sentiments of great respect and consideration, your obedient servants</salute> (Signed)<signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Jerh.</abbr>
                        <expan>Jeremiah</expan>
                     </choice> Evarts</name>
               </signed>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Elias Cornelius</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
