<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc186">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1840 May 8, Pulaski, Tennessee  [to] Jane T. Wood, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania  / Sarah Bet			 : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Bet, Sarah</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc186</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1840 May 8, Pulaski, Tennessee [to] Jane T. Wood, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania / Sarah Bet</title>
               <author>  Bet, Sarah</author>
               <date when="1840-05-08"> 
			 May 8, 1840</date>
               <extent> 4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated May 8, 1840 from Sarah Bet in Pulaski, Tennessee to her cousin Jane T. Wood in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.  The purpose of the letter is to answer a previous communication from Wood.  In the letter, Bet details many intriguing and interesting events about people and life in Pulaski.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Sarah Bet Letters</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-1875</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc186</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Bet, Sarah</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc186a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Pulaski</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>May 8th 1840</date>
               <salute>Ever dear and beloved Cousin</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your interesting epistle dated the 25th was received a few days go, and it is with much pleasure that I now hasten to answer it, though I must tell <add place="supralinear">you</add> at the commencement that I know of nothing very interesting or answering to write but I shall at least attempt to entertain you for a few minutes, though I fear I shall fail  to do so.    Oh! Jane how much I wish you were here to converse with me face to face, instead of <del>being</del> writing to you for I have <del type="overstrike">so</del> so much to tell you if I could see you, that I cannot write.</p>
            <p>Would you not prefer being in our little village enjoying yourself with us instead of being confined at school with those dry studies; yes I know you would.  <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> &amp; <choice>
                  <abbr>Mrs</abbr>
                  <expan>Misses</expan>
               </choice> Knox, <name>Gene Crockett</name>, and <name>Mary Park</name>, are now with us, and you cannot imagine what fine times we have.  We had a party on Sunday, and are to have another <del>on</del>  tonight and three or four next week.  Do <add place="supralinear">you</add> not think that this is doing very well for our little town the population not exceeding 1600 inhabitants. <pb n="2" facs="sc186b.small.jpg"/> You cannot imagine how many leave the girls here.   Since they have been staying at Mrs. <unclear>Aderms</unclear> the house has been more like an inn than a private house.  Jane has taken in the <choice>
                  <abbr>Hon</abbr>
                  <expan>Honorable</expan>
               </choice>
               <name>EJ Shields</name>, and Maury the handsome and dignified <del>Cou</del> Count Leathermen, and a dozen others too numerous to mention</p>
            <p>
               <unclear>Jane how did you hear of May day.</unclear>  I do not think I ever enjoyed myself so much in my life.  We had no Queen, but a delightful fire-one party in the woods.  We were gone all day, and had our dinner sent to us; returned to town late in the  evening, and had <add place="supralinear">a</add> party that night.</p>
            <p>Jane did you ever hear of so many marriages in your life. I declare it beats bob tail.  I expect by this time <name>Hate Hearney</name>    is a married man; we received a letter from him a few days ago, and he was to start the next day for his license.  I believe he is to <del>be</del> be united in the silken hands of matrimony to Miss <name>Mary Harris</name> of <name>Vicksburg</name>.  I am not going to believe it until I hear that he is married  He is always going to be  married but never makes it out, at least has not heretofore.     You wish to know what had become of <name>Dave Reynolds</name>.  Did you not know that he was married He was married to <name>Mary Abernathy</name> (cousin Oscar's old sweetheart) before I left <name>Nashville</name> I tell you what these college chaps "beats all nature" dont they?  They pretend to love mighty hard at first but they very soon get over it   <name>Tom Brown</name>, and <name>Alf Albernathy</name> are still here but they go by the appellation of the Exclusives.  There have <add place="supralinear">been</add> several college boys here lately, and amongst them was little <name>Billy Pikes</name>
               <pb n="3" facs="sc186c.small.jpg"/> Were you not acquainted him.  He was wonderfully taken with <name>Eliza Jane Brambitt</name>.</p>
            <p>But it is time for me to stop with my foolishness, as I have not time to write anymore now, as I have no  less than four more letters to write this morning.  Jane answer  this soon if you please and Jane be sure to come <add place="supralinear">home</add> this summer.</p>
            <closer>Give my love to all the girls, and believe <add place="supralinear">me</add> your Sincere Friend &amp; cousin <name>Sarah Bet</name>
               <pb n="4" facs="sc186d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Miss Jane T Wood Care of Miss Hawks Philadelphia  Pennsylvania <add>Mail</add>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
