<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl311">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1846 Apr. 14, Dresden, Tennessee [to] Adam Fergusson, Carthage, Ten[nessee] / M. D. Cardwell  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Cardwell, M. D.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl311</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1846 Apr. 14, Dresden, Tennessee [to] Adam Fergusson, Carthage, Ten[nessee] / M. D. Cardwell</title>
               <author>Cardwell, M. D.</author>
               <date when="1846-04-14">April 14, 1846</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated April 14, 1846, to Adam Fergusson in Carthage, TN from M. D. Cardwell in Dresden, TN.  Cardwell discusses his fondness for President Polk, and he mentions a cavalcade of Mormons on their way to settle in California.  Cardwell states that he hopes to start a regular correspondence with Fergusson.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers </note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">IV-G-1 b2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl311</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Cardwell, M. D.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl311a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Dresden</name>
                     <name type="place"> Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1846-04-14">April 14th 1846</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>having some leisure moments, I have concluded to dedicate them to you, to see if I can drive off the 'blues' and collect an idea worthy the perusal of one for whom I most certainly  entertain the highest regard But the question is, what shall I write?  Politics, they have become stale Shall I speak of <name type="place">Oregon</name>, the "Eden of the West" why with its history you are as familiar as myself _ Soon shall the  <choice>
                  <orig>Brittish</orig>
                  <reg>British join</reg>
               </choice> Lion Crouch and yield to the American Eagle with its stars and stripes  Shall I speak of <name type="person">Mr. Polk</name>, I should only breathe what is wafted on every breeze _ <unclear>?</unclear> , undoubtedly, is the most popular president we have ever had and that too deservedly so, every act of his administration has been marked with the most devoted and truly american principles _ Owing his elevation to <del type="overstrike">any</del> no particular portion of the  democratic party in the Country, he may be truly termed the "peoples president" and the voice of the nation is <q>A nations gratitude is sung <lb/> To thee our standard bearer, young <lb/> Though thou art, around they standard freemen press <lb/> And all thy acts approve and bless <lb/> Thy public acts we've closely scanned _ <lb/> We find them just, in wisdom planned.</q>  you must pardon my attempt in verse, but he deserves all praise — And his entire course meets my warmest approbation <pb n="2" facs="sl311b.small.jpg"/> But of what, and upon what subject shall I write _ should <gap agent="damage"/> gay spring, with her mantle of green was here, I should be far behind the  birds, for weeks you have heard them chant of a winter gone Should I speak of the face of the country,  you have seen that for yourself  Should I tell you I was happy, you would ask me to  Examine my heart _ . Should I say that I am unhappy, you _would say it would be unnatural to be otherwise  Well I will tell you one thing, if I am miserable, the world shall never know it _<q>I may weep though the tears I will hide, <lb/> When I think of the hour we parted, <lb/> Bow meekly, and tamely abide <lb/> The fiat one that is false-hearted.</q>
            </p>
            <p>By heavens here goes a <choice>
                  <orig>calvacade</orig>
                  <reg>cavalcade</reg>
               </choice> of Mormons, on their way to <name type="place">california</name>, poor deluded <del type="overstrike">wretch</del> creatures, I pity them from my heart _ It seems that they <choice>
                  <orig>labour</orig>
                  <reg>labor</reg>
               </choice> under some strange hallucination of mind, to quit, country 'kith and kin' to follow a few designing <choice>
                  <orig>impostures</orig>
                  <reg>imposters</reg>
               </choice> _ May the  Great architect shield and preserve them and may they yet be enlightened _ My health is good and hope these may find you and yours in the enjoyment of health and happiness</p>
            <p>My prospects in life are good so far as a living is concerned, of my troubles you have heard me speak This very unintelligible letter is intended to spur a regular <choice>
                  <orig>correspondance</orig>
                  <reg>correspondence</reg>
               </choice> should you deem it worthy by which I hope <add place="supralinear">to</add> receive many <unclear>?</unclear> to soothe a troubled heart  Hoping soon to hear from you</p>
            <closer>
               <salute> I remain your friend</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">MD Cardwell</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>A</abbr>
                        <expan>Adam</expan>
                     </choice> Fergusson <choice>
                        <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl311c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Dresden <choice>
                        <abbr>Te</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1846-04-15">15th April</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Adam Fergusson</name> Esqr</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>{<name type="place">Carthage</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>{<choice>
                        <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="top right">5</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
