<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc017">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1837 June 12, Knoxville, Te[nnessee] [to] H. M. Nelson,
			 Fayetteville, N[orth] Carolina / E[llis] S[ylvester] Chesbrough : a
			 machine-readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chesbrough, Ellis Sylvester</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Mays</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno>sc017</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50009925</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1837 June 12, Knoxville, Te[nnessee] [to] H. M.
				Nelson, Fayetteville, N[orth] Carolina / E[llis] S[ylvester] Chesbrough
				</title>
               <author>Chesbrough, Ellis Sylvester</author>
               <date when="1837-06-12">June 12, 1837</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This document is a letter from Ellis Sylvester
				Chesbrough of Knoxville, Tennessee, dated June 12, 1837 to H. M. Nelson in
				Fayetteville, North Carolina. Chesbrough, an educated professional, writes
				mainly of his experiences staying with people living in the Cumberland
				Mountains.</note>
               <note type="Collection"> Ellis Syvester Chesbrough</note>
               <note type="Box">n/a</note>
               <note type="Folder">MS-923</note>
               <note type="Document">sc017</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee </term>
               <term>North Carolina </term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chesbough, Ellis Sylvester</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc017a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Knoxville, 
					 <choice>
                           <abbr>Te.</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                     <date when="1837-06-12">June 12, 1837</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Yours of the 
			 <date when="---14">14th</date>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>ulto</abbr>
                  <expan>ultimo</expan>
               </choice> was forwarded to this place from 
			 <name type="place">Flat Rock</name>, and I was very glad to get it. I
			 suppose when you wrote you did not think it would have to follow me about so;
			 but so it is. I have been for some time, a little like Noah's dove which found
			 no rest for the sole of its feet. Lately they have been talking of sending me
			 into 
			 <name type="place">Kentucky</name> not to be stationed there however;
			 but whether this is really to be or not, I am not able to tell as
			 yet.</p>
            <p>So you have become familiar with "dwelling in tents". Well I am not
			 surprised that you should like it better than lodging in the farm houses
			 generally for if they are like some that I have been in, among the 
			 <name type="place">Cumberland Mountains</name>, an encampment must be
			 far preferable. One night I <choice>
                  <orig>staid</orig>
                  <reg>stayed</reg>
               </choice> at a house which
			 had but a single room, one door and I believe no windows. It was quite a
			 chilly night and the openings between the logs and planks were so large, that
			 the air had very free circulation without being subjected to much change of
			 temperature. For supper we had coarse corn bread and butter with
			 buttermilk without any plates and not a remarkably clean table cloth.
			 However as I am not very hard to please about food this did not trouble me a
			 great deal on looking around at my companions, all of whom were to sleep
			 with me in the same room, I found that there were eleven of us in all, viz, the
			 man of the house, his wife and five children, <pb n="2" facs="sc017b.small.jpg"/> two young women who
			 had walked five miles barefooted to help plant corn, and a young man besides
			 myself. As there were but two beds visible, I began to wonder how they
			 would dispose of us. From some cause or other they told me to go to bed first;
			 so I obeyed and commenced undressing myself before the women; which was rather
			 an awkward predicament for me to be placed in, being unaccustomed to such
			 proceedings and as you probably know, rather a bashful young man, when with the
			 ladies. The young women appeared to be quite as modest as myself and
			 turned their backs towards me. After getting into bed, the young man who had
			 been at work all day in the field and did not appear to be very clean, was put
			 in with me, and we two had one bed to ourselves. For the young women they
			 spread another on the floor, and most of the rest huddled together in the
			 third. Our bedstead was too short for me to stretch myself upon it. This, the
			 cool air and their covering made me quite glad to take an early departure the
			 next morning.
               </p>
            <p>The above specimen, is by no means, a fair criterion to judge the
			 people in this part of the country by. Though mostly plain they frequently live
			 very comfortably and possess a good degree of intelligence. In this place, I
			 find the society, so far as I have had leisure to enjoy it quite agreeable. To
			 be sure they are not so fashionable as the 
			 <name type="person">New Yorkers</name> or 
			 <name type="person">Bostonians</name> in many respects, yet to me,
			 this is anything but an objection <del type="overstrike">to them</del>. In this
		  respect, I do not agree with all my companions, some of whom, call it a dull
		  and stupid place. When people show a disposition to be atten <pb n="3" facs="sc017c.small.jpg"/> tive to strangers and are really so, in proportion to their
		  opportunities. I think it is a hard case, if we cannot be pleased, and make
		  allowances for circumstances.
               </p>
            <p>Your cousin whom I mentioned in my last was named 
			 <name type="person">Forby</name>, or something like I think and had
			 been employed a short time previously in 
			 <name type="place">Bangor</name> with 
			 <name type="person">Bedden</name> and 
			 <name type="person">McGaffey</name>, contractors. I believe he is a
			 native of 
			 <name type="person">Maine</name> and has been at sea a good deal,
			 although apparently not much over 20 years of age. He was perhaps a little
			 taller than you are; but not quite so stout. We left him in 
			 <name type="place">Norfolk</name> from which place he said that he
			 intended to proceed to 
			 <name type="place">Fayetteville</name>.</p>
            <p>My duties so far have been to superintend the surveys in this state.
			 At present there are two parties under me, one towards Kentucky and the other
			 towards 
			 <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N.</abbr>
                     <expan>North</expan>
                  </choice>
				Carolina</name>. We also have an office in this place. My brother
			 
			 <name type="person">Lewis</name>, whom I hear is rather unwell, 
			 <name type="person">Mr Bacet</name> and 
			 <name type="person">Mr Wyatt</name> are engaged in this state.
			 We expect to see the Major and 
			 <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Capt.</abbr>
                     <expan>Captain</expan>
                  </choice> Williams
				</name>here shortly. </p>
            <p>There are two Presbyterian Churches in this place. They are very
			 similar to the Trinitarian Congregationalists of 
			 <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N.</abbr>
                     <expan>New</expan>
                  </choice> England</name>. They
			 had an Episcopal Clergy <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>men</unclear> here for a
			 short time and tried to form a society; but did not succeed. I wish they had
			 one for the sake of several of our party, who don't seem to enjoy any other
			 form of worship.</p>
            <p>Remember me to 
			 <name type="person">Messrs. Lee and Bennett</name>. Tell the latter
			 if he has not gone to the north yet, that I wish him a great deal of happiness
			 in his intended change. Write soon </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Yours sincerely</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>E. S.</abbr>
                        <expan>Ellis Sylvester</expan>
                     </choice>
				  Chesbough</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1">
            <p>
               <add place="top">The last time I heard from home, which was about
			 ten days since, they were all as well as usual. In a letter which Father wrote
			 Lewis he mentioned a great many failures among the number, that of 
			 <name type="person">Mr Crary</name>, who was President of the
			 <unclear>Storington</unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Co.</abbr>
                     <expan>Company</expan>
                  </choice> I suppose you have heard of this
			 before. The finances of our country seem to have got into an awful
			 state. 20 per cent has been given here, for specie, on Bank notes of this
			 state.</add>
            </p>
            <p>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">H. M. Nelson</name>, 
				<choice>
                        <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Civil Engineer</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Fayetteville, 
				<choice>
                        <abbr>N.</abbr>
                        <expan>North</expan>
                     </choice> Carolina</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="Middle of back matter">From "Chesbough" Interesting account of life in the
		  Tennessee mountains.</add>
               <add place="bottom">Direct to Knoxville 
		  <choice>
                     <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                     <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
            </p>
            <p>
               <add place="bottom">You mentioned reading the Church service alone
			 on Sundays. It must be lonesome, when there is no other to take an interest in
			 it; but then if our hearts are right before God, we can enjoy his presence and
			 worship under almost any awkward circumstances. Indeed it is one of the
			 grandest features in our religion that it is adapted to every situation in
			 life, to which man can be lawfully called. Your present, is now in the
			 room with me, and as I often look into it, it frequently reminds me of
			 you.</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
