<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch018">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1802 Apr. 30, [to] Colo[nel Return J.] Meigs, Southwest Point, [Tennessee] / Archibald Roane: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Tennessee. Governor (1801-1803 : Roane)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch018</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44770308</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1802 Apr. 30, [to] Colo[nel Return J.] Meigs, Southwest Point, [Tennessee] / Archibald Roane</title>
               <author>Roane, Archibald, 1759-1819 [Tennessee. Governor (1801-1803 : Roane)]</author>
               <date when="1802-04-30">April 30,1802</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter from Archibald Roane, Governor of Tennessee (1801-1803), to Colonel Return J. Meigs, U.S. agent to the Cherokees at Southwest Point in Tennessee, dated April 30, 1802.  Roane reports that  two white men killed a Creek Indian in Jackson County (Tennessee) and the nearby inhabitants fear reprisal from the Indians.  He also advises Meigs to warn the Indians in his area not to hunt near Jackson County, as the local inhabitants are  alarmed.  Roane assures Meigs he will conduct an inquiry into the murder and seek punishment for the perpetrators.  Another letter from Roane on this topic also appears in the Southeastern Native American Documents Database as <ref>ch017</ref>.</note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true"> 22</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch018</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Creek Indians--Crimes against</term>
               <term>Creek Indians--Government relations</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n96010062"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Roane, Archibald, 1759-1819</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch018a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <date when="1802-04-30">30th April 1802</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir, </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have lately heard the disagreeable news that on the <date when="1802-04-21">21st of this month</date> a <name type="person">Creek</name> Indian was killed in <name type="place">Jackson County</name> not far from <name type="person">Mr. Blackburn</name>'s by two men of the names <name type="person">Richmond</name> and <name type="person">Erwin</name>.  I have not been yet able to get the information, with sufficient accuracy to determine what steps it will be necessary to pursue to bring the offenders to punishment if the Act should on examination be deserving of punishment.  My present impressions are that it was a very  unwarrantable Act, perhaps such an one for which the offenders ought to atone with their lives.<pb n="2" facs="ch018b.small.jpg"/>The Inhabitants near that place I understand are considerably alarmed and have collected, (a few families together), for greater safety apprehending that immediate retaliation is intended.  My Information is further, that <name type="person">Major Russell</name> has collected a party and gone to the mountain in search of some camps of Indians, If he should meet with them I dread the consequences.
               </p>
            <p>I think it would be prudent for the Indians to avoid going near that place in their hunting excursions until the present alarm subsides, as any man under apprehension of danger may be induced to do an Act for which he would afterward have cause to repent.  If you have received accurate information<pb n="3" facs="ch018c.small.jpg"/>on this subject please for make a statement of it to me.
               </p>
            <p>You may be assured I will do every thing in my power, consistent with Law to have an impartial enquiry into the nature of the  transaction, and the punishment of the offenders if they should be found to merit it.</p>
            <closer>I am Dear Sir with the highest  respect Your <choice>
                  <abbr>Mo Obdt Servt</abbr>
                  <expan>Most Obedient Servant</expan>
               </choice>
               <signed>
                  <hi>
                     <name type="person">Archibald Roane</name>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Col.o</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel</expan>
                        </choice> Meigs</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="ch018d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>From <name type="person"> 
                  <reg>Archibald</reg> 
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Govr</abbr>
                     <expan>Governor</expan>
                  </choice> Roane</name>
               <lb/>
               <date when="1802-04-30">April 30th 1802</date>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <p>
               <name type="person"> 
                  <reg>Archibald</reg> Governor Roane</name>s letter <date when="1802-04-30">30th <choice>
                     <abbr>Apl</abbr>
                     <expan>April</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <p>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Col.o</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel</expan>
                        </choice> Meigs</name> Agent for the War <choice>
                        <abbr>Depart.</abbr>
                        <expan>Department</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <lb/>
                     <name type="place">South West Point</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
