<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl697">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1829 Apr. 29, Greenville, Tennessee [to] Sam Houston, Nashville, Tennessee / T.A. Howard : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Howard, T.A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl697</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1829 Apr. 29, Greenville, Tennessee [to] Sam Houston, Nashville, Tennessee / T.A. Howard</title>
               <author> Howard, T.A. </author>
               <date when="1829-04-29"> 
			 April 29, 1829</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated April 29, 1829 from T.A. Howard in Greenville, Tennessee to his dear friend, Sam Houston in Nashville.  It is a letter of condolence over the news of Houston's resignation of the Governor's office.  He resigned as a result of a failed and scandalous marriage, that fell apart soon after the wedding.  In the letter, Howard offers his friend words of optimism and hope for his future.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Sam Houston Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">4</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl697</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</term>
               <term>Houston, Sam, 1793-1863.</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Howard, T. A.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl697a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Greenville (<choice>
                        <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>.)</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>29 <choice>
                     <abbr>apl</abbr>
                     <expan>april</expan>
                  </choice> 1829</date>
               <salute>My dear friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Since my arrival here, I saw your resignation of the office of chief magistrate of this state, and I need not tell you that such an item of <choice>
                  <orig>inteligence</orig>
                  <reg>intelligence</reg>
               </choice>, excited my deepest regret.__  To remain silent, when my friend had deemed it proper to take such a course, at the moment at which his country was holding out to him the most flattering prospect of a renewal of her confidence, would be unpardonable, and would prove me <choice>
                  <orig>recriant</orig>
                  <reg>recreant</reg>
               </choice> to every principle of noble and generous friendship.__ The confidence I have ever reposed in you, forbids me to imagine that the cause was either rash or ill advised; and <del>which</del> I deplore the event, and regret with the utmost poignancy, the existence of causes which may have led to this unexpected and unwelcome catastrophe, permit me to assure you <del>to assure you</del> in the sincerity of my heart, that the spirit of friendship unabated, and of confidence undiminished continues to <choice>
                  <orig>aminate</orig>
                  <reg>emanate</reg>
               </choice> my brow towards you.__  In retiring from the busy scene of political life, you ought to remember that you are still Houston; that although you may have misfortunes unforeseen, and therefore unprovided against visited upon you, yet that these things should not be permitted to drink up your spirits, or to prostrate him whose enemies could not in the days of prosperity find the means to destroy  Go where you will,__ let whatever duties await you which are inscrutable providence may appoint, I shall still remember with <unclear>the</unclear> highest feelings of friendship our mutual and unqualified attachment.</p>
            <closer>
               <add>May heaven preserve you.  </add>
               <signed>
                  <name>T A Howard</name>
               </signed>
               <add>Sam: Houston, State Governor of Tennessee</add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl697b.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Greenville <choice>
                           <abbr>T</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <date>3rd May 1829</date>
                  <lb/> 18 3/4 <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Gen</abbr>
                           <expan>General</expan>
                        </choice>. Samuel Houston, Nashville, Tennessee</addrLine>
                  </address> mail <lb/> T.A Howard <date>29 apl 29</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
