<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mc005">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1835 May 18, Kingston, Roane C[oun]ty, E[ast] Tenn[essee] [to] Charles F Welcker / Henry J Welcker: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Welcker, Henry J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>mc005</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50436637</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1835 May 18, Kingston, Roane C[oun]ty, E[ast] Tenn[essee] [to] Charles F Welcker / Henry J Welcker</title>
               <author>Welcker, Henry J.</author>
               <date when="1834-05-18">May 18, 1834</date>
               <extent>4 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a letter dated May 18, 1835, written to  Charles F. Welcker from his brother Henry J. Welcker in Kingston, TN.  Henry  updates his brother on the affairs of the family, including the current status of their father's property and their brothers' whereabouts and circumstances.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Welcker Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1833</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mc005</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Real property</term>
               <term>Surveys</term>
               <term>Railroads -- Design and construction</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Welcker, Henry Inman</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mc005a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Kingston Roane <choice>
                           <abbr>Cty E Tenn</abbr>
                           <expan>County East Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1834-05-18">May 18th 1834</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The present opportunity of addressing you a few lines affords me great pleasure—  I understand <choice>
                  <abbr>fr</abbr>
                  <expan>from</expan>
               </choice>
               <name type="person">J. W. Wester</name>  that you were in good health, and also that you were still well pleased with that County— Father took a trip to the W District about the <date when="--03"> first of March</date>  he went <name type="person">Judge Mitchell's</name> and found them all in good health he stayed only one day and <del type="overstrike">and</del> continued his <choice>
                  <orig>journy</orig>
                  <reg>journey</reg>
               </choice> when he arrived at <name type="place">Denmark</name> he found the timber on <add place="supralinear">his land</add> very much abused— There is a railroad in contemplation which will pass from <name type="place">Jackson</name> to the <name type="place">Tennessee River</name> , there have been three <choice>
                  <orig>routs</orig>
                  <reg>routes</reg>
               </choice> surveyed one passing 7 miles from Denmark one 5 and one passing over one corner of Father's land,— it is thought that it is most probable to pass over Fathers land. But let it pass where it may it will certainly enhance the value of land in that section of Country Father says Denmark is still improving tolerably fast  <pb n="2" facs="mc005b.small.jpg"/> Father on his return from Denmark Stayed at Judge Mitchell's Several days he says that <name type="person">Malindas</name> Children are in good health and that they are fine Children he says <name type="person">Margaret Elizabeth</name> reads better and with more  <unclear>su?</unclear> than any Child of  her age that he ever saw</p>
            <p>We have still received letters from brother <name type="person">Lewis</name> he has enjoyed very good health—. at the last <date when="--01">January</date> Examination he was 27th in French 3rd in drawing and 4th in Mathematics, and <choice>
                  <orig>infact</orig>
                  <reg>in fact</reg>
               </choice>  2nd in Mathematics as there were 2 above him each of whom were e<del type="overstrike">a</del>q<add place="supralinear">u</add>al to head</p>
            <p>I am still staying with <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jas</abbr>
                     <expan>James</expan>
                  </choice> H. Fain</name>  and expect to stay <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice>
               <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Geo</abbr>
                     <expan>George</expan>
                  </choice> S Gillespie</name> returns and opens  his goods, I am staying merely to get a little knowledge of the business and I do not know at this time whether or not I will continue at this business this summer or not</p>
            <p>Father says that if I like the business he will sit me up with a  capital of $2,000 at Denmark <unclear>next</unclear> Spring. If it   Should so happen I shall endeavor to get a partner.  But I would certainly be very Cautious in <choice>
                  <orig>chosing</orig>
                  <reg>choosing</reg>
               </choice> one, for in a case of that kind, a persons welfare depends very much on their partner There is but little news of a general character in this Country The <choice>
                  <orig>Neighbours</orig>
                  <reg>Neighbors</reg>
               </choice> have generally been well <pb n="3" facs="mc005c.small.jpg"/> I was taken with the mumps about 2 weeks ago and was very unwell for about 8 or 9 days the balance of the family have enjoyed very good health this winter and Spring—</p>
            <p>Brother <name type="person">Frederick</name> left home about 2 weeks Since he went to <name type="person">Knoxville</name> and there borrowed a horse from <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Francis</name>   and went <name type="place">Jefferson <choice>
                     <abbr>Cty</abbr>
                     <expan>County</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> and from there to <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                     <expan>William</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <unclear>R</unclear> Love's</name>  Father from there he wrote me a letter he would return to Knoxville for the purpose of returning the horse and that expected a letter from <name type="person">S Inman</name>  of <name type="place">Dandridge</name> letting him know whether or not he wished him to attend to business for him he said that if Inman did not want him he could get into a tolerable business in Knoxville I wrote him a letter and advised him if he could not get into business at Inmans to go to where you are I have not heard from him since and cannot tell what he will do— After I hear from him I will write you a letter and would in the meantime be very glad to receive one from you informing me what you are doing and what you expect to hereafter</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="mc005d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>Brother Lewis wrote a letter a short time since and requested permission to either to return home or to take short <choice>
                  <orig>excurtion</orig>
                  <reg>excursion</reg>
               </choice> through the northern States but father thinks it would be better for him to remain at the Academy <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> his time expires I expect to send this letter  to you by <name type="person">Mr <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                     <expan>William</expan>
                  </choice> Mason</name> who can inform you more about the news of this Country than I Could write you in a letter</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I remain your most affectionate brother</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Henry J Welcker</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Chas.</abbr>
                           <expan>Charles</expan>
                        </choice> F Welcker</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="bottom">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P.S.</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> There was judgements got on your note and Fathers against <name type="person">Jones</name> &amp; <name type="person">
                     <unclear>Jenkin</unclear>
                  </name> at last court and the money has been collected on the first you held against them about 3 months and <name type="person">
                     <unclear>Chelders</unclear>
                  </name> cannot get the money out of the Sheriff he wrote him <del type="overstrike">the</del> a letter a few days since and informed him he would take a judgement against him if he did not send the money immediately</add>
               <signed>
                  <emph>Henry J Welcker</emph>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
