<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="mc003"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Excerpt of a letter] 1833 Jan. 27, West Point, N[ew] Y[ork] [to] Father / [George Welcker] :a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Welcker, George</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><extent> ca. </extent><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>mc003</idno><idno>OCLC: 50436178</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Excerpt of a letter] 1833 Jan. 27, West Point, N[ew] Y[ork] [to] Father / [George Welcker]</title><author>Welcker, George</author><date value="1833-01-27">January 27, 1833</date><extent> 2p</extent><note type="summary">The following document is an excerpt of a letter written by George Welcker at the West Point military academy to his father in Tennessee.   In the letter, George updates his father on issues related to his schooling, including his position in recent class rankings and fellow Tennesseans at West Point.</note><note type="collection">Welcker Papers</note><note type="box">2</note><note type="folder">1833</note><note type="document">mc003</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Military Education</item><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">West Point <abbr expan="New York">N.Y.</abbr></name> <date value="1833-01-27">January 27th 1833 </date>&mdash;</addrLine></address><salute>Dear Father,</salute></opener><p>I have delayed a little longer than I expected to write to you, thinking that I would probably receive one from you, but now I have come to the conclusion that you have postponed writing until you receive my letter and I have therefore set about it.  &mdash;</p><p>Accordingly as I wrote you in my last our examination commenced on the first monday of this month and it finished but two or three days since, the standing of all the Cadets in their different studies has been arranged and published to them. &mdash; In french I am about the middle of my class and I have very little doubt but that I shall be able to rise in it at almost every examination, for I find that the more I study it the easier it becomes to me. &mdash; In mathematics which is much the most difficult and important study, there are only four above me and about seventy-five below me, and I am induced to believe that I shall at least not fall any for we have principally been engaged in the study of Algebra about which I know less than I do of most of the course over which we shall have to pass.&mdash; The algebra that we study here is something similar to a small one that I left at home, but this is at least as large as a volume of Hume's history of <name type="place">England</name>. &mdash; We finished that book and reviewed it several times between <abbr expan="september">sept.</abbr> and the first of January, besides reviewing two books of geometry&mdash; This was done only by the first section or division of my class in which there are about 20 Cadets &mdash; some of the other sections finished their algebra and some of them did not even get that far.&mdash;<pb n="[2]"/> We are now reviewing geometry and we will next study place and spherical trigonometry&mdash; upon these three last together with algebra principally depend all others mathematical branches, such as surveying, navigation, all the calculations in philosophy and astronomy, civil and military engineering <abbr expan="et cetera, et cetera">&amp;c &amp;c</abbr>&mdash; These branches and in fact all others that are learned here are taught more thoroughly at this place than at any other in the Union, and equally as much so as at any other place in the world.&mdash; The examination being now over, all those of my class whose conduct and progress in their studies have been such as to enable the Academic Board to report <orig reg="favorably">favourably</orig> of them, will receive in a short time from the War Department their full appointments as Cadets&mdash; as for my own part I have no fears about mine.&mdash; My class was at first about 120, it has 80 at present, and it is likely that not more than seventy of them will receive their appointments.&mdash; <name type="person">Mr. Williams</name> is about the middle of the class in mathematics, and he is about twenty below me in french, yet I think there is no doubt but that he will receive his appointment and will probably do very well &mdash; There is only one other <name type="person">Tennessean</name> in our class besides Williams and myself, and he is a young man from <name type="place">Nashville</name>  of whom I have almost despaired &mdash; In the first Class which will graduate in June there are two Tennesseans (viz) <name type="person">Mr. Crabb</name> from <name type="place">Knoxville</name> and <name type="person">Thomas</name> from <name type="place">Columbia</name>&mdash; in the second class there is one (viz) <name type="person">Henderson</name> from <name type="place">Franklin</name> who is a nephew of <name type="person"><unclear>Magr.</unclear> Eaton's</name> &mdash; in the third there is one (viz) <name type="person">Henderson</name> from the <name type="place">Western District</name>.&mdash; Ours is the fourth class.&mdash; <name type="person">Mr. Luke Lea <abbr expan="Junior">Jr.</abbr></name> who was elected carrier of the Electoral ticket of <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn.</abbr> was here a few days since in company with his brother who lately graduated at this place &mdash; he is assistant clerk to the senate of our Legislature and he seemed to be of opinion that Eaton would be the next senator</p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
