<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="mc030"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1846 Oct. 31 [to] Mrs. William R. Caswell / William R. Caswell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Caswell, William R.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>mc030</idno><idno>OCLC: 50474434</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1846 Oct. 31 [to] Mrs. William R. Caswell / William R. Caswell</title><author>Caswell, William R.</author><date value="1846-10-31">October 31, 1846</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated October 31, 1846 from Captain William R. Caswell to his wife in Jefferson County, Tennessee. Captain Caswell served in the Mexican-American War and was part of the Tennessee "Volunteers." Caswell wrote numerous letters to his wife while on duty in, and around Mexico.</note><note type="collection">William R. Caswell Papers</note><note type="box">MS-18, b1</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">mc030</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Mexican War, 1846-1848</item><item>United States</item><item>Mexico</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><emph><abbr expan="number">No</abbr> 20</emph><address><addrLine>Steamer <name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> Cross'</name>&mdash; <name type="place">Rio Grande</name>&mdash;<date value="1846-10-31"><abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr> 31st. 1846.</date></addrLine></address><salute>My Dear Wife</salute></opener><p>My last letter was from <name type="place">Monterey,</name> in which I gave you kind of journal up to the 22nd&mdash; I met with no adventure upon my return to <name type="place">Carmango</name> worth relating&mdash; I caught a bad cold either by getting my feet wet in a branch one night, on my return, or else by sleeping out in the Chaparral without a tent, which I did on two nights on my return, being the first time I have passed a night during the campaign without a shelter&mdash; The next morning after I returned to Carmango I went across the river to <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Gen.</abbr> Lamars,</name> camp to hunt for your <name type="person">Uncle Frank</name>, (whom I met on my way to Monterey, as I wrote you &caret;<add place="supralinear">in</add> my last) and to my great disappointment, I found he had left the camp the night before and had gone with the main body of his company about 10 miles distant upon his way to<name type="place"> Loredo</name>&mdash;I wrote a note which I sent &amp; which would overtake him before he should get any further, urging him to come back at once to my quarters in Carmango, but I had not heard from him when I left&mdash; I have met on board this boat, the 1st <emph>kinsman</emph> of my fathers' whom I have ever seen, a cousin of my father&mdash;his name is <name>Gatlin,</name> a brother of the Dr. Gatlin who was killed at Leade's battle ground in <name type="place">Florida</name>&mdash; this gentlemen is a Captain in the <abbr expan="United States">U.S.</abbr> Army&mdash; promoted from a Lieutenancy, for his gallantry in the battles of <name type="place">Resaca</name> &amp; <name type="place">Palo Alto</name>&mdash; he has been wounded in the battle of Monterey, (in the arm)&mdash; and is on his way to the <abbr expan="United States">U.S.</abbr> for the benefit of his general health which is not good&mdash; I think he is very much of a gentleman&mdash;<pb n="[2]"/></p><p>I heard <orig reg="yesterday">yesturday</orig> morning that our Regiment was on their way to <name type="place">Matamaroo</name> &amp; would probably reach these in a few days. I immediately tendered my resignation as Aid De Camp&mdash; and <abbr expan="received">recd.</abbr> orders from<name type="person"><abbr expan="General"> Gen.</abbr> Patterson,</name>  to take command of a detachment of our Regiment who had arrived at Carmango two days before&caret;<add place="supralinear">as invalids&mdash;</add> and proceed with them on board this steamer&mdash;the steam was up when I <abbr expan="received">recd.</abbr> my orders&mdash; I was on board in an hour&mdash; and shall soon be with my company again. I regret very  much to hear that <name type="person">James Brazelton</name> has behaved very badly (very dissipated) and that he has been discharged. I thought I was very badly hurt this morning&mdash; I went to take a bath in the wheel house of the S. Boat&mdash; the wheel was turning slowly, and I got as close to the wheel as I could, so that it might throw the water upon me&mdash; the steam was let on suddenly &amp; the wheel threw the water with such force I sprang farther off &mdash; my foot slipped &amp; I fell upon the open slats and cut a gash above my left ear which bled very profusely&mdash; but as soon as the bleeding ceased I dressed and ate a hearty breakfast. I feel no other inconvenience from it, except such I have often felt from a bruise, I will continue to write to you frequently, but my dear wife I have despaired of receiving your letters by mail&mdash; <abbr expan="though">tho</abbr> my anxiety is very great&mdash; to know how you are&mdash; how Eliza is&mdash; &amp; how the little boy is&mdash; I know I ought to be with my family&mdash; &amp; for one out of many other reasons that Eliza might be at school&mdash; <pb n="[3]"/> I have generally lived very economically &amp; saving and have had hopes of saving something very clever but my trip to Monterey&caret;<add place="supralinear">including purchases of mule &amp; mustang</add> &amp; this journey to join the regiment, will make a considerable addition to the hole in a <orig reg="months">moths</orig> pay which is made by necessary expenses&mdash; My calculations is that we will remain at or in the <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood</orig> of <name type="place">Matamoras</name> some two or three weeks, and then that we shall be marched toward <name type="place">Tampico</name>&mdash; it must be several months before I can get back home&mdash;</p><p>I had lost some flesh until my trip to Monterey since which time I have been fattening,&mdash; &amp; have felt stouter than I have since I left home&mdash;</p><p>Direct your letters to me&mdash;as <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> <emph>C</emph> <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr> <gap reason="hole in document"/> calvary&mdash; U. S. Army&mdash; <name type="place">Mexico</name>&mdash;</p><p>My love to Eliza&mdash;&amp; your Ma &amp; Hal&mdash; &amp; to our little boy&mdash;</p><closer><salute><abbr expan="Your affectionate">Yr affection</abbr> Husband</salute></closer><closer><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="William Richard">Wm R. </abbr>Caswell</name></signed><add place="bottom of page">the tremor of the boat has caused me to write so bad a hand.</add><pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs. Elizabeth C. Caswell</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Russelville</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Jefferson County</name></addrLine><addrLine>Tennessee</addrLine></address><add place="above address"><figure><figDesc>Postmark</figDesc></figure></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
