<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="mc037"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1846 June 14 [to] Mrs. William R. Caswell / William R. Caswell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Caswell, William R.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>mc037</idno><idno>OCLC: 50474658</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1846 June 14 [to] Mrs. William R. Caswell / William R. Caswell</title><author>Caswell, William R.</author><date value="1846-06-14">June 14, 1846</date><extent> 4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is letter dated June 14, 1846 from William R. Caswell to his wife in Jefferson County, Tennessee. Caswell writes that he is marching his troops to Memphis where they will go to Mexico to fight in the Mexican-American War. </note><note type="collection">William R. Caswell Papers</note><note type="box">MS-18, b1</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">mc037</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Mexican War, 1846-1848</item><item>United States</item><item>Mexico</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine>In Camp <emph><name type="place">Isabella</name></emph>, 6 miles from</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Washington. Rhea County</name><date value="1846-06-14">14th June 1846</date></addrLine></address><salute>My Dear Wife</salute></opener><p>I wrote to you a few lines from <name type="place">Campbell Station</name>.&mdash; The next day we came to <name type="place">Kingston</name>, and a few miles before we reached there, we were exposed to a rain, which drenched us thoroughly, and drooped our feathers&mdash; we had a rough time of it and <gap reason="hole in document"/> comfortable night; on <orig reg="yesterday">yesturday</orig> we came about 18 miles, and were greeted with another shower nothing remarkable occurred; at Kingston, my men being very wet, could not be kept from taking too much of what they called the "Rye&mdash;O"&mdash; <name type="person">James Brazelton</name>, took his full share, I expect he is to be very much trouble, but I will try every kind means to keep him from dissipation, and if I cannot succeed thus I will exercise my authority&mdash; which as Captain is more absolute than I could desire&mdash; There are others in my company, worse than James. And I have &caret;<add place="supralinear">already</add> been under the necessity of sending a Sergeant with a file of men, to bring several <unclear>soldiers</unclear> into camps, and put them under guard&mdash; I have had no other difficulty, except on account of  intoxication, that is to keep my men from drinking too much spirits&mdash;</p><p>I have lost a pair of of my Mackinaw Blankets, but I still hope to find them in the camp of the <name type="place">Claiborne Blues</name> or of <name type="person">Waterhouse</name>. We have left the Claiborne Blues 6 miles behind <orig reg="tonight">to-night</orig>&mdash; we were in a very hard rain this morning &amp; they <orig reg="stopped">stoped</orig> at a camp ground, we swam across a creek and came on to this a beautiful encampment which you will see we have named Isabella  for miss <pb n="[2]"/><name type="person"> Isabella White</name>, who is my 1st Lieutenants sweet heart.</p><p>I need not write you the particulars of our proceedings at <name type="place">Knoxville</name>, for <name type="person">Ann</name>will give you the particulars if she has not already done so&mdash; We have attracted the attention of every person in reach of the road;&mdash; I cannot tell you what route we shall go to <name type="place">Memphis</name> <orig reg="tomorrow">To-morrow</orig> I shall start my baggage <orig reg="wagon">waggon</orig>, across the <name type="place">Sequache Valley</name>, where I shall encamp <orig reg="tomorrow">to-morrow</orig> night, but I will march my company some 3 or 4 miles out of the way by Washington to meet with Waterhouse' company&mdash; The company can march 25 or 30 miles a day but the <orig reg="wagon">waggon</orig> cannot travel more than 18 or 20 miles&mdash; Thus far we have had very unfavorable weather upon the outset of the campaign, but I have done very well, and begin to get used to it, for notwithstanding the rains, I sleep sound at night and have escaped colds so far&mdash;</p><p>My company were paid $25.&mdash; each to buy clothing&mdash; I was responsible for their uniforms, and some other purchases, &amp; I got the money from the bank ($2,570.)&mdash; I have not paid off  all the men yet, but there will not be enough left for me to get my full share which is $120&mdash;.</p><p>I am very anxious to hear from you&mdash; Not a word have I heard from you since I left&mdash; Be sure to make <name type="person">Eliza</name> write; I cannot tell where to write to, now, unless, <del type="overstrike">at</del> <add place="supralinear">to</add> <name type="place">McMinnville</name>, but you will probably see from the "standard" what route we will travel to <name type="place">Memphis</name>&mdash; and by making a calculation, you can guess where to write&mdash; <name type="person">George Gillespie</name> is going with us to Memphis &amp; he is going to <name type="place">Nashville</name>, &amp; there get instructions what route we shall travel&mdash;</p><closer><salute>Your Affectionate husband</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="William Richard">Wm.R.</abbr> Caswell</name>&mdash;</signed><pb n="[3]"/><add place="top of page"><p>I have read over the foregoing letter, and feel that I ought to <orig reg="apologize">apologise</orig> for so poor a letter&mdash; The men calling every few minutes to know what they must do about their horses&mdash; their provisions <abbr expan="et cetera, et cetera">&amp;c, &amp;c</abbr> and thus I have my hands full&mdash;<abbr expan="yours">yrs</abbr> affectionately</p></add><pb n="[4]"/><add rend="different hand, ink"><address><addrLine>Washington <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tn</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1846-06-16">June 16, 1846</date>&rcub;</addrLine></address></add><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs. <abbr expan="William Richard">Wm.R.</abbr> Caswell</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Russelville</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Jefferson County</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
