<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="mc053"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1838 Nov. 5, Ross' Landing, Ten[nessee] [to] Mr. C[harles] F. Welcker, Talladega, Ala[bama] / A[lbert] S. Lenoir : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Lenoir, Albert S.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>mc053</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1838 Nov. 5, Ross' Landing, Ten[nessee] [to] Mr. C[harles] F. Welcker, Talladega, Ala[bama] / A[lbert] S. Lenoir</title><author>Lenoir, Albert S.</author><date value="1838-11-05">November 5, 1838</date><extent>4 p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated November 5, 1838, from Albert S. Lenoir at Ross' Landing, Tennessee to his brother-in-law Charles Frederick Welcker in Talladega, Alabama.  Albert discusses his personal business and that of the family, and he also talks of going soon to Roane County.  He also mentions the building of a Georgia railroad.</note><note type="collection">Welcker Papers</note><note type="box">MS-12, b2</note><note type="folder">1838</note><note type="document">mc053</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/> <opener><address><addrLine><name>Ross' Landing <abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><date><abbr expan="November">Novr</abbr> 5th 1838</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>Your kind letter of about the 23rd <abbr expan="September">Septr.</abbr> was <abbr expan="received">recd.</abbr> some time since &amp; should have been answered sooner, but business &amp; absence from home <del type="overstrike">must</del> has prevented it </p><p>I gladly accept your proposition to continue a more regular correspondence, and from present appearance I will not be likely soon again to offer business as an excuse for not writing, as I am now out of any kind__ my dear old uncle, Sam, <orig reg="stopped">stoped</orig> my per diem allowance on the 31st October &amp; I am now, as the boatsmen say "lying on my oars." </p><p>I was at Roane Court &amp; at your Mother week before last_ the family were all well, Henry &amp; DeWitt had both been unwell but had recovered._ Frederick started to <name>Arkansas</name> about two weeks ago, which the family did not know when I saw them__   They were then expecting that probably all the family would be together about the last of this month, as they had heard that you &amp; Lewis were both coming about that time, &amp; I promise to take Catherine up.</p><p>Times in the <name>Ocoee District</name> are becoming quite dull, all the troops are gone except a few at the Agency, perhaps our company_ &amp; all the Indians except about 1500 are on their way West, &amp; they are <pb n="[2]"/> to start very shortly, &amp; the absence of both these evils together with the lowness of the waters will have a tendency to produce quite dull times_ but the opening of the land Office in <name>Cleveland</name> this day will probably create some excitement_ I dont expect to trouble the office much myself_ I have been buying town property in this place for a speculation &amp; from present appearances it may turn out a bad speculation.</p><p>Our prospects have recd. a damper from the report of the Engineer for the <name><abbr expan="Georgia">Ga.</abbr></name> Rail Road being rather against us_ he reports <orig reg="favorably">favourably</orig> of the mouth of <name>Chickamauga</name> , a few miles above this, but we still have hopes of its being made to this place_ We have an older charter for a Rail Road than the one given to Ga. which will likely bring us in collision with Ga if she goes to the river at a different point.  Catherine wishes to be <orig reg="remembered">rembered</orig> to you &amp; <name>Mrs <abbr expan="Welcker">W.</abbr></name> and says she is sorry to learn that she will not have her company in <name>Roane</name> this fall &amp; she wishes to know if Margaret Elizabeth is coming up with you.</p><p>Our little family are in tolerable health, our little daughter now a few days over 9 months old is very stout &amp; hearty, and is certainly the loveliest little creature we ever saw__ we have never heard the name of yours_</p><p>Will this place be in your route to Roane, if so we could probably go <orig reg="together">to gether</orig> from here, <pb n="[3]"/> if we do not travel too slowly for you__ Our <unclear>Puss</unclear> is so large &amp; heavy we will have to haul her up.</p><p>Novr 6th</p><p>We are all well_ The mail will be closed shortly, &amp; I must close</p> <closer><salute>Affectionately</salute><signed><name><abbr expan="Albert">A.</abbr> S. Lenoir</name></signed><address><addrLine><name>Mr <abbr expan="Charles Frederick">C. F.</abbr>  Welcker</name></addrLine></address> <pb n="[4]"/> <address><addrLine>Ross Landing <abbr expan="Tennessee">Te</abbr></addrLine><addrLine>6 Nov.</addrLine></address> <add>12 &frac12;</add><address><addrLine>Mr. C F. Welcker</addrLine><addrLine><name><orig reg="Talladega">Taladega</orig></name></addrLine><addrLine><name><abbr expan="Alabama">Ala</abbr></name></addrLine></address> <add>Mail</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
