<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl030">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Land Indenture] 1834 Jun. 20 [Between Sam Houston and Margaretta D. H. McEwen] : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Houston, Sam</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl030</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50015370</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Land Indenture] 1834 Jun. 20 [Between Sam Houston and Margaretta D. H. McEwen]</title>
               <author>Houston, Sam</author>
               <date when="1834-06-20">June 20, 1834</date>
               <extent> 2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a land indenture between Sam Houston and Margaretta D. H. McEwen dated June 20, 1834. Houston is giving a parcel of land in the province of Texas to McEwen, a resident of Nashville, Tennessee. Houston acquired the land from Estevan Austin on January 9, 1833.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Tennessee Historical Society</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">AC 269 Miscellaneous documents, b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">I-D-1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl030</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Land tenure</term>
               <term>McEwen, Margaretta D. H.</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n82151189"
                        role="Associated name http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/asn">Houston, Sam, 1793-1863.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl030a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>This Indenture made this <date when="1834-06-20">twentieth day of June eighteen hundred and thirty four</date> between <name type="person">Sam Houston</name> of the <name type="place">State of Coahuila</name> and <name type="place">Texas</name> of the one part and <name type="person">Margaretta D. H. McEwen</name>, daughter of <name type="person">Robert H McEwen</name> of the City of <name type="place">Nashville</name> and State of <name type="place">Tennessee</name> of the other part. Witnesseth, That the said Sam Houston in consideration of the love and affection, high regard and esteem which he entertains for the said Margaretta D. H. McEwen as well as for other considerations good and valuable hath given, granted, aliened, enfeoffed, and confirmed; and by these presents doth give, grant, alien, enfeoff, and confirm unto the said Margaretta D. H. McEwen her heirs and assigns, a certain tract and parcel of land, lying and being in the province of Texas, being one fourth part of League number three and situated on the western side of <name type="place">Carancahuas Bay</name>. The undivided moiety of the league conveyed by <name type="person">Estevan T Austin</name> by, and dated <date when="1833-01-09">January the 9th 1833</date> to Sam Houston and containing one thousand one hundred and seven acres; with the <choice>
                  <orig>appurtinances</orig>
                  <reg>appurtenances</reg>
               </choice> thereof. — To have and to hold the said land with its <choice>
                  <orig>appurtinances</orig>
                  <reg>appurtenances</reg>
               </choice> unto the said Margaretta D. H. McEwen, her heirs and assigns forever.</p>
            <p>And the said Sam Houston, for himself, his heirs, executors and administrators, doth covenant and agree to, and with the said Margaretta D. H. McEwen her heirs and assigns by these presents, that she the said Margaretta her heirs and assigns, shall, and lawfully may, from time to time, and at all times hereafter, <choice>
                  <orig>peaseably</orig>
                  <reg>peaceably</reg>
               </choice> and quietly have, hold, use and occupy, possess, and enjoy the said parcel or tract of land hereby granted and confirmed with its <choice>
                  <orig>appurtinances</orig>
                  <reg>appurtenances</reg>
               </choice>, free, clear and fully discharged of, from and against all former and other gifts, grants, bargains, sales, jointures, feoffment dowers and estates, and of, from and against all former and other wills, charges and <choice>
                  <orig>incumbrances</orig>
                  <reg>encumbrances</reg>
               </choice>, whatsoever, had, done, or suffered by him, the said Sam Houston, his heirs or assigns, or any person, or persons lawfully claiming or to claim, by, from, or under him, them, or any of them.</p>
            <p>In witness whereof he the said Sam Houston hath hereunto set his hand, and affixed his seal this <date when="1834-06-20">twentieth day of June 1834</date>.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sam Houston <add place="next to signature">
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>seal</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </add>
               </signed>
               <add place="left of signature">Witness <lb/>
                  <unclear>
                     <name type="person">Ja Collinsworth</name>
                  </unclear>
                  <lb/>
                  <name type="person">Alpha Kingsley</name>
               </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl030b.small.jpg"/> Sam Houston <lb/> To Deed <lb/> Margaretta D. G. McEwen <lb/> ¼ League in Texas</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
