<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl762">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1819 Sep. 28, Murfreesboro, Tennessee [to]  Joseph McMinn / James Park: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Park, James</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl762</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1819 Sep. 28, Murfreesboro, Tennessee [to]  Joseph McMinn / James Park</title>
               <author> Park, James</author>
               <date when="1819-09-28">September 28, 1819</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated September 28, 1819 from James Park to the governor of Tennessee, Joseph McMinn.  The subject of the letter is the wretched condition of the Turnpike road between Knoxville and Sparta, and the growing difficulty that United States mail wagon carriers have in its passage.  In the letter, Park writes of mail routes throughout Tennessee.  He also asks the governor to consider whether or not a toll should be authorized on the Turnpike.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Joseph McMinn Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl762</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</term>
               <term>McMinn, Joseph, 1758-1824</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Park, James</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl762a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Murfreesboro</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>28th <choice>
                     <abbr>Septr</abbr>
                     <expan>September</expan>
                  </choice> 1819</date>
               <add>May it please your Excellency</add>
            </opener>
            <p>The undersigned contractors for transportations the <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>U.S</abbr>
                     <expan>United States</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>. mail from <name>Knoxville</name> to <name>sparta</name> beg leave respectfully to represent that they labor under considerable disadvantages arising from the <choice>
                  <orig>rought</orig>
                  <reg>wrought</reg>
               </choice> state of that part of the road called the Turnpike by which members who would otherwise prefer travelers in the stage are <choice>
                  <orig>detered</orig>
                  <reg>deterred</reg>
               </choice> there from and indeed were they to offer they could not be carried with safety as it is evident were the stages to take in as many on that road as is usual on other roads they must frequently break down and many failures of   the mail be thereby incurred</p>
            <p>The officers of the <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Post office <choice>
                  <abbr>Dept</abbr>
                  <expan>Department</expan>
               </choice> complain that the support of a line of stages from Knoxville to sparta but bring productive of passage money bears heavy on that office and have lately sent an agent to examine the state of those roads and report whether in his judgment stages can be run <add>therein</add>  with certainty that agent has reported the roads in general much out of repair and that the part of the road that is called the Turnpike <pb n="2" facs="sl762b.small.jpg"/> has been shamefully neglected from what cause this neglect has arisen we will not undertake to state, but beg leave to suggest the propriety of having the Law in relation to those road examined and such amendments made as the custom of the Legislature may deem necessary for the public good</p>
            <p>The support of a line of stages from Knoxville to <name>Nashville</name> for the Transportation of the mail and passengers is certainly desirable to the Citizens of this state and the more so when it is <choice>
                  <orig>considired</orig>
                  <reg>considered</reg>
               </choice> that on it depends the main western mail route to <name>New Orleans</name> being continued <del type="overstrike">throu &amp;</del> in that direction__</p>
            <p>We are solicitors also to ascertain the sense of the Legislature whether the owners of those Turnpikes are <choice>
                  <orig>authorised</orig>
                  <reg>authorized</reg>
               </choice> to require  that the United states mail shall pay Toll when conveyed in stages or on horseback over saw roads__ we know that it is not contemplated in the Contract and if considered Legal will make the contractors liable to pay upwards of <sic>of</sic> six hundred dollars per year for which no allowance will be made then by the Genl Government__</p>
            <p>Should your Excellency deem the foregoing remarks worthy of Legislative consideration we pray you to have the goodness to communicate them by so <pb n="3" facs="sl762c.small.jpg"/> __ doing we trust the public good will be advanced and <del type="overstrike">and</del>  a particular favor done</p>
            <closer>
               <add>Your <choice>
                     <abbr>Obt. Servts</abbr>
                     <expan>Obedient Servants</expan>
                  </choice>__ </add>
               <signed>
                  <name>James &amp; <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                        <expan>William</expan>
                     </choice> Park</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>PS</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> It will doubtless be recollected should the Legislature act on the subject of those roads that a considerable part of the mountain must be <choice>
                     <orig>passid</orig>
                     <reg>passed</reg>
                  </choice> over by the stages in the night__ <choice>
                     <abbr>Ja</abbr>
                     <expan>James</expan>
                  </choice>W Park</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl762d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Report James park esquire <date>2nd October 1819</date>
                  <lb/> Subject Past Roads__</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>His Excellency <name>Joseph McMinn</name> governor of <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
