<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl456">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter]    1842 Aug. 20, Cold Water [to] R[obert] H. McEwen, Nashville, Ten[nessee] / W.B. Robinson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Robinson, W. B.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl456</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1842 Aug. 20, Cold Water [to] R[obert] H. McEwen, Nashville, Ten[nessee] / W.B. Robinson</title>
               <author>Robinson, W.B.</author>
               <date when="1842-08-20">August 20, 1842</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from W.B. Robinson to his business associate Robert H. McEwen, dated August 20, 1842. Robinson is very concerned about his financial situation. He is in debt with no chance of repayment without irreparably damaging his families future. Robinson needs to meet in person with McEwen but is unable to travel due to poor health.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">McEwen Papers</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">7</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl456</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Working life</term>
               <term>Financial, Personal</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Robinson, W. B.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl456a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Cold Water</name>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Augt</abbr>
                           <expan>August</expan>
                        </choice> 20th 1842</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Col</abbr>
                        <expan>Colonel</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name>R H McEwen</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                     <expan>Dear</expan>
                  </choice> Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I am Truly sorry you cannot come out and let us Settle Our old matter and be done with it same time I am Truly in Despair I am Increasing in years and my Health has been very bad this season and for me to continue in this Situation is more than my mind can well bear </p>
            <p>I would go out to <name>Nashville</name> and Settle with you <unclear>there</unclear> if I could get <name>Gelliland</name> and <name>Rosebrough</name> to go with but the Situation of their Family will not admit of their absence and You Told me in Your own House that we could not Settle unless <choice>
                  <abbr>G &amp; R</abbr>
                  <expan>Gelliland and Rosebrough</expan>
               </choice> was present</p>
            <p>I do know your high Sense of Honor and Justice will not admit of My Sustaining all the Losses after doing all the Business in 1834 <name>A C McEwen</name> Sold my lot of Cotton (<name>W B Robinson</name>s) without Ever consulting me at a Sacrifice of 2500 Dollars and I collected all the Claims <choice>
                  <sic>of of</sic>
                  <corr>sic</corr>
               </choice> the Firm of W B Robinson in Cotton and Suffered Heavy Losses which entirely Left the Firm unable to pay her Debts and also has Swallowed up the Little Capitol I put into <pb n="2" facs="sl456b.small.jpg"/> The Concern your Knowledge of Business and Sense of Honor will say I should not Loose all Gelliland and R say they never Had any thing to do with the Firm of W B Robinson and they Cannot pay any thing at all and it Looks extremely Hard for me to Loose 15 Years Hard Labor and Still Remain in Debt more than I can possibly with the money I have pay the Interest and Support my Family you Say Hold on to the tail a Little I would willingly Hold on if my Little Family did not demand my particular and Immediate attention If I am poor they are Doubly Dear on account of my <unclear>Poverty</unclear>
            </p>
            <p>I want you to come out and let us Settle I will give up to the Last Dollar I have in the world I care not what the world may Say of my Conduct if the Worst <choice>
                  <orig>cours</orig>
                  <reg>course</reg>
               </choice> as I see no <choice>
                  <orig>othr</orig>
                  <reg>other</reg>
               </choice> chance I will avail myself of the Benefits of the BankRupt Law and pay my Debts there after as fast as I can after doing my Duty by my children I will not Ruin them and Cause them to be in <choice>
                  <orig>Lowr</orig>
                  <reg>Lower</reg>
               </choice> Ranks of Life if my Debts go unpaid for years</p>
            <p>I do just Say come out and Let us Settle Rosebrough will Start early this Fall to the South and be absent all winter I want a <unclear>fast</unclear> Settlement I do not <choice>
                  <orig>lingr</orig>
                  <reg>linger</reg>
               </choice> So vehemently to Try to take any advantage or to add our pang to your all ready <pb n="3" facs="sl456c.small.jpg"/> aching Heart I do feel for and if I could I would say Down every Dollar that you need at this time I am doing nothing at all to make money to pay my Debts and to suffer them to enemies without any possibility of Liquidating them looks like folly and for my entire Liberty placed at the control of my Creditors look Hard I do not know what to do Come out for the Lords Sake and let me make you Safe you Shall have Every thing I have on Earth I Hope you mentioned the note to Gelliland when he was in your City not long Since and arranged the matter I have not asked him what he done as I have not been an hour in his company Since his Return</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your Friend</salute>
               <signed>W B Robinson</signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl456d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Robinsons Store</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>Augt 27</date>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>W B Robinson PM <lb/> fr</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Col</abbr>
                        <expan>Colonel</expan>
                     </choice> R H McEwen</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>{<name> Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Ten</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>W. B. Robinson <lb/> 20 Augt 1842</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
