<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="mp008"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1825 Nov. 20 Memphis, [to] Rhea &amp; McCrabb / Charles L. Barth : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Barth, Charles L.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>mp008</idno><idno>OCLC: 50335539</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Memphis Public Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Memphis Public Library, 3030 Poplar Avenue, Memphis, TN 38111</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1825 Nov. 20 Memphis, [to] Rhea &amp; McCrabb / Charles L. Barth</title><author>Barth, Charles L.</author><date value="1825-11-20">November 20, 1825</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written to two merchants named Rhea &amp; McCrabb from a businessman named Charles Barth on November 20, 1825. In the letter, Barth discusses his business travels throughout Tennessee en route to New Orleans. He also gives Rhea &amp; McCrabb permission to take care of his affairs at home in Athens, Tennessee while he is away.</note><note type="collection">Historical Genealogical Documents</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">9</note><note type="document">mp008</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee -- Description and Travel</item><item>Business enterprises</item><item>Letters</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Memphis</name> <abbr expan="Mississippi"><unclear>Missipp</unclear></abbr>: <date value="1825-11-20"><abbr expan="November">Novb.</abbr> 20th. 1825</date></addrLine></address><salute>Worthy friends!</salute></opener><p>Not Knowing when I shall have the pleasure of seeing you again; I inform you of my <orig reg="safe">save</orig> arrival at this place. &mdash; After I left you I went on to <name type="place">Sparta</name>, but could not avenge my <orig reg="business">bisness</orig> to my satisfaction; I shall perhaps get my money there in about <unclear>eighteen</unclear>  and not before&mdash; from Sparta I went to <name type="place">Nashville</name>, and from there I <orig reg="proceeded">proceded</orig> on to the Western District, I have examined that we try <unclear>prety much</unclear> , and shall settle myself (if I can not do better) at <name type="place">Jackson</name> <name type="place">Madison</name> <unclear>cots less</unclear> &mdash; Tomorrow I start over the Mississippi into <name type="place">Arkansas <orig reg="Territory">Teritory</orig></name> towards <name type="place">Little Rock</name> on the Port &mdash; I shall have to through an unsettled &amp; wild country and having no company <gap reason="hole in document"/> I have to <unclear>Camp</unclear> out at <orig reg="Night">Neight</orig> shall find it very lonesome at the <unclear>Pash I sell</unclear> my horse and go from there by water to <name type="place">New Orleans</name>. &mdash; As to the servants and Notes I left with you I request you to do best you can to get the money &mdash; if they should not be <pb n="[2]"/> settled by Christmas, please put them out for collections in some you <unclear>officers finds</unclear> &mdash; If there are any letters at the post office for me please take them out, and open them, and if there should be anything of <orig reg="conveyance">conveyence</orig> in them why you might write a few lines to them about my not been in Athens &mdash; Please write me a few lines as soon as <orig reg="possible">posseble</orig>, and direct them &caret;<add place="supralinear">to</add> New Orleans, tell me how you do and how you came on and what prospect in business, I remember you very after &mdash; The horn calls for the boat to go over the river so <unclear>adieu</unclear> and a happy farewell</p><closer><signed>Charles L. Barth</signed><pb n="[3]"/><add place="above address"><name type="place">Memphis</name> <lb/> <date value="0000-11-22">Nov 22</date> 18&frac12;</add><address><addrLine><abbr expan="Messieurs">Mess</abbr> <name type="person">Rhea &amp; McCrabb</name></addrLine><addrLine>Merchants</addrLine><addrLine>Athens</addrLine></address><add place="below address">Mail &rcub;</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
