<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl047">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1840 Feb. 5, Hermitage [to] Rev[erend] H. M. Cryer / Andrew Jackson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Jackson, Andrew</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl047</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50030248</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1840 Feb. 5, Hermitage [to] Rev[erend] H. M. Cryer / Andrew Jackson</title>
               <author>Jackson, Andrew</author>
               <date when="1840-02-05">February 5, 1840</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by Andrew Jackson to the Reverend H. M. Cryer on February 5, 1840. In the letter, Jackson proposes to sell a tract of land on his property to help his son get out of debt. He asks for Cryer's help in finding someone who would want to buy the land. Jackson wants to sell the land for fifteen thousand dollars, with five thousand dollars as a down payment. This total price equals out to be approximately thirty dollars per acre of land.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Tennessee Historical Society</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">Miscellaneous documents J1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">62J</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl047</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Real property</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79088888"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl047a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Hermitage</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1840-02-05">February 5th 1840</date> —</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I reached home on the 2nd instant on our return, we had to struggle for ten days &amp; nights against the ice on the Mississippi — But the energy of our Captain, <name type="person">Irwin</name> &amp; his noble crew, and the smiles of a kind &amp; gracious providence, we reached <name type="place">Nashville</name> on the first where we were kindly greeted by numerous friends, and the whole Legislature in a body, and I am now reclining under the peaceful roof of the Hermitage with my dear little family, with improved strength <choice>
                  <abbr>tho</abbr>
                  <expan>though</expan>
               </choice>
               <choice>
                  <orig>labouring</orig>
                  <reg>laboring</reg>
               </choice> under a bad cold taken on board the boat amidst the Ice, and somewhat increased since I got home by a little imprudence.</p>
            <p>I had the pleasure of meeting with my old friend father Gwin, in good health, — but <choice>
                  <orig>disatisfied</orig>
                  <reg>dissatisfied</reg>
               </choice> with the lower country — has a wish to return &amp; spend his last days in <name type="place">Tennessee</name> if it meets the views of his wife, to whom he wrote by me — I made him an offer of <name type="person">Wards</name> place, now owned by me son &amp; <pb n="2" facs="sl047b.small.jpg"/> myself, which <del type="overstrike">the</del> Doctor, <name type="person">William Gwin</name> said if his father selected, he would buy for him — I enclosed the letter to <name type="person">Mrs Gwin</name>, requesting to know her determinations as yet I have not heard from her. To have this good old man my <choice>
                  <orig>neighbour</orig>
                  <reg>neighbor</reg>
               </choice> in my declining life would be a great pleasure to me. If Mrs. Gwin desires to return below, then my dear friend, I wish your aid in procuring a purchase of that fine track of land for us — My sons situation is such that we must sell and any individual who can advance five thousand dollars or four thousand can now have a great Bargain in that tract of land — It can be had, now, with an advance of $5000 — for fifteen thousand dollars, and the <choice>
                  <orig>ballance</orig>
                  <reg>balance</reg>
               </choice>  at one two &amp; three years without interest — if not punctually paid, interest from the date, this to induce punctuality. and on an advance of six thousand dollars, it can now be had for fourteen — thousand dollars, with the above credit &amp; conditions — Would not any one who has <choice>
                  <orig>mony</orig>
                  <reg>money</reg>
               </choice>
               <choice>
                  <orig> by</orig>
                  <reg>buy</reg>
               </choice> such an investment <pb n="3" facs="sl047c.small.jpg"/> ⁁ <add place="supralinear">shake</add> fifty percent in a few years, yea, the moment the present pressure passes away this tract will command thirty dollars per acre. This I will know, but a little imprudence has caused this necessity, and I would always <choice>
                  <orig>sacrafice</orig>
                  <reg>sacrifice</reg>
               </choice> property, than the credit of my adopted son or myself, therefore the <choice>
                  <orig>sacrafice</orig>
                  <reg>sacrifice</reg>
               </choice> of this fine tract is to be made — would not <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Elliott</name> invest his <choice>
                  <orig>mony</orig>
                  <reg>money</reg>
               </choice> in such a certain &amp; sure profit as this purchase would ensure — My dear Sir, furnish me a purchaser on the above terms &amp; the premium offered will be yours.</p>
            <p>This sale will free us from debt — and the fine plantation below will pay for itself &amp; <unclear>meet</unclear> a <choice>
                  <orig>surpluss</orig>
                  <reg>surplus</reg>
               </choice> and my Hermitage must sustain my <choice>
                  <orig>expence</orig>
                  <reg>expense</reg>
               </choice> — I will live within my means, &amp; my son from his paid for <choice>
                  <orig>expence</orig>
                  <reg>expense</reg>
               </choice>, I am sure will never be indebted again when clear of his present <choice>
                  <orig>dificulties</orig>
                  <reg>difficulties</reg>
               </choice> — Therefore my dear Sir it is that I am so solicitous to make the <choice>
                  <orig>sacrafice</orig>
                  <reg>sacrifice</reg>
               </choice> &amp; sale of the land to get him clear of debt &amp; myself from his liabilities. Have the goodness to write <pb n="4" facs="sl047d.small.jpg"/> me soon, and inform me of the prospects of a sale, or of any offers made where an advance of five or six thousand dollars will be made — Should your business lead you to <name type="place">Nashville</name> call &amp; give me a night — with my kind regards and that of my little family to you and yours expecting in due time the promised visit of you &amp; family. I remain your friend.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <emph>
                     <name type="person">Andrew Jackson</name>
                  </emph>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>The <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Revd H.</abbr>
                           <expan>Reverend Herdy</expan>
                        </choice> M. Cryer</name> —</addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>The <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Revd. H.</abbr>
                           <expan>Reverend Herdy</expan>
                        </choice> M. Cryer</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>near <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <orig>Gallatine</orig>
                           <reg>Gallatin</reg>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Sumner County</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
