<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl740">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1796 Oct. 25, Nashville, Tennessee [to] Dog Warrior, Creek Nation /  John Sevier: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Sevier, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl740</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1796 Oct. 25, Nashville, Tennessee [to] Dog Warrior, Creek Nation /  John Sevier</title>
               <author>Sevier, John </author>
               <date when="1796-10-25">October 25, 1796</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter from the governor of Tennessee, John Sevier in Nashville to the Dog Warrior, Mad Blue, and all the principal Chiefs of the Creek Nation.     In the letter, the governor expresses his feelings over the peace and and friendship that exists between the two nations, and assures their safety and protection when crossing into Cumberland to purchase ammunition and other supplies.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor John Sevier Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">B?</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl740</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Sevier, John, 1745-1815 Correspondence</term>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor (1796-1801 : Sevier)</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr89016779"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Sevier, John, 1745-1815</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl740a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To the Dog Warrior, Mad Blue, and all the principal Chiefs of the Creek Nation</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Friends!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your talk by Captain Chisholm affords me great pleasure.  The desire you so warmly express of peace and friendship with the <name>United States</name> is highly gratifying: and the preparatory step, you have so early <del>wisely</del>  taken <add>for</add>   establishing that friendly intercourse between the two nations, so highly interesting to both, on the principles of good faith and mutual confidence, is a proof of that wisdom and policy which mark a great nation.</p>
            <p>Friends! <lb/> I thank you for the assurances you give that no mischief shall be done on our frontiers, and doubt not, that our people will__ not be afraid to meet, to take each other by the hand; and eat,   &amp; smoke together in peace <add>harmony</add>  and friendship.</p>
            <p>Friends! <lb/>   You say that some of your people intend to Cumberland this winter, to purchase ammunition and other necessaries, and wish me to issue my proclamation, to protect them, <del>in their journey</del>   , and  prevent any mischief being done by ill designed persons <pb n="2" facs="sl740b.small.jpg"/>  persons among our people.  Be assured I shall <add>with pleasure</add>  comply with your request, and<del> use my utmost exertions to prevent  any of  your people from molested, or <unclear>interupted</unclear>  on their journey.__</del>
               <add>be assured that your people may go and <unclear>recursion</unclear>   the utmost security being without any apprehension of being violated or <choice>
                     <orig>interupted</orig>
                     <reg>interrupted</reg>
                  </choice> in their journey__</add>
            </p>
            <p>
               <del>Friends! <lb/> I thank you for your favorable opinion of me, and believe me,  when I declare, I was always a friend </del>
            </p>
            <p>
               <del>I shall also endeavor to preserve peace and harmony between our people and you, and prevent</del>
            </p>
            <p>I thank you for your favorable opinion of me.__ Believe me I always was, and every shall be a friend to <add>all</add> the red people who wish to preserve <add>that </add>   peace and harmony so desirable for all good men.  Under the influence of this friendship I shall  be vigilant in preventing any mischief, or enroachment on your hunting grounds; under the full assurance that you will <unclear>inport</unclear>  , continue to act <add>on</add>   the <add>firm principles</add>
               <del>influence</del>   of peace unity and good faith.</p>
            <closer>
               <add>a copy </add>
               <signed>
                  <name>J Sevier</name>
               </signed>
               <date>25 October 1796</date>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl740c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Copy of a letter to the Creek nation <date>25th October 1796</date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>No</abbr>
                     <expan>Number</expan>
                  </choice> 9 Recorded</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
