<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl260">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1843 March 20, Rock Cave, K[entuck]y [to] Emaline Hamilton, Nashville, Tenn[essee]     : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>House, Mary</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl260</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51217891</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1843 March 20, Rock Cave, K[entuck]y [to] Emaline Hamilton, Nashville, Tenn[essee]  </title>
               <author>House, Mary</author>
               <date when="1843-03-20">March 20, 1843</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to Emaline Hamilton from her sister Mary. It is dated March 20, 1843. Mary starts by apologizing to Emaline for not writing as often as she should. Mary writes about going to parties and to church since she has been in Rock Cave. She mentions how some people were scared of the Great Comet of 1843. Some believed it heralded the Second Coming. She sends her love to many family members.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">10</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl260</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Comets</term>
               <term>Religious thought -- 19th century</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">House, Mary</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl260a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Rock Cave</name>
                     <name type="place">Logan County</name>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Ky</abbr>
                           <expan>Kentucky</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                     <date when="1843-03-20">March 20th 1843</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear Sister</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have at last taken my pen to address you, but <choice>
                  <orig>allmost</orig>
                  <reg>almost</reg>
               </choice> without the hope  of being forgiven for my seeming neglect, of you, <choice>
                  <orig>altho</orig>
                  <reg>although</reg>
               </choice> it  may have appeared such, yet really it was not.</p>
            <p>I feel as if an <choice>
                  <orig>appology</orig>
                  <reg>apology</reg>
               </choice> was necessary for my very great procrastination, yet I feel  <choice>
                  <orig>incompitient</orig>
                  <reg>incompetent</reg>
               </choice> to the task of making one, such as you, on even I might deem sufficient, but one thing I know I can say, it is this, that  if you will deign to receive this scrawl, you shall not have me to complain of in future, as a procrastinating correspondent, but rather as one that <unclear>write</unclear> too frequently (for you know <choice>
                  <orig>thier</orig>
                  <reg>there</reg>
               </choice> is such a thing) if you could suppose such a thing were possible with me, you must therefore take the will for the <unclear>deed</unclear> ,  ⁁ <add place="supralinear">for</add> you may rest assured that I have willed you many a letter during this winter —</p>
            <p>But I must now <del type="overstrike">ttell</del> tell you some of the things that I have <pb n="2" facs="sl260b.small.jpg"/> been doing since I left <name type="place">Nashville</name> — in the first place, I have been trying to kill time, in the best possible manner, untill I should return to <choice>
                  <abbr>N</abbr>
                  <expan>Nashville</expan>
               </choice> , and then I have been going to parties and almost all kinds of <choice>
                  <orig>frolicks</orig>
                  <reg>frolics</reg>
               </choice> that you can imagine I have received and returned a great many visits, and yet it seems as though I was <choice>
                  <orig>scarcley</orig>
                  <reg>scarcly</reg>
               </choice> half through — I have also attended church a good deal — I attended the Methodist church at <name type="place">Pleasant Run</name> during the christmas week, at which place there was a considerable <choice>
                  <orig>reveval</orig>
                  <reg>revival</reg>
               </choice> of religion that commenced then, and has continued, ever since, <name type="person">Mr Redford</name> preached there on last Sabbath, and had quite a stirring time, <choice>
                  <orig>thar</orig>
                  <reg>there</reg>
               </choice> is also a reveval going on in the Methodist ⁁ <add place="supralinear">church</add> at <name type="place">Russellsvill</name> —</p>
            <p>I have heard that the people, generally throughout this county, and <name type="place">Simpson</name>, <choice>
                  <orig>ware</orig>
                  <reg>were</reg>
               </choice> greatly <choice>
                  <orig>freghtened</orig>
                  <reg>frightened</reg>
               </choice> at this comet, (or what ever else it is) that has made its appearance in the west, I heard that some <choice>
                  <orig>indeveduals</orig>
                  <reg>individuals</reg>
               </choice> in <name type="place">Franklin</name> closed their doors, and <choice>
                  <orig>wer</orig>
                  <reg>were</reg>
               </choice> ready  waiting for the end, this comet is also to be seen in the Morning <pb n="3" facs="sl260c.small.jpg"/> just before day, it certainly is a <unclear>very</unclear> strong appearance, at all events —</p>
            <p>mother Jimmy and my self <del type="overstrike">self</del> returned from Russellsville a few days since, where we had been visiting for three weeks, we had a very pleasant time, <name type="person">Susan Bibb</name> came out with us and remained <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> the day before yesterday, we enjoyed ourselves much in reading and singing, while she stayed with us,</p>
            <p>I would fill this sheet, but the fire has burnt down, and Nick and Henry are both asleep, and it is now past eleven oclock which is time that all sober discrete people should be in bed, Mother joins me in love to your Mother Susan Miss Jane, and to the boys Mort Jim and Joe, kiss <unclear>Matesy</unclear> and sister a hundred times for me, Jimmy sends a kiss to both give my love to Morty particularly, and ask him if he will forgive me for  my very bad conduct, and if he will I will promise him faithfully <del type="overstrike">that I</del> to do better here after, we are all well write to me soon and give me all of the news of the day <pb n="4" facs="sl260d.small.jpg"/> Remember me to <name type="person">Mr. Scoval</name> when you see him</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>in hast untill death your affectionate sister</salute>
               <signed>Mary</signed>
               <add place="middle of page, rotated">
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Mrs <name type="person">Emaline Hamilton</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Nashville</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>PS</abbr>
                  <expan>Post Script</expan>
               </choice> I wrote this on the twentieth, but have not had an opportunity to send it untill to day which is the 22nd, since I wrote the first of this letter, I have taken a very severe cold, in consequence of which I am quite <choice>
                  <orig>seck</orig>
                  <reg>sick</reg>
               </choice> , but hope that I will soon get better, let me hear from you soon <salute>your affectionate</salute>
               <signed>mary</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
