<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0325">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Deposition of David Taylor] 1843 Nov. 6, Washington County, District of Columbia  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0325</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: </idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>  [Deposition of David Taylor] 1843 Nov. 6, Washington County, District of Columbia</title>
               <date when="1843-11-06">November 6, 1843</date>
               <extent>2 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a deposition given by David Taylor regarding land belonging to The Pathkiller, a Cherokee Indian. Pathkiller lost the land sometime after the Treaty of 1819 and fought for years to regain it. Upon his death, his daughter and son-in-law, James Thomas Gardenhire fought to gain the value of that land.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> pa0325</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Legal documents</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Land tenure</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0325a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Washington city</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>&amp; Washington county</addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>This day personally came before me <name>A <choice>
                     <abbr>Thos</abbr>
                     <expan>Thomas</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> Smith one of the acting Justices of the peace in and for said county <name>David Taylor</name> aged 51 years a citizen of cherokee county He who after sworn accordingly to law deposeth and saith he was acquainted with a cherokee by the named of <name>Path Killer</name> who at the time the cherokee treaty of 1819 was concluded owned an improvement and resided on it at a place known by the name of PathKillers ferry on the <name>Tennessee river</name> on the lands ceded under that treaty. He obtained a reservation agreeably to the provisions of the treaty and deponent was one of the chain carriers when the <name>United States</name> Surveyor surveyed his reservation. It was laid off in a square and included the improvement the said PathKiller resided on at the date of the treaty. At that time as well as at the time his reservation was surveyed he was the head of a family consisting of his wife by the name of Susan. They had but one child a small girl by the name of sarah or sally who is at present the wife of <name>James T Gardenhire</name> and resides in the state of Tennessee having with their family become citizens of that state. The said susan wife of PathKiller died at <name>Thomas Foremans</name> to whom she had applied for medical aid in the year (1833) eighteen thirty three. PathKiller made every effort in his power to retain the possession of his reservation but by the unjust legislations of the state and impositions practiced on him by the white citizens he was finally dispossessed He applied to the courts of Justice to obtain his reservation and was prevailed <add>upon</add> (as deponent was informed) by the former board of Commissions to dismiss his suit under a promise to be paid for his reservation under the treaty of 1838 but afterwards his claim was not allowed He immigrated in 1838 and shortly afterwards died in Arkansas as deponent has been informed leaving the wife of James T Gardenhire his only child that he had by his wife that lived with him at the time he obtained his reservation sworn to and subscribed before me</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>David <add>his x mark</add>Taylor</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>this 6th <choice>
                        <abbr>Nov</abbr>
                        <expan>November</expan>
                     </choice> 1843</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>A Tho Smith <choice>
                        <abbr>JP</abbr>
                        <expan>Justice of the Peace</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="2" facs="pa0325b.small.jpg"/>
               <add>60 <lb/> 4th <choice>
                     <abbr>Comm </abbr>
                     <expan>Commission</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/> Depositions of  <lb/> David Taylor <lb/> In the claim of  <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jas</abbr>
                     <expan>James</expan>
                  </choice> T Gardenshire &amp; wife for the value <lb/> of a reservation <lb/> granted to PathKiller</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
