<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl020">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1849 Dec. [to] William M. Lowry / Andrew Johnson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Johnson, Andrew</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl020</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50014207</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1849 Dec. [to] William M. Lowry / Andrew Johnson </title>
               <author>Johnson, Andrew</author>
               <date when="1849-12">December 1849</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a portion of a letter written by Andrew Johnson circa 1849, to William M. Lowry. In the letter, Johnson discusses politics and his hatred for someone only referred to as Williams.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Andrew Johnson Letter</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">Correspondence by author, b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">J</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl020</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To1865</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79056304"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Johnson, Andrew, 1808-1875</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl020a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <add place="top of page">Date <date when="1849-12">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Dec.</abbr>
                        <expan>December</expan>
                     </choice> 1849</date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Recd</abbr>
                     <expan>Received</expan>
                  </choice> between 10th &amp; 20th Last 3pp of ALS. G-23 500.00</add>
            </p>
            <p>one other thing I will allude to as ⁁ <add place="supralinear">it</add> comes in upon me— <name type="person">Williams</name> says that he sent his letters to Henderson's Mill to mail them, believing that you <choice>
                  <sic>wild</sic>
                  <corr>would</corr>
               </choice> open  them and destroy them as he had sent one to the department sometime since and had never heard of it <del type="overstrike">since</del>
               <choice>
                  <orig>afterwurds</orig>
                  <reg>afterwards</reg>
               </choice>— I must confess that the <choice>
                  <orig>perusial</orig>
                  <reg>perusal</reg>
               </choice> of this man William's letters <choice>
                  <orig>supprises</orig>
                  <reg>suprises</reg>
               </choice> me, I did not believe he was so fiendish as he is on that they had the little P. O. so much at heart— If his letters are a true index to his heart on the inner man, it is as black and malignant as hell itself— My opinion has always been bad enough God knows about him; but when ⁁ <add place="supralinear ">you</add> come to read his letters and see the guile that is <choice>
                  <orig>lerking</orig>
                  <reg>lurking</reg>
               </choice> through them, you cannot view him as occupying a higher grade than ⁁ <add place="supralinear">the</add> reptile that crawls upon its belly with the <emph>vines</emph>
               <choice>
                  <orig>conceiled</orig>
                  <reg>concealed</reg>
               </choice> beneath its crooked fangs ready to <choice>
                  <orig>strick</orig>
                  <reg>strike</reg>
               </choice> and communicate blight and death to all who dare cross <del type="overstrike">those</del>
               <add place="supralinear"> its</add> path— having <unclear>succumbed?</unclear> into the <choice>
                  <orig>dimentions</orig>
                  <reg>dimensions</reg>
               </choice> of the poisonous <pb n="2" facs="sl020b.small.jpg"/> adder. he deserves to be tread upon and crushed by the indignant heel of every independent and honest hearted man— I think ⁁ <add>him</add> one of the vilest and most deformed of Adam's fallen race and if there was no other sin in the world besides what he contains it would require the advent and blood of another <choice>
                  <orig>Savour</orig>
                  <reg>Saviour</reg>
               </choice> to preserve it from being swept into an awful hell where the worm dieth not and the fire is not quenched. I sit down to write one page and no more, but have permitted ⁁<add place="supralinear">my self</add> to begin to think about this miserable creature, so I will stop at this about him— I repeat that I have hope of <choice>
                  <orig>stoping</orig>
                  <reg>stopping</reg>
               </choice> the whole proceedings; but let them do all the devilment possible—</p>
            <p>We have made no speaker as yet. <name type="person">Cable</name> has been <choice>
                  <orig>droped</orig>
                  <reg>dropped</reg>
               </choice> the run is now upon <name type="person">Potter</name> of <name type="place">Ohio</name>— what the ultimate result will be, at this time no one can tell— The whigs seemed determined to have <del type="overstrike">Whin</del>
               <name type="person">Winthrop</name> or no one— My own opinion that the whigs have a majority in the House which the sequel will show <pb n="3" facs="sl020c.small.jpg"/> I ⁁<add place="supralinear">am</add> still laboring under my affliction— it ⁁ <add place="supralinear">is</add> some better; but very painful at times still— I have not seen old <name type="place">Zack</name> yet; but intend to call ⁁<add place="supralinear">on</add> him soon— Your piece of  Gold I have not sold as yet but will do it in a short time— I have not <choice>
                  <orig>recieved</orig>
                  <reg>received</reg>
               </choice> a letter from any one since leaving <name type="place">Greeneville</name> giving an account of  matters and things —</p>
            <p>You will <choice>
                  <orig>parden</orig>
                  <reg>pardon</reg>
               </choice> the brevity of this letter as I intend to write more fully in my next— Give my best respect to the young men about the store— Tender my best respects to <name type="person">Mrs Lowry</name> and accept for yourself assuredness of my high esteem.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <emph>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>A.</abbr>
                           <expan>Andrew</expan>
                        </choice> Johnson</name>
                  </emph>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mr <choice>
                           <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                           <expan>William</expan>
                        </choice> M Lowry</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
