<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um071">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1841 Mar. 28, Columbia, [Tennessee] [to] Elizabeth Chester, et al., Jackson, Tennessee / M[ary] J[ane] Chester    : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um071</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50315464</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1841 Mar. 28, Columbia, [Tennessee] [to] Elizabeth Chester, et al., Jackson, Tennessee / M[ary] J[ane] Chester</title>
               <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
               <date when="1841-03-28">March 28, 1841</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by Mary Jane Chester to her mother, Elizabeth Chester, and other members of her family on March 28, 1841. In the series of short letters, Mary Jane discusses events going on in the family and with people she has come in contact with in Columbia, and she urges her family to keep in touch with her while she is away at school.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers MS 25 (March-April 1841)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">8</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um071</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Mary Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um071a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia</name> Female Institute</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1841-03-28">March 28th 1841</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Father</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>As this is the day that we have to write Compositions and perhaps is the only time that I shall have to write for one or two week. I have concluded to write to you my dear Father I have no news to tell you so you must be satisfied with a very short &amp; uninteresting letter. I was very much grieved to hear that Mama was so sick when you arrived at home but I hope by this time that she is perfectly recovered — If she is it would give me so much pleasure to receive a letter from her — Papa you cannot imagine how much pleasure your visit gave ⁁ <add place="supralinear">me</add> but I wish to see almost as much as I  did before you came, I wish that you all would live in Columbia, <gap agent="damage"/> how until I finish my Education, I know that it is a very selfish wish but <emph>you</emph> know it is impossible for human nature to be without some portion of selfishness. I was very much pleased to hear that <name type="person">Aunt Patsey</name> has recovered her health. I expect that her sickness was occasioned by <name type="person">Uncle Will's</name> absence but now that the time is so fast approaching for him to return she will get well I can assure you then. As soon as Uncle returns I want him to write me a long letter for he has never written me one line since I been away from home but I  <choice>
                  <sic>can can</sic>
                  <corr>can</corr>
               </choice> excuse that as <emph>he</emph> has not been at ho<gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>me</unclear> When he returns I must have a letter from him.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Aunt Walker</name> has had a very severe spell since — O she has suffered so much, they were all very uneasy about her, but they think that she is something better this morning. I have not been there since you left Columbia, for <name type="person">Mr Smith</name> is so very strict about us leaving the Institute. I suppose that you have received the third Number of the Guardian. there is an account of every thing respecting <name type="person">Miss Julia Gordon</name>. Some of her own writings Papa you cannot imagine how much she was beloved by all her class mates. <add place="left side of page, sideways">Tell <name type="person">Cousin Dick</name> that he must answer my letter soon. Tell <name type="person">Jack Hays</name> that I should like to receive a letter. I suppose that <name type="person">Mary Ormand</name> can almost write a letter. My love to <name type="person">Cousin Martha Ann</name>
                  <name type="person">Cousin Will</name> &amp; their <emph>children</emph>
               </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="um071b.small.jpg"/> Remember me to all the Servants <choice>
                  <abbr>M. J. C.</abbr>
                  <expan>Mary Jane Chester</expan>
               </choice>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1841-03-28">March 28th 1841</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dearest Mama</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I avail myself of Papa blank paper to say a few words to you. Do forgive me for my long silence for <unclear>and</unclear> feel that I ought not to have delayed so long in writing to you, but my dear Mama to tell you the truth I have had nothing at all to write that would interest you in the least. <name type="person">Cousin Ophelia Hays</name> sent for <name type="person">Miss Bills</name>, <name type="person">Kate Bowen</name>, &amp; myself to go out there &amp; remain until <choice>
                  <orig>Saturay</orig>
                  <reg>Saturday</reg>
               </choice> evening, and when we asked permission to go <name type="person">Mr F. G. Smith</name> said that we must be at home  (My home now the Institute) by Sunset. We were determined that we would not break his rules. so we got home just in time, so we were sitting out in the Front Porch when here comes Mr Smith (bowing all the time) Why young ladies it is more than I expected, I said Mr — You must have a very had opinion of us No indeed but I thought perhaps that you might be tempted to break the rules. Nevertheless the Western District stands  very very high in my estimation. Mama you must not think that I am trying to praise myself but just to think of Mr <choice>
                  <abbr>S —</abbr>
                  <expan>Smith</expan>
               </choice> being so deceitful. I do not like so much as I use to. I told Papa when he was here that I  was not going to take lessons in Music from <name type="person">Mrs Smith</name> any but I am very happy to inform him &amp; you that the new teacher has left the Institute &amp; I still continue to take lessons from Mrs Smith. I am very much pleased with her mode of teaching. Mama how does the <choice>
                  <orig>Parlour</orig>
                  <reg>Parlor</reg>
               </choice> look without the Piano. I am glad that it is gone, but still I cannot help from feeling sorry.</p>
            <p>The Rose bush that you sent me is growing very prettily. I was very much pleased with all the things that you sent me. I wish that I was at home to see some of your beautiful flowers— I know that every thing looks so pretty. Is <name type="person">aunt Narcissa</name> as fond of her Garden as ever. I can imagine that I see her &amp; Mary Ormand in the Garden together. Give my most sincere love to all my relations and Friends.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your ever affectionate &amp; confiding daughter </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>M. J.</abbr>
                        <expan>Mary Jane</expan>
                     </choice> Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <gap agent="damage"/>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="um071c.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>My dear brother<name type="person">John</name>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>You must excuse me for writing on <emph>Mama's</emph> and <emph>Papa's</emph> paper but indeed it is the only sheet of paper that I have ⁁ <add place="supralinear">in my</add>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Port-folio</orig>
                  <reg>portfolio</reg>
               </choice>, and I have concluded that you have determined not to write to me until I write to you. I am sure that you are not aware how much pleasure it gives me to receive letters from you, or you would write to me every <emph>Saturday</emph>. brother John do you attend as many parties as you did before I left home. I hope you enjoy <choice>
                  <orig>youself</orig>
                  <reg>yourself</reg>
               </choice> very much. Have you seen  <name type="person">Miss<emph>Ann Eliza <emph>Lancaster</emph>
                  </emph>
               </name> lately. You know that she once upon a time was your <emph>sweet hearts</emph>. I suppose that you have had the <choice>
                  <orig>honour</orig>
                  <reg>honor</reg>
               </choice> of <choice>
                  <orig>seein</orig>
                  <reg>seeing</reg>
               </choice>
               <name type="person">Miss Lyon</name>. do you think her handsome. O! I was so much delighted to hear that <name type="person">Brother Sam</name> could ⁁ <add place="supralinear">walk</add> — how I should like to see him strutting about I know that he looks so sweet &amp; pretty — My love to all.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your <choice>
                     <abbr>afft</abbr>
                     <expan>affectionate</expan>
                  </choice> Sister <choice>
                     <abbr>M. J. C.</abbr>
                     <expan>Mary Jane Chester</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mr John Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>My dear Sister</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>You must forgive me for writing to you on <emph>Papa's Mama's</emph> &amp; <emph>brother John's</emph> paper, but I shall have to offer the same excuse to you as I did to the others for I determine  write to you all to day as it has been so long a time since I had done myself the <choice>
                  <orig>Honour</orig>
                  <reg>Honor</reg>
               </choice> of writing to any of you. Sis I suppose that you have a little garden and a great many beautiful flowers. Do you remember the little garden that we used to have, but I suppose that is overgrown with weeds. Sis you must be sure to come up at the <emph>Examination</emph>. You must give my love your Doll, &amp; Cousin Mary Ormand. kiss sweet little Sam who is now Walking. kiss <name type="person">Will</name> &amp; <name type="person">King</name> also</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>M. J.</abbr>
                        <expan>Mary Jane</expan>
                     </choice> Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <emph>Miss Martha B. Chester</emph>
                     </name>.</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>My dear brother <name type="person">Robert</name>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>You not be offended at me for writing on <emph>Papa's Mama's brother John's</emph> &amp; <emph>Sister Martha's</emph> paper, but being determ<gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>ined</unclear> to write to you I took this best opportunity thinking that a short letter for each of you would satisfied. I suppose that you and Cousin <name type="person">Jackson Hays</name> has a great of pleasure together. has <name type="person">Uncle Sam</name> &amp; his family returned from <name type="place">Shelby</name> yet. My love to <name type="person">Cousin Jane Rawlings</name> ⁁ <add place="supralinear">&amp;</add> family </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="um071d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <add place="above address">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>postmark for March 30</figDesc>
                  </figure> 18¾</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mrs Elizabeth Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address">Mail Single</add>
               <add place="through address" rend="different hand, ink">
                  <date when="1841-03-22">22 March 1841</date>
               </add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
