<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl318">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1833 Aug. 6, Alexandria [to] A. Fergusson, Carthage, Tenn[essee] / John H. Davis   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Davis, John H.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl318</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1833 Aug. 6, Alexandria [to] A. Fergusson, Carthage, Tenn[essee] / John H. Davis</title>
               <author>Davis, John H.</author>
               <date when="1833-08-06">August 6, 1833</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from John H. Davis to A. Fergusson, dated August 6, 1833. Davis is requesting  information on divorce procedures. He wants to know  how easily a woman can be awarded a divorce, on grounds of adultery committed by the husband, if he does not protest it.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> IV-G-1 b3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">4</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl318</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Law and legislation</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Davis, John H.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl318a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Alexandria</name>
                     <date when="1833-08-06">August 6th 1833</date>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Mr <name type="person">A <choice>
                           <orig>Furgerson</orig>
                           <reg>Fergusson</reg>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I wish your <choice>
                  <orig>dvice</orig>
                  <reg>advice</reg>
               </choice> in case in which I am concerned I want you to write me and answer the following questions_ what cases of divorce come under the jurisdiction of the circuit court,, if I have been rightly informed the court takes cognizance of but <choice>
                  <orig>too</orig>
                  <reg>two</reg>
               </choice> cases <choice>
                  <abbr>viz</abbr>
                  <expan>videlicet</expan>
               </choice> too years absence and that of Adultery admitting this to be the fact I want to know if a woman petitions for a divorce charging <choice>
                  <orig>hir</orig>
                  <reg>her</reg>
               </choice> husband with adultery and he at the bottom of her petition acknowledges the charge if this will be sufficient for the court to act on and if the court will grant her petition when presented or should she get the affidavits of 2 or 3 witnesses to prove the fact I want you if you please to write me a blank form of petition to the circuit court at carthage in a case of a woman <del type="overstrike">for</del> charging her husband <pb n="2" facs="sl318b.small.jpg"/> with adultery and explain to me the nature of the whole matter from the nature of the subject I would suppose that if a woman presents a petition in case of adultery and the man acknowledges the charge and makes no objection to a divorce being granted that the court would immediately order her a divorce but of this you can inform me when you write me I wish you to say that if the thing goes into effect if you will attend to it and get it effected and what you will charge for the same__ what I have written to you I charge you as a <unclear>M,, M</unclear> to keep sacred until time shall make it known__ the case I have laid before you is one of importance you will therefore make me acquainted with everything <choice>
                  <orig>nessesary</orig>
                  <reg>necessary</reg>
               </choice> to effect it_ when you write you can leave the letter at uncle <unclear>Late</unclear> and he can send it to me and I will confer with you from time to time about give my love to Hester and oblige yours_</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">John,, H,, Davis,,</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl318c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mr A,, Furgerson <choice>
                        <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Carthage</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>care,, of Lat,, Hazard,,    <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>,,</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
