<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl207">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1844 Nov. 19, Russellville, KY [to] Mary  [House]  / Presley Ewing   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Ewing, Presley</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl207</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51206503</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1844 Nov. 19, Russellville, KY [to] Mary  [House]  / Presley Ewing</title>
               <author>Ewing, Presley</author>
               <date when="1844-11-19">November 19, 1844</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated November 19, 1844 from Kentucky politician Presley Underwood Ewing to Mary House of Davidson County, TN. Ewing updates House on family and local news, including the recent visit by her mother and rumors that he seeks a widow with children to marry.  Ewing also discusses his own mother's illness and his father's teaching job.  </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl207</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Kentucky -- Politics and government</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr91042138"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Ewing, Presley, 1822-1854</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl207a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Russellville</name>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Ky</abbr>
                           <expan>Kentucky</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                     <date when="1844-11-19">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Nov</abbr>
                           <expan>November</expan>
                        </choice> 19th 1844</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear <name type="person">Mary</name>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I was gratified a day or two since by one more letter from you, a satisfaction only inferior to that of seeing you personally. I am delighted to hear that your mother was pleased with her visit, &amp; the more so because it encouraged me to hope for a renewal of it. She left us as she has told you just as my Father &amp; Brother started for their winter visit or rather residence at <name type="place">Louisville</name>. She left us deserted by all in this haunted Castle, &amp; she can tell you how pertinaciously we labored to prolong her stay, &amp; how rigidly we exacted her promise for another visit on her part as well as your own, &amp; that right soon! I think if my Father, whose influence would have been added most warmly to our own, had remained at home, she would hardly have been able to get away for some time to come. Tell her I have been <choice>
                  <orig>retailing</orig>
                  <reg>retelling</reg>
               </choice> some of her anecdotes — for when she got through with the old ones brought to memory by the ⁁ <add place="supralinear">first</add> renewal of old associations, she <pb n="2" facs="sl207b.small.jpg"/> seemed to have an inexhaustible stock <choice>
                  <orig>bran</orig>
                  <reg>brand</reg>
               </choice> new just from the visit — tell her I have been endeavoring to repeat  some of them, but with no shadow of the affect they had from her. <name type="person">Miss Leona McCloud</name> has been spending a few weeks with us <del type="overstrike">f</del> &amp; has greatly brightened the dullness of our little household, but she leaves us soon. <name type="person">Mrs Macy</name> fortunately for us has recently <del type="overstrike"/> arrived, &amp; by the aid of her most excellent company, we are as cheerful a little party as you will find anywhere under the same circumstances;  but I think we might form a much more symmetrical circle around the fireside, by a little enlargement. We are all rather old — we lack young <unclear>backs</unclear>; I mean very little <unclear>backs</unclear> . Do come over and bring with you a half dozen children if convenient. But I expect from the anxiety of your Mother to see little <name type="person">Sallie</name> while she was here, that if you <del type="overstrike">with</del> were <choice>
                  <orig>bothe</orig>
                  <reg>both</reg>
               </choice> to come together your mother    would lose at least a hundred weight of flesh in pining for you. You are the better judges whether she can spare so much. From my known fondness for children connected with one or two little casual coincidences, rather <pb n="3" facs="sl207c.small.jpg"/> indicating <del type="overstrike">my</del> a like fondness for widows, the impression has gone abroad, that I am in pursuit of some widow with at least three children — four is my number they say, but three will do to begin with.</p>
            <p>I think mother has been really anxious to go over to <name type="place">Nashville</name>, but she has remained at home so long that she has lost some of her former energy and resolution. She hardly even gets ⁁ <add place="supralinear">up</add> to <name type="person">Uncle Wash</name>'s once in these months, &amp; her young relatives do not pretend to account <unclear>visit</unclear> with her. But I must confess ⁁ <add place="supralinear">she has had</add>
               <unclear>w</unclear> this contemplated trip more difficulties than usual to contend with and now that the season is so far advanced we <del type="overstrike">ha</del> can hardly hope for good weather of  sufficient duration to justify one of her health and age in undertaking the adventure. Do not wait for her to come over, but trust rather to the chances of taking her with you on your return. I do not see the force of your apology for not coming. You do not intend to be the active agent in <choice>
                  <orig>hireing</orig>
                  <reg>hiring</reg>
               </choice> another house yourself do you? One's being turned out of house is a poor reason for remaining at home. Our house has not yet been bought for an orphan asylum, <del type="overstrike">bu</del> though it is large enough to accommodate a few such agreeable orphans as <pb n="4" facs="sl207d.small.jpg"/> yourself.</p>
            <p>Father and <name type="person">Henry</name> are highly pleased with their situation &amp; circumstances. Henry writes that the students seem <del type="overstrike">attach</del> fond of Father. He finds the duties very light, but says "it is a <choice>
                  <orig>dirned</orig>
                  <reg>darned</reg>
               </choice> sight harder to learn the boys' names than the lectures, and he  <unclear/> throws the class into convulsions of laughter by his ludicrous mistakes <gap agent="damage"/> love to all and believe me</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>very Truly your Friend</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Presley Ewing</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
