<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um081">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1842 Oct. 16, Columbia, Tennessee [to] Col[onel] Robert J. Chester, Jackson, Tennessee/ M[ary] J[ane] Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um081</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50316754</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1842 Oct. 16, Columbia, Tennessee [to] Col[onel] Robert J. Chester, Jackson, Tennessee/ M[ary] J[ane] Chester </title>
               <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
               <date when="1842-10-16">October 16, 1842</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a letter, dated October 16, 1842, from Mary Jane  Chester to her father Colonel Robert J. Chester in Jackson, TN.  In the letter, Mary Jane writes about her social and academic affairs at the Female Institute in Columbia, TN.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers MS-25 (Jan-Dec 1842)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">10</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um081</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Mary Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um081a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia <del type="overstrike">Jackson</del> Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1842-10-16">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Oct.</abbr>
                           <expan>October</expan>
                        </choice> 16th 1842</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Papa</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>As there is no church in Town to day, I think that I could not better employ my time, than by answering your very kind letter.  I can assure you that it was received with great pleasure, as your letters always are, but I must confess this last with more than usual, I was also a little astonished for I had began to suspect that you all thought it of no consequence whether I heard from home or not; I am very glad to see that I was mistaken but you must remember that you promised to write me at least once in two weeks. and Papa always tell me something about the dear Children, for I am almost <emph>distracted</emph> to see them.  I awake very often in the night under the impression that I am at home and that little <name type="person">Sam</name> is with me —  I hope that you keep <name type="person">Emelina</name> at her <emph>knitting</emph>.  I am fearful that the children will not be so well <emph>fixed</emph> this winder as they have always been before.  I promise myself to be more useful when I return.</p>
            <p>Indeed I am grieved to hear that <name type="person">Olivia Day</name> has acted so very badly, how mortifying it must be to her Parents but I think that they are almost as much to blame as she is herself for they <pb n="2" facs="um081b.small.jpg"/> have never given her any of the advantages of Education, and I suppose no good advice, (such as I receive from you upon that subject.) she has not displayed her good taste in selecting <name type="person">Mr McRee</name> for I think that he is the last person that any one could fancy. Poor girl! I am afraid that she will "have her reward."</p>
            <p>I attended a small party at <name type="person">Mr. Wormleys</name>  on Friday evening and enjoyed myself very much, indeed I never was at a more pleasant Party.  I was also invited to join a Pic-nic on saturday but owing to the days being so unfavorable it was given out.  I felt a little disappointed for I know it would have been pleasant.  We intended spending the day about two miles from Town at the <name type="place">Sulphur Springs</name> , a very pretty place it is I am told. Papa I know that this does not interest you but I do not know what else to write about.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Mr. Smith</name> has requested each one of the girls to write home, and see if it is their parents wish that they should take Drawing lessons, but I think that I have as many studies as I can possibly attend to.  he expects a Tutoress on in a few days, who will teach nothing but drawing painting &amp; Embroidery.  Mr. Smith placed me in a much higher class in French than I anticipated, for which you may be sure I felt pleased. I intend to try and keep up with it.  You know that I never studied French but part of one Session before. <name type="person">Miss Lizzy</name> (my Tutoress) says that she thinks that I will make a very good Scholar.</p>
            <p>Dear Papa think that it is almost time for you to <choice>
                  <orig>fulfil</orig>
                  <reg>fulfill</reg>
               </choice> your <emph>Promise</emph> which that you would come up to see me, I do hope that I shall not be disappointed.  Tell Aunts<name type="person"> Patsy</name> and <name type="person">Narcissa</name>  that I am looking very anxiously for an answer to my letter, <name type="person">Cousin Jane</name> and <name type="person">Aunt Frances</name> that I should be delighted to receive a letter from them.  I hope that you yourself will not be so <emph>tardy</emph> in <pb n="3" facs="um081c.small.jpg"/> writing again.  Give my love to all.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your ever affectionate Daughter</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>M. J.</abbr>
                        <expan>Mary Jane</expan>
                     </choice> Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="um081d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="left of address">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>postmark for Oct. 18</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel</expan>
                        </choice> Robert J. Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson</name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="bottom" rend="different hand, ink">
                  <name type="person">Miss Mary Jane Chester</name>
               </add>
               <add place="below address" rend="different hand, ink">
                  <date when="1842-10-16">16 <choice>
                        <abbr>Oct</abbr>
                        <expan>October</expan>
                     </choice> 1842</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
