<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="sl022">[Writings] circa 1825 [for] New Jackson Paper / Andrew Jackson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Jackson, Andrew</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl022</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:  50014401</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Writings] circa 1825 [for] New Jackson Paper / Andrew Jackson</title>
               <author>Jackson, Andrew</author>
               <date when="1825">circa 1825</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document was written circa 1825 by Andrew Jackson on his thoughts for a republican newspaper which he titled "New Jackson Paper". In his writings, Jackson outlines his idea of the qualifications a  person would need to help publish this paper.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Sir Emil Hurja Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">7</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">8</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl022</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Newspaper publishing</term>
               <term>Newspaper employees</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79088888"
                        role="Author http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/aut">Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl022a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>
               <emph>New Jackson Paper</emph>
            </head>
            <p>A gentleman of this city is desirous of engaging a partner of talents and character to aid him in the publication of a daily newspaper in this place, to be conducted on republican principles, and to be devoted to the support of the next Administration, and, at the same time, to oppose the selfish views of the unprincipled faction who are struggling to make the ⁁<add place="supralinear">late</add> victory of the People the source of their own private <choice>
                  <orig>aggrandisement</orig>
                  <reg>aggrandizement</reg>
               </choice> and <unclear>enduement</unclear>. As a publication of   this kind, emanating from the Seat of Government, is at present a <unclear>diseduatum</unclear>,  and is anxiously  wished for by all who believe politics, <del type="overstrike">and</del> sound reason, and common decency to be compatible with each other, it is superfluous to say that the inducements it offers, to a suitable person, are very great; and if he entertains an elevated opinion of the good sense of the people, and their ability to <choice>
                  <orig>descriminate</orig>
                  <reg>discriminate</reg>
               </choice> between the boisterous demagogue and their real friend, he can have no doubt of the most unexampled success. To prevent unnecessary trouble, the applicant whose <del type="overstrike">character</del> principles and character can bear the following test, will be preferred; and none, varying much from it, need apply, as the advertiser has<del type="overstrike"> no</del>
               <add place="supralinear">neither a</add> desire to follow in the wake of others ⁁<add place="supralinear">nor</add> interfere with <del type="overstrike">their</del>
               <add place="supralinear">existing</add> plans. <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear>nor to  on  did already </unclear>
               </del>
            </p>
            <p>1. The successful applicant must be a republican in theory and practice; and, in order to prove that <del type="overstrike">they</del> ⁁ <add>his principles</add> are more deeply rooted than his tongue, will have to produce evidence not only that he has <emph>written</emph>, <emph>talked</emph>, and <emph>disclaimed</emph> about "liberty" and the "rights of the People," but that he has never, in private life, as an employer or the head of a family, abused his brief authority, or attempted to exercise an unwarrantable and despotic sway over the only portion of the People over whom he had ⁁<add>any</add> control. Positive evidence on this head is absolutely indispensable, and must emanate from <pb n="2" facs="sl022b.small.jpg"/> those only who have been, or now are, by chance or fortune, subjected to his will; for he who maltreats his own household, and acts the tyrant in miniature over the unfortunate, deserves to be treated with ineffable scorn and contempt when he <choice>
                  <orig>vapours</orig>
                  <reg>vapors</reg>
               </choice> about "liberty," and the "rights of the People." It is worse than folly to suppose that such a man can be a true patriot, <del type="overstrike">and</del>
               <add>or</add>, disinterestedly, devote his time and talents to the welfare of a <emph>whole</emph> nation. Therefore, in the absence of all evidence of <del type="overstrike">this</del>
               <emph>practical</emph> republicanism, what he has said or sung on the topic will be of no avail; for a truly good man will no more make a continual parade of his virtue and patriotism, than a virtuous matron would of her chastity and fidelity.</p>
            <p>2. If the applicant should have edited a paper during the past political campaign, he must produce evidence of his modesty and manliness when triumphant, and ⁁<add place="supralinear">of </add> his respect for the dignity of the People. If he attributes the late triumph to the reality with which the People  were led by him, rather than to their own <del type="overstrike">moods,</del>
               <add place="supralinear">determined spirit</add> his <del type="overstrike">will or </del> vanity <del type="overstrike">will not</del> is too preposterous to suit the views of the advertisers. If he has attempted, <add place="supralinear">to act as the peoples agent</add> with a view of gathering, for himself and his faction, the harvest which they <del type="overstrike">People</del> had <choice>
                  <orig>sown</orig>
                  <reg>sewn</reg>
               </choice>, his application will be rejected, and himself <del type="overstrike">treated as spu</del> subjected to the penalties ⁁ <add place="supralinear">usually</add> inflicted on ⁁<add place="supralinear">
                  <del type="overstrike">
                     <choice>
                        <orig>suporters</orig>
                        <reg>supporters</reg>
                     </choice> and</del>
               </add> the spurious representative of a <del type="overstrike">rich</del> ⁁<add place="supralinear">great</add> inheritance. <del type="overstrike">Finaly His actions must</del> His conduct since the election must have been such as to prove, that he did not consider "party the madness of many for the benefit of a few."</p>
            <p>3. In his new vocation, he must not attempt to palm himself off to the President elect as the People, nor attempt to dictate to him in their name. </p>
            <p>4. He must not be a man so contemptible where he is known, as to hope nothing from the influence of his personal character. Such men are complete nuisances in any country where they write the power of the press. Like sharpers, they sow dissensions among the People, persuade one portion of them that they are the natural enemies of the other, <pb n="3" facs="sl022c.small.jpg"/> and make them quarrel with each other, to enable themselves the more easily to rob and pick their pockets. If the party gains the ascendancy to which, by choice or accident, they attach themselves, they claim for the triumphant opinions the rewards which belong only to character and virtue; because they can only hope for success, ⁁ <add place="supralinear">by</add> stifling the <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear>reason</unclear>
               </del> common sense and reason of mankind, and exciting their passions. By these means, they ⁁<add place="supralinear">frequently</add> float on the torrent of popular fury; and, when it recedes, their neighbors are astonished to see them, <del>snug</del>
               <add place="supralinear">high</add> and dry, in <del type="overstrike">elevated </del> stations so far ⁁ <add place="supralinear">elevated</add> above their native element. With <del type="overstrike">nothing</del> little or nothing to risk, it is no wonder that such desperadoes are ever ready to embark in any party enterprise, provided they are afterwards permitted to scramble, (with the <del type="overstrike">modest</del>
               <add place="supralinear">meritorious</add> and patriotic, who are <del type="overstrike">always</del> most diffident) for the rewards of success. In short, they are so convinced that no revolution of the wheel of fortune can sink them lower, and so envious of others withal, that they would consider even a deluge a blessing, if it could only destroy the land marks of property and ⁁<add place="supralinear">the</add> gradations of character, and permit<del type="overstrike">ted</del> them<add place="supralinear">selves</add> to sail, unmarked and unmolested, over the general ruin. </p>
            <p>5. He must be opposed to the scalping system of editing and governing; and be no advocate for proscription in this <emph>free</emph> land, whilst he affects to lament and shed crocodile tears over persecution, for <emph>opinion's</emph> sake, in <name type="place">Europe</name> and elsewhere.</p>
            <closer>All letters, postpaid, and addressed through the <del>P. O.</del> post office to A. G. will be attended to.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
