<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um070">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1841 Mar. 26, Jackson, [Tennessee]     [to] Mary Jane Chester / Elizabeth Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Elizabeth</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um070</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50315321</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1841 Mar. 26, Jackson, [Tennessee]     [to] Mary Jane Chester / Elizabeth Chester</title>
               <author>Chester, Elizabeth</author>
               <date when="1841-03-26">March 26, 1841</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by Elizabeth Chester to her daughter, Mary Jane Chester, on March 26, 1841. In the letter, Elizabeth discusses  social events taking place in Jackson, such as marriages and parties, as well as events taking place with the people in their family. She asks her daughter not to ride on horses because she could get injured, and to always tell them the truth because they need to trust her while she is away from home.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers MS 25 (March-April 1841)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">8</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um070</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Elizabeth</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um070a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Jackson</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1841-03-26">Ma <add place="supralinear">r</add> ch <del type="overstrike">24</del> 26 41</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear Daughter</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Again to day I was disappointed in not receiving a letter from you, indeed I do not know what to think off your not w <add place="supralinear">r</add> iting had your Papa not have seen you <unclear>so lately</unclear> I should conclude that you were sick you really must write once a week at the least less than that I cannot be satisfied with hearing of the <choice>
                  <orig>unfortionate</orig>
                  <reg>unfortunate</reg>
               </choice> death of Miss Garden has shocked me greatly I should be miserable to think that you would get on a horse again you know how much <choice>
                  <orig>affraid</orig>
                  <reg>afraid</reg>
               </choice> I am of your riding I wish you my dear Child to send me your <choice>
                  <orig>promis</orig>
                  <reg>promise</reg>
               </choice> that you will not ride on horse back <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> I see you if you <choice>
                  <orig>promis</orig>
                  <reg>promise</reg>
               </choice> me I know that you will keep your word it is a source of great pleasure to know that your word can be <choice>
                  <orig>rilyed</orig>
                  <reg>relied</reg>
               </choice> on, Truth oh what a beautiful Gem thou <unclear>art</unclear> how much we should love and <choice>
                  <orig>honour</orig>
                  <reg>honor</reg>
               </choice> thee without thee there is no confidence between Parent &amp; Child in indeed in any relation whatever <pb n="2" facs="um070b.small.jpg"/> we had the pleasure of hearing from you through <name type="person">Mr Knox Walker</name> he stayed several days in town I saw him only twice he was on his way to see <name type="person">Catherine McLamer</name> at <name type="place">Memphis</name> the sun is just setting every thing looks Beautiful Flowers all in bloom how I wish you had some of our sweet Hyacinths and delightful flowers is your Rose living, Our Town has been quite gay for the last week I believe the Girls have all determined to get married if <emph>any one</emph> will have them <name type="person">Miss Patterson</name> and <name type="person">Calvin Henderson</name>
               <name type="person">Miss McIven</name> &amp; <name type="person">Mr Read</name>
               <name type="person">Miss Mariana Johnson</name> &amp; <name type="person">Mr Richard Fenner</name> are all married a grand Party to night at <name type="person">Mr Rick Jones'</name>
               <name type="person">Cousin Dick</name> is still <name type="person">Miss Lyons</name> devoted <unclear>rading</unclear> with and galanting her on all occasions what say you to that, you know not my dear Child how anxiously I long for your return <emph>home</emph> Papa says that you must graduate more of that when I see you, <name type="person">Martha</name> was delighted with her Pants they are beautiful I am vexed that you <del type="overstrike">dont get</del> do not have one handsome white <choice>
                  <orig>dess</orig>
                  <reg>dress</reg>
               </choice> at least there is no new goods in <name type="place">Jackson</name> or I would have some made here <name type="person">Mrs Swan</name> is making a common Lawn for you which I will send next week <name type="person">Mr Davidson</name> is going through <name type="place">Columbia</name> Papa is from home and it is <choice>
                  <orig>gitting</orig>
                  <reg>getting</reg>
               </choice> late and I must conclude by telling you to <choice>
                  <orig>imagin</orig>
                  <reg>imagine</reg>
               </choice>
               <pb n="3" facs="um070c.small.jpg"/> as much love a Mother can feel for a beloved child and feel assured that you occupy that place in my heart all the children send love and kisses to you Martha wants you to link some of your hair into a bracelet and send it in a letter to her I Pray the Father of us all to have you in his especial keeping</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>you affectionate Mother</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Elizabeth Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="below signature">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>PS</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> since writing the above another mail has come and no letter from you I am very <unclear>uneasy</unclear> abo <add place="supralinear">u</add> t you do write every week <name type="person">Aunt Narcissa</name> is now well went a fishing to day John <gap agent="damage"/> &amp; <name type="person">Jackson Hays</name> with her will write <gap agent="damage"/> next week. affectionately <choice>
                     <abbr>EC</abbr>
                     <expan>Elizabeth Chester</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <name type="person">Sam</name> is walking looks very sweet</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="um070d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="above address">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>post mark seal</figDesc>
                  </figure> 18 ¾</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Miss Mary Jane Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <emph>
                        <name type="place">
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                              <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </name>
                     </emph>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left of address">Mail }</add>
               <add place="right of address">
                  <date when="1841">1841</date>
               </add>
               <add place="below address, upside down">My Dear Mother <lb/>
                  <date when="1841-03-26">26 March 1841</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
