<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc061">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1845 Jun. 3 [to] Harmon G. Lea Esq [uire] / Hardin P. Shannon : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Shannon, Hardin P.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sc061</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 513144775</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1845 Jun. 3 [to] Harmon G. Lea Esq [uire] / Hardin P. Shannon</title>
               <author>Shannon, Hardin P.</author>
               <date when="1845-06-03">June 3, 1845</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by Hardin P. Shannon to Harmon G. Lea on June 3, 1845. The letter discusses Hardin Shannon's affiliation with the Whig political party and events that have transpired because of this affiliation. Shannon states that elections are going to be held soon and that he will run in the election as a Whig delegate.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Hardin P. Shannon</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-1347</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc061</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government</term>
               <term>Whig Party (Tenn.)</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Shannon, Hardin P.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc061a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Near <name type="place">Cheeks <choice>
                           <abbr>X</abbr>
                           <expan>Cross</expan>
                        </choice> Roads</name>
                     <name type="place">Grainger County</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1845-06-03">3rd June 1845</date>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Harmon G. Lea <choice>
                           <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                           <expan>Esquire</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Feeling very well assured that you are a true and unswerving <name type="person">Whig</name>, and that you desire the success of Whig principles and all the great &amp; glorious measures of the same. I write you <choice>
                  <orig>to night</orig>
                  <reg>tonight</reg>
               </choice>, in the true Whig spirit, partaking of &amp; congenial to that which animated &amp; warmed the bosoms of our patriotic ancestors in the ever memorable days of <choice>
                  <abbr/>
                  <expan>1776</expan>
               </choice> — To say that I am a firm, an unbending &amp; inflexible Whig, is but to report what I have always honestly felt <del type="overstrike">&amp;</del>
               <choice>
                  <orig>stile</orig>
                  <reg>still</reg>
               </choice> feel &amp; ever expect to remain while life &amp; reason remain. My principles are fixed &amp; are true as the polar star &amp; as unvarying. Vacillation — political equivocation &amp; <unclear>subterfuge</unclear> upon plain, broad &amp; leading questions of public policy I most heartily detest &amp; utterly despise. I love to see a man declare his sentiments, political, or otherwise with frankness— candor — honesty — plainness.—</p>
            <p>But enough of this. I think my course since I have become a candidate before the people for the station of Representative of my native Grainger is a sufficient proof of the sincerity of my heart in the declaration of my principles. &amp; my entire devotedness to the same. — I became a candidate at the request and by the solicitation of those who had known <pb n="2" facs="sc061b.small.jpg"/> me long and well — friends tried &amp; true. I who thought me worthy of their confidence &amp; support I felt grateful to them for their generous encouragement. I felt, as I still feel, willing to serve them as they Representative , to the best of my humble abilities. I went out among the people — I visited the different portions of the county &amp; it is, as is ever will be, a source of pride — of pleasure &amp; of gratification that I <choice>
                  <abbr>recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> encouragement wherever I went. — I feel grateful — deeply grateful to all of my friends for these peculiar favors. — <name type="person">Cal Cleveland</name> became a candidate sometime after I had &amp; also <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                     <expan>Esquire</expan>
                  </choice> Moore</name>. They were both older men, by far, than myself, but as my fellow citizens considered me worthy of their support. I felt willing to serve them My claims are equal to those of either of the other candidates. <choice>
                  <abbr>Cal C</abbr>
                  <expan>Cal Cleveland</expan>
               </choice> has served the people long, it is true, but he has been amply remunerated for the same to say nothing about a certain <emph>$48.00</emph> he <choice>
                  <abbr>recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> for services never rendered. I refer to the Journals. — Now, I manifested an entire willingness to submit my claims to the action of the freemen of the county from the first movement of my appearance before them. I wished Union &amp; Harmony &amp; a concentration of the Whig forces in the important contest now going on. —</p>
            <p>I consider it a matter of the utmost importance to have a Whig Legislation. at the ensuing session The reasons were obvious — You own good sense advises you what they are. Every genuine Whig comprehends them at a glance. — <add place="top of page above text">Please state the matter in the right light before <name type="person">Dr. S Shields</name> &amp; your uncle <name type="person">Jeremiah Jarnagin</name> &amp; all others you may see, &amp; if you think I deserve any thing at your hands I shall be grateful for any assistance you may render me. I only ask stern &amp; inflexible justice. <name type="person">H. Shannon</name>
               </add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sc061c.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>My friends say to me — Stick to the track. They will support me. I feel that they will. Some of them have even gone so far as to say that they will vote for <name type="person">McGinnis</name>, if Cleveland was his only opponent. I fully believe it. — <unclear>I onsto</unclear> to do for the best. —</p>
            <p>I do honestly prefer the success of my principles to any more personal promotion of my own. And if it was really essential to the success of our glorious principles, I would take a peculiar pride &amp; a pleasure in sacrificing any claims that I may have to the Nation upon the altar of my Country's good, if by so doing I could ensure their success. Each candidate has his friends but it is quite clear that the issue is now, as it has been all along between Cleveland &amp; myself. You have some idea how the <unclear>canvass</unclear> has progressed. I could fill this sheet in a detail of the matter but must be brief. On yesterday (Monday) we met at Rutledge &amp; made some speeches — Col. McGinnis merely declared himself a candidate — Cleveland followed in a rather singular speech — an attempt to vindicate himself &amp; his declarations. Since the commencement of this canvass — &amp; seemed to try to make the impression that he was the champion of <emph>our</emph> cause <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> — <choice>
                  <abbr>Esq.</abbr>
                  <expan>Esquire</expan>
               </choice> Moore presented himself next &amp; blazed away awhile &amp; seemed quite <unclear>Docile</unclear> &amp; tractable indeed. I followed &amp; avowed the same. Principles, that I have ever entertained &amp; expressed my willingness &amp; desire to abide by a fair expression of the will of the people, if that could be ascertained. I expressed my willingness to submit the whole matter to the people to be determined by their vote en masse on <date when="---21">21st</date> instant — at the time of the proposed adjustment of the Congressional matter. Cleveland would not agree to it, unless I would consent to go <gap agent="damage"/> &amp; remain perfectly still &amp; quiet until after the election. The blood of a freeman flows in my veins. I felt as <gap agent="damage"/> freeman. I acted as a freeman. I would not consent to <gap agent="damage"/> such arrangement. It was <choice>
                  <orig>ingenerous</orig>
                  <reg>ungenerous</reg>
               </choice> to say the least of it. He knew that my acquaintance was limited throughout the county — at least in some portions of it &amp; thought to take advantage of it. It is characteristic of the man. — The next proposition that was made was to this effect — that we leave the decision of the matter to the Grand Jury — the Court sitting &amp; appointing at the time. Cleveland &amp; Moore agreed to it <emph>immediately</emph>.</p>
            <p>I did not feel willing to enter into any such arrangement, without taking time for reflection — I told them so — considerable excitement got up — a good deal of warmth manifested. the advocates of the new proposition urging me to decide instantly whether or no.— I told them I would let them know my determination on Saturday next at <name type="place">Beans Station</name> — Moore was willing to consider the matter binding on him, but Cleveland would not, &amp; <unclear>remind</unclear> us I thought disposed to agree to nothing. Except it suited him, &amp; to his advantage. I have determined <emph>not</emph> to leave the decision of the matter to the ⁁ <add place="supralinear">proposed</add>
               <unclear>mind</unclear> Jury or any other than the Grand Jury of the whole people, assembled at the Ballot Box. I feel fully <pb n="4" facs="sc061d.small.jpg"/> sustained in the course I have pursued. I wish it to be distinctly ⁁ <add place="supralinear">understood</add>
               <unclear>inverse</unclear> that I am entirely willing &amp; desirous that the difficulty could be amicably &amp; satisfactorily adjusted at any time, before the general election. I feel a deep interest in the matter I ardently desire the success of our principles — &amp; would gladly do any thing, that could be done consistently  &amp; honorably for the success of the fame. But I have learned a few thing in relation to this matter, that fully convinces me, that there are <emph>
                  <unclear>more</unclear> workers</emph> engaged in their under handed business of intrigue &amp; management. I have several of the prominent leading characters, as I believe in my eye at this time, who are engaged in this business. — They are <emph>would-be Leaders</emph> — Cleveland is their man. They think to draw me in the snare, but I am in the alert &amp; am looking out for brokers ahead — I do not doubt, but that the proposition as to the Grand Jury <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice>, will be most grossly misrepresented by those whose interest it is to do so. My not agreeing to enter into the arrangement will be construed entirely different from what is the real fact of the matter. It will doubtless be placed to the score of contrariness &amp; obstinacy &amp; an unwillingness ⁁ <add place="supralinear">in me</add> to have the difficulty settled. Such is <emph>not</emph> the case. It is not true. — I have my reasons for not doing so — conclusive &amp; entirely satisfactorily to myself &amp; friends. — It was as uncertain as the wind to say the least of it. It could not possibly be a fair expression. We are to meet at Bean's Station on next Saturday &amp; see more about the whole matter. A pretty good attendance is expected &amp; desired. If it would not be too inconvenient, I would be extremely happy to see you up at the Station on Saturday next at the proposed meeting. Please excuse haste &amp; very bad writing as I have written in great haste.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am very sincerely your friend</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Hardin P. Shannon</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="left of address">I arrived home from Rutledge late this evening &amp; feeling anxious that you be acquainted with the facts in the case. I have taken the liberty to write you. If you cannot come to the Station, be so kind as to drop me a few lines, as a friend, on the whole matter. As soon after <choice>
                     <abbr>recpt</abbr>
                     <expan>receipt</expan>
                  </choice> as you conveniently can at <name type="place">Russelville</name> — &amp; oblige</add>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Yrs &amp;c</abbr>
                     <expan>Yours et cetera</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>Hardin P. Shannon</signed>
               <add place="above address">Russelville <choice>
                     <abbr>Tn</abbr>
                     <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/>
                  <date when="--06-04">June 4</date> Paid 10</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Harmon G Lea <choice>
                           <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                           <expan>Esquire</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Blane's <choice>
                           <abbr>X</abbr>
                           <expan>Cross</expan>
                        </choice> Roads</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Grainger County</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">East <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenne</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left of address">Mail }</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
