<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl619">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Legislative documents] 1842 Apr. 8, Albany, New York [to] James Jones, Nashville, Tennessee / William H. Seward : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Seward, William H.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl619</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Legislative documents] 1842 Apr. 8, Albany, New York [to] James Jones, Nashville, Tennessee / William H. Seward</title>
               <author>Seward, William H.</author>
               <date when="1842-04-08"> 
			 April 8, 1842</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">These are legislative documents sent to James C. Jones, Governor of Tennessee, by New York's Governor William H. Seward. They are resolutions adopted by the New York state legislature dated April 8, 1842. The resolutions concern regulations of the United States Postal Service. See also sl620.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor James Jones Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl619</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor (1841-1845 : Jones)</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>United States Postal Service</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50001408"
                        role="Associated name http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/asn">Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl619a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>STATE OF NEW-YORK</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>IN ASSEMBLY, <date>April 8, 1842</date>
               </add>
            </opener>
            <p>Resolved, As the sense of this Legislature, that the franking privilege tolerated by the post-office law of the <name>United States</name>, is a monopoly unsuited to the spirit of the age, subject to enormous abuses, and an unreasonable burden to the few letter correspondents that bear the principal expense of the establishment, and ought to be abolished.</p>
            <p>Resolved, That for the purpose of diminishing the burdens of correspondents, increasing the revenues of the post-office establishment, and restoring the community, rich and poor, to an equal participation in its benefits, letter postage ought to be greatly reduced, and the disparity between the charge of letters and other matter carried in the mail corrected.</p>
            <p>Resolved, (if the honorable Senate concur herein,) That our representatives and senators in Congress, be respectfully requested to use their best endeavors to procure a reform in the post-office laws based on the above views.</p>
            <p>Resolved, That the Executive of this State be respectfully requested to transmit copies of the foregoing resolutions and report, to the senators and representatives of this State, in Congress, and also to the Executives of our sister States, with a view to their being laid before their respective legislative bodies.</p>
            <closer>
               <add>
                  <lb/> By order, <lb/> J.O. Cole, Clerk. <lb/> 	STATE OF <name>NEW-YORK</name>.<lb/> IN SENATE <lb/>
                  <date>April 9, 1842</date>
                  <lb/> Resolved, That the Senate do concur in the said resolutions. <lb/> By order, <lb/> I.R. ELWOOD, Clerk.</add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl619b.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <note>STATE OF NEW-YORK. <lb/> EXECUTIVE DEPARTMENT, <lb/> Albany, <date>May 6th 1842</date>. Sir: <p>I have the honor to transmit to you a series of Resolutions, passed by the Legislature of this State, concerning the regulations of the Post-Office Department in the government of the <name>United States</name>.  <add>With very high respect, Your obedient servant, <name>WILLIAM H. SEWARD</name>.<lb/> William H. Seward <lb/> His Excellency. <name>James C. Jones</name> Governor of <name>Tennessee</name>
                        </add>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
