<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl077">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1839 Feb 13th, Lexington, [Ky] [to] Richard Alexander, Dixon Spring, Smith County, Tennessee/ James L. Alexander  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Alexander, James L.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl077</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50136919</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1839 Feb 13th, Lexington, [KY] [to] Richard Alexander, Dixon Spring, Smith County, Tennessee/ James L. Alexander</title>
               <author>Alexander, James L.</author>
               <date when="1839-02-13">February 13, 1839</date>
               <extent>4 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated February 13, 1839 from James L. Alexander to his father Richard Alexander in Dixons Spring, TN. James talks about how and when he expects to come home from school in Lexington, KY,  and he  asks his father to send him more money.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Alexander Papers Outgoing</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">VI-G-2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl077</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Kentucky</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Alexander, James L.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl077a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Lexington</name>
                     <date when="1839-02-13">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Feb</abbr>
                           <expan>February</expan>
                        </choice> 13th 1839</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear Father</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letter of the Third of February was received to day.  It gave me great pleasure to learn, that you all were in The enjoyment of a reasonable proportion of health. You Complain a little of my not writing oftener; and more especially of not directing my Correspondence to yourself and Ma— And I really think you have good reasons for dissatisfaction; but I trust you will not cherish for a moment the erroneous idea, or do me the great injustice, to suppose that my silence towards you has originated from a want of that filial affection which every Son should possess for his Father; and particularly one who has been so kind benevolent and indulging as you have towards me.  Nothing would be more mortifying to me than for you to suppose that I am destitute of the warmest affection and regard for you. I therefore hope you will pardon my negligence in not writing and receive This as an humble tribute of my love and affection, and in future ascribe my diffidence to a cause more <pb n="2" facs="sl077b.small.jpg"/> Congenial with my feelings.</p>
            <p>In your letter you desired me to inform you in what way I expected to return home. I had expected to go by water before I received a letter from <name type="person">William</name> about Two weeks since, In which he informed me that <name type="person">Richard</name>expected  to start to <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Phila</abbr>
                     <expan>Philadelphia</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> about the Fifteenth of this month, and that he would, or expected, to ride a horse as far as <name type="place">Lexington</name> or <name type="place">Maysville</name>, and Then leave him; and If I thought proper I Could ride The horse home. I was pleased with The arrangement; and wrote him That I wished him to do so. I wrote to him The 1st day of This month and have no doubt by This time he has received The letter. If he does not start before you receive This and he Concludes to come this way, I wish him to bring my over Shoes and wrappers and to bring a large pair of saddle Bags.  If he does not Conclude to ride a horse This way I prefer going home by water to your sending me a horse.— The report I have to make in regard to The state of my funds is not very <choice>
                  <orig>favourable</orig>
                  <reg>favorable</reg>
               </choice>. I had expected I would have a sufficiency but I find That I shall have to ask of you The remittence of about Thirty Dollars.      It will require about <pb n="3" facs="sl077c.small.jpg"/> Thirty <choice>
                  <abbr>Dolls</abbr>
                  <expan>Dollars</expan>
               </choice> to answer my purpose.</p>
            <p>I expect to leave here between The Tenth and Fifteenth of March.  The Lectures are beginning to drag very heavy indeed I am so much worn out, together with anxiety of mind That I do not expect to be benefitted from This forward. If <name type="person">Richard</name>  does not leave before you receive This I would like to ⁁<add place="supralinear">hear</add> immediately whether he <gap agent="damage"/> ⁁ <add place="supralinear">me</add> This way or not If he should come <gap agent="damage"/> bring me The money with him. If not <gap agent="damage"/> Confer me a <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favour</reg>
               </choice> by remitting <gap agent="damage"/> amount immediately. —</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your affectionate Son</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">James L. Alexander</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="below signature">P.S. Give my love to Ma <name type="person">Aunt Franky </name>and enquiring Friends <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>JLA</abbr>
                     <expan>James L. Alexander</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl077d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Richard Alexander </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Dixons Spring</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Smith County</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left of address">
                  <emph>Mail</emph>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
