<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mc044">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1837 Apr. 20, East Tenn[essee] College, Knoxville [to] Mr. Charles F. Welcker, Talladega, Ala[bama] / Fred[erick] A. Welcker : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Welcker, Frederick A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">mc044</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1837 Apr. 20, East Tenn[essee] College, Knoxville [to] Mr. Charles F. Welcker, Talladega, Ala[bama] / Fred[erick] A. Welcker</title>
               <author>Welcker, Frederick A.</author>
               <date when="1837-04-20">April 20, 1837</date>
               <extent>4 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated April 20, 1837, from Frederick A. Welcker at East Tennessee College (currently the University of Tennessee) to his brother Charles F. Welcker in Talladega, Alabama.  Frederick talks about the school, his examination, and the rival social societies.  He also discusses upcoming congressional elections and the candidates.  Finally, he expresses shock at the news that their sister Catharine had recently gotten married.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Welcker Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-12, b2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1837</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mc044</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Welcker, Frederick A.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mc044a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>East <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn.</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice> College</name>, <name>Knoxville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>April 20th 1837</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Brother Charles,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>after having been so long silent I am at a great loss to know how the commence addressing you.-</p>
            <p>For it would seem that I have no grounds upon which to <add>make</add> a due and plausible apology.- But I have been busily engaged; and am situated in a retired and secluded place, where I seldom see company or news papers; consequently it is not often I am possessed of such information as would prove interesting to a correspondent.- However let us dispense with this apology, for it has already been sufficiently protracted.-</p>
            <p>The examination in this institution took place two weeks since.- It has been customary in this as in all other chartered institutions to have one exhibition at the close of the examination; but on this occasion in its stead the two rival Societies held their anniversaries; and they are said to have thrown in the shade every thing in the line <pb n="2" facs="mc044b.small.jpg"/> of an exhibition that has been seen in the town.- you will see an account of it in the Register I sent Henry;  I had also made arrangements for and to be sent you, but through a mistake it was sent to <name>Jacksonville</name>.-</p>
            <p>
               <name>Monroe</name> and myself are continuing on College- hill this vacation.- He is employed in the practical part of  Surveying; I am principally employed in reading.- </p>
            <p>The period of our state elections is drawing near; and the candidates in this section are urging their <choice>
                  <orig>pretentions</orig>
                  <reg>pretensions</reg>
               </choice> with considerable warmth.- <name>Joseph L. Williams</name> and <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Robt.</abbr>
                     <expan>Robert</expan>
                  </choice> Anderson</name> are running for Congress in this district.- <name>Graves</name> has no opponent as yet for the Senate; nor has <name>
                  <unclear>Crosier</unclear>
               </name> opposition to represent this county in the house- <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Havron</name> of this <choice>
                  <abbr>Co.</abbr>
                  <expan>County</expan>
               </choice> and <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Mjr.</abbr>
                     <expan>Major</expan>
                  </choice> John Smith</name>   of <name>Roane</name> are offering for <unclear>floating</unclear> number.- I believe but two are running in Roane, <name>Stocton</name> and <name>Carter</name>.- On Monday last the <choice>
                  <abbr>Hon.</abbr>
                  <expan>Honorable</expan>
               </choice>
               <name>
                  <unclear>Bolig</unclear> Peyton</name>  delivered a speech to a large congregation composed of both sexes from this town and its vicinity.- He is not an avowed candidate for Governor <pb n="3" facs="mc044c.small.jpg"/> but will be; and will receive the support of <name>Judge White</name>'s friends</p>
            <p>I would say to sister Caroline, that I now begin to attach much belief to her remark, that girls were curious creatures.- I am the more disposed so at present from the fact, that my own sister in whom I reposed so much confidence, having been lately seized with an amorous fit, became engaged in marriage to a gentleman, and  actually consecrated herself his own peculiarly; and the matter was announced in the public prints and she had almost departed with him to a different state before I was apprised of the fact.- I do not mean to complain, for I had some knowledge that such an arrangement had been attempted; but I mention this circumstance merely to show my strong conviction, that girls are in some aspects strange creatures.- Since the subject of matrimony has been introduced I would <add>mention</add> I saw <name>Mr K. Love</name>  about two months since; and he informed me that <name>Mr. J. V. Mitchell</name>  had written him a letter informing <add>him</add> that his father was again married; but lately I have been induced to believe it was only a <choice>
                  <orig>jocke</orig>
                  <reg>joke</reg>
               </choice>.- Mr. Love was in good health <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c.</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> - I wish <add>my</add> respects to be presented to sister Caroline Margaret E. &amp; brother <choice>
                  <abbr>H. I.</abbr>
                  <expan>Henry Inman</expan>
               </choice> and I hope you will accept of the same from</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>your affectionate brother</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Fred.</abbr>
                        <expan>Frederick</expan>
                     </choice> A. Welcker</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To <name>Charles F. Welcker</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Esqr.</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="4" facs="mc044d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>postmark stamp: April 23, Knoxville, TN</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <add>Single</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mr. Charles F. Welcker</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Talladega</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Talladega <choice>
                           <abbr>Co.</abbr>
                           <expan>County</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr/>
                        <expan>Alabama</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>mail</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
