<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc221">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1826 Jan. 2, Mecklenburg, [to] F. S. Heiskell, Knoxville, Tennessee / J. G. M. Ramsey : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Ramsey, J. G. M.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc221</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1826 Jan. 2, Mecklenburg, [to] F. S. Heiskell, Knoxville, Tennessee / J. G. M. Ramsey </title>
               <author>Ramsey, J. G. M.</author>
               <date when="1826-01-02">January 2, 1826</date>
               <extent> 2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter written by J. G. M. Ramsey to F. S. Heiskell regarding the preservation of portions of documents pertaining to the Declaration of Independence.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Ramsey Letters</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-253</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc221</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Declaration of Independence</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>North Carolina</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n88068114"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Ramsey, J. G. M. (James Gettys McGready), 1797-1884</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc221a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Mecklenburg</name> near <name>Knoxville</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>Jany 2, 1826</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir}</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>You will receive herewith a pamphlet containing documents relative to the Declaration of Independence by Mecklenburg, County, <choice>
                  <abbr>N.C</abbr>
                  <expan>North Carolina</expan>
               </choice>. May 20, 1775. In addition to these I have collected other evidence in confirmation of the same transaction_ And <add>have</add> also <add>obtained</add> the signatures of many of the signees to the Declaration_</p>
            <p>An enthusiastic admirer of that lofty spirit of freedom &amp; Independence which glowed in the bosoms &amp; animated the deliberations of that Patriotic Convention I wish to rescue from comparative oblivion so <choice>
                  <orig>briliant</orig>
                  <reg>brilliant</reg>
               </choice> an event in the early history of our Country. One method of affecting this is to arrange the principal resolutions of that convention in a condensed form to which will be affixed the names of the members_ The accompanying manuscript will best illustrate the plan I had conceived_ I would also prefer that the names of those whose signatures I have been able to obtain should appear <del type="overstrike">in their</del> as they usually subscribed them but as you suggested that our artists were unable to execute full similes, that part might be omitted. I have thought that Horaces <unclear>aese perenning</unclear> should be either prefixed or appended to the declaration. If an obelisk or any such figure were on the sheet these words might be placed on its base_ But the execution I leave chiefly to yourself _ But I wish you to spare no pains in making it worthy of the eventful transaction it is intended to perpetuate_</p>
            <p>The vellum and satin I will furnish _ Let me first see a plan of the piece (on which I will give you my opinion) accompanied with any remarks you think proper about the number I should have struck_ the price <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>and et cetera</expan>
               </choice>.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Very Respectfully <lb/> yours &amp;c </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>J. G. M. Ramsey.</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <name>F. S. Heiskell</name>
               </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sc221b.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <name>F. S. Heiskell</name>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Knoxville</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Tennessee</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
