<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl281">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1846 Dec. 9, Clifton [to] A. J. Donelson, Berlin, Prussia / J. G. Martin, Jr.   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Martin, J. G., Jr.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl281</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1846 Dec. 9, Clifton [to] A. J. Donelson, Berlin, Prussia / J. G. Martin, Jr.</title>
               <author>Martin, J. G., Jr.</author>
               <date when="1846-12-09">December 9, 1846</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter, dated December 9, 1846, from J. G. Martin, Jr. to Andrew Jackson Donelson, who was acting as ambassador to Prussia at the time. Included is another letter from Martin to his sister. Martin writes Donelson about his land in Arkansas. Martin updates Donelson on the tax situation and says that no one wants to buy any of Donelson's land, just yet. Mr. Duncan has told Martin emigrants may want some land when they arrive in January. Martin updates Donelson on his farm: cotton, corn, hogs, sheep, and cattle. He expects cotton prices to rise by March. Martin also mentions that a slave, John Fulton wishes he had accompanied Donelson to Berlin. The second letter is to Martin's sister. Martin informs her of how the family is doing and how much they miss her. He also mentions local politics. He predicts that Henry Clay will be the next president.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">A. J. Donelson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> I-D-3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl281</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Real property</term>
               <term>Cotton</term>
               <term>Slaves</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Martin, J. G., Jr.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl281a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Clifton</name>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Dec</abbr>
                           <expan>December</expan>
                        </choice> 9th 1846</date>.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I received a letter from <name>Mr Duncan</name> a few days since, containing The tax receipts on all your <choice>
                  <abbr>Arks</abbr>
                  <expan>Arkansas</expan>
               </choice> lands for this year, amounting to $116, which Mr Duncan  paid in county <unclear>seriffs</unclear> and <name>Arkansas</name> money for $89. I settled this sum by Mr Duncans draft on me in <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice> of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                     <expan>William</expan>
                  </choice> E Woodruff</name>. Cousin Daniel paid me $42.50, which I supposed would be half the Taxes at the time it was received. Mr Duncan writes that there is but little prospect of selling any of your lands in <choice>
                  <abbr>Ark.</abbr>
                  <expan>Arkansas</expan>
               </choice> at this time, but that emigrants are expected in <name>Clark &amp; Union Counties</name> in this month and January. I have written to him, requesting that he would inform me if he should hear of any one that wishes to purchase any of your land, and telling him that any of your lands in Arkansas can be had for $150 <choice>
                  <abbr>pr</abbr>
                  <expan>per</expan>
               </choice> acre cash or $200 one third cash the balance in one and two years with good secured notes: I have made him an offer of your entire interest in Arks lands for $1500 cash; if he will give this, I think we had better accept it, but this I would not do until I should get your consent. for the present I have abandoned the idea of going to Arks this winter, and unless I have more <choice>
                  <orig>favourable</orig>
                  <reg>favorable</reg>
               </choice> accounts of the probability of selling your lands, I will postpone my trip until next winter.</p>
            <p>I saw your overseer <name>Mr Smith</name> on yesterday, who was busy repairing your Cotton press. he has employed <name>Mr Jackson</name> to assist him at $1.00 pr day, and says he can have the job completed for about $10.00: he finished pecking <pb n="2" facs="sl281b.small.jpg"/> Cotton about two weeks since amounting to the use of 100.000 <choice>
                  <abbr>lbs</abbr>
                  <expan>pounds</expan>
               </choice> and has just finished gathering in the corn but does not know the exact amount, he says however that he will have plenty to do him the ensuing year. he has killed sixty four hogs averaging 140 lbs. and has twenty yet to kill, which he says will average 150 lbs. he has a fine quantity of young hogs turned out for next years pork: but says you have entirely <choice>
                  <orig>two</orig>
                  <reg>too</reg>
               </choice> many cattle and sheep: Cotton has fallen from 1 a 1½ ¢ since the market opened having ranged from 6½ to 9½ and commands now from 7½ to 8¼, <del type="overstrike">and</del> they are making very great difference in the quality of cotton in <name>Nashville</name> this season: it is thought that by the 1st March cotton will command from 12 to 14 ¢ the crop being short in <name>Alabama</name>. <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Miss.</abbr>
                     <expan>Mississippi</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>
               <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Lou.</abbr>
                     <expan>Louisiana</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> Arkansas &amp; <name>Texas</name>. Cousin Daniel has just returned from your Miss farm — I have not seen him — but Mr Smith says he informed him that you will make a very fair crop there. Your negroes here are all in good health. <name>John Fulton</name> sends his best respects to Master and says he was a great fool for not going with you. all the Family join me  in much love to you.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Yours truly</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>J. G. Martin <choice>
                        <abbr>Jr</abbr>
                        <expan>Junior</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <opener>
               <salute>My Dear Sister</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I cannot refrain from availing myself of  this opportunity of saying a few words to you exclusively, whose absence from among us we all so much deplore, when shall we again see your beloved self, to cheer us all, and lend a charm to our existence? though I myself feel the loss that you have been to the circle which you formed the nucleus of, yet that loss has been felt ten fold more by our sisters. they <pb n="3" facs="sl281c.small.jpg"/> often speak of you in the most endearing terms, and tears will roll down their cheeks at the thought that they will not see you again perhaps for several years, but we all pray that you will soon again return to your own native land, and the thought that we are not forgotten by you reconciles us in some measure to your absence; write soon! and tell us how little Dany is, whether the excitement of Courtly palaces and the gay and gaudy trappings of Kings, and Princesses afford the pleasure of your own quiet place in the land of the Free and home of the brave.</p>
            <p>I saw <name>Grandma Donelson</name> on yesterday. the old Lady looks quite well and enquired particularly when I had heard from you, and sends her best love to you and the children:- Aunt Phila is not in very good health and has gone to Nashville to spend a few days with her Father. Uncle Stockley looks somewhat blue I suppose at the anticipation of pay day. <name>Grandma Anderson</name> is looking better than she has for some time past:- Uncle Billy as usual, is busy about his Farm. has completed a shingle machine which keeps even on rainy days <add>employed</add>  the old gentleman looks better than I have seen him for a great while or happier I should have said he says <name>Henry Clay</name> will be our next President, as the whigs have carried <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N.</abbr>
                     <expan>New</expan>
                  </choice> York</name>. Might being defeated, The Whigs are testing the popularity of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Campbell</name> one of the Heroes of <name>Monterey</name>,  and it is thought he will be nominated as a candidate for the next Governor of <choice>
                  <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                  <expan>Tennessee</expan>
               </choice> the Whig ticket: we  will have a match for him in <name type="person">Col Anderson</name> his equal in "gunpowder popularity." Aunt Martha is well. Cousin <name>Andrew Jackson</name> and Cousin Sarah have just returned from a trip to the north with which they were very much pleased: all the neighbors are well excepting <name>Mrs Shute</name>   who it is thought has the consumption. I suppose you have heard of <pb n="4" facs="sl281d.small.jpg"/> Uncle <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jno</abbr>
                     <expan>John</expan>
                  </choice> Anderson</name>s marriage to <name>Miss McLain</name>, a very interesting young lady from <name>Wilson County</name>. Cousin <name>Harper Sheppard</name> has sold the Hunter's <unclear>Well</unclear> to  <name>Mr Phil Shute</name> Brother of <name>Jno Shute</name>, for $8,500 cash, and Uncle Jno thinks of  moving to Miss this winter Cousin <name>Martha Harris</name> (<name>Martha McGreggor</name>) died about  two weeks since. — Pa is quite well.  Emily and her better half are still keeping house in Nashville and are very devoted to each  other. Sister Mary Cate &amp; Rachel are all well,  and all at old Clifton remain as you left. and your Brother James spends some <choice>
                  <orig>slepless</orig>
                  <reg>sleepless</reg>
               </choice> nights in <unclear>lingering</unclear> over some means of making the "almighty dollar" and has <add>at last conceived a scheme Tending that way. which he will not reveal until he can mature his plans. it is one however which comes in conflict with his motto. " Peu a Peu " and requires some risk — Jno &amp; Jack are growing rapidly. and all join me in love to their beloved sister. and the children</add>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your affectionate Brother</salute>
               <signed>J G Martin Jr</signed>
               <add>I wrote a letter to you dated the 16th <choice>
                     <abbr>Nov</abbr>
                     <expan>November</expan>
                  </choice> which was my last.</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Maj A  J</abbr>
                           <expan>Major Andrew Jackson</expan>
                        </choice> Donelson</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Maj A J Donelson</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Maj A. J. Donelson</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>U. S. Minister Plenipotentiary <choice>
                           <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                           <expan>et cetera</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Berlin</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Prussia</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
