<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0224">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1824 Oct. 2, [to] Alexander McCoy and Nathaniel Hicks / Charles R. Hicks : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Hicks, Charles R.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0224</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 45870054</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>  [Letter] 1824 Oct. 2, [to] Alexander McCoy and Nathaniel Hicks / Charles R. Hicks</title>
               <author> Hicks, Charles R.</author>
               <date when="1824-10-02">October 2, 1824</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document, dated October 2, 1824, contains instructions given to Alexander McCoy and Nathaniel Hicks by Charles R. Hicks for dealing with Cherokee who claim compensation for improvements they made on their lands.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> pa0224</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Land tenure</term>
               <term>Betterments</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr2001025844"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Hicks, Charles R.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0224a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Hartville</name>
                     <date>October 2nd 1824</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <add>Copy</add> Instructions for <name>Alexander McCoy</name> &amp; <name>Nathaniel Hicks</name> as commissioners for taking the numbers of the <name>Cherokee</name> families who have claimed on the <name>United States</name> for compensation for their improvements which they have left on the ceded lands, coming under the provisions of the Treaty of the <date>27th February 1819</date>, lying in <name>North Carolina</name>
               <name>Tennessee</name>
               <name>Georgia</name> &amp; <name>Alabama</name>, 1st upon which you are to act with care and enquire whether they had removed from the ceded lands before or after the cession  was made to the  United States, as some of the Cherokee families may have moved before the land was cede, who might be <unclear>Impressed</unclear> with a belief they were equally entitled  to compensations for their Improvements, with those families who had removed Since the cession of the lands to the Government __</p>
            <p>
               <add>2nd</add> The best manner in which you can adopt for Collecting the numbers &amp; names of the Heads of Each families that moved from the ceded lands, will be to go the head man who moved with them, &amp; to notify him the objects of your visit <pb n="2" facs="pa0224b.small.jpg"/> and let as many <choice>
                  <orig>claiments</orig>
                  <reg>claimants</reg>
               </choice> gather there as are convenient, and proceed to make enquiries of their names and the Town of <choice>
                  <orig>vilage</orig>
                  <reg>village</reg>
               </choice> they belonged to, the numbers of <choice>
                  <orig>Cabbins</orig>
                  <reg>Cabins</reg>
               </choice> they had left, the number by paces of length <add>and width</add> of their fields, the number of fruit trees, if any on their improvements when they left and to enter Each of the above items in Separate Columns, by numerical numbers before their names, &amp; what losses they Sustained from the Whites in their Stocks &amp; corn &amp; make such remarks opposite to Each name as may have sustained the loss &amp; to Enquire from others Such losses as they may represent ___,</p>
            <p>
               <add>3rd</add> You will be particular to Enquire of Each Head of families, whether they had taken certificates of Restoration for Land, And if taken the Reason they had in leaving their reservations, as several of which were returned to me, &amp; forwarded them to <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Meigs</name> which had been taken for them by their relatives not being present themselves, &amp; you will observe also to enter all the Heads of families who have been drove off <name>Frog Town</name> by the Whites but not as <pb n="3" facs="pa0224c.small.jpg"/> Claiments for their Improvements, but only with the object of ascertaining the losses they may have Sustained by this removal, as the Cherokee Nation Still claims her rights to the lands on that Side of the <name>Blue Ridge</name> had the boundary line been run according to the meaning &amp; Spirit of the Treaty of the 27th February 1819.</p>
            <p>
               <add>4th</add>You will first begin at Ellejoy Town to take the names of the Heads of families who reside perhaps above this old Town who have removed from the <choice>
                  <orig>ceeded</orig>
                  <reg>ceded</reg>
               </choice> land, from North Carolina, from thence on by <name>Cabbin Village</name> to <name>Potatoe Mine Creek</name>and about <unclear>
                  <name>Skeenee</name>
               </unclear> or <name>Devil Town</name> from thence to <name>
                  <unclear>Cu,rro,kee</unclear> Dicks</name> &amp; your Services will Commence on the day you Start at Two Dollars <choice>
                  <abbr>pr</abbr>
                  <expan>per</expan>
               </choice> day and your expenses allowed and advance you fifteen Dollars for This object &amp; should it fall Short, you will Keep an account of the Sum expended over the <del type="overstrike">allowance</del> Allowance<choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>etcetera</expan>
               </choice> &amp;c____</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Chas</abbr>
                        <expan>Charles</expan>
                     </choice> , R, Hicks</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="pa0224d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Copy of a letter of <lb/>  Instructions given to <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Messrs</abbr>
                     <expan>Misters</expan>
                  </choice> A. McCoy &amp; <lb/> Nathan Hicks for <lb/> taking the number of the <lb/> claiments for Improvements <lb/>
                  <unclear>lef</unclear> on the ceeded lands <lb/> under the provision of the <lb/> Treaty of the 27th of <choice>
                     <abbr>Febry</abbr>
                     <expan>February</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/> 1819______</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
