<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      version="3.5"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-5.xsd">
   <identifier type="local">mm061</identifier>
   <identifier type="oclc">48016357</identifier>
   <titleInfo>
      <title>[Photograph of a reduced scale reconstruction of a Cherokee council house at Red Clay State Park, Bradley County, Tennessee, taken circa 1980s] / [by Gerald F. Schroedl]: a machine-readable transcription</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <abstract>This photograph is of a reduced scale reconstruction of the Cherokee council house at the Red Clay site at Red Clay State Park in Bradley County, Tennessee. This reconstruction is of a summer council house, not the original house. The original council house would have been much larger in order to accommodate the nearly 5000 people who would have gathered there. By 1832, the state of Georgia had refused the Cherokee the right to hold council meetings unless the meeting dealt with treaties that gave away their lands. The Cherokee decided to move their capital from New Echota, Georgia across the state line to Red Clay, Tennessee because the state of Tennessee did not prohibit the Cherokees from meeting together. Thus, Red Clay became the seat of the Cherokee government in 1832 and lasted until the removal of the Cherokees to the west in 1838. Red Clay was composed of 11 general councils and the meetings were attended by up to 5000 people. It was at Red Clay that the Cherokee learned that they had lost all of their land and would be removed to the west. Red Clay consists of the sacred Blue Hole Spring, a reconstructed council house, and several reconstructed homestead buildings. Red Clay is also the home to the Eternal Flame, lit on April 6, 1984. The Cherokees took hot coals from their council fire at Red Clay on the Trail of Tears. The flame was later taken to Cherokee, North Carolina in the 1950s but was returned to Red Clay in 1984. This was the first symbolic step unifying the Eastern Cherokees with the Cherokee Nation in Oklahoma since their removal in 1838. Today Red Clay State Historical Park is not only a historical site, but is also an interpretive site on the Trail of Tears.</abstract>
   <originInfo>
      <dateCreated>1980s</dateCreated>
      <dateCreated encoding="edtf">1980</dateCreated>
   </originInfo>
   <subject>
      <topic>Photographs</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject>
      <topic>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject>
      <topic>Red Clay Site (Tenn.)</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject>
      <topic>Public buildings</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject>
      <topic>Historic sites</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject>
      <topic>Bradley County (Tenn)</topic>
   </subject>
   <name valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n78090514">
      <namePart>Schroedl, Gerald F.</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator"
                   valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/pht">Photographer</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <accessCondition type="use and reproduction"
                    xlink:href="http://rightsstatement.org/vocab/CNE/1.0/">Copyright Not Evaluated</accessCondition>
   <location>
      <physicalLocation>Frank H. McClung Museum</physicalLocation>
   </location>
   <relatedItem displayLabel="Project" type="host">
      <titleInfo>
         <title>Tennessee Documentary History</title>
      </titleInfo>
   </relatedItem>
   <relatedItem displayLabel="Collection" type="host">
      <titleInfo>
         <title>Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic Collection</title>
      </titleInfo>
   </relatedItem>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text" authority="iso639-2b">English</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordContentSource>Frank H. McClung Museum</recordContentSource>
      <languageOfCataloging>
         <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
      </languageOfCataloging>
      <recordCreationDate>2020-04-23-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <recordOrigin>This MODS record was generated into MODS v3.5 from the TEI teiHeader by
          University of Tennessee Libraries Digital Initiatives, using a stylesheet available at
          https://github.com/utkdigitalinitiatives/tei-to-mods.</recordOrigin>
   </recordInfo>
</mods>
