<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      version="3.5"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-5.xsd">
   <identifier type="local">mm079</identifier>
   <identifier type="oclc">48040355</identifier>
   <titleInfo>
      <title>[Photograph of the post hole pattern of an excavated townhouse at Chattooga, taken in 1993] / [by Gerald F Schroedl] : a machine-readable transcription</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <abstract>This is a photograph of the post hole pattern of an excavated townhouse at Chattooga. Townhouses were usually found in villages with a population of more than 350 people and was the most prominent building in the villages. Townhouses were where most of the social, ceremonial, and political activities took place in the village. Chattooga is a Cherokee archaeological site that was formerly called 'Cherokee Town.' Cherokee Town was an 18th century village associated with the Lower town Cherokee communities of northern Georgia and western South Carolina. The site is thought to have been occupied for only 160 years and was abandoned by the Cherokees in the 1740s. This site is given special attention because it retained early 18th century Cherokee material culture. This material culture is difficult to find and distinguish on other Cherokee sites of the same time period. The University of Tennessee (UT) and the Francis Marion National Forest conducted archaeological excavations at Chattooga during 1989-1994. The focus of these excavations was to develop a better understanding of the nature of the historical Cherokee occupation at the site and compare these findings with those found on other 18th century Cherokee sites. As a result of these excavations, archaeologists were able to identify and partially excavate the remains of five superimposed council houses. In addition, the excavations of two winter structures and one summer domestic structure were conducted. Through the use of surface collection, test pit excavations, and remote sensing equipment, vast amounts of artifacts and the location of additional buildings and features were found with minimal disturbance to the site. The excavation of Chattooga is still an active research project with additional findings in the process of being documented.</abstract>
   <originInfo>
      <dateCreated>1993</dateCreated>
      <dateCreated encoding="edtf">1993</dateCreated>
   </originInfo>
   <subject>
      <topic>Photographs</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject>
      <topic>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject>
      <topic>Excavations (Archaeology)</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject>
      <topic>Public buildings</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject>
      <topic>Historic sites</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject>
      <topic>Georgia</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject>
      <topic>South Carolina</topic>
   </subject>
   <name valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n78090514">
      <namePart>Schroedl, Gerald F.</namePart>
      <role>
         <roleTerm authority="marcrelator"
                   valueURI="http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/pht">Photographer</roleTerm>
      </role>
   </name>
   <accessCondition type="use and reproduction"
                    xlink:href="http://rightsstatement.org/vocab/CNE/1.0/">Copyright Not Evaluated</accessCondition>
   <location>
      <physicalLocation>Frank H. McClung Museum</physicalLocation>
   </location>
   <relatedItem displayLabel="Project" type="host">
      <titleInfo>
         <title>Tennessee Documentary History</title>
      </titleInfo>
   </relatedItem>
   <relatedItem displayLabel="Collection" type="host">
      <titleInfo>
         <title>Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic Collection</title>
      </titleInfo>
   </relatedItem>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text" authority="iso639-2b">English</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordContentSource>Frank H. McClung Museum</recordContentSource>
      <languageOfCataloging>
         <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
      </languageOfCataloging>
      <recordCreationDate>2020-04-23-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <recordOrigin>This MODS record was generated into MODS v3.5 from the TEI teiHeader by
          University of Tennessee Libraries Digital Initiatives, using a stylesheet available at
          https://github.com/utkdigitalinitiatives/tei-to-mods.</recordOrigin>
   </recordInfo>
</mods>
