<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      version="3.5"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-5.xsd">
   <identifier type="local">tl025</identifier>
   <identifier type="oclc">47826174</identifier>
   <titleInfo>
      <title>[Letter to] the Chiefs of the Creek Nation / the inhabitants residing on the Shawnee River</title>
   </titleInfo>
   <abstract>The following document is an undated letter addressed to the chiefs of the Creek Nation, which appears to have been written on behalf of the white settlers living along the Shawnee River. In this letter, the settlers appear to have been making an offer of peace with the Creeks. The letter states that the Chickasaws, who were in good relations with the whites, had informed the settlers that the majority of the Creek people wished to be at peace with them. However, the letter refers to several instances that were looked at as being acts of aggression by the Creeks, including the theft of some horses and the loss of white lives. The letter also mentions an instance in which the settlers stumbled upon a deserted Indian camp and retained the horses and other articles from that camp, securing them until it was known to what tribe they belonged. The settlers contend they moved to the West with the intention of being at peace with all the tribes there, nor, they state, do they wish to encroach upon Indian lands or molest Indian peoples.</abstract>
   <originInfo>
      <dateCreated>ca. 1800</dateCreated>
      <dateCreated encoding="edtf">1800</dateCreated>
   </originInfo>
   <subject>
      <topic>Letters</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject>
      <topic>Creek Indians--Government relations</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject>
      <topic>Chickasaw Indians--Government relations</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject>
      <topic>Creek Indians--Claims against</topic>
   </subject>
   <subject>
      <topic>Southern States</topic>
   </subject>
   <accessCondition type="use and reproduction"
                    xlink:href="http://rightsstatement.org/vocab/CNE/1.0/">Copyright Not Evaluated</accessCondition>
   <location>
      <physicalLocation>Tennessee State Library and Archives</physicalLocation>
   </location>
   <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
   <language>
      <languageTerm type="text" authority="iso639-2b">English</languageTerm>
   </language>
   <recordInfo>
      <recordContentSource>Tennessee State Library and Archives</recordContentSource>
      <languageOfCataloging>
         <languageTerm type="code" authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm>
      </languageOfCataloging>
      <recordCreationDate>2020-04-23-04:00</recordCreationDate>
      <recordOrigin>This MODS record was generated into MODS v3.5 from the TEI teiHeader by
          University of Tennessee Libraries Digital Initiatives, using a stylesheet available at
          https://github.com/utkdigitalinitiatives/tei-to-mods.</recordOrigin>
   </recordInfo>
</mods>
