<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc118">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Deposition of  Andrew Morrison]  1822 Sep. 28, Nashville, Tennessee, [to] the Clerk of Brackenridge Circuit Court, Hardinsburgh, Kentucky : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc118</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Deposition of  Andrew Morrison]  1822 Sep. 28, Nashville, Tennessee, [to] the Clerk of Brackenridge Circuit Court, Hardinsburgh, Kentucky  </title>
               <date when="1822-09-28"> 
			 September 28, 1822</date>
               <extent> 4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a deposition given in Nashville, Tennessee for a trial that was held in Hardinsburgh, Kentucky. Andrew Morrison gave the deposition on behalf of the defendants. His deposition was dated September 28, 1822, and the subject was the condition of the Ohio River, the month of October 1817.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Andrew Morrison Document</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">MS1951</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc118</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Legal documents</term>
               <term>Depositions</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc118a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>Agreeable to a Dedimus to us Directed from the <name>Brackenridge</name> Circuit Court in the State of <name>Kentucky</name> we have caused <name>Andrew Morrison</name> a witness for the Defendants in a suit depending in said court wherein <name>Peter Kemmell</name> is plaintiff and <name>Chenault &amp; Co</name>. are defendants to come before us at the <name>Nashville</name> Inn in the State of <name>Tennessee</name> on the 28th day of September 1822 said witness being sworn on the Holy <choice>
                  <orig>Evengelist</orig>
                  <reg>Evangelist</reg>
               </choice> of <choice>
                  <orig>Almity</orig>
                  <reg>Almighty</reg>
               </choice>
               <choice>
                  <orig>god</orig>
                  <reg>God</reg>
               </choice> Deposes and says as follows_</head>
            <p>Question 1st     Are you acquainted with boating on the <name>Ohio River</name>
            </p>
            <p>Answer I have followed boating on the Ohio for several years</p>
            <p>Question  Were you at <choice>
                  <orig>Pittsburg</orig>
                  <reg>Pittsburgh</reg>
               </choice> on the seventeenth of October 1817 and do you recollect the State of Ohio river on that day and for a few days before and after</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="sc118b.small.jpg"/>
            <p> Answer I remember well the Ohio river was in good order on the tenth or eleventh of October 1817 and kept in good <del type="overstrike">o</del> order<choice>
                  <orig> untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> the 28 or 29th of October when I left <name>Pittsburgh</name> with my family and landed at <name>Maysville<choice>
                     <abbr> Ky</abbr>
                     <expan>Kentucky</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>. on the fourth <del type="overstrike">of</del>
               <add>or</add> fifth of November 1817 and the river was so high that it was both difficult and dangerous to land</p>
            <p>Question How long does it generally take a boat to come from Pittsburgh to Jennings creek ten <choice>
                  <orig>mils</orig>
                  <reg>miles</reg>
               </choice> below flint <choice>
                  <orig>Isleand</orig>
                  <reg>Island</reg>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <p>Answer I think fourteen days would be a sufficient time with a good stage of water as was at that time allowing to <choice>
                  <orig>loose</orig>
                  <reg>lose</reg>
               </choice> time for head winds, I have had boats make the trip from <choice>
                  <abbr>Pitts</abbr>
                  <expan>Pittsburgh</expan>
               </choice> to Nashville in twenty five and twenty six days</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="sc118c.small.jpg"/>
            <p>Question  have you followed boating on the Ohio river and cumberland for several years and have you made a <choice>
                  <orig>livelyhood</orig>
                  <reg>livelihood</reg>
               </choice> at it and have you owned many boats</p>
            <p>Answer. I have made nearly all my living at boating since 1804 and was <choice>
                  <orig>verry</orig>
                  <reg>very</reg>
               </choice> largely concerned in <choice>
                  <orig>frighting</orig>
                  <reg>freighting</reg>
               </choice> goods from Pittsburg to Nashville from 1810 to 1817 and has had as many as seventeen boats arrive here from <choice>
                  <orig>Pittburg</orig>
                  <reg>Pittsburgh</reg>
               </choice> in six or seven months and farther this deponent sayeth <unclear>not</unclear>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>A. Morson</orig>
                     <reg>Andrew Morrison</reg>
                  </choice>
               </signed>
               <add>State of Tennessee <lb/> Davidson County {</add>
               <add>
                  <note>
                     <p>the foregoing deposition was taken before us two acting Justices of the peace for Davidson County at the day &amp; place named in the caption neither of us are interested in said cause nor council for either party the deposition is in the hand writing of the witness and sealed up by us and deposited in the post office near having been out of our possession given under our hands this 28th day September 1822</p>
                  </note>
               </add>
               <signed>
                  <name>Will Lytle</name>
                  <name>D.A.Dunham </name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sc118d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To the Clerk of Brackenridge Circuit Court <name>Hardinsburgh</name> Kentucky</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Andrew Morrison's deposition for the Defendant</add>
               <add>D.A. Dunham</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
