<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc172">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Bond] 1787 Sep. 12, North Carolina [owed to] Richard Caswell / Titus Ogden, William Blount, John Witgreaves : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc172</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Bond] 1787 Sep. 12, North Carolina [owed to] Richard Caswell / Titus Ogden, William Blount, John Witgreaves</title>
               <date when="1787-09-12"> 
			 September 12, 1787</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a bond dated September 12, 1787. It states that William Blount, Titus Ogden, and John Witgreaves owe Richard Caswell five thousand pounds. Caswell is governor of North Carolina.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">William Blount Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS 364</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc172</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>North Carolina</term>
               <term>Bond</term>
               <term>Blount, William, 1749-1800 </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc172a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>State of <name>North-Carolina</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>Know all men by these presents, That <name>Titus Ogden</name>
               <name>William __ Blount</name> &amp; <name>John Witgreaves</name> are held and firmly bound unto <del type="overstrike">the</del>
               <add>
                  <name>Richard Caswell</name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                     <expan>Esquire</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add> Governor and commander in Chief of the said State, in the sum of five thousand ____ pounds, current money, to be paid to the said  Richard Caswell Esqr or his successors, Governors or Commanders in Chief for the time being. To which payment well and truly to be made, we bind ourselves, our heirs, executors and administrators, jointly and severally, firmly by these presents. Sealed with our seals, and dated this <date>twelfth day of September Anno <choice>
                     <abbr>Dom.</abbr>
                     <expan>Domini</expan>
                  </choice> 1787</date>___</p>
            <p>The condition of the above obligation is such, That if the above bound Titus Ogden administrator of all and singular the goods and chattels, rights and credits, of Thomas Ogden deceased, do make or cause to be made, a true and perfect inventory of all and singular the  goods and chattels, rights and credits of the deceased, which have, or shall come to the hands, knowledge or possession of the said Titus Ogden or into the hands or possession of any person or persons, for him  and the same so made, do exhibit, or cause to be exhibited into the secretary's office, and one attested copy thereof to the county court, where orders for administration passed within  ninety days after the date of these presents; and the same goods, chattels and credits, and all other the goods, chattels and credits, of the deceased at the time of his death, which at any time hereafter shall come into hands or possession of the said Titus Ogden or into the hands or possession of any other person or persons for him do well and truly administer according to law, and further do make, or cause to be made, a true and just account of his said administration, within one year after the date of these presents; and all the rest and residue of the said goods, chattels and credits, which shall be found remaining upon the said administrator account (the same being first examined and allowed by the Governor and Council, superior or county court) shall deliver and pay unto such person or persons respectively as the same shall be due, pursuant to the true intent and meaning of the act in that case made and provided. And if it shall appear that any will or testament was made by the said deceased, and the executor or executors therein named do exhibit the same into court, making request to have it allowed and approved of accordingly, if the said above bounden, being thereunto required, do render and deliver the said letters on administration (approbation of such testament being first had and made in the said court) then this obligation to be void, otherwise to remain in full force and virtue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Titus Ogden <add>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>seal</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </add>
               </signed>
               <signed>Wm Blount <add>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>seal</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </add>
               </signed>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jn</abbr>
                     <expan>John </expan>
                  </choice> Witgreaves<add>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>seal</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </add>
               </signed>
               <add>Signed, Sealed and Delivered <lb/> in Presence of <lb/>
                  <name>
                     <unclear>SM</unclear> Arnett</name>
               </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sc172b.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Titus Ogden <lb/>
                  <unclear>Am</unclear>
                  <lb/> Bond</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
