<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl263">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1850 June 24, Nashville [TN] [to] George [House] / Mary [House]    : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Mary [House]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl263</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51217999</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1850 June 24, Nashville [TN] [to] George [House] / Mary [House]</title>
               <author> Mary [House]</author>
               <date when="1850-06-24">June 24, 1850</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Mary House to her husband George House, dated June 24, 1850. She tells him of a disturbing dream she had recently, where many of her loved one's were sick, dead or missing. She writes of the family and friends that she has been visiting and corresponding with. She mentions that cholera has come to Nashville.  Their daughter Sallie adds a few lines about her kittens.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl263</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">House, Mary</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl263a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                     <date when="1850-06-24">June 24th 1850</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My own My Dearest George</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>It is a week to day since I received your precious letter from <name type="place">Florence</name>; you have written to <name type="person">Mr McClelland</name>once <gap agent="damage"/> , by which means I heard you ever well; which was truly <choice>
                  <orig>grattifying</orig>
                  <reg>gratifying</reg>
               </choice> to your own devoted Mary, <choice>
                  <orig>altho</orig>
                  <reg>although</reg>
               </choice> the letter was not to herself —</p>
            <p>I dream of you every night, and two nights ago, I had a long, long, and disagreeable one about your being sick, I thought you had been sick for three long weeks, and you would not let me know one word of it that I might have flown to your bed side and nursed you tenderly, and faithfully (as a ⁁<add place="supralinear">loving</add> wife only can) through it M — I can assure you, I was in deep trouble I also dreamed that Tom was dead, and Toby was missing, <choice>
                  <orig>eather</orig>
                  <reg>either</reg>
               </choice> dead, or run off, I couldn't decide which — But I will say no more of this horrible dream; and hope it may go as "<name type="person">Rory Omore</name>" say, by <unclear>contraries</unclear> my dear"</p>
            <p>We are all well yet, and God grant this <choice>
                  <orig>blissing</orig>
                  <reg>blessing</reg>
               </choice> may continue until you return at least, <name type="person">Mrs Fowler</name> and her family <pb n="2" facs="sl263b.small.jpg"/> went out to <name type="person">Mr Greenfrel</name>s yesterday, but I suppose they will be in, in a few days Mortey Em and the whole "Ships Crew" spent the day with us, together with Jo, cousin Will, and <name type="person">Mr Burksdale</name>, notwithstanding, all this, J was lonely indeed Lou was to have been examined to day (monday) but Mr Burksdale concluded he had better hurry through with his business and go home to day, which rejoiced Lou very much as it released her from the examination. She with her father, <name type="person">Miss Loucey Bailey</name>, and several others, from <name type="place">Clarksville</name>, left for home this morning, at 11 oclock You will doubtless see from the papers, before you  receive this letter, that our city has again been visited with Cholera. It is true there is some Cholera here but as last year, it is confined principally to that portion of  the city south of Broadstreet — I received a long letter from aunt Hamilton on saturday. It was directed to both of us, she requests me, if you, are absent to answer it, which I will do in a few days, She say she confidently expects a visit from you and I by the first of August at farthest, Since you left I have <pb n="3" facs="sl263c.small.jpg"/> written a long letter to <name type="person">Ann Irwin</name>, but have not heard one word either from herself on Mary, on saturday <name type="person">Mr Bostick</name> received two long letter from Litton, the latest was dated <name type="place">Panama</name> 28th of May, "he say he is getting along finely, that the weather is a little too warm to fatten, but his <choice>
                  <orig>streangth</orig>
                  <reg>strength</reg>
               </choice> has increased" Mr <choice>
                  <abbr>B</abbr>
                  <expan>Bostick</expan>
               </choice> is so delighted, I would not be astonished if he wrote you a letter on the subject. Bilbo <unclear>arived</unclear> here yesterday, and Mr McClelland say the report about town is, that Bilbo say, he has more money than he knows what to do with; and he wants to see <name>House</name>, and <name> 
                  <reg>person</reg> Pitts</name> to get rid of it, I give you the report just as I heard it; <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr Mc</abbr>
                  <expan>Mr McClelland</expan>
               </choice> has not seen him yet, You have not said any thing about Crops' since you left, <choice>
                  <orig>wheather</orig>
                  <reg>whether</reg>
               </choice> or not the <choice>
                  <orig>droughth</orig>
                  <reg>drought</reg>
               </choice> has extended south of this, You were so near your Mother at  <name type="place">
                  <unclear>Freanna</unclear>
               </name> that I think it strange you did not visit her, but you certainly, will on your return I have heard of the death of <name type="person">Lucy Haughton</name>'s sister <name type="person">Mrs Binford</name>, not heard a word from Tommey, or Loucy, since you went away — Sallie say I must not close my letter without <pb n="4" facs="sl263d.small.jpg"/> saying something for her she says —</p>
            <p>Tell poppy, we are all well, I want to see him very much; I love him dearly I want him to make haste and come home Alice has one kitten alive and I gave her <del type="overstrike">to</del> and the kitten to cousin Ida the little gray kitten caught a mouse <del type="overstrike">an</del>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>and etcetera</expan>
               </choice>
               <lb/> your little daughter <lb/> Sallie</p>
            <p> I have written the above just as Sallie worded it <name type="person">Julia Davis</name> received a letter the other day from her brother, he was in <name type="place">Boston</name> when he wrote; she is looking for him <choice>
                  <orig>evry</orig>
                  <reg>every</reg>
               </choice> hour — Oh! how I long for your return — some times I fear I will never see you again, but I will endeavor to hope for the best; what could we do in this life without hope — But I must close that my letter may be ready for this evenings mail Lou charged me particularly, to send her very best love to you, Ma and Sallie send theirs, You don't know how much my Mother loves you <del type="overstrike">she say</del> I heard her tell some one since you have <choice>
                  <orig>bee</orig>
                  <reg>been</reg>
               </choice> gone , that she thought you <choice>
                  <orig>wer</orig>
                  <reg>were</reg>
               </choice> the greatest man in <name type="place">America</name> —</p>
            <closer>
               <add place="top margin, page 1, rotated">May you be happy, and may you enjoy good health, and be prosperous in your <gap agent="damage"/>
                  <unclear/> under <gap agent="damage"/> king, and return <choice>
                     <orig>spedily</orig>
                     <reg>speedily</reg>
                  </choice> to the bosom of your own Mary This is my constant prayer</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
