<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl392">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1834 Jan. 31, Port Tobacco,  Charles County, Maryland [to] William Fitzgerald, Weakley County, Dresden, West Tennessee / Sarah Fitzgerald   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Fitzgerald, Sarah</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl392</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1834 Jan. 31, Port Tobacco,  Charles County, Maryland [to] William Fitzgerald, Weakley County, Dresden, West Tennessee / Sarah Fitzgerald</title>
               <author>Fitzgerald, Sarah</author>
               <date when="1834-01-31">January 31, 1834</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated January 31, 1834 from Sarah Fitzgerald in Port Tobacco, Maryland  to her son William Fitzgerald in Dresden, Tennessee.  Sarah openly expresses grief with a blend of good humor concerning the long absence since having seen or had communication with her son.  She asks him to write her soon.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fitzgerald - Williams - Greer Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl392</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Fitzgerald, Sarah</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl392a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Port Tobacco</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jan.</abbr>
                     <expan>January</expan>
                  </choice> 31st - 1834</date>
               <salute>My Long absented, But well Beloved Son, William,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <name>Mrs. Sarah Fitzgerald</name>, Wishes to introduce herself to Her long absented, But not forgotten Son William- Understanding of late that he resides in <name>Dresden, <choice>
                     <abbr>W.</abbr>
                     <expan>West</expan>
                  </choice> Tennessee</name>, - She avails herself of the present opportunity, to ask him if he has forgotten his aged &amp; infirm Mother, - If he has forgotten Her who watched over his helpless infancy, with all the anxiety of a <choice>
                  <orig>doating</orig>
                  <reg>doting</reg>
               </choice> parent, - If he has forgotten Her, who Swam in Years of Parental regret, when he quit this, the County of his Childhood, &amp; his Birth. </p>
            <p>Oh! my Dearest Son, Receive this as a Sure pledge of my augmented  affection, - Receive it as the affectionate language of your Mother, who long since Supposed her Dear Son, to be amongst the number of those who are not permitted to revisit the earth. - But thanks to <add>Him</add>
               <del type="overstrike">him</del> who watches with a Father's eye the children of men ____</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="sl392b.small.jpg"/>
            <p>I have <choice>
                  <abbr>recd.</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> the consoling information from Doubtless authority viz. <choice>
                  <abbr>Hon</abbr>
                  <expan>Honorable</expan>
               </choice>. <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>D.</abbr>
                     <expan>Davy</expan>
                  </choice> Crockett</name> - that you and also your Brother John are well, that John is in <name>Pensacola, <choice>
                     <orig>Louisianna</orig>
                     <reg>Lousiana</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name>, &amp; that you have been twice elected as congressman from west, Tennessee    - From <gap agent="damage"/> intelligence I venture to dictate to you <gap agent="damage"/> this letter, Trusting that you may receive it safe although it Contains nothing more than the sincere prayers of a Mother, Grand - mother, two Sisters, &amp; a Brother, for your everlasting prosperity - O could I once more Behold the face of my Dear Son William - little did you think when you were in <name>Washington, DC.</name> that your Mother was But 32 miles distance living near Port <choice>
                  <abbr>Tob.</abbr>
                  <expan>Tobacco</expan>
               </choice> Charles County <choice>
                  <abbr>MD.</abbr>
                  <expan>Maryland</expan>
               </choice> Be pleased as Soon as you receive this to write me a letter in reply, - The mail is now waiting &amp; I am in haste, Sorrowfully do I say Farewell, Farewell.</p>
            <closer>Your affectionate Mother <signed>Sarah Fitzgerald</signed>
               <add>P.S. Direct your letter To Mrs. Sarah Fitzgerald <name>Port Tobacco</name>
                  <name>Charles County</name>
                  <name>Maryland</name>
               </add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl392c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Port <choice>
                        <abbr>Tob</abbr>
                        <expan>Tobacco</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>md</abbr>
                        <expan>Maryland</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Feby</abbr>
                        <expan>February</expan>
                     </choice>1</addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Hon. <name>William Fitzgerald</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Dresden, Weakley County</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>West Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>25</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
