<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um056">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1849 Feb. 23, College Hill, Hanover, [Indiana] [to] Miss Mary C. Porter / Ben [Sawtelle] : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Sawtelle, Ben</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um056</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50296113</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1849 Feb. 23, College Hill, Hanover, [Indiana] [to] Miss Mary C. Porter / Ben [Sawtelle]</title>
               <author>Sawtelle, Ben</author>
               <date when="1849-02-23">February 23, 1849</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by Ben Sawtelle to his niece, Mary C. Porter, on February 23, 1849. Ben attends South Hanover College in Indiana and tells Mary of the school and social events happening there. Ben also discusses events happening to acquaintances of theirs, as well as mentioning his support for the sewing and abolitionist societies with which Mary is involved.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Porter-Rice Family Letters MS 154 (Letters 1846-1849)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um056</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Indiana</term>
               <term>Wit and social status</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Sawtell, Benjamin N.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um056a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <emph>
                        <name type="place">College Hill</name>, <name type="place">Hanover</name>
                        <date when="1849-02-23">
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Feb</abbr>
                              <expan>February</expan>
                           </choice> 23d 1849</date>
                     </emph>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>
                  <emph>My own dear <name type="person">Katie</name>
                  </emph>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>With <emph>much</emph> joy, your, long, kind, and interesting epistle was received a few days ago. I had almost given up in despair, thinking that you were so much engaged with your old Friends, and enjoying yourself so well, that you never gave a passing thought to "Ben", but how agreeably was he surprised, when that welcome word yes! greeted his ears and a letter was handed out, with the welcome, and well known direction.</p>
            <p>As you state in your letter where you were when you wrote, I will tell you where I am, conversing, as you say, by means of pen, ink and paper with a loved one, far distant. I am sitting, at my little desk, in <emph>"Sky  Parlor"</emph> not alone, as the other boys are making plenty of noise, but I manage to write some way. It is Friday night, we have been down to the river to see some of the students off, tell <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Ed</abbr>
                     <expan>Edward</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>
               <name type="person">Pat Walker</name> is off for good. We all being somewhat fatigued, concluded not to go to society. It is quite muddy, and it has been debated with some spirit, whether there was any "<emph>Terra</emph> Firma" in, or about Hanover, except on a large rock. You ask me if it is not to good to think of, to converse face to face. I answer it is, for me. Yet my imagination will often take wings and fly to the land of the "Sunny South", and there rest amid the memories of many happy scenes past, and gone. And in my dreams, do I revisit <emph>"home"</emph> and see my friends, and am happy. But the visions of night are false, and I awake to find my self in Hanover. I have two <emph>homes</emph>, one where my Father is, the other where my Mother is.</p>
            <p>I feel very thankful to you all for being so kind as to let me come home, the session is out just 5 weeks from yesterday. I have a Valedictory to deliver before our Society, and I just commenced it. I am very hard pressed for time, I have little, very little time I can call my own. You speak of your <pb n="2" facs="um056b.small.jpg"/> Sewing Society. I consider myself a member of that <choice>
                  <orig>honerable</orig>
                  <reg>honorable</reg>
               </choice> body, if it is the old society, as I gave them, 25, half the <choice>
                  <orig>initian</orig>
                  <reg>initiation</reg>
               </choice> fee. I will pay the rest, when I have the pleasure of walking in after supper, and spending a few happy moments with the, handsome, lovely, and fair daughters of <name type="place">Memphis</name>. But I am afraid I shall feel lost in <choice>
                  <orig>thier</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice> company, as I have been in <choice>
                  <orig>thier</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice> company, that is of young Ladies, So few times <choice>
                  <orig>scince</orig>
                  <reg>since</reg>
               </choice> I left Memphis. And if I am somewhat <choice>
                  <orig>awkard</orig>
                  <reg>awkward</reg>
               </choice>, you all will know the reason.</p>
            <p>I have not been over to see <name type="person">Miss Anna</name>, to tell her I had <choice>
                  <orig>recieved</orig>
                  <reg>received</reg>
               </choice> a letter from you, but I must go tomorrow. <name type="person">Mr Nelson</name> is quite sick. The Young Ladies of this place say I am in love with a <name type="person">Miss Katie Woodard</name>, because I said she was the handsomest girl in town. On account of that I cannot succeed with any of them. They do not make much as I care for none of them, and there is no love lost, on either side.</p>
            <p>A few days ago, we all went up to <name type="place">Madison</name> to see Old Tuck and I saw the old Hero. I will give you the particulars when I get home. I <choice>
                  <orig>recieved</orig>
                  <reg>received</reg>
               </choice> a letter from <name type="person">Cy Clapp</name> a few days ago. He spent his Christmas vacation at B —  They were all well. He is in fine spirits, and wants to get married, which is more than I want to do. You ask me why I did not send that ring to you by <choice>
                  <abbr>Ed</abbr>
                  <expan>Edward</expan>
               </choice> or <name type="person">Bunyan</name>. I will tell you truth. I hated to part with it. I was on the point of giving it up, several times, but I could not let it go. It has not been off my finger <choice>
                  <orig>scince</orig>
                  <reg>since</reg>
               </choice> I left <choice>
                  <abbr>M —</abbr>
                  <expan>Memphis</expan>
               </choice> nor shall it until I am there. I do not know whether you will have to let the folks see this or not, but I would rather you would read it to them.</p>
            <p>I am sorry Bunyan has left <choice>
                  <abbr>M —</abbr>
                  <expan>Memphis</expan>
               </choice>. As I expect to see you soon, I will defer saying anything on that subject, I suppose you know what I mean. They have just sent up a bucket of Apples and we are feasting.</p>
            <p>And by the way we have had quite a renovation in affairs at our <pb n="3" facs="um056c.small.jpg"/> house. One of <name type="person">Judge Dunns</name>, Sons, with his wife have taken the reins of government. The way we are now is a caution. We have the best table in town. We put our own sugar, and cream (and it is cream) in our coffee, have two kinds of pies and everything in style, dining room carpeted <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> it will be no use for me to go on and enumerate, the many improvements that have been made during the past week.  <name type="person">Mrs Tillon</name> is up here now. She enquired about you yesterday.</p>
            <p>The Boys here say, or rather remarking, that they do dislike to get with a Young Lady who says only Yessir! No Sir! So do I. I have been unwell a little lately but have nevertheless tended recitations. I caught a bad cold, for I never caught a good one, and it settled in my head.</p>
            <p>I attend singing school every Thursday evening for a hour. <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Rev</abbr>
                     <expan>Reverend</expan>
                  </choice> Crowe</name> is teacher. The young Ladies attend, that is if any of the young men go with them, none of them get there by my help. Tell <choice>
                  <abbr>Ed.</abbr>
                  <expan>Edward</expan>
               </choice>, that <name type="person">Kalfus</name> is setting up to <name type="person">Miss Tuba</name> like <unclear>40</unclear> You must have had some very fine times at the Donation Party, as you was mistress of ceremonies. I gave some of the particulars to some of our good Abolitionists. They were somewhat surprised. That was quite an adventure which you relate. Did not the poor young man faint?</p>
            <p>I fear he would have hurt himself, if you had pushed him over the Falls. I hope I shall have the pleasure of seeing the Chap sometime, I just wish to see how he looks. You ought to have given me a description of him. I hope my Friends <name type="person">Miss H &amp; R Miller</name> are prospering finely. I think a <choice>
                  <orig>heape</orig>
                  <reg>heap</reg>
               </choice> of them. My love to them. And I might as well give my love, here, to all the young Ladies, but, as I have not time to write <choice>
                  <orig>thier</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice> names, please give my love to <emph>all</emph> that I am acquainted with, tell them I have the same respect and warm friendship, and Love for them as ever. All your Friends are well. The occupants of this room wish to be remembered to you. <pb n="4" facs="um056d.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>The Boys are talking, who they are going to take to decoration. I shall none. I cannot have so much enjoyment with anyone, as I had with Mary last Decoration. I suppose you remember some of the things that happened that day, and the days following. <name type="person">Aunt Fanny</name> sends her love to <unclear>Mamny</unclear>. She can manage to get in the door, hard work though. We all were glad to <choice>
                  <orig>heare</orig>
                  <reg>hear</reg>
               </choice> that <name type="person">Mr Rhea</name> had reached <choice>
                  <abbr>M —</abbr>
                  <expan>Memphis</expan>
               </choice> in safety. I am getting some what sleepy, and must say, <emph>"Good night"</emph> with happy dreams.</p>
            <p>Saturday morning. This morning dawned cloudy, and now it is raining. Oh the mud, somewhat similar to the "Plough of Despond". I visit the point and the Falls now and then. I always think of you. I am in hopes to climb about those Falls with you, sometime again.</p>
            <p>I have been waiting very anxiously, for an answer to my letter to <choice>
                  <abbr>Ed</abbr>
                  <expan>Edward</expan>
               </choice>, he must be very busy. If  he dont write I will give him a "Hooshier Breeze".</p>
            <p>I shall expect an answer to this, you must write soon so that it will get here before I leave. I <choice>
                  <orig>recieved</orig>
                  <reg>received</reg>
               </choice> that Visitor, and it was a welcome Visitor. It is mail day, and I am in hopes to get something from some of my <choice>
                  <orig>corespondents</orig>
                  <reg>correspondents</reg>
               </choice>. I expect <name type="person">Mr Frierson</name> and <name type="person">Davis</name> will go down with me. We will have a very pleasant trip. Nothing of importance has happened in the peaceful village of <choice>
                  <abbr>H —</abbr>
                  <expan>Hanover</expan>
               </choice> lately. Every thing goes on quite smoothly. I believe I have written all I can raise. My Love the Young Ladies at <name type="place">"Walnut Hills"</name>. My Love to all at Home. Take my hat full of Love for yourself. Do all you can for the Lord, among your associates. Write soon! Write soon! to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Uncle <name type="person">Ben</name>
                  <name type="place">
                     <emph>College Hill</emph>
                  </name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To <name type="person">Miss Mary C. Porter</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Memphis</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <emph>
                        <name type="place">
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Tenn.</abbr>
                              <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </name>
                     </emph>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
