<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl669">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter]  1839 Nov. 26, Nashville, Tennessee [to] J. R. Poinsett / James K. Polk : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Polk, James K.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl669</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1839 Nov. 26, Nashville, Tennessee [to] J. R. Poinsett / James K. Polk</title>
               <author>Polk, James K.</author>
               <date when="1839-11-26"> 
			 November 26, 1839</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to the Secretary of War, J. R. Poinsett from Governor James K. Polk. It is dated November 26, 1839. The main topic of the letter is the exchange of Bonds held in trust for the Cherokee Indians with the Girard Bank in Philadelphia. Polk writes that from that point on, all Bonds will be paid with specie.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor James K. Polk Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl669</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Banks and banking</term>
               <term>Bonds</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80145740"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Polk, James K. (James Knox), 1795-1849</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl669a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <add>(Copy)</add> Executive Department</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Novr</abbr>
                           <expan>Novembere</expan>
                        </choice> 26th 1839</date>__</addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Hon</abbr>
                        <expan>Honorable</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name>J. R. Poinsett</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Secretary of War</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have had the honor to receive your letter of the 14th Instant, informing me that a draft drawn some weeks since, for the interest due on the <date>1st of July</date> last on $250.000 in <name>Tennessee</name> state Bonds, held by the Government of the <name>United States</name>, in trust for the <name>Cherokee</name> Indians had been <unclear>protested</unclear> at the Girard Bank in <name>Philadelphia</name>, with the reason assigned that nothing but current Philadelphia funds would be paid for it, and requesting that such instructions may be given to the agent of the state, as will ensure the prompt payment of the amount in question ($6.250), as well as the interest to fall due subsequently. The Union Bank of Tennessee has heretofore acted as the agent of the state in making the payment of the semi-annual interest on these Bonds, and has uniformly made provision for its payment at the Girard Bank in Philadelphia, as it fell due <pb n="2" facs="sl669b.small.jpg"/> that being the plan stipulated for the payment of the interest, when the Bonds were negotiated. In regard to the interest due on the 1st of July last ($6.250)__ the President of the Union Bank informs me, that as the agent of the State, that Bank in the latter part of June, deposited the amount due on the first of July in the Girard Bank in Philadelphia to the credit of the "Commissioner of Indian affairs" and that the Secretary of the Treasury was advised of the fact by the Union Bank, under date of the 2nd of July last. The President of the Union Bank insists, that the Bank has discharged her duty, by making the deposit in species at the Girard Bank, to meet the payment which fell due on the 1st of July, and that the loss or inconvenience which may be suffered, by the subsequent suspension of specie payments by the Girard Bank, in October following, should be borne by the holder of the Bonds, who failed to call on the day for the amount due. Without undertaking to <del type="overstrike">decide</del> give an opinion as to the correctness of the <unclear>insuing presented</unclear> by the President of the Union Bank, I am informed by him, that he has addressed you on the subject, and <add>that he</add> has also addressed the agent of the Bonds at Philadelphia <add>with a view to make a proper arrangement <unclear> [unclear]</unclear>
               </add> and I have <unclear>every reason</unclear> to believe, from what what he informs me, that the payment will be made at an early <add>day</add>_ <del type="overstrike">Should the arrangement made by the Union Bank close alluded to fail to accomplish the object I will together</del> If it should not be paid by the Bank upon being infor <pb n="3" facs="sl669c.small.jpg"/> formed of the fact by you I will take such measures as my<del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear>and  that the credit of the state shall by war</unclear>
               </del> given to be proper with a view to ensure its payment and <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear>possitretity suffer en that such am using are</unclear>
               </del> preserve the credit of the state The interest on there <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear>taken as shall mean the payment of the money</unclear>
               </del> Bonds, which shall hereafter fall due, will be <unclear>presently</unclear>
               <del type="overstrike">at are early day.</del> paid in specie.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I Have the <choice>
                     <abbr>Hon</abbr>
                     <expan>Honor</expan>
                  </choice> to be <lb/> Very Respectfully <lb/> your <choice>
                     <abbr>obt svt</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>James K Polk.</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl669d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>copy <lb/> Letter to <lb/> J.R. Poinsett <lb/> Secretary of War <lb/> Novr 26th 39</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
