<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch014">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1838 Aug. 29, Georgetown [to] John Ross / [J.?] Mason Jr.: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Mason Jr., J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch014</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44760161</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1838 Aug. 29, Georgetown [to] John Ross / [J.?] Mason Jr.</title>
               <author>Mason Jr., J.</author>
               <date when="1838-08-29">August 29, 1838</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a copy of a letter from (J. ?) Mason Jr., in Georgetown to John Ross, Principal Chief of the Cherokee Nation, dated August 29, 1838.  Mason informs Ross that he has recently received information regarding the emigration of Cherokees to the Arkansas territory and expresses his desire to furnish mercantile goods, to be delivered through New Orleans.</note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> 1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">18</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch014 </note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Relocation</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Mason Jr., J.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch014a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>(Duplicate)<lb/>
               <salute>To <name type="person">Col. John Ross</name>.  Principal Chief of the <name>Cherokee Nation</name>
               </salute>
               <lb/>
               <dateline>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place"> 
                           <reg>DC</reg> Georgetown</name>
                        <name type="place">D.C.</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <date when="1838-08-29">August 29th 1838</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
               <salute>Dear Sir -</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I received some days ago a letter from <name type="person"> 
                  <reg>Winfield</reg> General Scott</name>, stating that arrangements had been made with you  other principal men of your people, for their Emigration west  that my propositions in the matter were of course inadmissible.  I was much gratified to find that you  your Indian friends had the entire disposal of this important matter- this arrangement will <unclear>resound</unclear> equally to the honor of <name type="person"> 
                  <reg>Winfield</reg> General Scott</name>  the government  to the comfort  I trust, satisfaction of the <name type="person">Cherokees</name>, under the trying  painful circumstances, in which, all have been placed.  I congratulate you therefore  your friends, upon the happy determination of this branch of the subject.</p>
            <p>I have now a proposition to make, to which I invite your serious consideration  that of your <name type="person">Cherokee</name> friends.  On establishing yourselves in the West, you will, besides subsistence, necessarily require for the use of all your people, a great quantity  variety of articles necessary to their comfort  well being- Such as woolens  cottons, for clothes- blankets- hardware of all sorts- glass- agricultural implements- mechanics tools- groceries- arms  powder <choice>
                  <abbr>c c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera et cetera</expan>
               </choice>- all these can in greater or lesser quantities, be doubtless bought, in the West, from Merchants  Traders; who foreseeing your wants may have goods ready to supply them.  These goods will have been<pb n="2" facs="ch014b.small.jpg"/>originally purchased in the Northern Cities, and probably, have passed <choice>
                  <orig>thro</orig>
                  <reg>through</reg>
               </choice> several hands, each charging a profit, before they reach your people, the consumers. of course under such circumstances they must be bought by the consumers at prices very far above the original cost  transportation to the point of delivery- such goods would in all probability be generally of inferior qualities.  Instead of relying upon such a source, would it not be better to make your purchases directly from this section of the Country?   to have the goods sent by way of <name type="place">New Orleans</name> to such designated points, in your <name type="place">Arkansas</name> Country, as might be accessible by water  most convenient to you?  Should <del type="overstrike">such</del>
               <add place="supralinear">this</add> proposition meet the approbation of your friends  yourself, I have to offer my services to carry it into effect- as to the business part of it.  I understand it perfectly  I trust you will believe that I will do it honorably  justly-  so far as protection from the Government may be required (should such be the case, as it may be) I think I can say, it will, at my request, be given when necessary to secure the safe transportation of <add place="supralinear">the</add> goods to your people.  In all cases it will be necessary that your orders should state fully  in detail the quality  quantity of each description of goods wanted- the places to which they are to be sent  the time of delivery at those places- <choice>
                  <orig>accomodating</orig>
                  <reg>accommodating</reg>
               </choice> the time of delivery, of course, to the proper periods for navigating the rivers to be ascended.  as to funds- with proper guarantee, I can raise any amount required- so that you need advance nothing- when I say proper guarantee, I mean such security as the<pb n="3" facs="ch014c.small.jpg"/>Banks would be satisfied with - or should the goods, be bought on credit, as would probably be the case, such security as would satisfy the Importers from whom purchased- as for instance, orders <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear/>
               </del>
               <add place="supralinear">or</add> drafts upon the Secretary of War <choice>
                  <abbr>Comsr</abbr>
                  <expan>Commissioners</expan>
               </choice>- of Indian affairs or other proper Officers accepted by him, to be payable on delivery of the goods at some designated point in <name type="place">Arkansas</name> or elsewhere- or any other mode by which payment would be secured-  I have to invite again your earnest attention to this subject not only in regard to the supplies that may be required by your own people, but by the Tribes around you, over whom, you and your friends, will undoubtedly exercise a great influence.  Such an arrangement would, I am persuaded be highly advantageous to the Indians, by securing for them the articles they may want on the lowest terms  of the required quality-  highly beneficial to me from the greatest extent of the operations.  <del type="overstrike">The</del> the percentage of profit would be small.  I shall be gratified to hear from you soon in reply to this letter and have to subscribe myself with great respect-
                  
               </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>your friend  <choice>
                     <abbr>ob.servt</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <unclear>J</unclear> Mason Jr</name>
               </signed>
               <lb/>
               <date when="1838-10-01">1st <choice>
                     <abbr>Octo.</abbr>
                     <expan>October</expan>
                  </choice> 1838</date>
               <lb/>The original of this letter was forwarded by mail to the care of your Brother Mr. <name type="person">Lewis Ross</name>- this goes <choice>
                  <abbr>thro</abbr>
                  <expan>through</expan>
               </choice>  the war Department- your early answer will much oblige<lb/>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <unclear>J</unclear> Mason Jr.</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
