<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl275">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1827 Dec. 10, Frankfort [to] Andrew J. Donelson   / Henry Banks : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Banks, Henry</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl275</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1827 Dec. 10, Frankfort [to] Andrew J. Donelson   / Henry Banks </title>
               <author>Banks, Henry</author>
               <date when="1827-12-10">December 10, 1827</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated December 10, 1827 to Andrew Jackson Donelson from Henry Banks. The letter includes a printed Memorial by Banks and discusses the presidential election.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">A. J. Donelson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">I-D-3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl275</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr92008138"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Banks, Henry, 1761-1833</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl275a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Printed page, A Memorial by <name type="person">Henry Banks</name>, <date when="1827-10-27">October 27, 1827</date>
                  </figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <pb n="2" facs="sl275b.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Frankfort</name>
                     <date when="1827-12-10">December 10th 1827</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Some time has elapsed since I have heard from you and although I cannot approve either of your or <name type="person">Andrew Hay</name>'s conduct to me, I find that I cannot notice the subject as it deserves without injuring the election of <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> . Jackson</name> which , I prize above all earthly considerations. If I had got that money or property while I was engaged in printing, it would have been devoted to that purpose and I am now confident, that he would have been then elected; but perhaps the developments which have happened may make the delay a fortunate one—</p>
            <p> I have been <choice>
                  <orig>labouring</orig>
                  <reg>laboring</reg>
               </choice> in the vineyard with much zeal and some success and although I have lost the power of writing <del type="overstrike">letters these this,</del> yet I can dictate and abet, The people of this state generally admit that I commenced and have steadily aided in the cause, my health and resources have both failed, and the cause of the failure I believe may be imputed to a combination formed against me of Coalition men including Judges and some monied men, who afforded considerable aid by the dextrous use of which a decree by antijackson judges has taken from me, property worth $100.000 for pretenses which I thought the most frivolous, but the decree has been pronounced and your acquaintance Darby is one of the gainers, and is now a man of wealth— I shall set this down to my patriotism and the weight that my exertions are believed to have had; but as I now believe that Jackson will be elected I declare that I would not consent to his failure for the $100.000 to be restored and <pb n="3" facs="sl275c.small.jpg"/> myself <choice>
                  <orig>honoured</orig>
                  <reg>honored</reg>
               </choice> with a seat in their cabinet.—</p>
            <p>It is true that I shall be compelled to abandon expectations which were flattering, but I hope to be one of those gratulations to my country which will be everlasting, and that I may have it in my power to say "Now Lord thy servant is ready to depart in peace mine eyes having witnessed my countrys glory and thy salvation.—</p>
            <p>I have since my misfortune circulated a few copies of letters to friends, if they do no good they will do no harm— I also forward to you, my memorial to congress and 40 pages of a book, the publication of which will cost a considerable sum, which if I had obtained my suit I <gap agent="damage"/> not have regarded.—</p>
            <p>you may give my respects to the Genl. &amp; say that my greatest regret is that I cannot do what I intended during the next year, that I now have manuscript <unclear>?</unclear> worthy of publication, but the Editor of the Jackson papers here, and myself are not nor never can be on good terms</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am Dear Sir your <choice>
                     <abbr>Obt Servt.</abbr>
                     <expan>Obedient Servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Henry Banks</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="bottom of page">you will see in my memorial that I lost by patriotism about $150.000 during the Revolution before I was of age, and now when I am on the brink of the grave to <choice>
                     <orig>loose</orig>
                     <reg>lose</reg>
                  </choice> more than $100.000 again for patriotism &amp; that I yet resolve while I live, to continue a patriot and at my post</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl275d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="above address">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Postmark 18 3/4</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <name type="person">Andrew J. Donaldson <choice>
                     <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                     <expan>Esquire</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="under address">
                  <name type="person">Henry Banks</name>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
