<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl187">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1833  Sep. 26, Bolivar [TN] [to] Cordy [i.e., Cordelia Brown] / S. L. McNeal     : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>McNeal, S. L.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl187</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51173916</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1833  Sep. 26, Bolivar [TN] [to] Cordy [i.e., Cordelia Brown] / S. L. McNeal     </title>
               <author>McNeal, S. L.</author>
               <date when="1833-09-26">September 26, 1833</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated Sep. 26, 1833, to a woman named Cordelia Brown from her uncle S. L. McNeal, who is probably an in-law of David Franklin Brown. McNeal is anxious for "Cordy" to come home.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Joseph Brown</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">THS-JB</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">224-239</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl187</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">McNeal, S. L.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl187a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Bolivar</name>
                     <date when="1833-09-26">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Sept</abbr>
                           <expan>September</expan>
                        </choice> 26th 18<unclear>33</unclear>
                     </date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear <name type="person">Cordy</name>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have postponed writing to you believing that you could have returned before this as your Aunt Jane. said she would return in the course of two weeks. and bring you with her we hear nothing from you. from Priscillas letter you learn the Death of Sister Mary. her Sufferings were great  which she bore with great fortitude.</p>
            <p>I have just <choice>
                  <orig>recieved</orig>
                  <reg>received</reg>
               </choice> a letter from your Uncle William he reached home in good health about  the  1st <choice>
                  <abbr>Inst.</abbr>
                  <expan>Instant</expan>
               </choice> having gone by land. he has not been out to your house yet but says all are well. and they complain as much at you for not writing to them, as you did. for not recieving <choice>
                  <orig>moore</orig>
                  <reg>more</reg>
               </choice> letters.</p>
            <p>I am still undetermined how to go to <name type="place">Texas</name> I would prefer going by land. but I cant think of taking you in that way. and unless I meet with Some <choice>
                  <orig>verry</orig>
                  <reg>very</reg>
               </choice> good traveling Company for you to go by <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N</abbr>
                     <expan>New</expan>
                  </choice> Orleans</name> I will go that way myself. I must determine soon how I go. We are all becoming verry anxious for you to come back and if you should not. meet with an opp<gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>ortunity</unclear>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl187b.small.jpg"/> to come sooner. <name type="person">Dr Peters</name> intends starting on the 29th for <name type="place">Nashville</name> and will return about the 12th when you can come with him though I verry much hope you will come sooner — Dr Peters will write to you when he will be in <name type="place">Columbia</name> So as to meet him, We have a letter to you from home and one from <name type="place">Oxford <choice>
                     <abbr>Miss.</abbr>
                     <expan>Mississippi</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> I would send them but fear you might not get them before leaving. I hope this will make you moore anxious  to come. We are all well.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Verry truly you Uncle</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">S L Mc Neal</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
