<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl178">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1830 Nov. 14 [to] Col[onel] Joseph Brown, Maury County, Tennessee / James Brown : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Brown, James</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl178</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51173256</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1830 Nov. 14 [to] Col[onel] Joseph Brown, Maury County, Tennessee / James Brown</title>
               <author>Brown, James </author>
               <date when="1830-11-14">November 14, 1830</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter to Col. Joseph Brown in Maury County, TN from his son James Brown, dated November 14, 1830.  In the letter, James discusses his previous plans to go into business with his brother Joseph and another man by the name of Estes as well as the house and plot of land that he has recently purchased.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Joseph Brown Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">THS-JB</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">171-180</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl178</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Brown, James</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl178a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1830-11-14">November 14th 1830</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Father</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I take the present <choice>
                  <orig>oportunity</orig>
                  <reg>opportunity</reg>
               </choice> of informing you that we are all well. I have seen <name type="person">Joshua</name> to day he and family are well, brother <name type="person">Franklin</name> &amp; wife were here last <choice>
                  <orig>wee</orig>
                  <reg>week</reg>
               </choice> &amp; were well,  their <choice>
                  <orig>litle</orig>
                  <reg>little</reg>
               </choice> boy grows finely &amp; is a  very fine child, I was at brother <name type="person">John</name>s some five  or six weeks since they were also well, <choice>
                  <orig>tho</orig>
                  <reg>though</reg>
               </choice> there has been considerable sickness in <name type="place">Tipton</name> this year, <name type="person">Nancy</name>es sister, <name type="person">Mrs Small</name>
               <choice>
                  <orig>dyed</orig>
                  <reg>died</reg>
               </choice> a day or two before I was there</p>
            <p>I was much astonished some time ago to learn that <name type="person">Joseph</name> had started on a trading expedition on the <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>missippi</orig>
                     <reg>Mississippi</reg>
                  </choice> River</name> but to what point he is steering I am not able to learn, only that he has gone down stream I had made an arrangement to go into the <choice>
                  <orig>mercantil buisiness</orig>
                  <reg>mercantile business</reg>
               </choice>, partly for his benefit or rather I have agreed with <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Keyes</name> to go into the buisiness at his suggestions, that if I would take <name type="person">Edwin Estes</name>  in he would assist us in <choice>
                  <orig>geting</orig>
                  <reg>getting</reg>
               </choice> every thing we wanted &amp; on such terms as I could meet the payments <pb n="2" facs="sl178b.small.jpg"/> after being advised of my means he thought them sufficient to begin with; after maturely considering the subject I <choice>
                  <orig>conclooded</orig>
                  <reg>concluded</reg>
               </choice> I would try it &amp; wish Estes to come out and agreed with him that he Joseph &amp; myself should go into the buisiness, but before Estes left this I learned Joseph had gone below, I have got John to <choice>
                  <orig>wright</orig>
                  <reg>write</reg>
               </choice> to such place as he may think most likely to <choice>
                  <orig>interrest</orig>
                  <reg>interest</reg>
               </choice> him requesting him to return, but <choice>
                  <orig>whither</orig>
                  <reg>whether</reg>
               </choice> he will return or not is quite uncertain, he has much shaken my confidence lately by his wil<del type="overstrike">l</del>d &amp; wandering calculations I should not have ⁁ <add place="supralinear">made</add> any such arrangements but for a wish to gratify him in his wishes to be in that kind of buisiness, still my opinion of Joseph is that he would not be competent to manage a <unclear>concern</unclear> alone, his great desire to sell would <choice>
                  <orig>allway</orig>
                  <reg>always</reg>
               </choice> lead him into losses &amp; <choice>
                  <orig>difficultys</orig>
                  <reg>difficulties</reg>
               </choice>, but <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>combinding</orig>
                     <reg>combining</reg>
                  </choice>
               </unclear> Estes who is said to be steady, &amp; having been twelve years in buisiness &amp; very cautious would I think <choice>
                  <orig>mak</orig>
                  <reg>make</reg>
               </choice> a safe concern my means are <del type="overstrike">about</del> not very good tho Col Keys thought  them sufficient, I have about seven thousand dollars due me within this &amp; the next year all good debts, out <pb n="3" facs="sl178c.small.jpg"/> of which I shall have to appropriate about fifteen hundred to the payment of my present contracts leaving a balance of 6500 but the Col says if I can <choice>
                  <orig>rais</orig>
                  <reg>raise</reg>
               </choice> 3000  it will be <unclear>sufficient</unclear> to keep up the stock</p>
            <p>you perhaps may haver heard of my purchase of a tavern establishment in <name type="place">Jackson</name>, but <choice>
                  <orig>maynot</orig>
                  <reg>may not</reg>
               </choice> be correctly informed I have bought the half of the establishment, the brick  <choice>
                  <orig>hous</orig>
                  <reg>house</reg>
               </choice> &amp; lot for the sum of $2000 my portion is to keep the hous &amp; pay half of the expense I the other half  &amp; divide profits <choice>
                  <orig>equaly</orig>
                  <reg>equally</reg>
               </choice> the payments are to be paid one fourth when we get possession, the balance in installments for three years, after the 1st payment we ex<gap agent="damage"/> to make the balance off of the hous; the present incumbent has paid $500 a year rent, and made over 5000 clear of all expense in less than three years, so that if we manage it well it must be good stock, I have been offered the cash in hand for it — my stage contract is better than I expected it as to money received from <choice>
                  <orig>pasingers</orig>
                  <reg>passengers</reg>
               </choice> ; it has heretofore been <choice>
                  <orig>agreatdeel</orig>
                  <reg>a great deal</reg>
               </choice> of trouble but we have recently divided the line, it is now very litle trouble, I have the part from Jackson to <name type="place">Bolivar</name> our new hous is nearly completed &amp; we have moved into it <pb n="4" facs="sl178d.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>Our little ones are all healthy and growing finely except <name type="person">Jane Elizabeth</name> had the ague &amp; fever 8 or 10 day this fall we have had no sickness among them, the twins are most ready to crawl — my respects to mother &amp; all friends</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">James Brown</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine> Col<name type="person">Joseph Brown</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Maury County</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address" rend="different hand, ink">James Brown letter 1830</add>
               <add place="below address">A Mintin of BJ Thomas</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
