<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl426">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1845 Sep. 18, Carthage, Tennessee [to unknown recipient] / A[dam] Fergusson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Fergusson, A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl426</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1845 Sep. 18, Carthage, Tennessee [to unknown recipient] / A[dam] Fergusson</title>
               <author>Fergusson, A.</author>
               <date when="1845-09-18">September 18, 1845</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Adam Fergusson dated September 18, 1845. The recipient is unknown. Fergusson is writing to obtain proof of a marriage.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">IV-G-1, B6</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl426</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Marriage</term>
               <term>Legal fees</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Fergusson, Adam</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl426a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Carthage</name>
                     <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>18th September 1845</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letter dated <date>2d august</date> last came to hand and I have been unable to answer it until now you State that <name>Rhoda Chitwood</name> was at the <choice>
                  <orig>weding</orig>
                  <reg>wedding</reg>
               </choice> but did not See them married also that <name>PatSey Tumsden</name>
               <name>John Blakinship</name> and <name>Fanny Dillon</name> can State the Same facts you mention also the names of Several persons who would be good Agents, also that It will take five or ten dollars or between five and ten to pay the <choice>
                  <orig>expences</orig>
                  <reg>expenses</reg>
               </choice> of taking the proof and getting the Same duly certified I inclose to you five dollars and hope that the Same will pay the Agent his fees and expences. I want two of the witnesses to State what they know of the marriage especially if they were there and that they were lawfully married on the day 1784 <add>or about the times they <choice>
                     <orig>recolect</orig>
                     <reg>recollect</reg>
                  </choice>
               </add> and before Seventeen hundred and ninety four when the affidavit is Sworn to let the magistrate before whom they were qualified give his certificate that he is acquainted with them and that they are entitled to full credit. Then let the clerk of the county court give his certificate as to the official Character of the magistrate and attach his Seal thereto. You will then inclose the Same to me at this place and any further expences will be duly Sent to you</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Respectfully</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>A.</abbr>
                        <expan>Adam</expan>
                     </choice> Fergusson</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P S</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> I have forgot the day and month that was Set down in their bible but the <unclear>witnesses</unclear> can recolect <lb/> A Fergusson</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
