<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl333">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] ca. 1850 Feb. 13, Aztalan, Wisconsin [to] A. Fergusson, Carthage, Tenn[essee] / H. S. Howell   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Howell, H. S.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl333</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] ca. 1850 Feb. 13, Aztalan, Wisconsin [to] A. Fergusson, Carthage, Tenn[essee] / H. S. Howell</title>
               <author>Howell, H. S.</author>
               <date when="1850-02-13">February 13, ca.1850</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from H. S. Howell to Adam Fergusson, dated February 13. It was written in the late 1840's. Howell asks for Fergusson's help in a deal Howell made with H. H. Holland, Buck Hart, and Mr. Farley.  Howell writes that he misses Tennessee, and that it was the happiest time of his life. He writes that he likes Wisconsin partly because it is a Democratic state. Howell is disappointed that the Whig party won the last election. He hopes they will not reverse the decisions, policies, and laws of the previous administration.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> IV-G-1 b4</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl333</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Business enterprises</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Howell, H. S.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl333a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Aztalan</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Feby</abbr>
                        <expan>February</expan>
                     </choice> 13 184<gap agent="damage"/>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>You may doubtless recollect that I <unclear>once</unclear> lived in <name type="place">Carthage</name> and took a warm interest in the success of the Democratic Party and the triumph of its principles__ so much so that I bartered a little according to the fashion of the times, on the final result__ I made our deal with <name type="person">H. H. Holland</name> by which I obtained his note, with Buck Hart security, for fifty dollars ($50.)__ when I left <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Tenn.</abbr>
                     <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> Holland refused <choice>
                  <abbr>payt.</abbr>
                  <expan>payment</expan>
               </choice> and I left the note with <name type="person">Mr. Farley</name> for collection of Hart__</p>
            <p>I received, about 2 years since, a letter from Farley stating he would soon get the money from Hart__ I have written him since but received no answer and am at a loss to know the reason being ignorant whether he still lives in Carthage or what has become of the note__  Will you have the goodness to make the necessary enquiry of Farley, or whom it may concern, and inform me of the result__  If Farley still has charge of the matter please request him to write me, or if his concern  have been left with others, enquire of them__</p>
            <p>If the note was never paid and Buck feels any  <choice>
                  <orig>desposition</orig>
                  <reg>disposition</reg>
               </choice>  to pay will you attend to the matter for me, or get others to do so who may have friendly intercourse with Hart__ <unclear>Jno</unclear> , Goodall for insta <gap agent="damage"/>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl333b.small.jpg"/> If Buck is not willing to pay the full amount <gap agent="damage"/> what you can get, as I suppose, if sued he would not pay anything__</p>
            <p>If you will attend to this matter and inform me as to the result you will confer a <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice> and much oblige an old friend —</p>
            <p>Since I left your state I have lived in <name type="place">Iowa</name> and the <name type="place">Jarseys</name>  but am now permanently, settled here_ I often think of my residence in Tenn_ the associations there formed and the many agreeable and pleasing interviews with friends and I <unclear>recur</unclear> to that period as the most happy in my life_ I admire the climate of Tenn_ and the habits and frank, open, kind feelings of the inhabitants, to such an extent that I regret at times ever leaving there_ I however like <name type="place">wisconsin</name> well. It is a young and thriving state and above all Democratic, and I trust will ever remain so_</p>
            <p>How have your schools prospered since I left are they flourishing_</p>
            <p>What kind of times had you during, that last canvass not as warm I suppose as in '44 The contest here was very dull and no excitement at all_ The Whigs were it is true the successful party, but it remains to be seen whether they dare to <unclear>change</unclear> the policy of the late administration and repeal the wise and wholesome Laws that have sustained the government and the country in times of trouble and unusualdifficulties: <pb n="3" facs="sl333c.small.jpg"/> Let them attempt to restore their "obsolete" <gap agent="damage"/> ures or revive the policy that has so often wreck <gap agent="damage"/> them and they will at the end of four years be blown skyhigh and rowed to a point on salt river never thought navigable_</p>
            <p>But political matters now seem dull &amp; tame and I will not dwell upon them_</p>
            <p>Accept my best regards to yourself and family. Is your son William still pursuing his studies and has he chosen his avocation for life</p>
            <p>Give my best considerations to my acquaintances in general_ <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Overton</name>
               <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Maj</abbr>
                     <expan>Major</expan>
                  </choice> Bruford</name>
               <name type="person">
                  <unclear>G C.</unclear> Allen</name>
               <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Sloan</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>and etcetera</expan>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>yours most truly</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">H. S. Howell</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Aztalan</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Wisconsin</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mr. <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>A</abbr>
                           <expan>Adam</expan>
                        </choice> Fergusson</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Carthage</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Tenn _</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="right of address">}</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl333d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>A. Fergusson <choice>
                        <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Carthage</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Tenn.</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
