<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um063">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1840 Dec. 19, Columbia, Tennessee [to]   Martha Butler Chester / M[ary] J[ane] Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um063</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50311219</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1840 Dec. 19, Columbia, Tennessee [to]   Martha Butler Chester / M[ary] J[ane] Chester</title>
               <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
               <date when="1840-12-19">December 19,  1840</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by Mary Jane Chester to her sister, Martha Butler Chester, on December 19, 1840. In the letter, Mary Jane describes how she will spend Christmas in Columbia, Tennessee, and wishes her sister and family a Merry Christmas at home in Jackson, Tennessee.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers MS 25 (December 1840)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um063</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Mary Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um063a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia Tennessee</name>
                     <date when="1840-12-19">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Decr.</abbr>
                           <expan>December</expan>
                        </choice> 19th 40</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Sister</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>This being Saturday, and as I have concluded that you do not intend writing to your poor Sister who is far away from you. I will write to you. I know that I would not have treated you as you have treated me. but I will forgive you if you will promise to be a better correspondent hereafter. If you know how much pleasure it gave me to receive your letter, I know that you would write to me again. Mother wrote me three or four weeks ago saying that ⁁ <add place="supralinear">both</add> you and brother <name type="person">John</name> intended writing that week to me, but I expect that you have forgotten me by this time. Sister please <choice>
                  <orig>anser</orig>
                  <reg>answer</reg>
               </choice> this letter as soon as you receive it, it would <choice>
                  <orig>releive</orig>
                  <reg>relieve</reg>
               </choice> my mind to see that you have not forgotten me. You cannot imagine ⁁ <add place="supralinear">how</add> much disappointed I was to hear that <name type="person">Aunt Narcissa</name> was not <choice>
                  <orig>comming</orig>
                  <reg>coming</reg>
               </choice> up to see me, but I was as much delighted to hear that Papa was coming up. I <choice>
                  <orig>wondor</orig>
                  <reg>wonder</reg>
               </choice> how I shall spend my Christmas the first one that I ever spent from home. You will all be so happy at <emph>home</emph> the very name of home makes me feel happy. I never knew how much I loved you all until I left home. There is no place like home according to my <choice>
                  <orig>oppinion</orig>
                  <reg>opinion</reg>
               </choice>. <choice>
                  <abbr>Sis</abbr>
                  <expan>Sister</expan>
               </choice> I am <choice>
                  <orig>affraid</orig>
                  <reg>afraid</reg>
               </choice> that you cannot read this printed letter for it is the first one that I ever <choice>
                  <orig>trid</orig>
                  <reg>tried</reg>
               </choice> to print. You must excuse me for not writing a longer letter for I have not time to write more. <pb n="2" facs="um063b.small.jpg"/>
               <choice>
                  <orig>O</orig>
                  <reg>Oh</reg>
               </choice>! it is so cold here. It is a great deal colder than in Jackson. I expect that I feel the cold more sensibly than if I was at home, for there are 40 odd girls, and only two fire places. You know that is not enough for us all to get by. I am so glad that you are not here this Winter on that account. I know that you would freeze. but I do want to so you so much. I know if was at home I would never speak an unkind word to you. Give my love to Mama &amp; Papa &amp; all the children. Aunt N. Aunt P. &amp; all my Uncles &amp; Aunts &amp; Cousins.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I remain your most affectionate Sister</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>M. J.</abbr>
                        <expan>Mary Jane</expan>
                     </choice> Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Miss Martha Butler Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="3" facs="um063c.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="above address">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>post mark for December 21</figDesc>
                  </figure> 18</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Miss Martha B. Chester</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address, upside down">
                  <date when="1840-12-20">20 <choice>
                        <abbr>Decr</abbr>
                        <expan>December</expan>
                     </choice> 1840</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
