<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl487">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1817 Aug. 25, Cairo [Tennessee, to] Colonel H. Sherburne / J[ames] Winchester: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Winchester, J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl487</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1817 Aug. 25, Cairo [Tennessee, to] Colonel H. Sherburne / J[ames] Winchester</title>
               <author>Winchester, J.</author>
               <date when="1817-08-25">August 25, 1817</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from General James Winchester to Colonel H. Sherburne, dated August 25, 1817. Winchester is writing about a town he laid off. He  denies the accusation that he laid it before the area was surveyed. Winchester writes that he waited for the Chiefs to take part in the line running, but that they were so late he had to start without them.  He mentions a treaty that was broken.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">James Winchester Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl487</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Winchester, James, 1752-1826 Correspondence.</term>
               <term>Chickasaw Indians -- Treaties</term>
               <term>Land question</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n96115844"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Winchester, James, 1752-1826</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl487a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Cairo</name>
                     <date>25th August 1817</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>your favor of the 7th instant came to hand by the last western mail to this place, given me the result of a council of the <name>chickasaw nation</name> on the subject on the line I have lately run It is not true that I <choice>
                  <orig>surved</orig>
                  <reg>surveyed</reg>
               </choice> and laid off a Town at the <name>chickasaw Bluff</name> before the line was run, but it is true that I was present when a town was laid off and surveyed at that place How this circumstance is supposed to have any effect on the <choice>
                  <orig>runing</orig>
                  <reg>running</reg>
               </choice> the line alluded to I cannot <choice>
                  <orig>concieve</orig>
                  <reg>conceive</reg>
               </choice> , with relation to due notice agreeably to the treaty, you know the first notice was made to depend upon <choice>
                  <sic>the the</sic>
                  <corr>the</corr>
               </choice> time of holding a treaty for the <name>salt springs</name> on Sandy; which was to have been held the <date>last of may</date> or <date>first <gap/> June</date>, and time enough was previously given  to the best of my recollection at least a month, the treaty was not held it is true, but it was only known about that time <del type="overstrike">that time</del> that it would not be held, and then to <pb n="2" facs="sl487b.small.jpg"/> to obviate all possible misunderstandings on the subject, I personally attended in the nation, when you was good enough to meet me at <name>Mr Allison</name>and when &amp; where you heard me ask major <name>James Colbert</name> when at what time the chiefs design to see the line run, could meet on the bank of  <name>Tennessee river</name> at the  place of beginning, and that he finally fixed on the first monday in June being the 7th day <del type="overstrike">of June</del> ; did not all the amount to due and seasonable notice; I <unclear>made</unclear> arrangements to commence the line <unclear>accordingly</unclear> but waited for the chiefs <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice>
               <date>thursday the 10th</date> when hearing nothing of them and perceiving  too if I delayed any longer that I should have to send to the settlement, near 100 miles, for an additional supply of provisions. under these circumstance I commenced the line, and on <date>saturday the 12th</date> when we had not <unclear>progressed</unclear> more than six miles, major James Colbert <unclear>joined</unclear> us. and told me the <gap/> chief was sick or they would have met me according to <unclear>appointment</unclear> or words to that effect, I then reported to him when and where I had commenced the line how far I had progressed <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>etcetera</expan>
               </choice> with all of which he <pb n="3" facs="sl487c.small.jpg"/> appeared to be satisfied and we progressed with harmony and  friendship on monday the <date>14th of June</date> when we had progress 16 miles <name>Captain Seely</name> the other chief joined, I reported to him as I had done to major Colbert he expressed no dissatisfaction, but went on very <choice>
                  <orig>chearfully</orig>
                  <reg>cheerfully</reg>
               </choice> except some times of an afternoon he complained that the compass run too far from the <unclear>seting sun</unclear>
            </p>
            <p>The instruments I used were the best which could be had in this country, and I believe they are equal in correctness to any in the united states, If it was true that the line was not taken up untill 8 or 9 oclock in the morning I cannot see how its correctness could be effected by it, But the reverse is the fact, I never saw more persevering mastery in private or public service than was exhibited in this occasion, the whole party rose soon after daylight breakfast was cooked and eat and the line take <gap/> between 6 or 7 oclock and continued untill <gap/> ut one oclock when dinner was prepared and sent to <del type="overstrike">him and</del> the party on the line, about one hour was given for dinner when the line was again taken up and  <choice>
                  <sic>continued untill  continued untill</sic>
                  <corr>continued untill</corr>
               </choice> about sundown not blazing the trees too according to <gap/> eaty so made a subject of complaint I hazard nothing in saying that the line is better <del type="overstrike">is better</del> marked than any line I ever saw in the <name>united states</name> and that the trees on each side of the line are marked bold according to the treaty,</p>
            <p>You are at liberty to read this letter to the chiefs of you place</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am very respectfully <lb/> Sir <lb/> Your most obedient servant</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>J</abbr>
                        <expan>James</expan>
                     </choice> Winchester</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Col</abbr>
                        <expan>Colonel</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name>H Sherburne</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>agent chickasaw</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>nation</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Copy of a letter <lb/> to <lb/> Col Shereburne <lb/> Agent Chickasaw nation</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
