<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0056">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Claim under the Treaties of 1817 &amp; 1819] 1837 August 14, Cherokee County Georgia : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0056</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Claim under the Treaties of 1817 &amp; 1819] 1837 August 14, Cherokee County Georgia </title>
               <date when="1837-08-14"> 
			 August 14, 1837</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a claim, dated August 14, 1837 made by Eleanor Ragsdale, a Cherokee woman who possessed property in the state of Georgia. Ragsdale is requesting a valuation of her property and to be compensated under the Treaties of 1817 and 1819.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> n/a</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Legal documents</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Claims</term>
               <term>Land tenure</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0056a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>
               <name>Georgia </name>
               <lb/>
               <name>Cherokee County</name>{</head>
            <p>In a Treaty made between the <name>United States</name> and the <name>Cherokee</name> Indians in the year (1819) Eight-teen Hundred and Nineteen_<name>Eleanor Ragsdale</name> a Cherokee Indian was possessed of the following property or Improvements that never was valued to her._To wit, One Improvement with fifteen acres of cleared land under good fence with one Dwelling House 22 feet long 16 feet wide, one spring house 8 feet square_one table 14 feet long 12 feet wide, and Two Hundred bearing Peach Tree said improvement lying <add>on</add> the waters of warhoo creek in <name>Hall county</name> and State of Georgia_also</p>
            <p>One other Improvement with <add>fifteen</add> acres of cleaned land sixteen under a good Fence with one Dwelling House_18 feet long, 16 feet wide, one kitchen 14 feet long, 12 feet wide,  one stable 14 feet long 12 feet wide, and a good House Lot also 2 corn cribbs 12 feet long 8 feet wide. Each_ the said Improvements Lying on <name>Chestatee River</name> in the County of <name>Habersham</name> and State of Georgia_ And both Impovements estimated to be worth Six Hundred and Ninety five Dollars <pb n="2" facs="pa0056b.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>Georgia <lb/> Cherokee { Personally came before me Eleanor Ragsdale &amp; <name>John Conner</name>, and after beingDuly sworn deposeth and saith that the above claim and Improvements are just and true as they stand stated sworn to before me_ August 14th 1837</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>Mr. Whitaker </name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr> J.P.</abbr>
                     <expan>Justice of the Peace</expan>
                  </choice> Eleanor <add>her x mark</add> Ragsdale <add>John Conner</add>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <note>
                     <p>State of Georgia <lb/> Cherokee county { I do herby certify that <name>William Whitaker</name> whose certificate appears to the above affidavit was at the time it is dated an acting Justice of the Peace in and for said county, duly sworn and commissioned and that as such, and that the signiture is genuine_</p>
                     <p>Given under my hand and private seal, there being no seal of Office this 14th day of August 1837</p>
                  </note>
               </add>
               <signed>
                  <name>William Grisham</name>
               </signed> Deputy Clerk <lb/> Cherokee Inferior Court <lb/> Georgia <pb n="3" facs="pa0056c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Eleanor's Ragsdale's <lb/> Claim for Reservation <lb/> under the Treaties of <lb/> 1817 &amp; 1819_</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
