<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="gc010">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1820 Dec. 14, Cahaba [to] James Moore King, Rutherford County, Tennessee / W[illi]m G. Parrish  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Parrish, William G.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harding</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>gc010</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1820 Dec. 14, Cahaba [to] James Moore King, Rutherford County, Tennessee / W[illi]m G. Parrish  </title>
               <author>Parrish, William G.</author>
               <date when="1820-12-14">December 14, 1820</date>
               <extent> 3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated December 14, 1820 to James Moore King from William G. Parrish.  Parrish writes of crop yields, and a disappointment at King for not relocating nearby.  </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">James Moore King Papers Correspondence 1820-1823</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">gc010</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Crop losses</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Parrish, William G.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="gc010a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>Cahaba  <choice>
                  <abbr>Ala</abbr>
                  <expan>Alabama</expan>
               </choice>
               <date when="1820-12-11">11<choice>
                     <abbr>Dec</abbr>
                     <expan>December</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date>
               <add>From <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                        <expan>William</expan>
                     </choice> G. Parrish</name> 1820 </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mr. James M. King</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Rutherford County </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="top right of center">25</add>
               <pb n="2" facs="gc010b.small.jpg"/>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Cahauba </orig>
                  <reg>Cahaba</reg>
               </choice>
               <date when="1820-12-14">Dec. 14th 1820</date>
            </opener>
            <salute>Dear James</salute>
            <p> Your highly esteemed favor was duly Received, and it affords me much pleasure to find that you have not forgotten us, although we are <choice>
                  <orig>seperated</orig>
                  <reg>separated</reg>
               </choice> so far from each other.  I at one time enjoyed the pleasing hope, that we are many years resolved,  should become near  neighbors in this pleasant, and salubrious clime; but hearing that you have again entered in the delightful pursuits  of Agriculture in your State.  precludes all hope of enjoying that pleasure I fondly anticipated.   </p>
            <p>It is a source of much regret with me.  to hear that you have earnestly and warmly selected the   fair hands of an amiable and accomplished girl, and that you have been <choice>
                  <orig>unsuccessfull</orig>
                  <reg>unsuccessful</reg>
               </choice>.  This is a check that has rendered the life, of many a   promising youth, a misery to himself and a pest to society,  But I trust your firmness, and good sense, will counteract such effects, and that you will engage again  in the pursuit of a companion, possessing such qualities as will render you a useful and happy Citizen.  You must recollect that women are capricious, and that a Revolution in the Moon, or two causes a change in their opinion; I would therefore pursue the warm track as often as the Moon undergoes a revolution <pb n="3" facs="gc010c.small.jpg"/> in twelve  months, , and for a  small premium, I would warrant your success.  No doubt you are getting tired of this subject, therefore I leave it.  <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Thos.</abbr>
                     <expan>Thomas</expan>
                  </choice> &amp; Devane King</name>, arrive here about the <date when="1820-11-25">25th of <choice>
                     <abbr>Nov.</abbr>
                     <expan>November</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date>, they bring so many of a pleasing nature, Money very scarce.  and many people entirely ruined, amongst others <name type="person">J. Fellows</name>.  My <choice>
                  <orig>domestick</orig>
                  <reg>domestic</reg>
               </choice> cares are about to be increased, before this reaches you,  I hope to be blessed with a fine Son.  Our crop is not very good we made about 4,000 Bushel Corn, and about 40.000 <add place="supralinear">
                  <unclear>lb</unclear>
               </add> Cotton.  I think upon the whole you had better visit the Macidore girl, and come and Settle on those rich <choice>
                  <orig>praires</orig>
                  <reg>prairies</reg>
               </choice>.  Devane is very anxious to see you he says you must write him.  we are not very well, we all have horrid colds.  The family all joins in love to you</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am your friend.</salute>
               <signed>Wm G Parrish</signed>
               <add place="bottom left of page">to James M King</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
