<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl288">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1850 Feb. 3, Nashville [TN] [to] A. J. Donelson [Jr.] / A. J. Donelson   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Donelson, A. J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl288</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1850 Feb. 3, Nashville [TN] [to] A. J. Donelson [Jr.] / A. J. Donelson </title>
               <author>Donelson, A. J.</author>
               <date when="1850-02-03">February 3, 1850</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Andrew J. Donelson to his son of the same name, dated February 3, 1850. Donelson writes that he was upset by a false report that Andrew Jr.  had been killed by Indians. Donelson has just returned from Germany, where he was serving as ambassador, and reports that his home and financial situation are better than he had hoped. He writes that he is worried about Andrew Jr. and that he is going to speak to a colonel about some vacation time for his son. Donelson hopes that being in danger will make Andrew Jr. a better man but  regrets that he has chosen a dangerous career.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">A. J. Donelson Papers </note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">I-D-3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">4</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl288</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Donelson, Andrew Jackson, 1799-1871</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl288a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>At home <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Feby.</abbr>
                           <expan>February</expan>
                        </choice> 3d. 1850</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Son</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your affectionate letter of the <date>1st <choice>
                     <abbr>Nov</abbr>
                     <expan>November</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date> reached us here at <name>Nashville</name> a few days ago. As I passed <choice>
                  <orig>thro</orig>
                  <reg>through</reg>
               </choice>
               <name>Washington</name> I examined your reports to the Engineer office where I heard for the first time of the report which  had circulated a few weeks that you had been killed by the Indians. You cannot conceive what painful thoughts this report created, even when I knew that it was unfounded. It leaves still the apprehension that you are in danger, and that your safety depends on a great degree of personal firmness and vigilance. These qualities you possess, but above all <pb n="2" facs="sl288b.small.jpg"/> you have learned to rely on the protection of a kind Providence which is a better <choice>
                  <orig>sheild</orig>
                  <reg>shield</reg>
               </choice> than can be supplied by human means.</p>
            <p>At the date of your letter you had not learned of my departure with all the family from <name>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Frankfort</orig>
                     <reg>Frankfurt</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name>. we sailed from <name>Southampton</name> on the <date>15th Nov.</date>  in the steam ship Hermann, and reached home in good health on the <date>10th <choice>
                     <abbr>Jany</abbr>
                     <expan>January</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date>. I found my house much <choice>
                  <orig>delapidated</orig>
                  <reg>dilapidated</reg>
               </choice>, but the farm in better condition than I expected . The negroes were in good health. Looking at my debts and means to pay them my condition is not so bad as I had anticipated. I have reason to <choice>
                  <orig>beleive</orig>
                  <reg>believe</reg>
               </choice> that I can discharge all <pb n="3" facs="sl288c.small.jpg"/> my obligations without any sale of property should the price of cotton continue good for two years. I go in a few days to <name>Mississippi</name> for the purpose of arranging my affairs there and making another crop <del type="overstrike">there</del> .</p>
            <p>The source of greatest <choice>
                  <orig>uneaseness</orig>
                  <reg>uneasiness</reg>
               </choice> to us all is your <choice>
                  <orig>seperation</orig>
                  <reg>separation</reg>
               </choice> on to <unclear/> and distant a frontier. I told <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <unclear>Cotten</unclear>
               </name> that it was too great a sacrifice and that he must <choice>
                  <orig>releive</orig>
                  <reg>receive</reg>
               </choice> you. My hope is that early in the spring you will be allowed to visit us.</p>
            <p>My time has been occupied in refurnishing my house. when this is done John will be sent to the college at Nashville and Rachel to the female Academy. your Ma will be confined again in a few days. <pb n="4" facs="sl288d.small.jpg"/> I have not yet visited our relations in the neighborhood, but have seen them all. They are well and enquire affectionately after you.</p>
            <p>I cannot think, my dear Son, of the dangers which surround you without feeling that I am somewhat to blame for you entering upon a career <del type="overstrike">which</del> thus exposed . But it is too late to remedy the evil, in any other way than to meet it manfully. If you live through it, as I pray to God that you may; it may be the means of future good. May it strengthen your constitution and enable you to return with you mind and heart made wiser and better by danger, and better qualified to serve your country &amp; friends.</p>
            <p>All of us join in love &amp; prayers for you preservation</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Yr. aff</abbr>
                     <expan>Your affectionate</expan>
                  </choice> Father</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>A J</abbr>
                        <expan>Andrew Jackson</expan>
                     </choice> Donelson</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
