<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl753">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1799 Dec. 9, Knoxville, Tennessee [to] United States Congress / John Sevier : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Sevier, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl753</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1799 Dec. 9, Knoxville, Tennessee [to] United States Congress / John Sevier</title>
               <author> Sevier, John</author>
               <date when="1799-12-09">December 9, 1799</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is an open letter dated December 9, 1799 from the governor of Tennessee, John Sevier to the congress of the United States.  The subject of the letter is a ferry crossing of the Clinch river, and the marking out of a road as an alternative to the people's current situation in its regard.  Specifically, the documents requests that the issue of marking out a road as stipulated by the fifth article of the treaty of Holston with the Cherokee Indians be laid before the President of the United States.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor John Sevier Papers			</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">7</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl753</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Sevier, John, 1745-1815</term>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor (1796-1801 : Sevier)</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr89016779"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Sevier, John, 1745-1815</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl753a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Knoxville</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>December 9th 1799</date>
               <salute>Gentlemen</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>By the inclosed law you will be informed, that the Legislature which passed it have made it my duty, to lay it through you before the President of the <name>United States</name> and to request him to appoint persons of the description therein contained to mark out the road Stipulated for by the fifth article of the treaty of <name>holston</name> and in conformity thereto I instruct you to lay it before him, and to request him to make an appointment of such persons as are therein described, and for the purposes therein contemplated.__</p>
            <p>This is all that is positively <choice>
                  <orig>injoined</orig>
                  <reg>enjoined</reg>
               </choice> on one as a duty yet I think it necessary to apprise you that it is probable that some persons who are acquainted with its concerns will make Statements to the President against his making Such an appointment, the Statements alluded to I am taught to believe will be to the following effect, "that at the Treaty of Tellics in the talks public or private between the Commissioners of the United States, and the Cherokees the latter were given to understand that the present Ferry across Clinch, which is much to their emolument should in future be the ferry across that river under the fifth article of the Treaty of Holston,"__</p>
            <p>The answer to Such Statements is, that nations are governed in their intercouse with each other by the Treaties formed between them and not by the conversation that passes between the negotiators while they are forming <pb n="2" facs="sl753b.small.jpg"/>    If the President should say to you, "Since the people of Tennessee are dissatisfied with the passing of the Clinch at the present ferry which way to they wish it to pass,"  The answer is to be found in the act itself namely The levelest paying as much regard to distance as shall accord with the conveniency of passing the water causes at fords and the mountains at the gaps most easy of assent" and such certainty is the true construction of the article of the Treaty, and such I trust will be the Execution of it__ But should the President ask "what are the particular objections to passing Clinch at the present ferry" The answer is, first that a toll or <choice>
                  <orig>feriage</orig>
                  <reg>ferriage</reg>
               </choice> is exacted under Military <choice>
                  <orig>coertion</orig>
                  <reg>coercion</reg>
               </choice> for the benefit of the Cherokees in violation of their stipulation for a free road__  If any have a right to exact any sum however small, they may exact any other sum however large, and thereby deprive the Citizens of the United States of the benefit of the Stipulation for a free road.__  The principle is the same, extended to a cent a pound or a million__</p>
            <p>Secondly, That it takes cash from the pockets of those who are compelled to pay this ferriage for the benefit of the indians, and is Singularly oppressive to the movers to <name>Mero</name> district with their families, wagons, baggage and Stock as much so that many of them heretofore have been compelled to fall a part of their Stock or other property under its value to pay it__</p>
            <p>Thirdly the delay unavoidable attending the passing ferries with families, <choice>
                  <orig>waggons</orig>
                  <reg>wagons</reg>
               </choice>, baggage and Stock, and the consequent <choice>
                  <orig>expence</orig>
                  <reg>epense</reg>
               </choice> of such delay__ <pb n="3" facs="sl753c.small.jpg"/> Fourthly, the dangers incident to a deep and wide ferry__ Fifthly, That the road leading by it is more hilly and circuitous than could be marked out to pass the Clinch at a very good ford only about two miles above it, and at this ford the Indians claim the land only upon the north side their claim upon the South having been extinguished by the treaty of Tellico.__ </p>
            <p>These reasons must convince you, if you did not already know it, that the people of Tennessee would feel a great grievance <choice>
                  <orig>rumoved</orig>
                  <reg>removed</reg>
               </choice> in the road only being changed from the ferry to this ford, which is generally passable about eight months in the year.__  I would not be understood by the above observations to give an opinion that this ford is the place where persons authorized to lay out the road the levelist and shortest way as the <gap/>
               <unclear>document is torn</unclear> would take it across the Clinch, I only mean to say if no more can be obtained that the road crossing at the ford in <choice>
                  <orig>preferance</orig>
                  <reg>preference</reg>
               </choice> of the ferry will be a great relief to the people and for the above reasons.__</p>
            <p>And again if the President will not make an appointment of Commissioners to lay out the road in the latitude as contemplated by the act, nor order that it shall pass at the Ford in preference of the ferry, cant a middle ground be taken namely for the Indians to keep their ferry and their road open to, and from it, and for the treaty road to be opened by the ford.__</p>
            <p>This would <choice>
                  <orig>aford</orig>
                  <reg>afford</reg>
               </choice> a choice to <add>monied</add>  travelers and give great relief to movers and poor people, But observe I do not advise this, only Suggest it in case nothing better can be done <pb n="4" facs="sl753d.small.jpg"/> And again should the President <del>of the United States</del>  have reasons, which I cannot discover or think possible for <del>continuing</del>   the present passway from Washington to Mero district by way of the ferry being in future considered as the road established by the fifth article of the Treaty of Holston, you will in my judgment consult the true interest of the people of Tennessee in pointing out to him the propriety and necessity of <del>(his so declaring by some written instruments, because if he passes the act over without appointing some)</del>   his appointing Commissioners to Straighten and mark it__ </p>
            <p>For you will observe unless he does appoint persons to mark the road, that the Commissioners appointed by the act have no authority to act under it, in other words they will have no authority to open it, or to exact a toll upon it for keeping it in repair.__<gap/>
               <unclear>document is torn</unclear>  present state it is passed with difficulty and must be daily growing worse, so long as there shall be no law to authorize the opening and repairing it,__ That this is a Subject in <del>upon</del> which the Legislative and people of Tennessee feel much affected <add>is well known to you all</add>   hence you will see the propriety of giving me the earliest and fullest information of your proceedings, and of the determination of the President thereon.__</p>
            <p>It may not <add>however</add>   be unnecessary to remind you, that the Legislature of 1797, complained of the ferry across Clinch as a grievance in their memorial to the President and Congress, and that the Legislature of 98 presented the Subject to you again in their instructions by Resolutions, and now in 99 it comes again before you in form of the present act, this may cannot but convince the President that the people consider themselves labouring under a great <choice>
                  <orig>grievence</orig>
                  <reg>grievance</reg>
               </choice>, from which they have a right founded on treaty to be relieved and redressed</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
