<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0027">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1812 Dec. 31, Fort Massac, Ill. [to] Return J. Meigs, Highwassee Garrison / John Ross : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Ross, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0027</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1812 Dec. 31, Fort Massac, Ill. [to] Return J. Meigs, Highwassee Garrison / John Ross </title>
               <author>Ross, John</author>
               <date when="1812-12-31">December 31, 1812</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter written in 1812 by John Ross to Return J. Meigs, Agent to the Cherokee Indians, Ross describes his trip down the Tennessee River from Fort Massac.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0027</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Government relations</term>
               <term>Indians, treatment of</term>
               <term>Indian agents</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n82214557"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Ross, John, 1790-1866</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0027a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Fort Massac</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>December 31st 1812.</date>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We arrived at this place last evening and have this day received the public stores left at this place by Mr <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Saml</abbr>
                     <expan>Samuel</expan>
                  </choice> Riley</name>_we had a safe voyage down to this place. When at Colberts I have been informed that a party of whitemen who have built block houses on <name>Tennessee</name> river near the mouth, had killed three cherokees that was descending the river about the 1st <choice>
                  <abbr>Inst</abbr>
                  <expan>Instant</expan>
               </choice>._</p>
            <p>About forty miles above this place on the 28th Inst. we was <choice>
                  <orig>haled</orig>
                  <reg>hailed</reg>
               </choice> by a party of white men, and desired us to go to them, I inquired for what, one of them observed to give them the news. I told him we had no news worth their attention_ discovering that I was not disposed to go to them, he observed that they were <add>directed</add> by a Garrison of men near that place to stop every boats descending <add>the river</add> to <choice>
                  <orig>examin</orig>
                  <reg>examine</reg>
               </choice> if any Indians was on board <pb n="2" facs="pa0027b.small.jpg"/> as they were not permitted to come about that place, and said if we did not go to them, that they would come to us, when they were answered to come on, he then observed that a boat had passed early that morning who had informed them that a party of Indians had followed them during the night before and said D__n his soul if the two men who then stood behind me was not Indians &amp; that he would raise a company of men to pursue &amp; kill us, I told <del type="overstrike">they</del>
               <add>him the two men were</add> Spaniards, and <add>I </add> did not regard their threats, he desired to hear one of them speak. Accordingly <name>Peter</name> spoke to them. they insisted that it was an Indian boat &amp; mounted their horses &amp; galloped off, a few miles below we concluded it was good policy to let <name>Kalsatee</name> out of the boat, &amp; accordingly did, &amp; appointed a place to meet him, but was disappointed in meeting, until yesterday morning the old man overtook us where we waited <add>for</add> him, one mile above the mouth of Tenn, after a disagreeable walk of about thirty miles_They however did not pursue us but am convinced that it may be imputed <pb n="3" facs="pa0027c.small.jpg"/> to the independent manner in which I answered them, which confounded their apprehension of it being an Indian boat, the report of the three men being killed is confirmed at this place. but not certain to what nation they belong. Those men are represented to be a <choice>
                  <orig>sett </orig>
                  <reg>set</reg>
               </choice>of <unclear>Bandits</unclear> placed there by <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl </abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice>Ramsey</name> of Kentucky or Ohio (whose character is equally atrocious) to commit depredations on Indians indiscriminate in place of being useful to the Government they are injurious_ means ought to be resorted to, to prevent further murders of inoffensive Indians until that period it will be quite imprudent &amp; unsafe for Indians to attempt to descend the river.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have the honour to be with Sentiments of Respect &amp; conside <gap agent="damage"/> Sir <choice>
                     <abbr>yr Obt Servt</abbr>
                     <expan>your Obedient Servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Jno</abbr>
                        <expan>John</expan>
                     </choice> Ross</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <note>
                     <p>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>NB</abbr>
                           <expan>Nota Bene</expan>
                        </choice> I have received all the articles specified in <choice>
                           <abbr>Lt</abbr>
                           <expan>Lieutenant</expan>
                        </choice>
                        <name> J Prices</name> receipt except the flat bottom boat. One beaver trap &amp; four tin cups which are miss<gap agent="damage"/>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </add>
               <pb n="4" facs="pa0027d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Col</abbr>
                              <expan>Colonel</expan>
                           </choice>
                           <name>Return J. Meigs</name>
                        </name>Agent for <name>Cherokees </name>
                        <unclear>Pr mail}</unclear> Highwassee Garrison</addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <name>John Ross</name>' letter 31st December 1812 from <name>Fort Massac</name>___ Had received the public stores &amp;c__ Indians killed as reported </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
