<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch049">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dr. [Elizur] Butler's statement respecting his interview with Col[onel] Sanford, 1831 June 20, Camp Gilmer, [Murray County, Georgia] : a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch049</idno>
            <idno>oclc: 44845332</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The University of Tennessee Special Collections Library.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Dr. [Elizur] Butler's statement respecting his interview with Col[onel] Sanford, 1831 June 20, Camp Gilmer, [Murray County, Georgia]</title>
               <date when="1831-06-20">June 20, 1831</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">Statement by Elizur Butler, Christian missionary living in the Cherokee Nation, extracted from a letter dated June 20, 1831.  Butler describes a meeting that took place between himself and Colonel Sanford at Camp Gilmer. Colonel Sanford voices his disapproval of missionaries and threatens to imprison Butler again or forcibly remove him and his family if he does not move. Butler states that Samuel Worcester, another missionary to the Cherokee, and himself are intent on staying in the Nation until they are removed by force.</note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">State Library Cherokee Collection)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">29</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch049</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital  Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Missionaries</term>
               <term>Murray County (Ga.)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch049a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <add place="top">N.<lb/>
                  <name type="person">Dr. Butler</name>'s statement respecting his interview with <name type="person">Col. Sanford</name>, at <name type="place">Camp Gilmer</name>, when he went to deliver himself to the guard, in compliance with his promise, when arrested on the <date when="--05-07">7th of May</date>, contained in a letter dated <date when="1831-06-20">June 20th, 1831</date>.
                  </add>
            </p>
            <p>I arrived at head quarters on Friday, the first. <name type="person">Col. Sanford</name> told me I might have considered the letters I received as absolving me from the promise made by me when previously arrested.  I told him I did not consider them so, for there was no reference made in them to my former arrest, and that I was under a moral obligation to fulfil my engagement.  He said there was no need of descending to so metaphysical points; but that he was glad to see me so scrupulous, and that he would also be glad to see me equally scrupulous on other points.  He was highly displeased with the course some missionaries were taking.  He accused missionaries and Christians as being guilty of nearly all the evils existing in the world; and called them political fire-brands, who were sending their baneful influence through the <name type="place">United States</name>.  He said, also, that they were engaged in a systematic plan to unite church and<pb n="2" facs="ch049b.small.jpg"/>state; and many other things equally ridiculous.  I expected for an hour, whilst engaged conversation, that he would order me to be arrested, as the ten day allowed for my removal had already expired.  Indeed  he once said, "As you are here you may as well stay."  Very well, sir, I replied, it will be just as you say.  He endeavored for some time to induce me to promise to remove my family from the disputed territory; but I told him positively that I would make no such engagement.  He enquired particularly respecting <name type="person">Mrs. Butler</name>'s health; and, if asked, would probably say, that it was on her account, and through kindness to me, and in hopes that I would finally consent to remove, that he suffered me to return home.  The permission was, however, voluntary in him.  I did not request it.
               </p>
            <p>In the course of his conversation with me, <name type="person">Col. Sanford</name> that the missionaries could make such arrangements as they pleased for their families, but that if they continued where they were, he would shortly turn them and their effects into the highway, and put very different families into their dwellings; and added, that it would probably be better for missionaries and Christians to wander in the mountains and caves of the earth, clad in sheep-skins and goat-skins, as they did of old; and that this would probably produce an increase of piety.  He told me that if I did not get out of the way, he would arrest me again in a few days.  With our present feelings,<pb n="3" facs="ch049c.small.jpg"/>
               <name type="person">Mr. Worcester</name> and myself, with our families, will remain until removed by force, unless we receive different advice from the Committee.  Should my family be turned out of the house, they will be comfortably accommodated at the nearest neighbors until they can be removed to some other station.  When arrested, I shall doubtless have to walk eighty or an hundred miles, and perhaps shall be hand-cuffed, or have a chain around my neck.
               </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
