<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl185">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1831 July 9, Nashville [to] John Gill Jr., Philadelphia Pa. / Joseph P. Brown    : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Brown, Joseph Porter</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl185</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51173814</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1831 July 9, Nashville [to] John Gill Jr., Philadelphia Pa. / Joseph P. Brown    </title>
               <author>Brown, Joseph Porter </author>
               <date when="1831-07-09">July 9, 1831</date>
               <extent>8p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated July 9, 1831 to John Gill Jr. from Joseph P. Brown regarding various business deals including stocks and real estate.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Joseph Brown Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1-8</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl185</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Business enterprises</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Brown, Joseph Porter</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl185a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                     <date when="1831-07-09">July 9th 1831</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Yours of the <date when="--06-25">25th June</date>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>ulto.</abbr>
                  <expan>ultimo</expan>
               </choice> came to hand this morning, and found me just sitting down to write for <name type="person"> Mr. Trabue</name> who contemplates starting for your city tomorrow—</p>
            <p>I would have written you immediately on my return home, but a difficulty presented itself in the execution of the deed for the property which not yet being removed prevents me from forwarding it at this time a circumstance I regret exceedingly on my own account as well as yours—</p>
            <p>It seems necessary by the certificate that my wife must be of <emph>"full age"</emph> before her signature can be good &amp; valid, now if this means 21 years, as it most undoubtedly does, we just lack 2 months of the time from tomorrow, She having been born on the <date when="1810-09-10">10th of September 1810</date>, Jane will be of full age 2 days afterwards, so that there will be a delay unexpected and disagreeable to all parties. I had taken the deed with the intention of having it executed, when this <pb n="2" facs="sl185b.small.jpg"/> examination of it satisfied me it would not answer <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> everything was fact beyond a doubt— As soon as the period mentioned arrives I will have it done in such manner as to secure it to you ⁁ <add place="supralinear">&amp; your successors</add> fully &amp; unequivocally forever. In the mean time my family, <add place="supralinear">with myself</add>, express their regret that the formality of law prevents them from executing these papers without this unreasonable delay —</p>
            <p>The Mayor of our city has been absent for some weeks on a mission (for the Indians) from the general government, which would have forever-led me ⁁<add place="supralinear">still further</add> from having the deed authenticated, In the interim however we have a mayor pro tem, but as your laws are so particular it would be best perhaps to wait for the return of the mayor elect, it is likely he will be here before the 10th <choice>
                  <abbr>Septr</abbr>
                  <expan>September</expan>
               </choice> and you may rest assured that <del type="overstrike">it</del> ⁁<add place="supralinear">the deed</add> will be transmitted without any further delay, or deposited in any person's hands here that you may think proper to select.</p>
            <p>I enclose you, Fifty dollars which you will reserve $45 and credit balance to <name type="person">Shirley</name>
               <name type="person">Brown</name> &amp; <name type="person">Walker</name> on your Books— <pb n="3" facs="sl185c.small.jpg"/> All our goods have arrived, we have opened  however only a part of them, the house being thrown into Confusion by the addition of a third story, which our Landlord is making to the house, we have nevertheless sold about $6000 since we received the  stock and as far as they have opened my partner's &amp; others have adjudged it the best selected stock in the City indeed business is always dull at this season, and it owing entirely to the style &amp; character of the goods that we have made these sales, the men not Coming down to purchase any them but groceries have been literally <unclear/> to make a purchase of goods, and which must do them good at <unclear>home</unclear>— we Could have sold 6 or 8000 more ⁁<add place="suprelinear">to</add>
               <emph>new accounts </emph> and I believe to good <unclear>rules</unclear>, as they purchased Subsequently at other houses on the houses offered us, but we declined, not being <emph>entirely satisfied</emph> about the punctuality of the men though we believed them perfectly solvent— In reply to your inquiries I know but little of <name type="person">Mr Bradford's</name> affairs, hearing of his failure at <name type="place">Louisville</name> I hurried home fearing that in the vortex Mr Shirley might have suffered, as Mr B had the settlement of the debts of Shirley West &amp; Co. but I found Mr S has seen into this matter <pb n="4" facs="sl185d.small.jpg"/> in time, and from all I can learn, there is enough retained by <name type="person">Mr West</name> to pay the debts of that firm and of West Moss &amp; Co. Some money say $8 or $9.000 dollars has already been remitted in Cash &amp; good paper to <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Philad</abbr>
                     <expan>Philadelphia</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> in discharge of a part of the old debts, and the balance I expect will be met with certainly if not ⁁<add place="supralinear">exactly</add> with promptness— I know of none who will suffer here by Bradford save one or two sharers, the heaviest loss will fall upon <name type="place">New Orleans</name>, the amount I am not <unclear>apprized</unclear> of or on whom it may fall, <choice>
                  <orig>Rumour</orig>
                  <reg>Rumor</reg>
               </choice> with her thousand  tongues is at work, but vague &amp; uncertain as this species of information is  it will not do to rely upon it — Mr West I presume will not go to New Orleans untill the business of his concerns <del type="overstrike">are</del> ⁁ is settled up, which will probably take  more time than he anticipates, — Mr Shirley will lose about $1400 by Bradford, the balance if due by him to Mr S out of the old business, for part the latter's profits— Bradford is now superintending the building of a steam Boat at this place &amp; owned by Jas Woods &amp; Co. &amp; to be  commanded by Bradford, I should judge from this that his mercantile career is at an end— By the bye what was only rumour <pb n="5" facs="sl185e.small.jpg"/> yesterday is confirmed today by a letter from New Orleans viz that B. F. West has failed in consequence of his responsibilities for Bradford, ⁁<add place="supralinear">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>amt</abbr>
                     <expan>amount</expan>
                  </choice> said to be $20000.</add>
               <name type="person">N &amp; J Dick</name> are also in for a considerate amount but they can stand these things— The 2 notes of Bradford for 1400 and odd dollars Mr Shirley informs me is in your possession, they will be paid at maturity without infringing upon Mr S's interest in this house he having other assets to meet them with, and we Calculate most certainly upon fulfilling our engagements promptly <unclear>—</unclear> I do not know what effect the late news about his Brother's failure will have upon Mr. West's intention to <del type="overstrike"/>
               <add place="supralinear">remove to</add> New Orleans time will <choice>
                  <orig>develope</orig>
                  <reg>develop</reg>
               </choice> these matters—</p>
            <p>You have doubtless heard of <name type="person">C M Connell's</name> failure, he is paying his Creditors 60 to  80 <choice>
                  <abbr>cts</abbr>
                  <expan>cents</expan>
               </choice> in the dollar, his endorsement I suppose will not be paid— Dick has returned from Orleans, but I do not know whether he is doing any thing or not— At <name type="place">Louisville</name> I called to see <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Thos</abbr>
                     <expan>Thomas</expan>
                  </choice> Powell</name>, who is sick as that place he is in a very precarious Situation and I fear will hardly recover, it is likely he will go <pb n="6" facs="sl185f.small.jpg"/> into a decline, induced ⁁<add place="supralinear">I believe</add> by the <del type="overstrike"/> abuse of his Constitution in early life ⁁<add place="supralinear">from the too frequent use of <unclear>mercurial</unclear> preparations</add> he is under the case of <name type="person">Doct. Baum</name> a celebrated physician there and may perhaps recover his wanted strength, but coming from a family where weakness of the lungs &amp; chest were partially hereditary and Complaining withal of a pain in the breast, I think <del type="overstrike">he</del> a complete recovery problematical— I have not heard of him for several weeks and do not know his present Situation—</p>
            <p>I found my family and friends in good health with the exception of <name type="person">Mr Mills</name> my brother-in law, he had been Confined several weeks previous to my return with a general decline if I might so call it, and a week ago we Committed his earthly remains to the tomb, he has left a wife &amp; child, to mourn his separation from them, at a period when they were indulging in the fondest hopes of lasting happiness—</p>
            <p>I have now I believe in my prolix way attempted to answer all your enquiries and give you such other information as I thought <pb n="7" facs="sl185g.small.jpg"/> would interest you — I will add that <name type="person">Soving</name> has purchased out the stock of <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jno</abbr>
                     <expan>John</expan>
                  </choice> McClelland</name> deceased <name type="place">Russellville <choice>
                     <abbr> Ky</abbr>
                     <expan>Kentucky</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>, is in business there with his brother in law<name type="person"> G W Whitaker </name> and I have no doubt you will get the money due the  estate of <name type="person">Campbell</name> very shortly—</p>
            <p>This will be handed you by Mr ⁁<add place="supralinear">E</add> Trabue one of the successors to West Moss &amp; Co. it is a good house, sell them all you can, I am confident they will not disappoint you, I merely give this as information to you, they have <gap agent="damage"/> to the house for letters &amp; Mr Shirley <del type="overstrike">has</del> requested me to give  them letters to you and others, The weather is excessively warm, I hope the reasons given for this delay of the deed will be satisfactory, at all events keep Cool! and it will be forthcoming at the time specified it would be of no ⁁<add place="supralinear">more</add> use if made out sooner than the one you have in your possession, indeed it would be an ⁁<add place="supralinear">exact</add> copy, except the certificate </p>
            <closer>
               <salute> Yours Sincerely</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">J P Brown</name>
                  <add place="left of signature">PS Present my best respects to Mrs. Campbell and the young Ladies my family also desire to be remembered to them }</add>
               </signed>
               <pb n="8" facs="sl185h.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">John Gill <choice>
                           <abbr>Junr Esqr</abbr>
                           <expan>Junior Esquire</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>care Messers Gilo Ferguson &amp; Co</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Merchants</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>
                     <add place="left of address">W E Trabue}</add>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address">1831 <name type="person">Joseph P Brown</name>
                  <lb/> July 9th <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Recd</abbr>
                     <expan>received</expan>
                  </choice> 25th <lb/> answered August 2nd</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
