<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0031">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1813 Aug. 6, Highwassee Garrison, [to] John Armstrong, Secretary of
                    War / Return J. Meigs : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Meigs, Return J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0031</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 44923606</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of
                        Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
                        teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
                        included in the text. For all other use contact the Special Collections
                        Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue,
                        Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1813 Aug. 6, Highwassee Garrison, [to] John Armstrong, Secretary
                        of War / Return J. Meigs</title>
               <author>Meigs, Return J.</author>
               <date when="1813-08-06">August 6, 1813</date>
               <extent> 6p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter from Return J. Meigs, Agent to
                        the Cherokee Nation, to John Armstrong, Secretary of War. Meigs asks
                        permission to employ the Cherokees as soldiers to protect themselves, and
                        their property from the Creek Indians and the British.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0031</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1
                    spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward
                    which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Government relations</term>
               <term>Creek Indians -- Warfare</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n92008354"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Meigs, Return Jonathan, 1740-1823</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0031a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Highwassee Garrison</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>6th August
                        1813</date>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have received your letter covering a Talk from the Big Warrior to <name>Colonel
                        Hawkins</name> &amp; have endeavored to make a proper rise of it here._ I
                    have also received your letter of the 16th July <choice>
                  <abbr>ult.</abbr>
                  <expan>ultimo</expan>
               </choice>
                    accompanied by two letters addressed to you by the honorable <name>Mr
                        Fort</name> relating to certain salt peter caves &amp; shall attend to your
                    observations on the subject._</p>
            <p>On the 22nd of May last I addressed a letter to you on the subject of the payment
                    of the Cherokee annuity for the current year. I have lately received a letter
                    from the receiver of public monies in <name>Madison County</name> M. Territory
                    informing that he can probably furnish the amount required for the object by the
                    last of September next. I therefore propose to pay the annuity to the Cherokees
                    sometime in October next provided it shall meet your approbation. It has never
                    been considered proper to pay out the money except in the presence of the<name>
                        U</name> States Troops_ at present there are no Troops of any description
                    here the few that were here were withdrawn about ten days ago to join their
                    Corps, Riflemen <pb n="2" facs="pa0031b.small.jpg"/> ordered it is said to the <choice>
                  <abbr>N</abbr>
                  <expan>North</expan>
               </choice>. Western Army__ It is very doubtful whether <del type="overstrike">Troops</del> peace can be preserved on this extreme frontier without the
                    aid of Troops. The civil war amongst the <name>Creeks</name> has placed the
                        <name>Cherokees</name> in a <choice>
                  <orig>disagreable</orig>
                  <reg>disagreeable</reg>
               </choice>
                    situation, should <add>the</add> insurgent get the ascending they will if
                    possible corrupt the Cherokees for the hostilities of the insurgent party is in
                    fact against the <name>United States</name>_ A number of the well disposed
                    Creeks have fled to the Cherokee Villages for safety. I have advised the
                    Cherokee Chiefs not to let any of the insurgent party come into their country
                    because it will subject them to the suspicion of the white people on the
                    frontier__ The friendly Creeks <choice>
                  <orig>applyed</orig>
                  <reg>applied</reg>
               </choice> to the
                    Cherokees for aid &amp; a number armed but I believe none of them did march. The
                    headmen of the Cherokees advised first to wait the effect of pacific measures
                    &amp; have appointed a meeting of their National Council for that purpose_ Since
                    the removal of the troops the Cherokee feel themselves unsafe_ their northern
                    boundary line is more than 250 miles in length_ A number of Intruders are on
                    their land, others are preparing to go on, nothing but military force can
                    restrain these aggressions_ one strong company of troops, one part stationed
                    here &amp; another part in Tellico would <pb n="3" facs="pa0031c.small.jpg"/> perhaps be sufficient to
                    keep peace on this long line by frequent <choice>
                  <orig>patroling</orig>
                  <reg>patrolling</reg>
               </choice>. The conduct of the Cherokees has been decidedly friendly__at
                    the commencement of the war. Several young chiefs offered to raise
                        <add>men</add> &amp; offer their service to the government_ I asked a young
                    chief whether he <choice>
                  <orig>thot</orig>
                  <reg>thought</reg>
               </choice>, in case the Cherokees should
                    be employed they could be restrained from <choice>
                  <orig>commiting</orig>
                  <reg>committing</reg>
               </choice> acts of Barbarity, he <choice>
                  <orig>replyed</orig>
                  <reg>replied</reg>
               </choice>
                    that they could be restrained_ I would not suffer them to act except against the
                        <choice>
                  <orig>Britchish</orig>
                  <reg>British</reg>
               </choice> &amp; their Allies__ If the
                        <name>British</name> continue their savage warfare what can be done to
                    prevent it? Shall we suffer it? it is difficult for humanity to answer_ It may
                    be asked what interest have the Cherokees in this war I answer they owe the U.
                    States more than they are able to repay_ The United States have saved their
                    nation from perdition_ they have raised them up from a state of hunters to <choice>
                  <orig>Hurdsmen</orig>
                  <reg>Herdsmen</reg>
               </choice>, Cultivators &amp; manufactures_ While under
                    the English they learned nothing useful, they acquired nothing from the English
                    but vices which placed their own in the light of comparative virtues, they then
                    left them confirmed in their savage customs &amp; manners &amp; without a single
                        <pb n="4" facs="pa0031d.small.jpg"/> stipulation for their preservation_ The United States then
                    took them by the hand &amp; made them happy compared with their former
                    condition_ There is no doubt the insurgent Creeks are acting on concert with the
                    English <choice>
                  <abbr>thro</abbr>
                  <expan>through</expan>
               </choice> the northern Indians. every disaster
                    on our side is magnified &amp; touted to the Southern Tribes who for want of
                    proper information are liable to be deceived &amp; acted on by the events of the
                    moment.__</p>
            <p>With the greatest deference &amp; respect &amp; with pure motives I beg leave to
                    suggest whether it would not be good policy to make some provisional arrangement
                    for the employment of a good number of the Cherokees_ six or eight companies of
                    100 men in each having 4 officers to each company The whole making two
                    Battalions having one Major to each Battalion_ all the officers including that
                    of Majors should be Cherokees_ The other field officers should be white men
                    calculated for such Troops. Such character might be found__ These Corps might be
                    employed <choice>
                  <orig>seperately</orig>
                  <reg>separately</reg>
               </choice> or combined but more
                    especially as light Troops, it would preclude the necessity of detailing &amp;
                    some times almost breaking up the regular Corp for desultory <pb n="5" facs="pa0031e.small.jpg"/>
                    service._</p>
            <p>In some of my former communications to the war department I stated my opinion
                    that it would be difficult to keep these people as idle spectators of the war it
                    being well known that they have a passion for war, &amp; that if the war should
                    be continued they will if possible have a hand in it some where_. By taking a
                    respectable number of their best people into service the fidelity of the whole
                    nation will be secured &amp; they will render a service they justly owe the
                    United States</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am sir very respectfully <choice>
                     <abbr>yr obt</abbr>
                     <expan>your obedient</expan>
                  </choice>
                        servant</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Return J. Meigs</name>
               </signed>
               <add>P.S. It
                        may perhaps be <choice>
                     <abbr>thot</abbr>
                     <expan>thought</expan>
                  </choice>, extraordinary, but I am
                        confident the Cherokees can be well officered by Cherokees in the grades I
                        have mentioned. <choice>
                     <abbr>RJM</abbr>
                     <expan>Return Jonathan Meigs</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>The Honorable<name> John Armstrong</name> Secretary of War</addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="6" facs="pa0031f.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Letter to General Armstrong <lb/>
                        Secretary of War <lb/> Subject <lb/> Arming the Cherokees <lb/> 6th of
                        August 1813</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
