<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm048">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Drawing of Tellico Blockhouse, American Federal period trading
			 and military post from 1794-1807, Lower Little Tennessee River] : a
			 machine-readable transcription</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Tara Hottenstein</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. 3k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>mm048</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 45104618</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Museum, University of
				Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Drawing of Tellico Blockhouse, American Federal period
				trading and military post from 1794-1807, Lower Little Tennessee River]</title>
               <date/>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This is a drawing of the Tellico Blockhouse.
				The Tellico Blockhouse was constructed in 1794-95 adjacent to the earlier Fort
				Loudoun at the confluence of the Tellico and Little Tennessee Rivers in what is
				presently Monroe County as a federal outpost. In 1805 federal officials and
				Overhill Cherokees negotiated a treaty at the Tellico Blockhouse which moved
				the federal agency south to the mouth of the Hiawassee. By 1807 the federal
				government abandoned Tellico and moved the rest of its agency to the Hiawassee
				River post, the new center of the Overhill Cherokee settlement. Excavations of
				the Tellico Blockhouse were conducted by the University of Tennessee from
				1972-1974 in anticipation of the flooding of the lower Little Tennessee River
				by the Tellico Dam Reservoir. Excavations of the Blockhouse were conducted
				under contract with the National Park Service and the Tennessee Valley
				Authority (TVA). Principal investigator, Alfred K. Guthe. Field Director,
				Richard R. Polhemus.</note>
               <note type="collection">Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note type="document">mm048</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Charts, drawings, etc.</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</term>
               <term>Salvage archaeology</term>
               <term>Historic sites</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Military bases</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mm048.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Artists reconstruction of Tellico blockhouse, American
				  Federal period military and trading post on Lower Little Tennessee River,
				  occupied 1794-1807. Artist unknown. This information was provided by the Frank
				  H. McClung Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
