<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tl209">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1828 Oct. 2, Tuskaloosa, Alabama [to] Governor [Sam] Houston, State of Tennessee / John Murphy: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Murphy, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>tl209</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 49945038</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1828 Oct. 2, Tuskaloosa, Alabama [to] Governor [Sam] Houston, State of Tennessee / John Murphy</title>
               <author>Murphy, John</author>
               <date when="1828-10-02">October 2, 1828</date>
               <extent>4 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a letter, dated October 2, 1828, from Alabama Governor John Murphy to Sam Houston, governor of Tennessee (1827-1829).  Murphy states that recent act passed by the US Congress called for the opening of a canal at the Muscle Shoals in Alabama.  Murphy writes to solicit the cooperation and assistance of the state of Tennessee, not only in building the proposed canal, but also to build a railroad running through the valleys of the Mississippi River.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Sam Houston Correspondence</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> Jackson - Woods, 1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">tl209</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Canals -- Design and construction</term>
               <term>Railroads -- Designs and construction</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Alabama</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr95008438"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Murphy, John, 1786-1841</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tl209a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Executive Department <name type="place">Alabama</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tuskaloosa</name>
                     <date when="1828-10-02">Oct. 2d. 1828</date>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>His Excellency</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Governor Houston</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>  State of <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>You will excuse the liberty which I take by the present attempt to open a correspondence with your Excellency on a subject which may prove highly important to both States, and certainly not less desirable to the State over which you have the <choice>
                  <orig>honour</orig>
                  <reg>honor</reg>
               </choice> to preside, than to the State of Alabama. By a very munificent Act of the last Session of the Congress of the <name type="place">United States</name>   the source of a very considerable fan has been placed at the disposition of the State of Alabama for the opening a Canal around the obstruction of the Navigation at the <name type="place">Muscle Shoals</name>, a work highly important to this State &amp; I should suppose not less interesting to the State of Tennessee. But even the accomplishment of this object, so much and so long desired, and which must unquestionably prove of so great utility to a large portion of the States of Alabama and Tennessee, will not affect <choice>
                  <orig>every thing</orig>
                  <reg>everything</reg>
               </choice> which   I hope may be conveniently done for their advantage, and which will give to these interesting portions of both States, the full benefit of their great natural resources.  The improvement at the Muscle Shoals, will open the great Market of <name type="place">New Orleans</name> to <name type="place">East Tennessee</name> , and to a large part of the State of Alabama on the <name type="place">Tennessee River</name>. I say open it, for the precarious and temporary communication which nature has furnished with that Market, is <pb n="2" facs="tl209b.small.jpg"/> attended with so much <choice>
                  <orig>difficutly</orig>
                  <reg>difficulty</reg>
               </choice>, expense, and uncertainty, as to render it but a small convenience in comparison to the improved and constant Navigation which is contemplated by the Canal.  The Market of New Orleans, however, important as it must ever be in general, will be frequently attended with material disadvantages.  It must often be overtaken in the produce which Tennessee and Alabama would have occasion to lend to it, and this state of things must become continually more perplexing, as the improvement of the immense valley of the <name type="place">Mississippi</name> progresses.  The City of <name type="place">Mobile</name> would be more free from this inconvenience, &amp; will in general, I think, afford a better Market for the produce of this State of and East Tennessee, than the City of New Orleans.  There would also be the advantage, of passing on that commercial route through the consuming Country, for many of the Articles, and giving to the grower the advantage of selling immediately to the consumer. At all events, by opening both Markets, very singular benefits must be obtained, and then would be afforded to our <unclear>citizens</unclear> every possible means of selling their produce at a fair price, and perhaps of making exchanges highly beneficial to all parties. But I extend merely  to hint at these subjects in the present communication. An intercourse with Mobile must be opened by Canal or Rail Road, connecting the Navigable waters of the Tennessee River with Steam Boat Navigation on the Alabama. I am inclined to think that a rail road would be far preferable to a Canal, and indeed nature seems to have furnished <pb n="3" facs="tl209c.small.jpg"/> every facility for a rail Road along the  <choice>
                  <orig>vallies</orig>
                  <reg>valleys</reg>
               </choice> running in the direction of the point of communication with the Alabama.  There is plenty of the best iron ore and mineral coal on the route, which might be of use in the construction of the road itself, and afterwards furnish important Articles of  home supply; and commence along that road.  The <choice>
                  <orig>Vallies</orig>
                  <reg>Valleys</reg>
               </choice> are very <unclear>hard</unclear> and of considerable length, so that in them the expense of graduating the Road would be very inconsiderable.  There will no when be much <choice>
                  <orig>elivation</orig>
                  <reg>elavation</reg>
               </choice> to overcome, and should it be thought best to construct the Rail Road of wood, very durable materials of that description will be found at hand  along the whole route.  The liberal donation which we have received from the General Government, together with assistance from the State of Tennessee ,⁁<add place="supralinear">over</add> in a small degree proportioned to the benefits to be derived by the State from these improvements, opening to it alike and at its option, the commerce of Mobile and New Orleans, would enable the State of Alabama, or both states in conjoined operation, to accomplish the Canal at the Muscle Shoals, and the rail Road from some convenient point on the Tennessee, to Steam Boat navigation on the Alabama. I cannot but believe that even these two objects accomplished, incalculable benefits to the present and future <pb n="4" facs="tl209d.small.jpg"/> condition of the Country would be effectually secured. It would seem to ⁁<add place="supralinear">be</add> doing all, that in this way, can possibly be done to <unclear>assure</unclear> the property of an extensive and fertile tract of country in both States.  I submit to the discretion and foresight of your Excellency, whether the present would not be  a very propitious moment to evidence both States to engage in a great and conjoint effort for their mutual and common benefit.  The fund already at  command would encourage the State of Alabama to engage in enlarged operations, especially if the liberal assistance and cooperation of the State of Tennessee would enable her to anticipate, with more certainty and confidence, a speedy and successful result.  The very want of cooperation hereafter, which I think will be more difficult to obtain, may long continue this <unclear>barrier</unclear> to the prospects of both, which some energy at the present favorable moment, and an enlightened spirit of concert would speedily and easily remove.  I write all this without any expression of the will of the Legislature, and the object is to prepare for any favorable impulse, or peradventure to partake in giving the impulse itself.  I should be glad to be favored with the views of your Excellency, and on some future occasion it will afford me great pleasure to give you mine more fully &amp; in detail.  I am assured that your Excellency would be disposed to promote any practical, useful and liberal object. I have the honor to be most respectfully</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Yr</abbr>
                     <expan>Your</expan>
                  </choice> most <choice>
                     <abbr>Obt. Svt</abbr>
                     <expan>Obedient Servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">John Murphy</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>His <choice>
                        <abbr>Exy.</abbr>
                        <expan>Excellency</expan>
                     </choice> Governor Houston</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>State of Tennessee
ine&gt;</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
