<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl129">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1840 Apr. 1,  Clover Dale, T[ennessee] [to] Mrs A[nn] Jane Bell, Cornplanter, Venango County, P[ennsylvani]a / W[illia]m Bell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Bell, William</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl129</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50541412</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1840 Apr. 1,  Clover Dale, T[ennessee] [to] Mrs A[nn] Jane Bell, Cornplanter, Venango County, P[ennsylvani]a / W[illia]m Bell </title>
               <author>Bell, William</author>
               <date when="1840-04-01">April 1, 1840</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter, dated April 1, 1840, from William Bell in Dickson County, TN to his sister Ann Jane Bell in Venango County, PA.  In the letter, William briefly mentions several subjects, including farming operations, the depressed state of the farming business, and his plans to value the property of their father's plantation.  William also discusses a debating society he has joined with the intention of debating in favor of the temperance movement.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">19</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl129</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Temperance and religion</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Bell, William</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl129a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Clover Dale </name>
                     <date when="1840-04-01">April 1 1840</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sister</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I received your affectionate letter of <date when="--03-01">march 1</date> &amp; would have answered it sooner had not <name type="person">Margaret</name> &amp; <name type="person">Sarah</name> written to you so lately, it afforded us much pleasure as it was in accordance with our feelings.  The Girls are very anxious to see you and be in <choice>
                  <orig>you</orig>
                  <reg>your</reg>
               </choice> society, but they cannot consent to leave the home, where they have been raised &amp; where they have passed their happiest as well as most melancholy hours.  As for myself I should be very happy to see you &amp; the rest of the family, but under the present circumstances I do not know when I shall have that pleasure.</p>
            <p>I think you were perfectly <gap agent="damage"/> in reserving your <gap agent="damage"/> es <gap agent="damage"/> &amp; should you ever be in the circumstances mentioned by <name type="person">Mr Bell</name>  I should feel happy in adding to your comforts &amp; then be indebted for the many <choice>
                  <orig>benifits</orig>
                  <reg>benefits</reg>
               </choice> &amp; attentions received from you in past days.</p>
            <p>I think it would be ad — <pb n="2" facs="sl129b.small.jpg"/> visable, &amp; if it meets with your approbation, I will get <name type="person">Squire Caldwell</name> &amp; an assistant, who knows the value of property to value the plantation &amp; every thing belonging to it, as I wish to have every ⁁ <add place="supralinear">thing</add> correct.</p>
            <p>I was very sorry to hear of Mr Bell's misfortune in the mill line, as they are very difficult to repair, when injured by floods.</p>
            <p>You were complaining of the hard times, we are not exempt from it here produce bears a dull sale &amp; no persons can get money, except the merchants &amp; Constables, as for myself I do not require much at present, though the debts amount to more than I expected, they will not be demanded for some time.</p>
            <p>As you will take an interest in our farming operations, I shall give you a sketch We have thirty acres of land ready for planting which I intend to do in a few <gap agent="damage"/> is a debating Society <gap agent="damage"/>
               <name type="person">Bartons</name>
               <gap agent="damage"/> , near the Baptist Church as they were so much opposed to the Temperance — Society, I joined it merely to debate on that subject. The Society <choice>
                  <orig>apointed</orig>
                  <reg>appointed</reg>
               </choice> the fourth saturday in May to decide whether the temperance <pb n="3" facs="sl129c.small.jpg"/> society is a good cause or a bad one. You will be surprised at any reasonable man were he to say it was a bad cause yet there are a great many, who are fond of drink, and know that it would be disgraceful for them to  indulge, were the temperance reform to gain the <choice>
                  <orig>ascendency</orig>
                  <reg>ascendancy</reg>
               </choice>, these men say every thing they can  against the society</p>
            <p>Excuse my short letter as I have to go to <name type="place">Charlotte</name>, and were I not to put it in the office <choice>
                  <orig>to day</orig>
                  <reg>today</reg>
               </choice>, I should not have an opportunity of sending it for some time.</p>
            <p>  I would <gap agent="damage"/> to hear from you often as I <gap agent="damage"/> same affectionately regards for y <gap agent="damage"/> as when you lived with us.</p>
            <p>Remember me to <name type="person">Martha</name>
               <name type="person">Wylie</name> &amp; <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>The.</abbr>
                     <expan>Theodore</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>
            </p>
            <p>The girls join me in love to you all.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I remain your affectionate Brother</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                        <expan>William</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <gap agent="damage"/> Bell</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl129d.small.jpg"/>
               <add rend="different hand, ink">
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Charlotte <choice>
                              <abbr>T</abbr>
                              <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <date when="1840-04-07">
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Apl</abbr>
                              <expan>April</expan>
                           </choice> 7 40</date>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <add place="right">25</add>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mrs <choice>
                           <abbr>A.</abbr>
                           <expan>Ann</expan>
                        </choice> Jane Bell</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Cornplanter</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Venango County</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Pa</abbr>
                           <expan>Pennsylvania</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
