<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc185">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1839 Nov. 20, Nashville, Tennessee [to] Jane T. Woods, Philadelphia, Penn.  / Sarah Bet : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Bet, Sarah</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc185</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1839 Nov. 20, Nashville, Tennessee [to] Jane T. Woods, Philadelphia, Penn.  / Sarah Bet </title>
               <author> Bet, Sarah</author>
               <date when="1839-11-20"> 
			 November 20, 1839</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated November 20, 1839 from Sarah Bet in Nashville to Jane T. Woods in Philadelphia.  The purpose of the letter is to answer a previous letter from Woods and to inform her of social events in Nashville.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Sarah Bet Letters</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-1875</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc185</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Social life and customs.</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Bet, Sarah</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc185a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Nashville</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>November 20th 1839</date>
               <salute>My Dearest Cousin Jane</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>As I have finished writing my fifth lesson for the morning and have a few leisure minutes, I thought I could employ them very agreeably indeed by answering your most affectionate epistle, which was handed to me a quarter of an hour ago by Uncle Crutcher and for it I must offer my most cordial thanks, for your punctuality in writing so soon, after the reception of mine, and now to commence will inform you that your friends are all enjoying good health I saw your Father, Mother, and sisters, at church last Sabbath, but did not have an opportunity of speaking to them What has become of Jim? I have not seen anything of him in a Coons age.  I expect he has gone south, as he told me the last time that I had any conversation with him (which was a day or two before Uncle Gusten left that he expected to go to <name>New Orleans</name> with his uncle, and I expect he has gone.</p>
            <p>
               <name>Nashville</name> is tolerable gay at this time.  There has been several large parties lately, and a few weddings.  Miss <name>Eliza Moffis</name>
               <pb n="2" facs="sc185b.small.jpg"/> and <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr.</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Budd are married at last, after so long engagement.  His mother was very much opposed to their marrying, and she went down to <choice>
                  <abbr>Mrs</abbr>
                  <expan>Misses</expan>
               </choice> John T Hills, and was married by the Reverend Mr Howell.  Mr Moffis is here at this time, but intends leaving with his family in a few days for <name>Texas</name>.</p>
            <p>We had a run away match from the Academy on the same night.  The girls name was Miss mcDaniel, but I do not recollect the gentleman's name.  he was Carpenter by trade, and he name should have been "Sally Brown," as I suppose you have heard of <add place="supralinear">a</add> song by that name.</p>
            <p>There were two deaths in town last week, which occasioned a great deal of regret.  They were both young gentleman, Mr <name>Elk Brown</name>, and Mr Goodish Mr Burn's faunt aide in <name>Philadelphia</name>, and he had only been here a year or two.</p>
            <p>Our examination commences the 9th of December, and continues four days.  There will only be two graduates, <name>Eliza Janie Brambett</name>, and myself,  I am very busy indeed preparing my studies, as we have a great many to be examined on.  I declare I never was so busy in all my life.  Besides my studies I have several very difficult pieces to play on the Piano, and I have just taken them, and therefore they will require a great deal of practice, in order to be played as they should be.  Our school is very large this session; there are at present two hundred, and twenty pupil.  <name>Martha Anderson</name>, and <name>Marion Cannon</name> have returned to school, and <name>Maria Richmond</name>, (that went to school with you at Dr Berry's is also here.  She desires to <pb n="3" facs="sc185c.small.jpg"/> be remembered very affectionately to you.  I will return home immediately after the examination class, and I will not return anymore to <add place="supralinear">this</add> school as I will receive my sheepskin.  But evening draws on and admonishes me to close my letter.  Give my best love to Ann, and tell her I will be very glad if she will comply with her promise.  Remember me also to <name>Marg Lewis</name>, <del>and</del> when you see her, and <name>Martha Fubue</name>, and <name>Ann Overton</name>.</p>
            <closer>Your dearest Cousin <signed>Sarah Bet</signed>
               <add>NB. Please answer this letter, and direct it to <name>Pulaski</name>, as I will leave <name>Nashville</name> before that can reach here <pb n="4" facs="sc185d.small.jpg"/>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Miss <name>Jane T. Woods</name> Care of miss hawks <name>Philadelphia</name>
                        <name>
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Penn</abbr>
                              <expan>Pennsylvania</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <lb/> Mail</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
