<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc134">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1829 Oct. 29, Alexandria, Virginia [to]  David Burford, Nashville, Tennessee / J[ourdan] M. Saunders : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Saunders, Jourdan M.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc134</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1829 Oct. 29, Alexandria, Virginia [to]  David Burford, Nashville, Tennessee / J[ourdan] M. Saunders</title>
               <author> Saunders, Jourdan M. </author>
               <date when="1829-10-29"> 
			 October 29, 1829</date>
               <extent> 4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated October 29, 1829 to David Burford from his business partner Jourdan Saunders. Saunders was on a slave trading trip and wrote about one slave who cut off all the fingers on his right hand and another who ran away. He informed Burford that the trip would not render a profit unless he recovered the runaway slave.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">David Burford Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-935</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc134</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Slave trading -- American history</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Saunders, Jourdan M.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc134a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Alexandria</name>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Octr</abbr>
                           <expan>October</expan>
                        </choice> 29th 1829</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear Burford</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I arrived here yesterday with fourteen negroes, eight fellows two boys and four women &amp; girls all marketable except one woman I bought for $75 in a settlement with my friend Roach I have my passage <add>engaged</add> and will probably depart tomorrow for <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N</abbr>
                     <expan>New</expan>
                  </choice>. Orleans.</name>  The price of the passage for each slave $17 and my own $30_ fellows have cost me from $400 to $435 boys and girls all in proportion all with certificates I have had the misfortune to <choice>
                  <orig>loose</orig>
                  <reg>lose</reg>
               </choice> our first rate fellow that ran off on the 13th of September and have never <choice>
                  <abbr>recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> any certain account of him until I came here, I am now satisfied that he is still lurking in his former range in one of the adjoining counties on the <name>Virginia</name> side of the <name>Potomac</name>, and <add>have</add> been informed that I can obtain $350 for him running but it is out of my power to do anything more at present than to constitute an agent to attend to the business which I have accordingly done with directions to ship him to me at N. Orleans as soon as he may be taken_ in addition to this, I bought a fellow a few days since at $400., he was confined with another fellow which I purchased about the same <add>time,</add> to a tree in a gentlemans yard, and in my absence to make some further trades in the same neighborhood he got possession of an axe, and cut off all of the fingers of his right hand, a circumstance that no human <choice>
                  <orig>forsight</orig>
                  <reg>foresight</reg>
               </choice> could have guarded against._ my object at present is to dispose of the stock I have on hand and direct my attention to the collection of our claims in La_ I have abandoned the idea of returning to this country for the present winter unless their should be some <choice>
                  <orig>favourable</orig>
                  <reg>favorable</reg>
               </choice> change in the markets_ I have laid out all my <pb n="2" facs="sc134b.small.jpg"/> money and sold your man for <unclear>$807</unclear> under the disadvantages of hard luck, I cannot flatter you with the prospect of making any thing on the trip, unless the runaway should be taken, then their purchase would afford reasonable profit_ </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>your friend</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>JM Saunders</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sc134d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Maj</abbr>
                              <expan>Major</expan>
                           </choice>. David Burford</name>
                        <del type="overstrike">Carthage</del>
                        <name>Nashville</name>
                        <name>Tennessee</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>postmark</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
