<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl413">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1830 Jun. 29, Carthage [Tennessee] [to] Louisa C. Hazard / A. Fergusson: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Fergusson, A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl413</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1830 Jun. 29, Carthage [Tennessee] [to] Louisa C. Hazard / A. Fergusson</title>
               <author>Fergusson, A.</author>
               <date when="1830-06-29">June 29, 1830</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Adam Fergusson to his sister-in-law Louisa C. Hazard, dated June 29, 1830. Fergusson writes  of an address to the students at Locust Grove Female Academy by the Honorable Felix Grundy, Esq. Grundy hopes to involve the ladies in the Temperance movement. Fergusson feels that their voices are very respected and that their involvement will be beneficial.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">IV-G-1, B6</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl413</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Temperance</term>
               <term>Manners and customs</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Fergusson, Adam</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl413a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Carthage</name>
                     <date>June 29th 1830</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>To miss <name>Louisa C. Hazard</name>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <gap/> Louisa will please <gap/>
               <unclear>permit me</unclear> to present <gap/>  and <name>Mrs Weathered</name> to the young Ladies of Lou <gap/> Grove <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>etcetera</expan>
               </choice> ,, and herself, the very eloquent and appropriate address of the <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Hon.</abbr>
                     <expan>Honorable</expan>
                  </choice> Felix Grundy <choice>
                     <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                     <expan>Esquire</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> delivered at the late close of the examination of the <name>Nashville</name> female <choice>
                  <orig>Accademy</orig>
                  <reg>Academy</reg>
               </choice> and particularly to the young Ladies of that institution The remarks are Just and <choice>
                  <orig>hapily</orig>
                  <reg>happily</reg>
               </choice> chosen and of such a character as to apply to any institution of the kind. One of the principle motives of the address was to enlist the female influence against one of the most odious vices that degrade and destroy the other Sex. <choice>
                  <abbr>Viz</abbr>
                  <expan>Videlicet</expan>
               </choice> that of drunken <add>n</add> ess. And as the design is certainly laudable: I see no impropriety in appealing to the good Sense and promising talents of the Young Ladies of Locust <gap/> rove female Accademy to unite in So laudable an undertaking. Situated in one of the fairest portions of <name>Tennessee</name> uniting among <unclear>others</unclear> the advantages of a rich section of  country <unclear>inhabited by the</unclear> most <choice>
                  <orig>intelegent</orig>
                  <reg>intelligent</reg>
               </choice> and respectable citizens with <gap/>
               <choice>
                  <orig>abeleties</orig>
                  <reg>abilities</reg>
               </choice> of the teachers Locust grove <gap/> Nation <choice>
                  <orig>amoung</orig>
                  <reg>among</reg>
               </choice> the <choice>
                  <orig>formost</orig>
                  <reg>foremost</reg>
               </choice> of like kindred <gap/> The young ladies I presume need not be reminded of the influence their <choice>
                  <orig>oppinions</orig>
                  <reg>opinions</reg>
               </choice> have on Society many of them live in Different Sections of <gap/> consequently when they return to <unclear>their homes</unclear>
               <gap/> are sought after and taken as a guide <gap/> in which they <unclear>move</unclear> If in those circles <gap/>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl413b.small.jpg"/> enumerated in the enclosed address prevail they have only to discountenance and put down its authors with contempt and the work of reform is accomplished With many thanks for  your <choice>
                  <orig>verry</orig>
                  <reg>very</reg>
               </choice> polite letter your Sister Joins with me in expressing through you to Mr and Mrs Weathered our <gap/> wishes f <gap/> ture health and <gap/>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Respectfully</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>A.</abbr>
                        <expan>Adam</expan>
                     </choice> Fergusson</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
