<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl573">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1822 Jan. 9 [to] James Winchester, Cairo, Tennessee / William Martin   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Martin, William</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl573</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1822 Jan. 9 [to] James Winchester, Cairo, Tennessee / William Martin</title>
               <author>Martin, William</author>
               <date>January 9, 1822</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to General James Winchester from Colonel William Martin, dated January 9, 1822. Martin writes mostly about the current political situation. He mentions France, the economy, and Congress. Martin is disappointed with the lack of progress Tennessee is making. He hopes that reforms will be attempted, but worries that the effort  would be futile.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">James Winchester Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">8</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl573</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Martin, William, 1765-1846</term>
               <term>Politics, society, and economy</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2009202801"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Martin, William, 1765-1846</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl573a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Bellview</name>
                     <date>9th <choice>
                           <abbr>Jany</abbr>
                           <expan>January</expan>
                        </choice> 1822</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your Kind letter of the 4th <choice>
                  <abbr>ult</abbr>
                  <expan>ultimo</expan>
               </choice> was <choice>
                  <abbr>recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> some time ago. It is with much pleasure I hear of the continued health,&amp;  prosperity of a long tried friend_ &amp; one too who has been well proved &amp; found sound to the core. reciprocal &amp; well confirmed friendship, is one of the highest enjoyments experienced in <unclear>social</unclear> life. How pleasant to have a friend to whom we can on all occasions unbosom our whole heart.</p>
            <p>The Presidents message at the meeting of the 17th congress, is less Interesting than any of the Kind which I have seen this I suppose is owing to the steady &amp; <unclear>unterrupted</unclear> state of our national affairs. However that of our commercial relations with <name>France</name> is an exception The extent of this evil I suppose not to be great, as it respects a partial part of our commerce only. The complaint of France about the <unclear>apollo</unclear> , and their rights at <name>New orleans</name>, appear to have so little foundation that she will not (I think) sincerely urge them.</p>
            <p>As was to have been expected the P has touched the Florida dispute with a sparing &amp; tender hand. This notwithstanding, it is probable from the character, &amp; peculiar <pb n="2" facs="sl573b.small.jpg"/> standing of one of the actors in that <choice>
                  <orig>Dramma</orig>
                  <reg>Drama</reg>
               </choice> And from the inordinate thirst our congress people have to talk, that much of the time of that body will be wasted on this subject.</p>
            <p>It is true as you say that much of the time of our Legislature is employed in attending to little, local concerns. This to a reasonable extent is right,_ but it is <choice>
                  <orig>induly</orig>
                  <reg>unduly</reg>
               </choice> to the neglect of the primary Interest of the common wealth. How this evil is to be <choice>
                  <orig>remidied</orig>
                  <reg>remedied</reg>
               </choice> , in the present ignorant, &amp; <unclear>vitiated</unclear> state of society I Know not For in the choice of men to represent us in that body, we see that merit in the estimation of the Electors, is but a minor consideration. Hence <orig>untill</orig> we become more wise &amp; more virtuous, we shall in this respect be no better off. It appears to me, that all the other states so far as my information goes, are improving. But poor Tennessee, is retrograding or at best stationary. I take no pleasure in entertaining this opinion of the country which I love above all others. And it is this high regard I have for my state, which makes me feel, so pungently on the occasion.</p>
            <p>Are reforms hopeless? cannot the old leaven be purged out? And cannot the people be brought to see their best Interest?</p>
            <p>I have sometimes thought that attempts of this kind would be vain. But from <pb n="3" facs="sl573c.small.jpg"/> the great importance of the occasion, <del type="overstrike">anoth</del> and effort ought to be made. Let the wise &amp; the good, unite their energies, to desire &amp; carry into effect, some ways &amp; means to better our condition. I think it practicable, and it would <add>be</add> honorable at least, to make the attempt. And if you &amp; I, from the wear of many years <del type="overstrike">m</del>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>shd</abbr>
                  <expan>should</expan>
               </choice> not live to see and enjoy the benefits Our offspring may.</p>
            <p>The Books and papers of the commissioners office, of 1807 were  by act of assembly delivered over to the <choice>
                  <orig>Regester</orig>
                  <reg>Register</reg>
               </choice> of the Land office where they remained untill the setting of the last Genl assembly, which an act passed directing that they shd be delivered to the possession of the present <choice>
                  <orig>bord</orig>
                  <reg>board</reg>
               </choice> . whether they are delivered to the clerk, or whether they will not be delivered untill the board meets- (<date>1st april</date>) I know not. at any rate you can get the paper  you speak of, by applying to <name>Mr Blackfan</name>, if delivered, and if not, to <name>Mr McGavock</name>.</p>
            <p>Our family is in usual health. my own is very good with the exception of a <choice>
                  <orig>cronick</orig>
                  <reg>chronic</reg>
               </choice> complaint with which I have had to conflict many years.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>with sincere regard I am your friend____</salute>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                     <expan>William</expan>
                  </choice> Martin</signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl573d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <name>William Martin</name>
                  <lb/> 9th Jan 1822</add>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Dixons Spring</name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>T</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <date>Jany 14th 1822</date>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Genl <name>James Winchester</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Cairo</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Sumner County</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>mail }</add>
               <add>
                  <table>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">1½ tons I</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">300</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Steel <unclear>&amp; con</unclear>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">50</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">Boarding</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">150</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">500</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">wages</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">240</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">740</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">rent of shop <lb/> and tools</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">150</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">890</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">for keeping a clerk advancing money for <unclear>martin an collecting &amp;</unclear> }</cell>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">211</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1"/>
                        <cell role="data" rows="1" cols="1">
                           <unclear>1101</unclear>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
