<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl210">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1844 Oct. 6 Nashville [TN] [to] G. W. House, Lowesville [i.e., Louisville], Alaba[ma] / Jos[eph] D. Hamilton   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Hamilton, Joseph D.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl210</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51207226</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1844 Oct. 6 Nashville [TN] [to] G. W. House, Lowesville [i.e., Louisville], Alaba[ma] / Jos[eph] D. Hamilton</title>
               <author>Hamilton, Joseph D.</author>
               <date when="1844-10-06">October 6, 1844</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated Oct. 6, 1844, from Joseph D. Hamilton to G. W. House. The letter is written on letterhead promoting the 1844 presidential campaign of Henry Clay and his vice presidential running mate Theodore Frelinghuysen.  Hamilton describes a recent Whig convention. He gives an account of some local social news. Hamilton also reports on the family, and tells G.W. that he is needed at home to meet with a visitor.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">9</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl210</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Clay, Henry, 1777-1852</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Hamilton, Joseph D.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl210a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                     <date when="1844-10-06">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Oct</abbr>
                           <expan>October</expan>
                        </choice> 6th 1844</date>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Capt</abbr>
                        <expan>Captain</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name type="person">G.W. House</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <add place="left">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>This is a campaign picture of Henry Clay and his running mate for the 1844 presidential election, Theodore Freylinghuysen.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>This is a picture of a man on a horse with the banner "The Mill Boy." </figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>After some reflection I have come to the conclusion to fulfill the promise I made, to write to you my text being at the head of the letter (<name type="person">Clay</name> &amp; <name type="person">Frelinghuysen</name>) I Shall proceed</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Too</orig>
                  <reg>Two</reg>
               </choice> of our Company's turned out yesterday afternoon the ( Harrison Guards &amp; <unclear>Straightouts</unclear> ) in full Uniform and in large numbers. <unclear>The SSG's</unclear> had a small Flag, stars &amp; stripes &amp; Clay &amp; Frelinghuysen on it. Each member of the company <del type="overstrike">member</del> has one of these stuck in the <choice>
                  <orig>mussle</orig>
                  <reg>muzzle</reg>
               </choice> of his musket I never saw them make so great a display before; and so well calculated to inspire the hearts of the youn<add place="supralinear">g</add> Whigs after tea <name type="person">Mr Sha<add place="supralinear">u</add>l</name>
               <unclear>Ye<add place="supralinear">a</add>nger</unclear> was escorted to the Court <pb n="2" facs="sl210b.small.jpg"/> House when he delivered a zealous and enthusiastic address to the Whigs of Nashville. He was followed then by <name type="person">Mr Sake See</name> of <name type="place">Mississippi</name> and then after all our <choice>
                  <orig>Govenor</orig>
                  <reg>Governor</reg>
               </choice> was seen by some one ⁁ <add place="supralinear">in the Room</add> who mentioned his name and you may well Expect what followed. He was called for by the audience with ⁁ <add place="supralinear">such</add> shouts of applause that he could not resist them. He then <choice>
                  <orig>arrose and address</orig>
                  <reg>arose and addressed</reg>
               </choice> the people in his usual cheerful  &amp; eloquent style with his address the meeting closed</p>
            <p>we have received a portion of our goods and <choice>
                  <orig>traid</orig>
                  <reg>trade</reg>
               </choice> opens pretty fair. Mother &amp; Miss Ann <choice>
                  <orig>wer</orig>
                  <reg>were</reg>
               </choice> down in town yester evening. There is no news of importance all are well &amp; <del type="overstrike">healthy</del>
               <add place="supralinear">hearty</add> . <unclear>Mort Em</unclear> &amp; all the children have gone to <name type="place">Wilson County</name> to take a respite from business for a week or two. Mort took his gun and Hunting <choice>
                  <orig>impliments</orig>
                  <reg>implements</reg>
               </choice> w<add place="supralinear">i</add>th him. I presume he will spend the better part of his time in Hunting while he remains there There have been several we<add place="supralinear">d</add>dings since you left <choice>
                  <abbr>Col</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice>
               <name type="person">Billy Bryan</name> to Miss <name type="person">Macon Cannon</name> (the Cannon <del type="overstrike">wrote it</del> find clear that time to a certainty) also Mr <name type="person">Henry Morgan</name> to Miss <name type="person">Julia Demeval</name> all of this City</p>
            <p>You must ⁁ <add place="supralinear">hasten</add> home as soon as possible as there is a gentleman here ⁁ <add place="supralinear">who</add> wishes to see you very much he is waiting on you and is very much afflicted. It is partly on his  account that I write to you. He is a particular <choice>
                  <orig>freind</orig>
                  <reg>friend</reg>
               </choice> of mine, <del type="overstrike">we</del>
               <add place="supralinear">and</add> says that he has tried <name type="person">Jennings</name> for 18 months but <pb n="3" facs="sl210c.small.jpg"/> has found no relief. Tell my Dear sister and the little ones that I am very anxious  to see them say to Jimy that he will have to eat a heap if he grows as large as his Uncle Jassee . It is now dinner time and I believe Ill lay my pen aside and Try it after dinner —</p>
            <p>Well here we are, again and nothing more to say Give my best respects to your Mother, Brother &amp; Sister Louisa and all the <choice>
                  <orig>ballance</orig>
                  <reg>balance</reg>
               </choice> of the Family Say to Sister that her friends enquire after her frequently Mother is very anxious to see you all and sends her love</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My love to sister and the little ones <lb/> Yours in  haste</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Jos.</abbr>
                        <expan>Joseph</expan>
                     </choice> D. Hamilton</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl210d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Capt G.W. House</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <orig>Lowesville</orig>
                           <reg>Louisville</reg>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Alaba.</abbr>
                           <expan>Alabama</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
