<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl289">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1850 Apr. 25, Tulip Grove [TN] [to] A. J. Donelson [Jr.] / A. J. Donelson   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Donelson, A. J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl289</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1850 Apr. 25, Tulip Grove [TN] [to] A. J. Donelson [Jr.] / A. J. Donelson</title>
               <author>Donelson, A. J.</author>
               <date when="1850-04-25">April 25, 1850</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Andrew Jackson Donelson to  his son of the same name, dated April 25, 1850. Donelson is looking forward to a visit from Andrew Jr. Donelson reports on the christening of his youngest daughter, Catharine. He wants to stop farming in Mississippi because the climate is unfavorable for cotton and other crops. Donelson writes that the religious fervor of Tulip Grove has dramatically decreased, but he hopes that this will change. He writes that good health is the most important gift from God.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">A. J. Donelson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> I-D-3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">4</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl289</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Working life</term>
               <term>Religion</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Donelson, Andrew Jackson, 1799-1871</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl289a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Tulip Grove</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>April 25th 1850</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Son</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letter of the <date>27th <choice>
                     <abbr>Feby</abbr>
                     <expan>February</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date> with one to your Sister Mary came in due time. Nothing can be more gratifying to us than to know that you have weathered in safety the exposures of the past winter, and that the period draws nearer and nearer when we may be blessed again with your presence in the family circle I have written to you twice since my return, but fear that you do not receive letters addressed from this point. We are again well arranged in our household matters and by the time you reach us hope to have our house newly papered and painted, so that should you or Mary wish to marry, our friends may meet in <choice>
                  <orig>cumfort</orig>
                  <reg>comfort</reg>
               </choice> to partake of our happiness.<pb n="2" facs="sl289b.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>John is at school with <name>Mr Hume</name> in <name>Nashville</name>. Rachel is at the female academy. Both are doing well. The other children are at home. Last sunday we had our infant, born since our return, christened. Her name is Catharine.</p>
            <p>I have recently returned from <name>Mississippi</name> where I am trying to make another crop, but would sell the place if I could get a reasonable price. That climate is becoming almost as uncertain as this for cotton and is far less favorable to the other agricultural products.</p>
            <p>Among the changes in the neighborhood there are none that strike me more forcibly than that which has occurred in the religious sentiment. The congregation at our church has dwindled to almost nothing and exhibits but little of the fervor which prevailed when you were a boy. Nashville and its <choice>
                  <orig>nieghbourhood</orig>
                  <reg>neighborhood</reg>
               </choice> used then to visit us and our church was a point at which the talented and brilliant ministers of <pb n="3" facs="sl289c.small.jpg"/> the gospel delighted to stop. Now it is with difficulty that we obtain a preacher. But I hope there will soon be a reaction and that when you come again things will wear a better aspect, and our society become again distinguished for its support of religion and good order.</p>
            <p>I am saving a good horse for you and will have ready for you a body servant.</p>
            <p>Take care of your constitution, and remember that of all the gifts of God that of good health is the most precious. we may struggle against poverty but without health there is no capacity for the acquisition of any of the cumforts of life.</p>
            <p>I will write you <choice>
                  <orig>evry</orig>
                  <reg>every</reg>
               </choice> month. Accept the prayers of all the family for your safety and happiness, and our hopes that you may join us again before the year is gone</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Yr.</abbr>
                     <expan>Your</expan>
                  </choice> affectionate father</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>A J</abbr>
                        <expan>Andrew Jackson</expan>
                     </choice> Donelson</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Lieut.</abbr>
                        <expan>Lieutenant</expan>
                     </choice> A J Donelson</addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl289d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Lieut A J Donelson</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
