<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl208">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1836 Aug. 8 [to] Sarah B. Hamilton, Russellville, KY / James M. Hamilton   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Hamilton, James M</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl208</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51206601</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1836 Aug. 8 [to] Sarah B. Hamilton, Russellville, KY / James M. Hamilton</title>
               <author>Hamilton, James M.</author>
               <date when="1836-08-08">August 8, 1836</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated Aug. 8, 1836 to Sarah B. Hamilton from James Hamilton. He sends many greetings to friends. He writes about the local, and personal news. He also mentions that President Jackson plans a visit to Nashville soon.</note>
               <note type="transcriber's" anchored="true">There is a second letter from an unnamed sibling of James Hamilton's added onto to the first letter. In it the author announces that he/she has sent money to an uncle, and mentions how enjoyable a recent camp meeting was. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl208</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</term>
               <term>Kentucky</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Hamilton, James M</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl208a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Dear Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>as it has been Some Time since I have written to you or received a letter from you and as I have no <del type="overstrike">apogy</del>
               <add place="supralinear">apology</add> to make I hope you will excuse my long <choice>
                  <orig>scilence</orig>
                  <reg>silence</reg>
               </choice> I have no news of importance to relate to you only Brother and mySelf are well <choice>
                  <orig>an</orig>
                  <reg>and</reg>
               </choice> enjoying good health we expect the president of the <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>U. S</abbr>
                     <expan>United States</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> to visit <name type="place">Nashville</name> in a day or <choice>
                  <orig>too</orig>
                  <reg>two</reg>
               </choice> as he resides at his private residence —</p>
            <p>Give my best respects to my Dear sister and <choice>
                  <orig>tel</orig>
                  <reg>tell</reg>
               </choice> her I have received but one letter from her I <choice>
                  <orig>herd</orig>
                  <reg>heard</reg>
               </choice> that you all had your Election in <name type="place">kentucky</name> and it was evident that Mr <unclear>Hice</unclear> would stay at home that gratified me very much tel <name type="person">Mr S N Dawson</name> for the Jacksonites have not <del type="overstrike">posolited</del>
               <add place="supralinear">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>prosolited</orig>
                     <reg>proselyted</reg>
                  </choice>
               </add> me <choice>
                  <orig>nether</orig>
                  <reg>neither</reg>
               </choice> has the camelites —</p>
            <p>Present My best respects to <name type="person">J &amp; P Gilbert</name> and tel them to write to me soon tel me how they are pleased with their business <unclear>its</unclear>  for my  <choice>
                  <orig>parte</orig>
                  <reg>part</reg>
               </choice> I think it <unclear>is</unclear> a very profitable business <pb n="2" facs="sl208b.small.jpg"/>  but had I employed my time as I should have <choice>
                  <orig>dun</orig>
                  <reg>done</reg>
               </choice> I should have been much better qualified for the business than I am —</p>
            <p>Give my best respects to all <choice>
                  <orig>inquireing</orig>
                  <reg>inquiring</reg>
               </choice> friends <del type="overstrike">who may in</del>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Yours <unclear>in haste</unclear>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">James M Hamilton</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="post script">
                  <note>
                     <p>Give my love to her and tell her that I Shall expect a long letter from her Shortly I do not expect that <name type="person">Mrs. Saffasans</name> will visit you this Summer as She expect to Start to her new home Shortly miss <name type="person">nancy</name> calculates going with her they are all at the farm now</p>
                     <p>Give my Best respects to my friend <name type="person">Mr Chapman</name>
                        <choice>
                           <sic>and and</sic>
                           <corr>and</corr>
                        </choice> tell him not to  think wrong of me for not answering his letter as I am very anxious to do so but he must take the will for the deed until I get an <choice>
                           <orig>oppertunity</orig>
                           <reg>opportunity</reg>
                        </choice> give my love to uncle <name type="person">Jos</name>s family and tell me in your next how cousin <name type="person">mary</name> and her Beau <unclear>come on courting</unclear> tell <name type="person">will</name> to write to me present my respects to all of the <choice>
                           <orig>neighbours</orig>
                           <reg>neighbors</reg>
                        </choice> and also to aunt <name type="person">Marah</name> and <name type="person">Charles Step</name> is well</p>
                     <p>give my love to Brother Jo and tell him to learn fast and be a good Boy your affectionate Son <choice>
                           <orig>MORTIMER </orig>
                           <reg>MONSIEUR</reg>
                        </choice> HAMILTON</p>
                  </note>
               </add>
            </closer>
            <pb n="3" facs="sl208c.small.jpg"/>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Monday <choice>
                        <orig>knight</orig>
                        <reg>night</reg>
                     </choice>
                     <date when="1836-08-08">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Aug</abbr>
                           <expan>August</expan>
                        </choice> 8 1836</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I told <del type="overstrike">Requested</del>
               <add place="supralinear">Told</add> Brother James when he <unclear>wrote</unclear> a Letter home if he did not fill up the Sheet I would <gap agent="damage"/>in it he has Brought this up to knight for me to fill up you will perceive that he <add place="supralinear">has</add> written it in a very hasty manner he has not dated it and the orthography is bad <choice>
                  <orig>wee</orig>
                  <reg>we</reg>
               </choice> are all well at present I Suppose you have received my letter before this time and I am anxiously expecting one from you I Sent the money I Spoke of in my letter to you To Uncle <gap agent="damage"/> By <name type="person">Russell Moore</name> if he has not received it before this reaches you please <unclear>inform</unclear> him that Mr Moore has it the <choice>
                  <orig>musquetoes</orig>
                  <reg>mosquitoes</reg>
               </choice> trouble me So that I must def <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>writing</unclear> until morning</p>
            <p>Tuesday Morning <lb/> I went out on white ⁁ <add place="supralinear">Creek</add> Last Sunday to a camp meeting and I heard two excellent Sermons from the <name type="person">Rev Mcpherin</name> and <name type="person">Green</name> wee have had a great deal of rain here in a few days past I Should like very much to visit you Shortly but I will not be able to do so probably until next Spring I wish very much you would come over Shortly all of your friends are anxious to See you If you do not come Send Sister as Soon as you can and tel her go to School the Balance of this years — why does She not write to me? tell her I think She cannot conceive what a pleasure it is to me to receive a letter from her or She would have written before now <pb n="4" facs="sl208d.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mrs <name type="person">Sarah B Hamilton</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Russelville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Logan</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>cty</abbr>
                        <expan>county</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Ky</abbr>
                           <expan>Kentucky</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
