<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0021">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1808 Mar. 5, Oosunaleh [to] Return J. Meigs, Indian agent, War Department   / Cherokee Chiefs : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Cherokee Chiefs</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0021</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1808 Mar. 5, Oosunaleh [to] Return J. Meigs, Indian agent, War Department / Cherokee Chiefs</title>
               <author>Cherokee Chiefs</author>
               <date when="1808-03-05">March 5, 1808</date>
               <extent> 4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter to Return J. Meigs, agent to the Cherokee Indians, from the Cherokee Chiefs. The Chiefs complain that the government is allowing too many "white people" to move onto Cherokee land.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0021</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Treaties</term>
               <term>Indian agents</term>
               <term>Real property</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Cherokee Chiefs</name>
               </term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Chubroah</name>
               </term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Kutuwaskee</name>
               </term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Sour Mush</name>
               </term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Tuskegawhee</name>
               </term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Sanannueu</name>
               </term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Crying Son</name>
               </term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Culsawathu</name>
               </term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Katihee</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0021a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Oosunaleh</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date when="1808-03-05">March 5th 1808</date>
               <salute>Friend &amp; Brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We received your letter of the 8th of last month, we consider you as the organ of the <name>United States</name> to the <name>Cherokees</name>, who no doubt have instructed you to do us justice avoiding to the existing treaties we consider ourselves as nation of people, who are to be governed by a majority of the <choice>
                  <orig>apointed</orig>
                  <reg>appointed</reg>
               </choice> Chiefs, but cannot  in no case be governed by what two<unclear>extra</unclear> men does_</p>
            <p>We consider ourselves bound to protect us a privilege which has ever Governed by our former Chiefs_ you certainly ought to know that we <add>would</add>
               <choice>
                  <orig>atempt</orig>
                  <reg>attempt</reg>
               </choice> to Destroy the result of a Deliberate Majority of the Chiefs In Council</p>
            <p>We recollect when you held a treaty at Tellico four years ago which time you said, the Cherokees were making you a boy <choice>
                  <orig>be cause</orig>
                  <reg>because</reg>
               </choice> we had appointed <name>John Lowry</name>
               <name>John McLemore</name>
               <name>broom</name> and <name>Tallotiskee</name> to treat with you, now we cannot suppose you would have treated with these men you termed boys, we cannot consider ourselves bound to be governed by a treaty concluded by a <choice>
                  <orig>meniority</orig>
                  <reg>minority</reg>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <p>you say we ought to consider well on these poor white people we know what we have passed in our former Council, respecting them single men has been privileged to remain in our nation, till term of hire is out and you yourself have encouraged them to marry our women <pb n="2" facs="pa0021b.small.jpg"/> and then they would be come as one of our people but we never privileged <choice>
                  <orig>familys</orig>
                  <reg>families</reg>
               </choice> to come in as labourers and you say if <del type="overstrike">you</del> we open our ears to the Discontented people that we should always have trouble and our friends</p>
            <p> now we tell you, you are the very person that causes, the Disturbance by <unclear>permiting</unclear> white women and Children to come into the nation as labourers_ and that too on <choice>
                  <orig>publick</orig>
                  <reg>public</reg>
               </choice> lands <del type="overstrike">who</del> without the <del type="overstrike">per</del> Sanction by the Chiefs in council</p>
            <p>you say you Dont Countenance renting lands we will tell who rented lands <name>John Walker</name>
               <name>John Rodgers</name> one hundred Dollars a year for three <add>years</add> this Dont look like raising corn and you appear to encourage leasing our lands to <unclear>Idleness</unclear> instead of encouraging our people_</p>
            <p>young <unclear>reats</unclear> to dusk</p>
            <p>Turtle at home to <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Majr</abbr>
                     <expan>Major</expan>
                  </choice>. Rusell</name> on <name>brave Creek</name>
               <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Saml</abbr>
                     <expan>Samuel</expan>
                  </choice> Riley</name>_ this is all before not far distance</p>
            <p>You say we misconceive respecting the removal <name>Mr Hall</name> we have nothing to say and we may be wrong but we think if you had move Black Smith to the valley towns the poorest part of the nation, we should have thought better of it, then to have removed him to where<del type="overstrike"> this</del> there is <unclear>Somaspy</unclear> Shop so near_</p>
            <p>we inform you that great number of <choice>
                  <orig>moveing</orig>
                  <reg>moving</reg>
               </choice> familys comes out of <name>Georgia </name>by <name>High tower</name> to the <unclear>Fox town</unclear> which road was objected to in the war office and these Travellers goes through a part of the wilderness where the Creeks resorts and we shall expect you will <unclear>prohibit</unclear>
               <pb n="3" facs="pa0021c.small.jpg"/> Traveling it as we shall not think bound <del type="overstrike">to them</del> protect them or their property or Deem it ought to be brought to be <unclear>truley<add>nt</add>
               </unclear> against Cherokees should <choice>
                  <orig>the</orig>
                  <reg>they</reg>
               </choice> meet with loss and send a paper &amp; to that purport and we will turn to the federal road_ </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>Chubroah</name>
                  <name>Kutuwaskee</name>
                  <name>Sour Mush</name>
                  <name>Tuskegawhee</name>
                  <name>Sanannueu</name>
                  <name>Crying Son</name>
                  <name>Culsawathu</name>
                  <name>Katihee</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Col</abbr>
                        <expan>Colonel</expan>
                     </choice>. Return J Meigs</name>
               </add>
               <pb n="4" facs="pa0021d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Coln.</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel</expan>
                        </choice> Return J. Meigs</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Agent War <choice>
                        <abbr>Depart</abbr>
                        <expan>Department</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Highwassee</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Letter from the <lb/>Cherokee Chiefs at <lb/> Eustamalle <date>5 March<lb/> 1808</date>
                  <lb/> answered the <date>14 March 1808</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
