<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl412">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1830 Jul. 18, Carthage, Tennessee [to] Joshua M. Coffee, Alexandria, Smith County, Tennessee / Adam Fergusson   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Fergusson, Adam</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl412</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1830 Jul. 18, Carthage, Tennessee [to] Joshua M. Coffee, Alexandria, Smith County, Tennessee / Adam Fergusson</title>
               <author>Fergusson, Adam</author>
               <date when="1830-07-18">July 18, 1830</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated July 18, 1830 from Adam Fergusson in Carthage, Tennessee to Joshua M. Coffee in Alexandria, Tennessee.  In the letter Fergusson informs Coffee of a rumor that the clerk of the County Court may resign his office, and that if this speculation is correct, he would like to be considered for the job.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl412</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Court administration</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Fergusson, Adam</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl412a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Carthage</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>18th July 1830</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I <choice>
                  <abbr>adress</abbr>
                  <expan>address</expan>
               </choice>
               <add>you</add> upon a subject which seems to threaten to agitate the People of <name>Smith County</name> before long; In this I may be mistaken but if I am it will be the case of many others.  It is whispered about and <del>seem</del> the opinion Seems to be gaining ground that our clerk of the County Court will resign his office,  <add>at  the next year</add> and two <choice>
                  <orig>canidates</orig>
                  <reg>candidates</reg>
               </choice> are already in nomination.  I would here remark that I think the idea is premature and as far as my enquiries go the present clerk will be Sustained in office at least the peace of Smith County would require it.  I would further remark that I would no means insinuate any thing as respectful to the present Clerk on the contrary I would like to see him <del>Sustained</del> Remain as he is  But should it prove otherwise and a new clerk is to be elected, you with the rest of <add>your</add>
               <del>the</del> fellow Justices will be called upon in your official capacity to make a Suitable choice to fill his place.  In doing this Your Judgement will be exercised to <del>make a Suitable choice Judge of the</del>
               <add>deliver on the</add> qualifications of those who may be candidates.  Among those who will offer their <choice>
                  <orig>pretentions</orig>
                  <reg>pretensions</reg>
               </choice> for that High and respectable office I hold myself as one.  I have been in office <gap agent="damage"/> I have had <unclear>transactions</unclear> with most of the people of this county and I feel no small pride in saying that they have on all <choice>
                  <orig>ocations</orig>
                  <reg>occasions</reg>
               </choice> given me the most flattering <pb n="2" facs="sl412b.small.jpg"/> proofs of their confidence.  My <choice>
                  <orig>acquantance</orig>
                  <reg>acquaintance</reg>
               </choice> with <add>you</add> as I trust is of such a character as to enable you to <del>weigh</del>
               <add>judge</add> of my qualifications and give them that  <choice>
                  <orig>Suport</orig>
                  <reg>Support</reg>
               </choice> which you may think them enabled to.  I would here remark that I belong to no party and have kept myself aloof from all <choice>
                  <orig>conections</orig>
                  <reg>connections</reg>
               </choice> with the <choice>
                  <orig>politicks</orig>
                  <reg>politics</reg>
               </choice> of the day. <del>and as</del> I hope your are not one of those who will form your <choice>
                  <orig>oppinion</orig>
                  <reg>opinion</reg>
               </choice> or provide your <choice>
                  <orig>Suport</orig>
                  <reg>Support</reg>
               </choice> until you know who all are candidates With regard to necessary qualities to make <add>a clerk</add> they consist of so many that room cannot be found here <add>so enumerate them</add>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Sufice</orig>
                  <reg>Suffice</reg>
               </choice> it to Say that I intend calling upon you when and <choice>
                  <orig>wher</orig>
                  <reg>where</reg>
               </choice> we will talk of matters and things in general I would like to see you here on <add>the evening of tuesday</add> the 21 it being our regular meeting, and I know your friends generally would like to see you.</p>
            <p>If in the course of your acquantance you should meet with an <choice>
                  <orig>oppurtunity</orig>
                  <reg>opportunity</reg>
               </choice> of conversing with some of the Justices of the peace upon the Subject (and I do think it necessary) you will be so kind as to mention me as a candidate. I understand  the other candidates  spoken of are <name>Don C  Dixon</name> and <name>David Greer</name> but your own <del>good</del> prudence must tell <choice>
                  <abbr>y </abbr>
                  <expan>you</expan>
               </choice> that there will be many more.  <del>I put</del>
               <gap agent="damage"/>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl412c.small.jpg"/> I wish <choice>
                  <orig>yo</orig>
                  <reg>you</reg>
               </choice> to write to me on the receipt of this letter either by the first oppurtunity or by mail and would like to hear your views on the subject and also the opinions of your friends. <add>as it is out of my power to leave home</add> Give my respects to your friends and I hope you will pardon the trouble this may give <add>you</add> I wish you to consider this as a confidential consideration as it is not known how matters will turn out until time shall give evidence</p>
            <closer>with Sincere respect I am yours &amp;c <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>A</abbr>
                        <expan>Adam</expan>
                     </choice> Fergusson</name>
               </signed>
               <add>Atttest<lb/>
                  <name>Jona Picket</name>t <lb/> Jona Pickett</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl412d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>James</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Joshua M Coffee </name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name> Alexandria</name>
                     <name>Smith County</name>
                     <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Copy</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
