<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl635">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> [Letter] 1850 Jun. 20, Winchester, Ten[nessee] / John T. Slatter : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Slatter, John T.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl635</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> 1850 Jun. 20, Winchester, Ten[nessee] / John T. Slatter</title>
               <author> Slatter, John T.</author>
               <date when="1850-06-20">June 20, 1850</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from John T. Slatter dated June 20, 1850. It may be to Governor William Trousdale. Slatter is explaining his past orders from former governors of Tennessee regarding the supply of arms to the militia. He mentions Governors Brown and Cannon. Slatter also mentions the  involvement of the militia in the U.S.-Mexican War.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor William Trousdale Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl635</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- Militia</term>
               <term>Military supplies</term>
               <term>Mexico</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Slatter, John T.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl635a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Winchester</name>
                     <name>Franklin <unclear>Bo</unclear>
                     </name>, Ten</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>June 20th 1850</date>.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>During the administration of <choice>
                  <abbr>Ex. Gov.</abbr>
                  <expan>Excellent Governor</expan>
               </choice>
               <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N. S.</abbr>
                     <expan>Neill Smith</expan>
                  </choice> Brown</name>, I <choice>
                  <abbr>recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> instruction from him to collect all of the Public Arms and accoutrements in this country, and report the same to him when collected. I have now in or about collected them all, and can have them ready to send to <name>Nashville</name> at any time. I am informed that the first stand of arms <choice>
                  <orig>brot</orig>
                  <reg>brought</reg>
               </choice> to this <choice>
                  <abbr>co</abbr>
                  <expan>county</expan>
               </choice> was 22 or 3 years since__ They were drawn for the use of a volunteer company, and used by them, some 6 years; at the expiration of which time, the company and muskets were pretty well wornout The captain who commanded the company has been since lied, and but few of the <choice>
                  <abbr>Co.</abbr>
                  <expan>Company</expan>
               </choice> Now remain in this county The 2nd stand of Arms but to this county was in 1837 or 8_ They were brought to this County, for the use of another volunteer Company which was organizing here__ Ex_ Gov. <name>Cannon</name> was then in this <unclear>place,</unclear> and authorized the Company to send <add>to</add>
               <name>Nashville</name> and yet a stand of Arms which was done. About that time, the <name>Texas</name> was Commenced, and some of the Company left for the seat of war, Camping with them some 8 or 10 of the Muskets__ and I have been in formed that they used them to a great advantage in <choice>
                  <orig>massacreeing</orig>
                  <reg>massacring</reg>
               </choice> the Mexicans. The first stand of  Musket are nearly all worn out or lost. The last stand is in a tolerable fair condition <add>considering</add> what they have been through. I had them in my possession, or partly so, until the presidential Election in 1844 when I gave them up to the Democrats, and they were used by them during the Presidential Canvass of that year. Ex_ Gov. Brown <choice>
                  <orig>refered</orig>
                  <reg>referred</reg>
               </choice> me, in his letter, to the act of 1845-6, pages 291 <choice>
                  <abbr>n</abbr>
                  <expan>and</expan>
               </choice> 292. I presume that it is expedient <pb n="2" facs="sl635b.small.jpg"/> for you to take some action <del type="overstrike">with</del> upon the subject They can be repaired in the Penitentiary without Call to the state. I find it a hard matter to keep them together &amp; the sooner they are removed the better. It was the intent of Ex Gov <choice>
                  <abbr>B.</abbr>
                  <expan>Brown</expan>
               </choice> to have them all Collected and <choice>
                  <abbr>retd</abbr>
                  <expan>returned</expan>
               </choice> to Nashville. I should be pleased to hear from you upon the subject. I can refer you to <add>the</add>respectable portion of the community here for the Correctness of my statements____</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>with the highest respect I am your <choice>
                     <abbr>obdt servt</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>John T Slatter</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
