<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl148">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1820 Jan. 8, Frankfort, Kent[uck]y [to] Andrew Crockett, Franklin, Tennessee / R. J. Todd    : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Todd, R. J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl148</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50556458</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1820 Jan. 8, Frankfort, Kent[uck]y [to] Andrew Crockett, Franklin, Tennessee / R. J. Todd</title>
               <author>Todd, R. J. </author>
               <date when="1820-01-08">January 8, 1820</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a  letter from R. J. Todd to Andrew Crockett dated January 8, 1820. Todd is updating Crockett on a land deal and the laws pertaining to it.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Andrew Crockett Papers II-J-5</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">B:2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">F:11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl148</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Real property</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Todd, R. J.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl148a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Frankfort: <choice>
                           <abbr>Kenty</abbr>
                           <expan>Kentucky</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                     <date when="1820-01-08">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Jan</abbr>
                           <expan>January</expan>
                        </choice> 8 1820</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Since you were here nothing has occurred worthy of particular notice. As yet nothing further has been done with relation to our Claim in <name type="place">Woodford</name> . I have seen some of my brothers in Law, and have heard that some one or two of the persons on the Land would perhaps compromise, but are so little interested as to offer terms which would be no consequence or inducement to accept — There is an attempt now making in the Legislature to amend the occupying Claimant Law so as ⁁ <add place="supralinear">to</add> have the Land valued at the time of the occupants settling on it; This if passed of which I am afraid will be in amount taking away the Land from the person suing — upon consultation together, on the subject of this Law and the propriety of compromising should it pass, I am requested by some of the heirs to know whether you would be willing either <pb n="2" facs="sl148b.small.jpg"/> to purchase or to sell out — in as much as the Land if in the hands of one could be managed to better advantage — We presume that if either the alternatives of buying or selling was presented you would prefer selling as your residence &amp; your property is in Tennessee — From the Surveyors plate, It appears that <unclear>
                  <name type="person">Biun</name>'s</unclear> claim owned by <name type="person">Greeney</name>'s which we have lost is about 700 acres; That from the manner that Court of appeals say The survey should be made (even if we should ever recover) we will lose at least 500 acres more — this added to what you and my father have sold will make about 1700 acres which would leave you say 1600 acres or thereabout — The <emph>glorious</emph> uncertainty of the Law may take away even that — Should you be disposed to sell out your title only, you will please write and let me know how much you have sold <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> and also the price you would be willing to <pb n="3" facs="sl148c.small.jpg"/> take for your remaining interest — Should we Consider it under all circumstances a fair and reasonable price in what we consider at the best a <unclear>risqing</unclear> bargain; I will inform you either of our acceptance or rejection of it — The occupying Claimant Law is so <choice>
                  <orig>unfavourable</orig>
                  <reg>unfavorable</reg>
               </choice> to those suing, that we are not disposed to risk much, and you know the quality of the Land — None of us have even seen it — You will let us hear from you <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>as soon</unclear> soon as convenient — In the mean time I shall do all things necessary to bring things to a close, but I am persuaded in any event that the Claim will never be settled but by compromise unless we advance large sums for Improvements made on the Land —</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Yours <choice>
                     <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                     <expan>et cetera</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">R. J. Todd</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="lower left corner">I shall be in this place about 4 or 5 weeks longer, but you can write to me either here or in <name type="place">Lexington</name>.</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl148d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">M. Andrew Crockett</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Franklin</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left of address">Mail</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
