<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm037">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Photograph of an archaeological pit feature at the former site
			 of the mid-18th century Cherokee town of Chota, taken in 1974] / [by David
			 Stansberry]: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Stansberry, David</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Catherine Michelle Love</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Tara Hottenstein</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. 3k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>mm037</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 45090536</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Museum, University of
				Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Photograph of an archaeological pit feature at the former
				site of the mid-18th century Cherokee town of Chota, taken in 1974] / [by David
				Stansberry</title>
               <author>Stansberry, David</author>
               <date>1974</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This is a 1974 photograph of an archaeological
				pit feature at the former site of the mid-18th century Cherokee town of Chota.
				Pits were dug for burial purposes and for storage of refuse. Chota was
				recognized by Native Americans and European settlers as a powerful social and
				economic influence and was regarded as the capital of the Cherokee nation.
				Excavations of Chota and other Overhill Cherokee villages were conducted as
				part of the Tellico Archaeological Project by the University of Tennessee in
				anticipation of the flooding of the lower Little Tennessee River by the Tellico
				Dam Reservoir. The university worked under contract with the National Park
				Service and TVA. Principal investigator, Alfred K. Guthe. Field Director,
				Gerald F. Schroedl.</note>
               <note type="collection">Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note type="document">mm037</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Photographs</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</term>
               <term>Salvage archaeology</term>
               <term>Historic sites</term>
               <term>Refuse and refuse disposal</term>
               <term>Chota Site (Tenn.)</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Photographer http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/pht">Stansberry, David</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mm037.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Recording an archaeological pit feature at Chota, mid-18th
				  century. Excavations by University of Tennessee, 1974. Photograph by David
				  Stansberry. This information was provided by the Frank H. McClung
				  Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
