<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl142">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] [18]28 Dec. 23, Nashville, [TN] [to] John Cocke, Washington, [D.C.] / [illegible]   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>[illegible]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl142</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50555627</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] [18]28 Dec. 23, Nashville, [TN] [to] John Cocke, Washington, [D.C.] / [illegible]</title>
               <author>[illegible]</author>
               <date when="1828-12-23">December 23, 1828</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to John Cocke dated December 23, 1828. The writer is in favor of the US developing a permanent navy. The writer's opinion is that the people in a republican country (as far as keeping their personal freedoms)  are safer because of their navy than they would be from an army. He is also concerned about protecting valuable ports from blockade.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">John Cocke Papers V-J-3</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">F:8</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl142</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>United States -- Navy -- Organization</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name>unknown</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl142a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                     <date when="1828-12-23">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Dcr</abbr>
                           <expan>December</expan>
                        </choice> 23d -'28</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The presidents message has come to hand &amp;  is a State paper of a high order of respectability. I See nothing in it <del type="overstrike">however</del>, but Such information as it was the duty of the president to communicate to Congress except the <choice>
                  <orig>recomendation</orig>
                  <reg>recommendation</reg>
               </choice> of appropriation for the increase of the Navy; and on which Subject I would have been equally well Satisfied had his wishes been expressed even in Stronger terms. I have been raised a Navy man. My old Father was the Steady and constant friend and Supporter of old <name type="person">John Adams</name>, because, ( &amp; for this reason only, ) <del type="overstrike">what</del> he was  boldly <choice>
                  <orig>infavour</orig>
                  <reg>in favor</reg>
               </choice> of a Navy, and a strong military power, in times of <del type="overstrike">war</del>
               <add place="supralinear">peace</add> — I mean a regular force —  the latter I have ever <choice>
                  <orig>Consedered</orig>
                  <reg>Considered</reg>
               </choice> as dangerous to republican institutions; but <del type="overstrike">in</del> a Navy it matters not how strong, Can never be dangerous to the liberties of this <choice>
                  <orig>Republick</orig>
                  <reg>Republic</reg>
               </choice>; and I humbly <choice>
                  <orig>concieve</orig>
                  <reg>conceive</reg>
               </choice> that the <unclear>west</unclear> — the people of the <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Vally</orig>
                     <reg>Valley</reg>
                  </choice> of <choice>
                     <orig>Messesseppi</orig>
                     <reg>Mississippi</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> are as much interested therein as the people of <name type="place">Boston</name> or <name type="place">New York</name>: — Suppose at the commencement of the last war, ( <date when="1812-01">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jany</abbr>
                     <expan>January</expan>
                  </choice> 1812</date>, ) the enemy had lost a fleet of forty sail in the mouth  of the <choice>
                  <abbr>Messpi.</abbr>
                  <expan>Mississippi</expan>
               </choice> and entirely <choice>
                  <orig>bockaded</orig>
                  <reg>blockaded</reg>
               </choice> the Same, and by being relieved, &amp; <choice>
                  <orig>Sustaned</orig>
                  <reg>Sustained</reg>
               </choice> continued to do so for ten years; — Continually threatening <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Norleans</orig>
                     <reg>New Orleans</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name>, and by this <unclear>theory</unclear> Kept the upper Country in continual <choice>
                  <orig>allarm</orig>
                  <reg>alarm</reg>
               </choice>, and a large standing <unclear>lace</unclear> quartered there <pb n="2" facs="sl142b.small.jpg"/> winter and Summer — Will you Calculate <choice>
                  <sic>the  the</sic>
                  <corr>the</corr>
               </choice> consequences? The Key of terrors appeared in <choice>
                  <orig>meletary</orig>
                  <reg>military</reg>
               </choice> form, at <unclear>Durodins</unclear> &amp; <name type="place">waterloo</name>— Hence too odiously — but let a half a dozen <choice>
                  <orig>melitia</orig>
                  <reg>militia</reg>
               </choice> armies perish at <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N.</abbr>
                     <expan>New</expan>
                  </choice> Orleans</name> with yellow fever, and where can troops be had to supply <choice>
                  <orig>thier</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice> place? <emph>Not on the <name type="place">upper Mississippi</name>
               </emph> — aside from this consideration: a ten years blockade, would ruin the country &amp; produce a revolt to our own <choice>
                  <abbr>Govt</abbr>
                  <expan>Government</expan>
               </choice> , <del type="overstrike">unless</del>
               <add place="supralinear">if</add> I am ⁁ <add place="supralinear">not</add> greatly mistaken — unless Some great <unclear>anxiety</unclear> Cause, existed to prevent it. No people on the South for an equal extent of <choice>
                  <orig>teretory</orig>
                  <reg>territory</reg>
               </choice> , are So delicately situated, Geographically. in times of war with an Enemy commanding a large Naval force, as those of the <name type="place">valley of the Mississippi</name>. <unclear>Whos often</unclear> been said to me by the, <emph>"Gun <unclear>Boat</unclear>"</emph>  now  that no fleet Could during the summer blockade the mouth of the river — Suppose the  <name type="place">Island of Cuba</name>, and <name type="place">port of the Havana</name> at the disposal of such enemy; with the power of employing Sailors from the <name type="place">west Indies</name> ?  will every man say the blockade could not be sustained <del type="overstrike">?</del> without Naval opposition? I have so well persuaded myself that this is the most assailable point indirectly ⁁ <add place="supralinear">in the U.S.</add> in terms of war with a Naval enemy, that I think us expense Should deter a western man from <choice>
                  <orig>Garding</orig>
                  <reg>Guarding</reg>
               </choice> against it — and there is only one Security — a Naval power <choice>
                  <orig>Sufficently</orig>
                  <reg>Sufficiently</reg>
               </choice> strong to beat the enemy from <add place="supralinear">our shores</add> the coast, : — And hence, I deem a gradual increase of the Navy the undoubted policy of the Western people. I pray your Sir, to take this as it is <unclear>meant a more</unclear> scheming upon one of my hobbies — the other is the encouragement of <choice>
                  <orig>domestick</orig>
                  <reg>domestic</reg>
               </choice> manufacturing I had greatly rather See a direct tax , than see the country clothed from <name type="place">England</name>, <name type="place">France</name>, &amp; the <name type="place">East Indies</name> — and were I in congress I would <pb n="3" facs="sl142c.small.jpg"/> vote for an increase of tax upon fine cloths and coarse cotton <choice>
                  <orig>fabricks</orig>
                  <reg>fabrics</reg>
               </choice> ⁁<add place="supralinear">imported</add> Our wool is equal to the Spanish; and our cottons above the <unclear/> must find a market at home, if they find any that will Justify growing them. I have some experience in the latter branch of business, and think the common saying, that the South is taxed for the benefit of the North, is mere cant — unnerving cant, for which I never have heard any good  reason offered.</p>
            <p>Last night at 12 <choice>
                  <orig>oclok</orig>
                  <reg>o'clock</reg>
               </choice> departed this life our friend <name type="person">Judge Staywood</name> , after  a <choice>
                  <orig>fiew</orig>
                  <reg>few</reg>
               </choice> days illness. I think he was 66 He submitted to his fate with great fortitude — <unclear>rest</unclear> that Solemn resignation which every man should feel, when <choice>
                  <orig>biding a dieu</orig>
                  <reg>bidding adieu</reg>
               </choice>  to this world .</p>
            <p>we have abundant crops <unclear>here and any</unclear> example within any day.</p>
            <p>In the way of <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> matters, we have nothing — literally nothing.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>with great respect, accept my best wishes</salute>
               <signed>
                  <unclear/>
               </signed>
               <add place="lower left corner">
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Gnl. Jn</abbr>
                        <expan>General John</expan>
                     </choice> Cocke</name>
               </add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl142d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="above address">Free</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Hon.</abbr>
                        <expan>Honorable</expan>
                     </choice> John Cocke.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Washington</name>.</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
