<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="mc004"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1833 Aug. 18, Mouth of Poplar Creek [to]  Geo[rge] L. Welcker, W[est] Point, New York / Cha[rle]s F. Welcker: a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Welcker, Charles</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>mc004</idno><idno>OCLC: 50436466</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1833 Aug. 18, Mouth of Poplar Creek [to]  Geo[rge] L. Welcker, W[est] Point, New York / Cha[rle]s F. Welcker</title><author>Welcker, Charles</author><date value="1833-08-18">August 18, 1833</date><extent> 4p</extent><note type="summary">The following document is a letter dated August 18, 1833, written by Charles F. Welcker in East Tennessee to his brother George L. Welcker in West Point, New York.  Charles writes to inform his brother of the latest news from home, including the results of recent elections and an update on the well-being of friends and family.</note><note type="collection">Welcker Papers</note><note type="box">2</note><note type="folder">1833</note><note type="document">mc004</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</item><item>Military education</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine>Mouth of <name type="place">Poplar Creek</name><date value="1833-08-18"><abbr expan="August">Aug.</abbr> 18th 1833</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Brother</salute></opener><p>I sit down this good sabbath day to write you a letter, we have waited thus long for the happening of certain events that we might give you a full account of as I Should have written sooner among other things the collection of that money at <name type="person">Huntsville</name>  is one which is not yet Accomplished however <name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> <unclear>Brandon</unclear></name> has written that it is ready in his hand and will be transmitted by mail so soon as he receives the proper authority which has recently been sent him but as yet no return although there has been time for it to have been down.  The elections is another <add place="supralinear">the results of</add> which I will give you in as brief a manner as possible.  <name type="person">Blair</name> is   <abbr expan="representative">repr.</abbr> to <abbr expan="Congress">Congr.</abbr> in the 1st <abbr expan="District">Dest.</abbr> beating <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Carter</name> about 11 &amp; <name type="person">Tom Arnold</name> 25 hundred votes Carter knocked Arnold off the stump whilst he was making a speech a short time before the Elections <name type="person">Bunch</name>  in the 2nd beating <name type="person">Cocket Lea</name> in the 3 beating <name type="person">Joseph Williams</name> &amp; <name type="person">Finley Gellespie</name> <unclear>standofer</unclear> is our representative beating <name type="person">Green</name> 1100 &amp; some add votes &amp; so an <name type="person">Cal Vernon</name> beat <name type="person"><unclear>Brazzeal</unclear></name> for <orig reg="senate">sennate</orig> <pb n="[2]"/> by a great majority I know not how much In the <name type="place">Knoxville</name> district <name type="person">Spencer Jarnagan</name> is the <unclear><abbr expan="member">membr</abbr></unclear> for <abbr expan="representative">repr.</abbr> <name type="person">stocton</name> is our <abbr expan="member">membr</abbr> beating <name type="person">John W. Wester</name> 240 &amp; <name type="person"><abbr expan="Buchanan">Buchn.</abbr></name> upwards of 400 Votes <name type="person">Gilliland</name> declined &amp;  gave his support to Stocton or Wester would have been him The most essential of those members you will no doubt have heard from before this reaches you &amp; also those of the western members to Congress however the first account was that <name type="person">Fitzgerald</name>  was one of the delegates from this state but am of the last <name type="place">Nashville </name>papers contradicts that report &amp; declares <name type="person"><emph>Davy</emph> Crockett</name> the man by a majority of 49 votes</p><p>I will Quit this Epistle &amp; give you something else that you will probably feel more interested in. I have seen &amp; heard from <name type="person"><abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr> H. Love</name> <orig reg="occasionally">occationally</orig> he was the last account well &amp; selling <name type="person">judge Mitchell's</name> Book I received a letter from J Mitchell yesterday he and his friends were all well there is <unclear>some</unclear> little Cholera in that County Though there has been none in <name type="place"><abbr expan="East Tennessee">E Tenn</abbr></name> yet at least there is a great deal of skepticism about its being in <name type="place">Knoxville</name> &amp; in <name type="place">Kingston</name> the only two <pb n="[3]"/> places that it has been said to be which are any way near us <name type="person">Henry</name> is doing well in Kingston at school &amp; <name type="person">Catharine</name> is also advancing with her studies Very well &amp; seems to have some taste for painting Father talks of sending them both to Knoxville after this session is out.  <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;c</abbr> <name type="person">Frederick</name> is also doing finely &amp; was in good health 4 days ago we are all well though a few months ago Mother had a spell of <orig reg="spitting">spiting </orig>Blood to which you know she is <orig reg="occasionally">occationally</orig> subject &amp; which <unclear></unclear> her very much but at present her health is pretty much restored we received two letters <gap reason="document damaged" desc="from"/> you one a short time before &amp; the other after your annual examination both of which were very satisfactory besides two reports of the board of visitor, one from you &amp; the other from the war <unclear><abbr expan="department">dept.</abbr></unclear> Things generally seem to be getting along here about as usual I shall start on the morrow in company with <name type="person">James Francis </name> &amp; <name type="person">samuel McCally</name> to the <name type="person">Creek</name> purchase in Acre I have rented my miles &amp; farm for 4 years they are neither a source of much income or satisfaction to me I have <orig reg="temporarily">temperarially</orig> disposed of them to Father and will dispose of them finally if possible <pb n="[4]"/> I am going to this country for the purpose of getting into some kind of business that does not require a capital to commence when this is accomplished I will write and inform you of everything I can accept the respects on well wishes of all <add place="center of page"><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mr. <abbr expan="George">Geo.</abbr> L. Welcker</name> <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr></addrLine><addrLine>Military Academy</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="West">W.</abbr> Point</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">New York</name></addrLine><addrLine>mail</addrLine></address></add> </p><p>Your friends Brother  &amp; sisters Your parents and also this hasty but sincere assure of the love and esteem  of your Brother</p><closer><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Charles">Chas</abbr> F Welcker</name></signed><address><addrLine><emph>To <abbr type="George">Geo</abbr> L. Welcker</emph></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
