<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="mc014"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1832 Sept. 5 [to] Mr. Gillespie / William Richard Caswell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Caswell, William Richard</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>mc014</idno><idno>OCLC: 50449225</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1832 Sept. 5 [to] Mr. Gillespie / William Richard Caswell</title><author>Caswell, William Richard</author><date value="1820-05-03">September 5, 1832</date><extent> 2p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated September 5, 1832, written by William Richard Caswell to one Mr. Gillespie. The letter discusses possible candidates for the Senate.</note><note type="collection">William R. Caswell Papers</note><note type="box">MS-18, b1</note><note type="folder">1</note><note type="document">mc014</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville </name><date value="1832-09-05"><abbr expan="September">Sep.</abbr> 5th 1832</date></addrLine><addrLine><name type="person">Mr. Gillespie</name></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>Everything was going on so well at home, that I concluded day before yesterday, to come down here , and breathe the same atmosphere with the great men of our nation. Last evening, I was in the company of the President, <abbr expan="General's">Genl's</abbr> <name type="person">Eaton</name>, <name type="person">Carrol, </name> &amp; <name type="person">Coffee</name>&caret;<add place="supralinear"><name type="person">Judge White Houston</name><abbr expan="and et cetera and et cetera"> &amp;c &amp;c.</abbr></add> Eaton is spoken of very strongly for Senator, though I can scarcely believe that he will be a candidate. Great interest and excitement is manifested by almost every person in the election. <name type="person">Mr. Foster</name>, is engaged every moment of his time in electioneering, and requested me to write to you. He says that <name type="person">McFarland</name> he thinks will vote for him, but he fears that <name type="person">Mr. Fain</name> &amp; <name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Brazelton</name> will make him (Mc F.) render a rigid account to his constituents for his vote. Mr Foster says that you can do something with Mr. Fain &amp; <abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Brazelton, to relieve Mr. McFarland from this embarrassment; I have written a short letter, to Mr. Fain, but you will see him, and can talk to him upon the subject. I find that the papers you sent to Mr. F. have been filed in the Secretary's office, but <name type="person">McGraw</name> has neglected to send the papers, which he promised to do. The secretary says that I can file them at my leisure. I will write to <abbr expan="Major">Maj.</abbr> McGraw immediately, &amp; request him to forward the <add place="supralinear">necessary</add> papers without delay.</p><pb n="[2]"/><p>I have not said much yet about the claim of  <name type="person">Carters</name> heirs, but <name type="person">D. Dickinson</name> has promised me to attend to it. I <abbr expan="talked">talk'd</abbr> with <abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> <name type="person">Wiley</name> about it, he gave me to understand that <name type="person">Mr. Gillespie</name> of <name type="place">Blount <abbr expan="County">Cy</abbr></name> would introduce a resolution that will suit the claim But I do not think that <abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Wiley <add place="supralinear">will</add> give the measure his support; he is in my opinion a recreant and an apostate from his old friends &amp; their interest. He is I am told boarding at <name type="person">Grundy's</name> son in law's house ( <name type="person">I McGavock</name>);  and electioneers hard for Grundy. I still think Mr. Fosters Prospect good, even against<name type="person"> J. H. Eaton</name> </p><p>I shall return home tomorrow &amp; I will write to Elizabeth, as soon as I return. Give my love to her &amp; to the family.</p></div1><closer><salute>Yours Affectionately</salute></closer><closer><signed><name><abbr expan="William Richard">Wm Richd</abbr> Caswell</name></signed><add><p>The legislature is waiting upon the committee of the congressional districts&mdash;It is pretty generally understood that J.H. Eaton will be run for the Senate. Mr. Foster says he will fight him to the ditch. I have just placed your papers in the hands of  D. Dickinson, who promises to attend to them. </p></add><salute><abbr expan="Yours and et cetera">Yrs. &amp;c</abbr></salute><signed>Caswell</signed></closer></body></text></TEI.2>
