<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="mc015"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Minutes of Rail Road meeting] 1836 June 28 / A. C. Eaton : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Eaton, A. C.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>mc015</idno><idno>OCLC: 50449596</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Minutes of Rail Road meeting] 1836 June 28 / A. C. Eaton</title><author>Eaton, A. C.</author><date value="1836-06-28">June 28, 1836</date><extent>1 p</extent><note type="summary">This document is the minutes from a railroad meeting dated June 28, 1836. Four delegates were chosen to attend a convention to be held in Knoxville, Tennessee on July 4th 1837. Delegates from all over the United States would then discuss the construction of a railroad from Cincinnati, Ohio to Charleston, South Carolina. </note><note type="collection">William R. Caswell Papers</note><note type="box">MS-18, b1</note><note type="folder">2</note><note type="document">mc015</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Railroads -- Design and construction</item><item>Business meetings</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>United States</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="writing"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><date rend="penciled in" value="1836-06-28">June 28 1836</date></opener><head>Rail Road Meeting</head><p>In pursuance of Public Notice previously given The citizens of <name type="place">Russelville Jefferson County <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name> convened on Tuesday<date value="1836-06-28"> 28th June 1836</date>.</p><p>On Motion of <name type="person"><abbr expan="Robert">Robt</abbr> Patten</name> <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> <name type="person">A. C. Eaton</name> was called to the chair; &amp; on motion of  <name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel George">Col Geo</abbr>  T. Gillespie; </name> <name type="person">John S. Moffett</name> was appointed Secretary; <name type="person"><abbr expan="Major William Richard">Maj Wm R.</abbr> Caswell</name> then addressed the meeting on the subject of Internal improvement; &amp; offered the following preamble &amp; resolutions which were unanimously adopted;  whereas on the <date value="0000-07-04">4th July</date> next a convention is to be held in<name type="place"> Knoxville</name> of Delegates from every part of the <name type="place">United States</name> which is immediately interested in the construction of a Rail Road from <name type="place">Cincinnati</name> to <name type="place">Charleston</name> and whereas we approve of said convention and believe that the interest of this <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood</orig> requires that we should be represented in said convention. Therefore Resolved 1st that four delegates be <del type="overstrike">appointed from</del> this <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood </orig>to attend said convention with authority to Represent the will and Interest of this section of Country</p><p>Resolved 2nd That our delegates be and they are hereby instructed to use all proper means to promote &amp; facilitate the construction of said Rail Road.</p><p>The meeting proceeded to appoint <name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel George T.">Col Geo T. </abbr>Gillespie</name>  <name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> A. C. Eaton</name> <name><abbr expan="Major William Richard">Maj Wm R</abbr> Caswell</name> &amp;<name type="person"> Mr James W. Deaderick</name> as the four delegates in conformity with the 1st Resolutions adopted</p><p>Resolved 3rd That the proceedings of this meeting be signed by the chairman &amp; secretary and a copy thereof forwarded to the editors of the Knoxville Register &amp; East Tennessean for Publication</p><closer><salute>The meeting then adjourned</salute></closer><closer><signed><name type="person">John S.Moffett</name>secretary</signed></closer><closer><signed><name type="person">A. C. Eaton</name> Chairman</signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
