<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="mc024"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1835 Dec. 18 [to] Henry Welcker / Catharine Welcker : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Welcker, Catharine</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>mc024</idno><idno>OCLC: 50472614</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1835 Dec. 18 [to] Henry Welcker / Catharine Welcker</title><author>Welcker, Catharine</author><date value="1835-12-18">December 18, 1835</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated December 18, 1835 to Henry Welcker from his sister Catharine Welcker. Catharine writes of various events that  occurred in her boarding school in Kingston Tennessee.</note><note type="collection">Welker Papers</note><note type="box">MS-12, b2</note><note type="folder">June-Dec. 1835</note><note type="document">mc024</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Boarding school students</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine>Kingston <unclear>H Acd.</unclear><date value="1835-00-00">1835</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Henry</salute></opener><p>I have long and <orig reg="patiently">patienty</orig> waited in the hope of receiving a letter from you but have as oft been disappointed. </p><p>I have often dwelt with anxiety on the seeming neglect with <orig reg="which">wich</orig> I was treated by you. but <orig reg="consoled">cosoled</orig> myself with the idea that it did not <orig reg="precede">procede</orig> from any want of affection but rather from negligence.</p><p>was I Just.</p><p>I heard the other day that <name type="person">Mr. Howell</name> the son-in-law of <name type="person">Mrs. Richards</name> traveled one day in company with <name type="person">Mr. Mitchell</name>, while on his to the state of <name type="place">Mississippi</name>. Sister <name type="person">Malinda</name> and her family were with him they were all well.</p><p>our school commenced on the second Monday in <abbr expan="November">Nov</abbr> there are only 24 scholars and sister <name type="person">Mary</name> and myself make 2 of that number. we board at <abbr expan="Doctor">Doct </abbr><name type="person">Jordan's.</name> Mary studies Geography and I study Chemists and rhetoric.</p><p>I received a letter from Brother <name type="person">Frederic</name> a few days since he said that he had been very busily engaged since he left home; he was very much pleased with the arrangements of the boarding house and College&mdash; he said that<name type="person"> James H. Paine,</name><name type="person">W. Hardon,</name> <name type="person">P.M W.</name> and himself were all in one room together Perfect they have some <unclear>rare</unclear> time there I know they do if they are as bad <pb n="[2]"/> as the school girls are. for you may depend we have real <orig reg="jovial">jovel</orig> times here, and if you were here we would introduce you to the King and Queen.  it is quite an amusing play.</p><p>tell sister <name type="person">Caroline</name> to write to me I have been expecting a letter from her for some time.</p><p>give my love to all the family and as for yourself accept a large portion of love from your sister</p><closer><signed><name type="person">Catharine J. Welcker</name></signed><add><name type="person">Henry J. Welcker</name></add><add><abbr expan="Post Script">P.S.</abbr> tell aunt <name type="person">Milly </name>that Miss<name type="person"> Sarah</name> and Mr. Hail were united in the bonds of Matrimony a few weeks since.</add><pb n="[3]"/><address><addrLine>Kingston<abbr expan="Tennessee"> Ten</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1835-12-18"><abbr expan="December">Dec.</abbr> 18th 1835</date></addrLine></address>&rcub;<add><address><addrLine>Mr Henry J. Welcker</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Talladega Alabama</name></addrLine></address></add><add place="top of letter">18 3/4</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
