<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="mc022"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1846 Oct. 10 [to] Mrs. W[illia]m R. Caswell / W[illia]m R. Caswell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Caswell, William R.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>mc022</idno><idno>OCLC: 50474409</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1846 Oct. 10 [to] Mrs. W[illia]m R. Caswell / W[illia]m R. Caswell</title><author>Caswell, William R.</author><date value="1846-10-10">October 10, 1846</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written by Captain William Richard Caswell to his wife on October 10, 1846. Captain Caswell was a volunteer from Tennessee who served in the Mexican-American War. In the letter, Caswell expresses his unhappiness that his wife has not written to him in a while, in addition to his concern for her and their family's health. Caswell also discusses events going on in the war and the character of the other soldiers stationed with him. He concludes the letter by expressing his, as well as another soldier's, interest in learning to speak Spanish in order to understand what is being said around him.</note><note type="collection">William R. Caswell Papers</note><note type="box">MS-18, b1</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">mc022</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Mexican War, 1846-1848</item><item>United States</item><item>Mexico</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><add place="top of page">No 18</add><address><addrLine><name type="place">Camargo, Mexico</name> <date value="1846-10-10">10th October 1846</date></addrLine></address><salute>My Dear Wife.</salute></opener><p><name type="person"><abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr> Brookins Campbell</name>, from <name type="place">Washington County</name>, arrived here <orig reg="yesterday">yesturday</orig> evening, direct from <name type="place">Tennessee</name>, by way of <name type="place">Nashville</name> - My first question to him, was to ascertain how your health was and <orig reg="although">athough</orig> he could give me no direct answer to my interrogatories upon this subject, yet I derived much comfort from my cross examination of him, and Mr. Royston who came with him - They said they did not hear particularly how you was but merely that all were well - this of course was no satisfaction but they said they saw <name type="person">Eliza</name>, in a carriage with <name type="person">Mary</name>, returning from a visit to <name type="person">Ann</name> in <name type="person">Knoxville</name>, &amp; from this I <orig reg="inferred">infered</orig> your health must have materially improved, or Eliza would not have left you. - And I could only guess, whether you was at home or not - They saw my Mother at Nashville, she was on a visit to <name type="person">Mrs. Foster</name>, who was very sick - My mother sent me a very fine black silk cravat, and &caret;<add place="supralinear">2</add> pairs of Lambs - wool socks -<name type="person">James Nichol</name> wrote to me, that Ma had heard from you, and that you was very well. I expect it was about such information as I received <abbr expan="through">thro'</abbr> <name type="person"><abbr expan="Major Campbell">Majr. C.</abbr></name> I have only received one letter from you (and that was by <name type="person"><abbr expan="Lieutenant">Lieut.</abbr> Turnley</name>) Since I left home. I suppose my letters have been sent to <name type="place">San Antonio</name>. - If I had <abbr expan="received">recd.</abbr> them I should have had many of my anxious conjectures explained, relative to your <orig reg="health">heath</orig> &amp; comfort, relative to Eliza, to our little boy - to your Ma, &amp; Mary, <name type="person">Alfred</name>, <name type="person">Henry</name>, <name type="person">Ann</name> &amp; our family, our servants, our <orig reg="neighbors">neighbours</orig> - <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp; c</abbr> - What has become of <name type="person"><abbr expan="Thomas">Thos.</abbr> M. Anderson</name> - If he is at home - tell him to write me all the little <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood</orig> news - and direct his letter to "<name type="person">Captain <abbr expan="William Richard">Wm. R</abbr>. Caswell</name>" "  Care of <name type="person"><abbr expan="Brigadier General">Brig. Gen.</abbr> Pillow</name>." "<unclear>Hd Irs.</unclear> 2nd Brigade. <name type="place"><abbr expan="United States of America">U.S.A</abbr></name>". "<name type="place">Mexico</name>"- And so you can direct your letters; But I cannot tell where our Head Quarters may be when a letter will reach me from home, after you receive this.. I have calculated that the war would now be ended without any more fighting, but our negotiations must proceed slowly, and that therefore I shall be delayed some time yet in my return home - <pb n="[2]"/> The Officers of the Army however, generally believe that the war is to be protracted - and carried on with rigor and energy - A <orig reg="dispatch">despatch</orig> messenger from <name type="place">Washington City</name> passed here last Thursday, on his way to <name type="place">Monterey</name>, with secret orders to <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Taylor</name>, - I suppose I know their substance <abbr expan="through">thro'</abbr> a letter from the President to <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Gen.</abbr> Pillow</name> - We are looking for a reply from <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Taylor in a few days - with Orders to <name type="name"><abbr expan="General">Gen</abbr>. Patterson</name> with <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Pillow &amp; his command and a considerable force, to make a pressing attack upon the enemy <hi>in another direction</hi> - And my calculation is that in about two weeks more I shall join my company at <name type="place">Matamoras</name> - and proceed along the Western Coast of the Gulf - But no calculations are to be relied on, by a person who has to obey any and all orders he may receive - You know an armistice was agreed upon by <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Taylor &amp; <unclear>Ampudid</unclear>, that there should be a cessation of hostilities for two months - this ends on &caret; <add place="supralinear">or about</add> the <date value="0000-11-20">20th <abbr expan="November">Novr</abbr></date>- and at the end of the Armistice, we will be ready to enter with renewed energy upon the war - Under this view of my future course, I shall not be farther north, of this, or west in this latitude, on military duty - and having nothing now to do but to await orders - I expect to take a trip of pleasure to<name type="place"> Monterey</name>, and to go up with a company which leaves here on day after <orig reg="tomorrow">to-morrow</orig>, - <name type="person">David Cummings</name> is the only <name type="person">East <orig reg="Tennessean">Tennesseean</orig></name> who will probably go with me - and when I get to Monterey or soon after my return (for I shall remain there but a few days) I will write to you - and if I can collect materials, with leisure to write - I will write a letter to some of our papers - which you will see ( if published) and will not be repeated in my letter to you - I have just within the last hour concluded to go to Monterey - I may meet with some obstacle &caret; <add place="supralinear">in contrary orders-</add> <name type="person">Balie Peyton</name> and <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Marshall</name> have been expected to fight a duel here <orig reg="today">to-day</orig> - as they quarrelled <orig reg="yesterday">yesturday</orig> &amp;, struck each other with their fist <pb n="[3]"/> It has however been compromised &amp; settled this evening - <name type="person">Mr. Royston</name> tells me that <name type="person">Sam. Carter</name>. has resigned and returned home - I am surprised at this - if you see Sam. tell him to write to me - I have interrogated <name><abbr expan="Mr. Royston">Mr. R.</abbr></name> very closely - but I regret he could not give me any more particular news about you - <date value="0000-10-12"><hi><abbr expan="October">Octr</abbr>. 12th</hi></date>. I have received <orig reg="today">to-day</orig> a letter from Henry, which I do assure was very gratifying to me, and tell him whenever I can render him as great favor I will do so; but my letters to you must be <del type="overstrike">an an</del> answers to him, and to Eliza -This morning I was on duty in furnishing details of workmen in the Quarter Masters department, as blacksmiths - And in making up a company to visit Monterey, to start on day after <orig reg="tomorrow">to-morrow</orig> morning, for you must recollect that, a small party is considered to be in danger of being cut off by Robbers, whom we generally suppose to belong to Canales band - In the afternoon, I met with a duelling party, two <name type="place">Texas</name> Captains with their seconds I went out with them upon the ground - we all concluded to try and make up the difficulty - at one time we gave up the hope of a compromise, &amp; squared ourselves to see them fire at 40 <abbr expan="yards">yds</abbr> distant with rifles but it was finally compromised - And to gratify my curiosity, in this - I exposed myself to a thorough drenching of <orig reg="rain">raine</orig> - I have no news of any change in the position or movements of the Army - The only movements now going on are heavy baggage trains, loaded with provisions, from here to Monterey, and guarded generally by some 200 Soldiers - And within the last day or two - many <name type="person">Texas Rangers</name> who have been discharged, returning home &caret; <add place="supralinear">many</add> with trophies - such as Mexican Lances, swords, guns, Saddles - horses <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;c</abbr> - <abbr expan="Although">Altho</abbr> I have not <abbr expan="received">recd.</abbr> letters - I know they have been written - you must keep up writing, for I think I shall begin to receive them soon- In the mean time. I shall write every day or two &amp; <orig reg="dispatch">despatch</orig> you a letter at least every week or two - I take more pleasure in  <pb n="[4]"/> writing to than any other person - Give my love to Eliza - Kiss the little boy for his father - I would say many things to Eliza but she knows I love her very much, and she is too good a girl to need any advice from me - I wish she were at school &mdash; My love to your Ma - &amp; Henry &amp; the rest of the family present</p><closer><salute>Your Affectionate Husband</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="William Richard">Wm. R.</abbr> Caswell</name><add place="center of page"> <add place="above address" cert="different hand, different ink"><unclear>B ????</unclear></add><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs. <abbr expan="William Richard">Wm. R.</abbr> Caswell</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Russelville</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Jefferson County</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine></address></add><add place="left of address"><name type="person">Captain Reynolds</name> and myself occasionally call up a <name type="person">Mexican</name> who may be passing - and make him to talk for us to learn the language - but we make very little progress - <lb/> <abbr expan="Your">Yr</abbr> Husband. <abbr expan="Caswell">C.</abbr></add></signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
