<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="mc035"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1846 Jul. 22 [to] Benjamin McCulloch / William R. Caswell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Caswell, William R.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>mc035</idno><idno>OCLC: 50474625</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1846 Jul. 22 [to] Benjamin McCulloch / William R. Caswell</title><author>Caswell, William R.</author><date value="1846-07-22">July 22, 1846</date><extent> 3p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated July 22, 1846 from Captain William Caswell to his father, Benjamin McCulloch of Murfreesboro Tennessee. Caswell wrote from aboard the Steamship Champion on his wait to fight as one of the Tennessee volunteers in the Mexican-American War.</note><note type="collection">William R. Caswell Papers</note><note type="box">MS-18, b1</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">mc035</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Mexican War, 1846-1848</item><item>United States</item><item>Mexico</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine>Steam Boat Champion<date value="1846-07-22">22nd July 1846</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Pa,</salute></opener><p>When I left <name type="place">Knoxville,</name> I fully intended to come<abbr expan="through"> thro</abbr> <name type="place">Murfreesboro</name> &amp; expected then to march my company <abbr expan="through">thro</abbr> there, but I could not, &amp; regretted it very much. Upon our arrival at <name type="place">Memphis, </name> the election of field officers took place in a few days &amp; I was so simple as to be a candidate for <abbr expan="Lieutenant Colonel">Lieut. Col.</abbr> against what I am <orig reg="persuade">persuad</orig> was a combination&mdash; I have been repeatedly told since, that if the election had been delayed ten days I could have beat any man in the regiment for <abbr expan="Colonel Commandment">Col. Comdt.</abbr> this may however have been flattery&mdash; The command of a Captain is the prettiest command in the Army&mdash; but I have been persuaded to leave my company, and act as Aid to <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Pillow</name> with the privilege of rejoining my company upon the <name type="place">Rio Grande,</name> when they shall reach there, but to reach there they will have a toilsome march of three months&mdash; I have a comfortable situation&mdash; I left my company this morning &amp; am now on board this boat, in company with <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr>. Pillow &amp; <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Butler </name>of <name type="place"><abbr expan="Kentucky">Ky.</abbr></name>  we will make no longer stay in <name type="place">Orleans</name> than we can procure a conveyance to <name type="place">Point Isabel,</name>  unless some of the <name type="place">Tennessee</name> volunteers, should still be there, &amp; we should be delayed, in procuring transportation for them.</p><p>If I had taken the land route, and lived, <pb n="[2]"/> two or three months longer in camps, I believe I should have recovered of the dispersion but in the Generals Staff, I am tempted with all the luxuries of good eating&mdash; I have met with no acquaintance in the army yet from <name type="place">Rutherford</name> except <name type="person">George McKnight,</name>  who is a jovial fellow &amp; had become very intimate with me &amp; particularly so with my 1st Lieutenant. Give my love to Ma &amp; all the family Tell Ben &amp; Phil and<name type="person"> Mr. Hord</name> to write to me, to <name type="place">Matamoras</name>&mdash; " Captain&mdash; Tennessee Cavalry."</p><closer><salute>Yours Affectionately</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="William Richard">Wm. R.</abbr> Caswell</name></signed><pb n="[3]"/><add place="above address" cert="stamped on address page"><figure><figDesc>Postmark</figDesc></figure>STEAM</add><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mr. Benjamin McCulloch</name></addrLine><addrLine>Murfreesboro</addrLine><addrLine>Tennessee</addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
