<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tl217">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Constitution of the Cherokee Nation, 1827 Jul. 24, New Town Echota: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>tl217</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 49961787</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Constitution of the Cherokee Nation, 1827 Jul. 24, New Town Echota</title>
               <date when="1827-07-24">July 24, 1827</date>
               <extent>24p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is the constitution drafted on July 24, 1827 that sparked the beginning of the modern Cherokee Nation.  The document was a product of a Constitutional Convention of 1827, headed by John Ross, who was elected the first Chief of the Cherokee Nation when the constitution was put into effect the following year.  In the constitution, which was largely patterned after the United States', the Cherokees referred to themselves as a sovereign entity and outlined  three branches of government.  Although the Constitution of the Cherokee Nation was largely developed in order to prevent the forced removal of the Cherokee, it was only ten years after its adoption that the Cherokee were ultimately displaced.    </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true"> Constitution of the Cherokee Nation </note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">Tennessee State Library, Miscellaneous documents</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">tl217</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Politics and government</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Legal status, laws, etc.</term>
               <term>Sovereignty</term>
               <term>Southeastern U.S.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tl217a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <add place="top right">1</add> We the Representatives of the people of the <name type="place">Cherokee Nation</name>, in Convention assembled in order to establish justice ensure tranquility, promote our common welfare, and secure to ourselves and our posterity the blessings of liberty acknowledging with humility and gratitude the goodness of the sovereign ruler of the Universe <choice>
                  <orig>offording</orig>
                  <reg>affording</reg>
               </choice> us an opportunity so favorable to the design and imploring his aid and direction in its accomplishments do ordain and establish this Constitution for the Government of the Cherokee Nation.</p>
            <p>Article 1st.</p>
            <p>The boundaries of this nation embracing the lands solemnly guaranteed and reserved forever to the Cherokee Nation the treaties concluded with the <name type="place">United States</name> is as follows, and which shall forever hereafter remain unalterably the same; To wit: Beginning on the north bank of <name type="place">Tennessee River</name> at the <choice>
                  <orig>uper</orig>
                  <reg>upper</reg>
               </choice> part of the <name type="place">Chickasaw Old Fields</name> thence along the main Channel of said River <add place="supralinear">including</add> all the islands therein to the mouth of <name type="place">Highwassee River</name> thence up the main channel of said river including Islands to the first Hill which closes in on said river about two miles above <name type="place">highwassee Old Town</name>  thence along the ridge which divides the waters of the <name type="place">highwassee Little Tellico</name> , to the Tennessee river at <name type="place">Tallassee</name> thence along the main channel including Islands to the junction of <name type="place">Cowee</name> &amp; <name type="place">Nonteyalee</name> thence along the ridge in the fork of <pb n="2" facs="tl217b.small.jpg"/> said river to the top of the blue ridge, thence along the blue ridge to the <name type="place">Unicoy Turnpike road</name> thence a straight line to the nearest main source of the <name type="place">Chestotee</name> ; thence along its main channel, including Islands to the <name type="place">Chatahoochie</name> and thence down the same to the Creek boundary at <name type="place">Buzzard roast</name>, thence along the boundary line which separates this and the <name type="place">Creek Nation</name>, to a point on the <name type="place">Coosa river</name> opposite the mouth of <name type="place">Wills Creek</name> thence down along the South Bank of the same to a point, opposite <name type="place">Fort Strothers</name> thence up the river <add place="supralinear">to</add> the mouth of Wills Creek, thence up along the east Bank of said Creek to the west branch, thereof and up the same to its source &amp; thence along the ridge which <choice>
                  <orig>seperates</orig>
                  <reg>separates</reg>
               </choice> the <name type="place">Tombigby</name> &amp; Tennessee waters, to a point on the top of said ridge thence a due north Course to <name type="place">Camp Coffee</name>, on Tennessee which is opposite the <name type="place">Chickasaw Island</name>, thence to a place of beginning</p>
            <p>Section 2. The <choice>
                  <orig>sovereignity</orig>
                  <reg>sovereignty</reg>
               </choice> &amp; jurisdiction of this Government shall extend over the Country within the boundaries above described, and the lands therein is &amp; shall remain the Common property of the nation; but  the improvements made thereon and in possession of the citizens of the nation, are the exclusive &amp; indefeasible property of the citizens respectively who made or may rightly be in possession of them provided that the Citizens  of the nation possessing exclusive and <orig resp="#indefeasible">indefeasable</orig> rights to their respective improvements, <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear/>
               </del> expressed in this <pb n="3" facs="tl217c.small.jpg"/> article, shall possess no right nor power to dispose of their improvements in any manner whatever to the United States  individual states, nor to individual Citizens thereof and that whenever any such Citizen or Citizens shall remove with their effects out of the limits of this nation and become Citizens of any Other government all their rights and <choice>
                  <orig>privoleges</orig>
                  <reg>privileges</reg>
               </choice> as Citizens of this nation Cease, Provided nevertheless the legislature shall have power to readmit by law, all the rights of <choice>
                  <orig>Citizen Ship</orig>
                  <reg>Citizenship</reg>
               </choice> to any such person or persons who may at any time desire to return to this nation by memorializing the General Council for such readmission — Moreover, the Legislature Shall have power to adopt such laws &amp; regulations as its wisdom may deem expedient and proper to prevent the citizens from monopolizing improvements with the view of speculation.</p>
            <p>
               <emph>Article 2.</emph> The powers of this Government shall be divided with three distinct departments, the legislative, Executive, and Judicial. 2nd. No person or persons belonging to one of these departments shall exercise any of the powers properly belonging to either of the others; except in cases herein after expressly directed or permitted.</p>
            <p>
               <emph>Article 3.</emph> The Legislative power shall be vested in two distinct branches, a Committee and a Council each to have a negative on the other, and both to be <unclear>stiled</unclear> the General Council of the Cherokee nation, and the style <pb n="4" facs="tl217d.small.jpg"/> of their acts and laws shall be Resolved by the Committee and Council in General Council Convened.</p>
            <p>Section 2. The Cherokee Nation as laid off into eight Districts, shall remain so.</p>
            <p>Section 3. The committee shall consist of two members from each district and the Council shall consist of three members from each district, to be chosen by the qualified electors of their respective districts for two years, and the elections to be held in every district on the first monday in <date when="--08">august</date> for the year <date when="1828">1828</date> and every succeeding two years thereafter.  and the <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Council shall be held once a year to be convened on the second Monday of October in each year at <name type="place">New, echota</name> no person shall be eligible to a seat in the general Council but a free cherokee male citizens, who shall have attained  to the age of <choice>
                  <orig>twenty five</orig>
                  <reg>twenty-five</reg>
               </choice> years the descendants of Cherokee men by all free women (except the african race) whose parents  may <add place="supralinear">be</add> or may have been living together as man and wife according to the Customs &amp; laws of this nation &amp; shall be entitled to all the rights and <choice>
                  <orig>privoleges</orig>
                  <reg>priveleges</reg>
               </choice> of this Nation, as well as the posterity of cherokee woman by all free men, no person who is of a negro or <choice>
                  <orig>mulato</orig>
                  <reg>mulatto</reg>
               </choice> parentage either by the father or mother side, shall be eligible to hold any office of profit or honor or trust under this Government The electors and members to the G
eneral Council shall in all cases except in those of treason, felony, or breach of <pb n="5" facs="tl217e.small.jpg"/> the peace be <choice>
                  <orig>privoledged</orig>
                  <reg>privileged</reg>
               </choice> from arrest during their attendance at elections and the General Council, and in going to or returning from the same.  In all elections by the people the electors shall vote Vi — Va — Voce.</p>
            <p>Elections for members to the General Council  for <date when="1828">1828</date> shall be held at the place of holding their several courts &amp; at the other two precincts in each Districts which are designated by the law under which the members of this convention were elected, and that the district Judges shall superintend the elections within the precinct of their respective Court Houses; and the <choice>
                  <orig>marshalls</orig>
                  <reg>marshals</reg>
               </choice> &amp; Sheriffs to superintend the precincts which may be assigned them by the Circuit Judges of their respective District, together with one other person who shall be appointed by the circuit Judges for each precinct within the District of their respective Circuits, and the Circuit Judges shall also appoint a clerk to each precinct, The <choice>
                  <orig>superintendant</orig>
                  <reg>superintendent</reg>
               </choice> &amp; clerks shall on the Wednesday morning <choice>
                  <orig>preceeding</orig>
                  <reg>preceding</reg>
               </choice> the elections assemble at their respective court Houses and proceed to examine and ascertain the true state of the polls and shall Issue to each member duly elected a Certificate and also make an official return of the state of the polls of election to the Principal Chief and it shall be the duty of the Sheriffs to deliver the same to the executive office provided nevertheless the <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Council shall have power <pb n="6" facs="tl217f.small.jpg"/>  after the elections of <date when="1828">1828</date> to regulate by law the precincts &amp; <choice>
                  <orig>superintendants</orig>
                  <reg>superintendents</reg>
               </choice> &amp; clerks of election in the several Districts.</p>
            <p>Section 4. All free male Citizens (excepting negroes &amp; descendants of white &amp; Indian men by Negro women who may have been set free) who shall have attained to the age of 18 years shall be equally entitled to vote at all public elections, —</p>
            <p>Section 5. Each house of the General Council shall judge of the qualifications, elections &amp; returns of its own members</p>
            <p>Section 6. Each house of the <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl.</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Council may determine the rules of its proceedings punish a member for disorderly <choice>
                  <orig>behaviour</orig>
                  <reg>behavior</reg>
               </choice> and with the Concurrence of two thirds expel a member, but not a second time for the same cause.</p>
            <p>Section 7. Each House of the <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl.</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Council  when assembled shall choose its own officers, a majority  of each House shall constitute a quorum to do business, but a smaller number may adjourn from day to day, and compel the attendance of absent members, in such manner and under such penalties as each House may prescribe —</p>
            <p>Section 8 — The members of the Committee Shall each receive from the public Treasury a compensation for their services — which Shall be, two dollars and fifty cents per day, during their attendance at the general Council, and the Members of the Council, Shall each receive, Two dollars per day <pb n="7" facs="tl217g.small.jpg"/> for their Services during their attendance at the General Council provided that the same, may be increased or diminished, by law; but no alteration shall take effect, during the period of service of the Members of the General Council, by whom such alterations shall have been made —</p>
            <p>Section 9. The General Council, shall regulate by law, by whom, and in what manner, Writs of election Shall be issued, to fill the vacancies which may happen, in either branch thereof </p>
            <p>Section 10. Each member of the General Council before he takes his seat, Shall take the following oath or affirmation, to wit — I A.B. do solemnly swear or affirm, as the case may be, that I have not obtained my election by bribery, treats or any undue, and unlawful Means, used by myself or others, by my desire, or approbation for that purpose, that I consider myself Constitutionally qualified as a member of <gap agent="damage"/> and that in all questions, and measures which may come, before me, I will give my vote, and So conduct myself, as may in my judgment appear most conducive to the interest and prosperity of this nation, and that I will bear, true faith and allegiance to the same <pb n="8" facs="tl217h.small.jpg"/> and to the utmost of my ability, and power observe, confirm to Support and defend the Constitution thereof.</p>
            <p>Section 11.  No person who may be convicted of felony before any Court of this nation, Shall be eligible to any office or appointment, of honor profit or trust, within this nation —</p>
            <p>Section 12. The General Council Shall have power to make, all laws and regulations, which they shall deem necessary and proper, for the good of the nation, which shall not be contrary to his Constitution —</p>
            <p>Section 13. It shall be the duty of the General Council to pass such laws, as may be necessary and proper, to decide differences, by Arbitrators to be appointed by the parties, who may choose that summary mode of adjustment —</p>
            <p>Section 14 — No power of suspending the laws of this nation Shall be <choice>
                  <orig>excercised</orig>
                  <reg>exercised</reg>
               </choice> unless by the Legislature or its authority</p>
            <p>Section 15. That no retrospective laws nor any law, impairing the obligation of contracts shall be passed —</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>16</unclear> The Legislature shall have power to make laws for laying &amp; collecting taxes for <pb n="9" facs="tl217i.small.jpg"/>  the purpose of raising a revenue —</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>17</unclear> All Bills making appropriations shall originate in the Committee; but the Council may propose amendments or reject the same —</p>
            <p>Section 18. All other Bills, may originate in either House, Subject to the concurrence, or rejection of the other —</p>
            <p>Section 19. All acknowledged Treaties shall be the Supreme law of the land</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>20</unclear> The General Council shall have the sole power of deciding on the Construction of all treaty stipulations. the Council Shall have the Sole power of impeaching —</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>21</unclear> All impeachments shall be tried by the Committee when sitting for that purpose the members shall be upon oath or affirmation no person shall be Convicted without the Concurrence of two thirds of the members present</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>22</unclear> The principal chief assistant principal Chief and all civil officers under this nation shall be liable to impeachments for any misdemeanor in office, but judgement in such cases, shall not extend for than removal office, and disqualification to hold any office of honor, trust, or profit, under this nation the party whether convicted or acquitted, shall neverthe- <pb n="10" facs="tl217j.small.jpg"/> less be liable to indictment trial judgement &amp; punishment according to law,</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>23</unclear> The supreme executive power of this nation, shall be vested in a principal chief who shall be chosen by the <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl.</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Council and shall hold his office four years to be elected as follows the <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl.</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Council by a joint vote shall at their second annual session after the rising of this convention and at every fourth annual session thereafter on the second day after the two houses shall be <choice>
                  <orig>organised</orig>
                  <reg>organized</reg>
               </choice> and competent to proceed to business elect a principal Chief.</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>24</unclear> No person except a natural born citizen shall be eligible to the office of principal Chief neither shall any person be eligible to that office who Shall have not attained to the age of <choice>
                  <orig>thirty five</orig>
                  <reg>thirty-five</reg>
               </choice> years.</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>25</unclear> There shall also be chosen at the same time by General Council in the same manner for four years an assistant principal Chief in case of the removal of the principal Chief from office or of his death resignation or inability to discharge the powers and duties of the said office the same shall devolve on the assistant principal Chief until the inability be removed or vacancy filled by the General Council; The General Council may by law provided for the case of removal death resignation or inability both of the principal and assistant principal chiefs declaring what officer shall then act as principal chief <pb n="11" facs="tl217k.small.jpg"/> until the disability be removed or a principal chief Shall be elected, the principal chief and assistant principal chief shall at stated times receive for their services a compensation which shall neither be increased nor diminished during  the period for which they shall have been elected. And they shall not receive within that period any other <choice>
                  <orig>imolument</orig>
                  <reg>emoluments</reg>
               </choice> from the Cherokee nation or any other person.</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>26</unclear> Before the principal chief enters on the execution of his office he shall take the following oath or affirmation: "I do solemnly swear or (affirm) that I will faithfully execute the office of Principal Chief of the Cherokee Nation and will to the best of my ability preserve, protect &amp; defend the constitution of the Cherokee Nation."</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>27</unclear> He may on extraordinary <choice>
                  <orig>occassions</orig>
                  <reg>occasions</reg>
               </choice> convene the <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl.</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Council at the seat of government. He shall from time to time give to the general Council information of the state of the Government and recommend to their consideration such measures as he may think expedient. He shall take care that the laws be faithfully executed. It shall be his duty to visit the different Districts at least once in two years to inform himself of the general 
Condition of the Country</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>28</unclear> The assistant principal chief shall by <pb n="12" facs="tl217l.small.jpg"/> virtue of his office aid &amp; advise the principal chief in the administration of the Government at all times during his continuance in office.</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>29</unclear> Vacancies that may happen in offices the appointment of which is vested in the general council, shall be filled by the principal Chief during the recess of the General Council by granting commission which shall expire at the end next session.</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>30</unclear> Every bill which shall have passed both houses of the General council shall before it becomes a law be presented to the principal Chief of the Cherokee Nation if he approves it he shall sign it but if not he shall return it with his objections to that house in which it shall have Originated who shall enter the objections at large on their journals  and proceed to reconsider it if after such reconsideration two thirds of that house shall agree to pass the Bill it shall be sent together with the objection to the other House by which it shall likewise be reconsidered and if approved of by two thirds of that house it shall become a law. If any Bill shall not be returned by the principal Chief within five days (sundays excepted) after it shall have been present to him the same shall be a law in like manner as if he had signed it unless the General Council by their adjournments prevents its return in which case it <pb n="13" facs="tl217m.small.jpg"/> shall be a law unless sent back within three days after their next meeting</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>31</unclear> Members of the general Council and all officers Executive &amp; Judicial shall be bound by oath to support the Constitution of this Nation and to perform the duties of their respective offices with fidelity </p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>32</unclear> In case of disagreement between the two Houses with respect to the time of adjournment the principal chief shall have power to adjourn the <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl.</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Council to such a time as he thinks proper Provided it be not to a period beyond the next constitutional meeting of the same</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>33</unclear> The Principal Chief shall during the sitting of the <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl.</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Council attend at the seat of government</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>34</unclear> There shall be a council to consist of three men to be appointed by the joint vote of both Houses to advise the principal Chief in the executive part of the Government whom the principal chief shall have full power at his discretion <del type="overstrike">and</del> to assemble and he together with the assistant principal Chief and <choice>
                  <orig>Counsellors</orig>
                  <reg>Counselors</reg>
               </choice> or a majority of them may from time to time hold and keep a council for ordering and directing the affairs of the nation according to law</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>35</unclear> The members of the Council shall be chosen annually</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tl217n.small.jpg"/>
            <p> Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>36</unclear> The Resolution and advice of the Council shall be recorded in a Register and signed by the members agreeing thereto, which may be called for, by either House of the General Council, and any Councilor may enter his dissent, to the Resolution of the majority —</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>37</unclear> The Treasurer of the Cherokee Nation shall be chosen by the joint vote of each House of the General Council for the term of two years —</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>38</unclear> The Treasurer shall before entering on the duties of his office give bond to the nation with Securities to the satisfaction of the Legislature, — for the faithful discharge of his trust </p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>39</unclear> No money shall be drawn from the Treasury but by Warrant from the principal Chief, and in consequence of appropriation made by law</p>
            <p>Section <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>40</unclear> It shall be the duty of the Treasurer to receive all public monies.  and to make a regular Statement and account of the receipts and expenditure of all public monies to the annual Session of the General Council </p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tl217o.small.jpg"/>
            <p>Article 1st.</p>
            <p>The Judicial powers shall be vested in a Supreme Court, and such Circuit and inferior Courts as the General Council may from time to time ordain and establish.</p>
            <p>Article 2nd.</p>
            <p>The Supreme Court, shall consist of three Judges, any two of whom, shall be a quorum —</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art.</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 3 — The Judges of each Shall hold their commissions four years, but any of them may be removed, from Office, on the address of two thirds of each House of the General Council, to the principal Chief, for that purpose —</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 4 — The Judges of the Supreme and Circuit Courts, Shall at stated times receive a compensation which shall not be diminished  during their Continuance in Office but they, Shall receive no fees or perquisites of Office — nor hold any other Office, of profit or trust, under this nation or any other power —</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 5 — No person shall be appointed a Judge of any of the Courts, before he shall have attained <pb n="16" facs="tl217p.small.jpg"/> to the age of thirty years, nor shall any person continue to <choice>
                  <orig>excercise</orig>
                  <reg>exercise</reg>
               </choice> the duties of any of the said offices after he Shall have attained, to the age of seventy years —</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 6. The Judges of the Supreme and Circuit Courts, shall be appointed by joint vote of each House, of the General Council —</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 7 — There shall be appointed in each district Render the Legislative authority as many Justices of the peace as may be deemed the public good require — and whose powers, duties and duration in office shall be clearly designated</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 8 — The Judges of the Supreme Court, and Circuit Courts shall have complete criminal Jurisdiction in such cases, and in such manner, as may be pointed out, by law —</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 9 — Each Court shall Choose its own clerks for the term of four years, but such clerks shall not be continued in office unless their qualifications, shall be adjudged and approved of by the Judges — of the Supreme Court, and they shall be removable for breach of good <choice>
                  <orig>behaviour</orig>
                  <reg>behavior</reg>
               </choice>, at any time by the Judges of the respective Courts.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tl217q.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 10 — No Judge Shall sit on the trial of any cause, where the parties shall be connected with him by affinity, or consanguinity, except by consent of the parties — In cases all the Judges of the Supreme Court, Shall be intrusted in the event, if any cause, or related to all or either of the parties, the legislature may provide by law for the Selection of three men of good Character, and knowledge for the determination of thereof who shall be specially commissioned by the principal Chief for the case.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 11 — All writs and other process shall run in the name of the Cherokee nation, and bear <choice>
                  <abbr>test</abbr>
                  <expan>testimony</expan>
               </choice>, and be signed by the respective Clerks</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 12 — Indictments shall conclude against the peace and dignity of the Cherokee nation —</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 13 — The Supreme Court shall hold its Session Annually at the seat of Government to be convened on the second Monday of October in each year</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 14 — In all continual prosecutions the accused Shall have the right of being heard of demanding the nature and cause, of the <pb n="18" facs="tl217r.small.jpg"/> accusation against him, of meeting the witness face to face of having compulsory process for obtaining witnesses in his favor — and in prosecutions by indictments or information, a speedy public trial by an impartial Jury of the vicinage nor shall he be compelled to give evidence against himself —</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 15 — That the people shall be secure in their persons houses papers and possessions from unreasonable seizures and searches &amp; that no warrant to search any place or to seize any person or things shall issue without describing them as nearly as may be, nor without good excuse, supported by Oath or affirmation — all prisoners shall be bailable, by Sufficient securities <add place="supralinear">unless</add> for capital offences, where the proof is evident or presumption great —</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 16 — Whereas the Ministers of the Gospel are by their profession dedicated to the service of God "and Care of souls" and ought not to be divested from the great  duty of their functions — Therefore no minister of the Gospel, or public preacher of any Religious persuasion, whilst he continues in <pb n="19" facs="tl217s.small.jpg"/> the <choice>
                  <orig>excercise</orig>
                  <reg>exercise</reg>
               </choice> of his pastoral functions, shall be eligible to the Office of Principal Chief or a seat in either House of the general Council —</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 17 — No persons who denies the being of God, of future state of rewards and punishments, shall hold any office in the Civil departments of this nation —</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 18 — The free <choice>
                  <orig>excercise</orig>
                  <reg>exercise</reg>
               </choice> of religious worship and serving God without destruction, Shall forever be allowed within this nation, provided that this liberty  of conscience, Shall  not be so construed, as to excuse acts of licentiousness, or Justify practices inconsistent with the peace of safety of this nation —</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 19 — Whenever the General Council Shall  
determine, the expediency of appointing Delegators, or other public agents, for the purpose of transacting business with the government of the United States, the principal Chief shall have powers, to recommend, and by the advice and consent of the committee shall appoint and commission such delegates or public agents accordingly, and on all matters of — <pb n="20" facs="tl217t.small.jpg"/> interest touching the rights of the Citizens of this nation, which may require attention of the United States Government, The principal Chief Shall keep a friendly correspondence with government through the medium of the proper officers —</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 20 — All commissions shall be the name and by the Authority of the Cherokee nation and be sealed with the Seal of the Nation and be signed by the principal Chief — The principal Chief shall make use of his private Seal until a national seal shall be provided —</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 21. A Sheriff shall be elected in each district by the qualified electors thereof who shall hold his office for the term of two years unless sooner removed.— Should a vacancy Occur Subsequent to an election, it shall be filled, by the principal Chief, as in other cases and the person so appointed, Shall continue in Office, until the next General election when such vacancies, shall be filled, by the qualified electors, and the sheriff then elected shall continue in for two years —</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tl217u.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 22. There shall be a Marshall appointed by a joint vote of both Houses of the General Council for the term of four years, whose compensation and duty shall be regulated by law, and whose  jurisdiction shall extend, over the Cherokee Nation —</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 23.  No person shall for the same offence be twice put in jeopardy of life or liberty nor shall any persons property be taken or applied to public use, without his consent provided that nothing shall be so construed in this clause as to impair the right and power of the General Council to lay and collect taxes — That all Courts, shall be open and every person for an injury done him in his property, person, or reputation, shall have remedy by due course of law</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Art</abbr>
                  <expan>Article</expan>
               </choice> 24 — The right of trial by Jury shall remain inviolate. </p>
            <p>Religion, Morality, and knowledge being necessary to good government and the preservation of liberty, and the happiness of Mankind Schools and the means of education, shall forever, be encouraged in this nation <pb n="22" facs="tl217v.small.jpg"/> The appointment of all officers not otherwise directed by this constitution, shall be vested in the legislature —</p>
            <p>All Laws in force in this nation at the passing of this constitution shall so continue until altered or repealed by the Legislature except when they are temporary in which case they shall expire at the times respectively <choice>
                  <orig>limitted</orig>
                  <reg>limited</reg>
               </choice> for their duration if not continued by acts of the Legislature.</p>
            <p>The General Council may at any time propose such amendments to this Constitution as two thirds of each House shall deem expedient and the Principal Chief shall issue a proclamation directing  all the Civil officers of the several Districts to promulgate the same as extensively as possible within their respective Districts at least nine Months previous to the next general election and if at the first session of the General Council after such general election two thirds of each House shall by yeas and nays ratify such proposed amendments they shall be valid to all intents and purposes as parts of this Constitution provided that such proposed amendments shall be read on three several <pb n="23" facs="tl217w.small.jpg"/> days in each house as will when the same are proposed as when they are finally ratified</p>
            <p>Done in Convention at <name type="place">New Town <lb/> Echota</name> this <date when="1827-07-24">24th day of July 1827</date>.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="24" facs="tl217x.small.jpg"/>
            <p>Constitution <lb/> of the <lb/> Cherokee Nation <add place="below" rend="different ink">
                  <date when="1827">1827</date>
               </add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
