<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl216">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1834 Oct. 7. Mount Pleasant, Ala[bama]  [to] Sally B. Hamilton, Clarksville, Tennessee / Geo[orge] W. House   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>House, Geo[rge] W.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl216</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51213058</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1834 Oct. 7. Mount Pleasant, Ala[bama]  [to] Sally B. Hamilton, Clarksville, Tennessee / Geo[orge] W. House</title>
               <author>House, Geo[rge] W. </author>
               <date when="1834-10-07">October 7, 1834</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from George House to his mother in law Sally B. Hamilton, dated Oct. 7, 1834. He writes that he has had success with his  cure for rheumatism, and that he will try to get a patent for it. He mentions a nearby revival, and that his mother is at a Baptist association in Huntsville. He believes that religion is vital to human happiness. He also writes of family business.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl216</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Medical care</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Religious life</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">House, George W.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl216a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Mount Pleasant</name>
                     <date when="1834-10-07">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Oct</abbr>
                           <expan>October</expan>
                        </choice> 7th 34</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We reached this in safety on Thursday Morning last but did not find all well — Brothers two sons <unclear/>
               <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>Ge</unclear> orge were both attacked the morning of our arrival and have been quite sick until Yesterday, when they seemed much better — the others of the family are well with the exception old Aunt Edy — Penny's Mother — who has something like acute Rheumatism in her left wrist  and arm I have undertaken to cure it with my new mixture, of which You recollect I <unclear>dreamed</unclear> while at Valmont — before I left <name type="place">Nashville</name>Mortimer prepared for me a half gallon which I have with me — have found great relief myself from the use of it  only three or four times. and am confident I shall make a cure in both cases — There has been much sickness Throughout the whole country and many of my acquaintances and very worthy citizens have give <gap/> long home to try the realities of another <gap agent="damage"/> what is all the wealth and <choice>
                  <orig>honour</orig>
                  <reg>honor</reg>
               </choice> of <gap agent="damage"/> ld compared to the immortality of the soul <gap agent="damage"/> true religion alone that refines &amp; elevates the <gap agent="damage"/> religion that cherishes virtue and <unclear>checks</unclear>
               <gap agent="damage"/> tis religion that raises man above <pb n="2" facs="sl216b.small.jpg"/> the common herds without it man cannot be happy — With it, he is not only prepared to live and enjoy life, but he is prepared to die — it gives contentment to the mind — and contentment, no doubt is the true Philosophers stone — We left Nashville the first day of the month, the day on which <name type="person">Mr Brown</name> gave possession and had quite a pleasant <gap agent="damage"/> three passengers besides ourselves — I had the pleasure of making <name type="person">Professor <unclear>Bonfils</unclear>
               </name> acquaintance the evening before we left and I am fully persuaded that you would be much better situated with him upon the ridge, than a present — it would bring you near your children and would be employment for you — in which you would delight — If you accept of the professors invitation I think in all probability Brother would be willing to send Ann to have her under your charge and <name type="person">Mr Chambliss</name> would be induced to send his daughter Emily — tell Joseph if so he will have an opportunity of again beholding her say tell him that <name type="person">Charles Regney </name>still lingers around near where she is — and is no doubt as much in love as ever — <gap agent="damage"/> and "fuss" (the Poney) are both fat — Rose lov <gap agent="damage"/> slick and bla <gap agent="damage"/> as ever</p>
            <p>Mother and Brother <gap agent="damage"/>ry much disappointed at your not coming <gap agent="damage"/> all took them by <choice>
                  <orig>supprise altho</orig>
                  <reg>surprised although</reg>
               </choice>  I had in <gap agent="damage"/> them ten days be <gap agent="damage"/> that we would <unclear>such</unclear> in <gap agent="damage"/> did — but the <pb n="3" facs="sl216c.small.jpg"/>
               <gap agent="damage"/> was not received until the day after our arrival —</p>
            <p>The Cotton Crop will be greatly more than an average one in this County — notwithstanding the great drought The prospect for rain to day looks fluttering Mother is now fourteen miles below Huntsville attending an association by the Baptist — There has been a great revival in this  <choice>
                  <orig>neighbourhood amung</orig>
                  <reg>neighborhood among</reg>
               </choice> the Cumberlands — and many have been added to their church about Three miles from this —</p>
            <p>I was sorry to learn that the report of <name> 
                  <reg>person</reg> Judge Ewing</name>'s having joined the Church was all fudge —</p>
            <p>Mary joins me in her love to you and Joseph and her respects to <name> 
                  <reg>person</reg> Mr. G. A. Stenny</name> &amp; Lady. The <gap agent="damage"/> ( if at home) the little girls and young <gap agent="damage"/> my respects to all — Tell old aunt <unclear>Fanny</unclear> That I have an idea of taking out a patent for my Rheumatic mixture — that it is a perfect King cure all — when You write direct You letter to <name> 
                  <reg>place</reg> 
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Loueville</orig>
                     <reg>Louisville</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name>
               <name> 
                  <reg>place</reg> Madison County</name>
               <name> 
                  <reg>place</reg> 
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Alaba</abbr>
                     <expan>Alabama</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> and write soon —</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>adieu <lb/> Your Son</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Geo W</abbr>
                        <expan>George Washington</expan>
                     </choice> House</name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P. S.</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> Mr. Brown gave Mary the little dog <unclear/> but we disliked the <unclear>trouble</unclear> of bringing her — so we left her — I wrote to Oscar <gap agent="damage"/> I left N and expect to hear <unclear>from</unclear> him shortly <gap agent="damage"/> ave written to <name type="person">Mr <unclear>Bleane</unclear>
                  </name> to come and see me — he <gap agent="damage"/>returned without his wife, and report says he intends <gap agent="damage"/> to <name type="place">Virginia</name> shortly — how true Can't — say —</signed>
               <add place=" up left margin">desires his respects to Yourself and Joseph — <unclear> Emmeline</unclear> were very Kind to us while at <name type="place">Nashville</name> —</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl216d.small.jpg"/> Mary speaks of writing to ⁁ <add place="supralinear">Miss</add>
               <name type="person">Jane Brown</name> by this mail — and I shall write to sister Emmeline by the by I saw a <unclear>letter</unclear> to her from <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice>
               <unclear>St</unclear> before we left which leads to the belief that the Genl lost his heart when last at Nashville and between us Miss <name type="person">Josephine Woods </name>I think is the object. Em says it would go down — <add place="center of page, rotated">
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Loueville Ala 1834</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Oct 10</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Mrs <name type="person">Sally B. Hamilton</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Clarksville</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>    for she has perhaps heard the <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>sen</unclear> ntiments of the said Miss upon the subject — I sh <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>all wr</unclear> ite to the Genl <unclear/> and direct my letter to cle<gap agent="damage"/>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
