<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl601">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1829 May 23, Athens, Tennessee [to] William Hall, Nashville, Tennessee / J.C. Mitchell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Mitchell, J.C.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl601</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1829 May 23, Athens, Tennessee [to] William Hall, Nashville, Tennessee / J.C. Mitchell</title>
               <author>  Mitchell, J.C.</author>
               <date when="1829-05-23"> 
			 May 23, 1829</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated May 23, 1829 from J.C. Mitchell to Tennessee governor William Hall.  In the letter, Mitchell writes of the circumstances surrounding the previous governor, Sam Houston after his humiliating marriage scandal, and flight from Nashville dressed in disguise.  Mitchell assumed the governorship in the month prior to the writing of this letter, he served through October. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor William Hall Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl601</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Houston, Sam, 1793-1863.</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Mitchell, James C.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl601a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Athens <choice>
                        <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>May 23d 1829</date>
               <salute>Dear <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I regret the circumstances which have imposed upon you the duties of Governor of <name>Tennessee</name> Poor Houston he rose like the flames of the morn to perish with the mid-day sun It is on his account and not yours that I have my regrets__ You will I have no doubt believe me <sic>me</sic> sincere when I say to you that it would afford me much pleasure to have it in my power to address you as the Governor of Tennessee elected by the suffrage of the people instead of having the office cast upon you by act and <choice>
                  <orig>apperation</orig>
                  <reg>apparition</reg>
               </choice> of Law And I believe if you could get the better of your almost unconquerable modesty that you could me made the Governor of Tennessee when you should choose to tender your service But as the stern decrees of fate had been sent forth against Houston I am <choice>
                  <orig>truely</orig>
                  <reg>truly</reg>
               </choice> glad that Tennessee had such a Patriot at the head of her Senate to <choice>
                  <orig>recive</orig>
                  <reg>receive</reg>
               </choice> into his hands the Executive reins Because I know you will impartially administer the <choice>
                  <orig>afairs</orig>
                  <reg>affairs</reg>
               </choice> of the State which fall within the Executive sphere__ Under this knowledge of your worth I shall present the application of  my friend <name>Elikee S. Barclay</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>esqr</abbr>
                  <expan>esquire</expan>
               </choice> for the office of Solicitor General of the Solicitarial District composed <pb n="2" facs="sl601b.small.jpg"/> of <name>Monroe</name>
               <name>Blount</name>
               <name>Jefferson</name>
               <name>Sevier</name>&amp;     <name>Cocke</name> Counties with a confidential hope of his success At Barclay is a man of fine Education and a well read and sound lawyer eminently qualified to discharge the duties of solicitor to the best interest of the District and to his our honor and emulate it__   He is poor and has a worthy growing family hanging on his arm for support.  I feel quite confident that the appointment can not be bestowed on a more <choice>
                  <orig>diserving</orig>
                  <reg>deserving</reg>
               </choice> man or one that would reach more Universal satisfaction  From the above it would be <choice>
                  <orig>superflous</orig>
                  <reg>superfluous</reg>
               </choice> to say that <choice>
                  <abbr>mr</abbr>
                  <expan>mister</expan>
               </choice> Barclays appointment would be of high gratification to your old &amp; devoted friend </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>J.C. Mitchell</name>
               </signed>
               <add>His Excellency William Hall</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl601c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Athens <choice>
                     <abbr>T </abbr>
                     <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                  </choice>May 24th Paid 18 3/4 His Excellency William Hall Nashville (<choice>
                     <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                     <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                  </choice>)</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl601d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> H Mitchell 23 May '29 Recommend <choice>
                     <abbr>ES</abbr>
                     <expan>Elikee S.</expan>
                  </choice> Barclay in place of Wilkinson</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
