<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl003">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gen[eral] Jackson's Farewell Address, Together with His Proclamation to S[outh] Carolina, printed 1850, Harrisburg [printed by] J. M. G. Lescure : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Jackson, Andrew</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl003</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 49998144</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Gen[eral] Jackson's Farewell Address, Together with His Proclamation to S[outh] Carolina, printed 1850, Harrisburg [printed by] J. M. G. Lescure</title>
               <author>Jackson, Andrew</author>
               <date when="1850">1850</date>
               <extent> 14 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a booklet, printed by J. M. G. Lescure in 1850, which includes President Andrew Jackson's Farewell Address and his Proclamation to South Carolina.  The Farewell Address was given on March 4, 1837, as Jackson prepared to retire from the presidency and from public life in general.  In the address, he discusses his presidency's contributions to the nation, as well as his opposition to the national bank and nullification.  The Proclamation to South   Carolina was written on December 10, 1832, in response to an earlier decision of the state legislature of South Carolina to nullify a recent tariff bill passed by the federal government.  Jackson severely chastises the insistence that states are sovereign and have the right to nullify federal laws, and he accuses South Carolina of trying to disrupt the Union and transgressing the Constitution.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Sir Emil Hurja Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">7</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">18</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl003</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>United States Politics and government 1815-1861</term>
               <term>United States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79088888"
                        role="Author http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/aut">Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="cover">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl003a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <add place="top" rend="written text">Wade</add>
               <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Gen.</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Jackson's</name> FAREWELL ADDRESS,</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="sc">Together With His</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PROCLAMATION TO <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>S.</abbr>
                     <expan>South</expan>
                  </choice> CAROLINA</name>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="sl003b.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>GEN.</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> JACKSON'S FAREWELL ADDRESS,</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="sc">to the</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PEOPLE OF THE <name type="place">UNITED STATES</name>,</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="sc">together with his</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PROCLAMATION TO SOUTH CAROLINA</p>
            <p>Harrisburg:</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">J. M. G. Lescure</name>, Printer to the State.</p>
            <p>
               <date when="1850">1850</date>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="sl003c.small.jpg"/>
            <head>TO THE PEOPLE OF THE UNITED STATES</head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="sc">Fellow Citizens</hi>:— Being about to retire finally from public life, I beg leave to offer you my grateful thanks for the many proofs of kindness and confidence which I have received at your hands.  It has been my fortune, in the discharge of public duties, civil and military, frequently to have found myself in difficult and trying situations, where prompt decision and energetic action were necessary, and where the interest of the country required that high responsibilities should be fearlessly encountered—and it is with the deepest emotions of gratitude that I acknowledge the continued and unbroken confidence with which you have sustained me in every trial.  My public life has been a long one, and I cannot hope that it has, at all times, been free from errors.  But I have the consolation of knowing that, if mistakes have been committed, they have not seriously injured the country I so anxiously endeavored to serve; and, at the moment when I surrender my last public trust, I leave this great people prosperous and happy, in the full enjoyment of liberty and peace, and honored and respected by every nation of the world.</p>
            <p>If my humble efforts have, in any degree, contributed to preserve to you these blessings, I have been more than rewarded by the honors you have heaped upon me; and above all, by the generous confidence with which you have supported me in every peril, and with which you have continued to animate and cheer my path to the closing hour of my political life.  The time has now come, when advanced age and a broken frame warn me to retire from public concerns; but the recollection of the many favors you have bestowed upon me is engraven upon my heart, and I have felt that I could not part from your service without making this public acknowledgment of the gratitude I owe you.  And if I use the occasion to offer to you the counsels of age and experience, you will, I trust, receive them with the same indulgent kindness which you have so often extended to me; and will, at least, see in them an earnest desire to perpetuate in this favored land, the blessings of liberty and equal laws.</p>
            <p>We have now lived almost fifty years under the Constitution framed by the sages and patriots of the Revolution. The conflicts in which the nations of <name type="place">Europe</name> were engaged during a great part of this period—the spirit in which they waged war against each other, and our intimate commercial connections with every part of the civilized world, rendered it a time of much difficulty for the government of the United States.  We have had our seasons of peace and of war, with all the evils which precede or follow a state of hostility with powerful nations.  We encountered these trials with our Constitution, yet in its infancy, and under the disadvantages which a new and untried government must always feel when it is called upon to put forth its whole strength, without the lights of experience to guide it, or the weight of precedents to justify its measures.  But we have passed triumphantly through all these difficulties.  Our Constitution is no longer a doubtful experiment, and, at the end of nearly half a century, we find that it has preserved unimpaired the liberties of the people, secured the rights of property, and that our country has improved and is flourishing beyond any former example in the history of nations.</p>
            <p>In our domestic concerns there is everything to encourage us, and if you are true to yourselves, nothing can impede your march to the highest point of national prosperity.  The States which had  so long been retarded in their improvement, by the Indian tribes residing in the midst of them, are at length relieved from the evil; and this unhappy race—the original dwellers in our land—are now placed in a situation where we may well hope that they will share in the blessings of civilization, and be saved from that degradation and destruction to which they were rapidly hastening, while they remained <pb n="4" facs="sl003d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top, middle">4</add> in the States; and while the safety and comfort of our own citizens have been greatly promoted by their removal, the philanthropist will rejoice that the remnant of that ill-fated race has been at length placed beyond the reach of injury or oppression, and that the paternal care of the General Government will hereafter watch over them and protect them.</p>
            <p>If we turn our relations with foreign powers, we find our condition equally gratifying.  Actuated by the sincere desire to do justice to every nation, and to preserve the blessings of peace, our intercourse with them has been conducted on the part of this government in the spirit of frankness, and I take pleasure in saying that it has generally been met in a corresponding temper.  Difficulties of old standing have been surmounted by friendly discussion, and the mutual desire to be just; and the claims of our citizens, which had  been long withheld, have at length been acknowledged and adjusted, and satisfactory arrangements made for their final payment, and with a limited, and, I trust, a temporary exception, our relations with every foreign power are now of the most friendly character—our commerce continually   expanding, and our flag respected in every quarter of the world.</p>
            <p>These cheering and grateful prospects, and these multiplied favors, we owe, under Providence, to the adoption of the Federal Constitution.  It is no longer a question whether this great country can remain happily united, and flourish under our present form of government.  Experience, the unerring test of all human undertakings, has shown the wisdom and foresight of those who formed it; and has proved, that in the union of these States there is a sure foundation for the brightest hopes of freedom, and for the happiness of the people.  At every hazard, and by every sacrifice, this Union must be preserved.</p>
            <p>The necessity of watching with jealous anxiety for the preservation of the Union, was earnestly pressed upon his fellow citizens by the Father of his Country, in his farewell address.  He has there told us, that "while experience shall not have demonstrated its impracticability, there will always be reason to distrust the patriotism of those who in any quarter, may endeavor to weaken its bonds;" and he has cautioned us, in the strongest terms, against the formation of parties, on geographical discriminations, as one of the means which might disturb our Union, and to which designing men would be likely to resort.</p>
            <p>The lessons contained in this invaluable legacy of <name type="person">Washington</name>  to his country men, should be cherished in the heart of every citizen to the latest generation; and, perhaps, at no period of time could they be more usefully remembered than at the present moment.  For when we look upon the scenes that are passing around us, and dwell upon the pages of his parting address, his paternal counsels would seem to be not merely the offspring of wisdom and foresight, but the voice of prophecy foretelling events and warning us of the evil to come.  Forty years have passed since this imperishable document was given to his countrymen.  The Federal Constitution was then regarded by him as an experiment, and he so speaks of it in his address; but an experiment upon the success of which the best hopes of his country depended, and we all know that he was prepared to lay down his life, if necessary, to secure to it a full and a fair trial.  The trial has been made.  It has succeeded beyond the proudest hopes of those who framed it.  Every quarter of this widely extended nation has felt its blessings, and shared in the general prosperity produced by its adoption.  But amid this general prosperity and splendid success, the dangers of which he warned us are becoming every day more evident, and the signs of evil are sufficiently apparent to awaken the deepest anxiety in the bosom of the patriot.  We behold systematic efforts publicly made to sow the seeds of discord between different parts of the United States, and to place party divisions directly upon geographical distinctions; to excite the <hi rend="i">south</hi> against the <hi rend="i">north</hi>, and the <hi rend="i">north</hi> against the <hi rend="i">south</hi>, and to force into the controversy the most delicate and exciting topics;—topics upon which it is impossible that a large portion of the Union can ever speak without strong emotion.  Appeals, too, are constantly made to sectional interests in order to influence the election of the Chief Magistrate, as if it were desired that he should favor a particular quarter of the country, instead of fulfilling the duties of his station with impartial justice to all, and the possible dissolution of the Union has <add place="top, middle">5</add> at length become an ordinary and familiar subject of discussion.  Has the warning voice of Washington been forgotten?  or have designs already been formed to sever the Union? Let it not be supposed that I impute to all of those who have taken an active part in these unwise and unprofitable discussions, a want of patriotism or of public virtue.—The honorable feeling of State pride, and local attachments, find a place in the bosoms of the most enlightened and pure.  But while such men are conscious of their own integrity and honestly of purpose, they ought never to forget that the citizens of other States are their political brethren; and that, however mistaken they may be in their views, the great body of them are equally honest and upright with themselves.  Mutual suspicions and reproaches may in time create mutual hostility, and artful and designing men will always be found, who are ready to foment these fatal divisions, and to inflame the natural jealousies of different sections of the country.  The history of the world is fully of such examples, and especially the history of republics.</p>
            <p>What have you to gain by division and dissension? Delude not yourselves with the belief that a breach once made may be afterwards repaired.  If the Union is once severed, the line of separation will grow wider and wider, and the controversies which are now debated and settled in the halls of legislation, will then be tried in fields of battle, and determined by the sword.  Neither should you deceive yourselves with the hope, that the first line of separation would be the permanent one, and that nothing but harmony and concord would be found in the new associations formed upon the dissolution of this Union.  Local interests would still be found there, and unchastened ambition.  And if the recollection of common dangers, in which the people of these United States stood side by side against the common foe; the memory of victories won by their united valor; the prosperity and happiness they have enjoyed under the present Constitution; the proud name they bear as citizens of this great republic; if all these recollections and proofs of common interest are not strong enough to bind us together as one people, what tie will hold united the new divisions of empire, when these bonds have been broken and this Union dissevered?  The first line of separation would not last for a single generation; new fragments would be torn off; new leaders would spring up; and this great and glorious republic would soon be broken into a multitude of petty States, without commerce, without credit; jealous of one another; armed for mutual aggression; loaded with taxes to pay armies and leaders; seeking aid against each other from foreign powers; insulted and trampled upon by the nations of Europe, until harassed with conflicts, and humbled and debased in spirit, they would be ready to submit to the absolute dominion of the military adventurer, and to surrender their liberty for the sake of repose. It is impossible to look on the consequences that would inevitably follow the destruction of this government, and not feel indignant when we hear cold calculations about the value of the Union, and have so constantly before us a line of conduct so well calculated to weaken its ties.</p>
            <p>There is too much at stake to allow pride or passion to influence your decision. Never for a moment believe that the great body of the citizens of any State or States can deliberately intend to do wrong.  They may under the influence of temporary excitement or misguided opinions, commit mistakes; they may be misled for a time by the suggestions of self interest; but in a community so enlightened and patriotic as the people of the United States, argument will soon make them sensible of their errors; and, when convinced, they will be ready to repair them.  If they have no higher or better motives to govern them, they will at least perceive that their own interest requires them to be just to others as they hope to receive justice at their hands.</p>
            <p>But in order to maintain the Union unimpaired, it is absolutely necessary that the laws passed by the constituted authorities should be faithfully executed in every part of the country, and that every good citizen should, at all times, stand ready to put down, with the combined force of the nation, every attempt at unlawful resistance, under whatever pretext it may be made, or whatever shape it may assume.  Unconstitutional or oppressive laws may no doubt be passed by Congress, either from erroneous views, or the want of due consideration; if they are within the reach of judicial authority, the remedy is easy and peaceful; and if from the character of the law, it is an abuse of power not within the control of the judiciary, then free discussion and calm <pb n="5" facs="sl003e.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top, middle">6</add> appeals to reason and to the justice of the people will not fail to redress the wrong.  But until the law shall be declared void by the courts, or repealed by Congress, no individual, or combination of individuals, can be justified in forcibly resisting its execution.  It is impossible that any government can continue to exist upon any other principles.  It would cease to be a government, and be unworthy of the name, if it had not the power to enforce the execution of its own laws within its own sphere of action.</p>
            <p>It is true that cases may be imagined disclosing such a settled purpose of usurpation and oppression, on the part of the government, as would justify an appeal to arms.  These, however, are extreme cases, which we have no reason to apprehend in a government where the power is in the hands of a patriotic people; and no citizen who loves his country would, in any case whatever, resort to forcible resistance, unless he clearly saw that the time had come when a freeman should prefer death to submission, for if such a struggle is once begun, and the citizens of one section of the country arrayed in arms against those of another in doubtful conflict, let the battle result as it may, there will be an end of the Union, and with it, an end to the hopes of freedom. The victory of the injured would not secure to them the blessings of liberty; it would avenge their wrongs, but they would themselves share in the common ruin.</p>
            <p>But the Constitution cannot be maintained, nor the Union preserved, in opposition to public feeling, by the mere exertion of the coercive powers confided to the General Government.  The foundations must be laid in the affections of the people; in the security it gives to life, liberty, character and property in every quarter of the country; and in the fraternal attachment which the citizens of the several States bear to one another as members of one political family, mutually contributing to promote the happiness of each other.  Hence the citizens of every State should studiously avoid every thing calculated to wound the sensibility or offend the just pride of the people of other States; and they should frown upon any proceedings within their own borders likely to disturb the tranquility of their political brethren in other portions of the Union.  In a country so extensively as the United States, and with pursuits so varied, the internal regulations of the several States, must frequently differ from one another in important particulars, and this difference is unavoidably increased by the varying principles upon which the American colonies were originally planted; principles which had taken deep root in their social relations before the Revolution, and therefore, of necessity influencing their policy since they became free and independent States.  But each State has the unquestionable right to regulate its own internal concerns according to its own pleasure; and while it does not interfere with the rights of the people of other States, or the rights of the Union, every State must be the sole judge of the measures proper to secure the safety of its citizens and promote their happiness, and all efforts on the part of people of other States to cast odium upon their institutions, and all measures   calculated to disturb their rights of property, or to put in jeopardy their peace and internal tranquility, are in direct opposition to the spirit in which the Union was formed, and must endanger its safety.  Motives of philanthropy may be assigned for this unwarrantable interference; and weak men may persuade themselves for a moment that they are laboring in the cause of humanity, and asserting the rights of the human race, but every one, upon sober reflection, will see that nothing but mischief can come from these improper assaults upon the feelings and rights of others.  Rest assured that the men found busy in this work of discord are not worthy of your confidence, and deserve your strongest reprobation.</p>
            <p>In the legislation of Congress, also, and in every measure of the General Government, justice to every portion of the United States should be faithfully observed.  No free government can stand without virtue in the people, and a lofty spirit of patriotism; and if the sordid feelings of mere selfishness shall usurp the place which ought to be filled by public spirit, the legislation of Congress will soon be converted into a scramble for personal and sectional advantages.  Under our free institutions, the citizens of every quarter of our country are capable of attaining a high degree of prosperity and happiness, without seeking to profit themselves at the expense of others; and every such attempt must in the end fail to succeed, for the people in every part of the United States are too enlightened not to understand their own rights and interests, and to  <add place="top, middle">7</add> detect and defeat every effort to gain undue advantages over them; and when such designs are discovered, it naturally <choice>
                  <orig>provoks</orig>
                  <reg>provokes</reg>
               </choice> resentments which cannot always be easily allayed.  Justice, full and ample justice, to every portion of the United States, should be the ruling principal of every freeman, and should guide the deliberations of every public body, whether it be State or National.</p>
            <p>It is well known that there have always been those amongst us who wish to enlarge the powers of the General Government; and experience would seem to indicate that there is a tendency on the part of this government to overstep the boundaries marked out for it by the Constitution. Its legitimate authority is abundantly sufficient for all the purposes for which it was created; and its powers being expressly enumerated there can be no justification for claiming anything beyond them.  Every attempt to exercise power beyond these limits should be promptly and firmly opposed.  For one evil example will lead to other measures still more mischievous; and if the principle of constructive powers, or supposed advantages, or temporary circumstances, shall ever be permitted to justify the assumption of a power not given by the Constitution, the General Government will before long absorb all the powers of legislation, and you will   have, in effect, but one consolidated government.  From the extent of our country, its diversified interests, different pursuits and different habits, it is too obvious for argument that a single consolidated government would be wholly inadequate to watch over and protect its interests; and every friend of our free institutions should be always prepared to maintain unimpaired, and in full vigor, the rights and sovereignty of the States, and to confine the action of the General Government strictly to the sphere of its appropriate duties.</p>
            <p>There is, perhaps, no one of the powers conferred on the Federal Government so liable to abuse, as the taxing power.  The most productive and convenient sources of revenue were necessarily given to it, that it might be able to perform the important duties imposed upon it, and the taxes which it lays upon commerce being  concealed from the real payer in the price of the article, they do not so readily attract the attention of the people as smaller sums demanded from them directly by the tax-gather.  But the tax imposed on goods enhances by so much the price of the commodity to the consumer; and, as many of these duties are imposed on articles of necessity, which are daily used by the great body of the people, the money raised by these imposts is drawn from their pockets.  Congress has no right, under the Constitution, to take money from the people, unless it is required to execute some one of the specific powers entrusted   to the government; and if they raise more than is necessary for such purposes, it is an abuse of the power of taxation, and unjust and oppressive.  It may, indeed happen that the revenue will sometimes exceed the amount anticipated, when the taxes were laid.  When, however, this is ascertained, it is easy to reduce them; and, in such a case, it is unquestionably the duty of the government to reduce them; for no circumstances can justify it in assuming a power not given to it by the Constitution, nor in taking away the money of the people, when it is not needed for the legitimate wants of the government.</p>
            <p>Plain as these principles appear to be, you will yet find that there is a constant effort to induce the General Government to go beyond the limits of its taxing power, and to impose unnecessary burdens upon the people.  Many powerful interests are continually at work to procure heavy duties on commerce, and to swell the revenue beyond the real necessities of the public service; and the country has already felt the injurious effects of their combined influence.  They succeeded in obtaining a tariff of duties bearing most oppressively on the agricultural and laboring classes of society, and producing a revenue that could not be usefully employed within the range of the powers conferred upon Congress; and, in order to fasten upon the people this unjust and unequal system of taxation, extravagant schemes of internal improvement were got up, in various quarters, to squander the money, and to purchase support.  Thus one unconstitutional measure was intended to be upheld by another, and the abuse of the power of taxation was to be maintained by usurping the power of expending the money in internal improvements.  You cannot have forgotten the severe and doubtful struggle through which we passed, when the Executive department of the government, by its <pb n="6" facs="sl003f.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top, middle">8</add> veto, endeavored to arrest this prodigal scheme of injustice, and to bring back the legislation of Congress to the boundaries prescribed by the Constitution.  The good sense and practical judgment of the people, when the subject was brought before them, sustained the course of the Executive; and this plan of unconstitutional expenditure for the purpose of corrupt influence is, I trust, finally overthrown.</p>
            <p>The result of the decision has been felt in the rapid extinguishment of the public debt, and the large accumulation of a surplus in the treasury, notwithstanding the tariff was reduced, and is now very far below the amount originally contemplated by its advocates.  But rely upon it, the design to collect an extravagant revenue, and to burden  you with taxes beyond the economical wants of the government, is not yet abandoned.  The various interests which have combined together to impose a heavy tariff, and to produce an overflowing treasury, are too strong, and have too much at stake to surrender the contest.  The corporations and wealthy individuals who are engaged in large manufacturing establishments, desire a high tariff to increase their gains.  Designing politicians will support it, to conciliate their favor, and to obtain the means of profuse expenditure, for the purpose of purchasing influence in other quarters; and since the people have decided that the Federal Government cannot be permitted to employ its income in internal improvements, efforts will be made to seduce and mislead the citizens of the several States, by holding out to them the deceitful prospect of benefits to be derived from a surplus revenue collected by the General Government, and annually divided among the States.  And if, encouraged by these fallacious hopes, the States should disregard the principles of economy which ought to characterize every republican government, and should indulge in lavish expenditures exceeding their resources, they will, before long, find themselves oppressed with debts which they are unable to pay, and the temptation will become irresistible to support a high tariff, in order to obtain an surplus for distribution. Do not allow yourselves, my fellow citizens, to be misled on this subject. The Federal Government cannot collect a surplus for such purposes, without violating the principles of the Constitution, and assuming powers which have not been granted.  It is, moreover, a system of injustice, and, if persisted in, will inevitably lead to corruption, and must end in ruin.  The surplus revenue will be drawn from the pockets of the people, from the farmer, the mechanic, and the laboring classes of society; but who will receive it when distributed among the States, where it is to be disposed of by leading State politicians who have friends to favor and political partisans to gratify? It will certainly not be returned to those who paid it, and who have most need of it, and are honestly entitled to it.  There is but one safe rule, and that is, to confine   the General Government rigidly within the sphere of its appropriate duties.  It has no power to raise a revenue, or impose taxes, except for the purposes enumerated in the Constitution, and if its income is found to exceed these wants, it should be forthwith reduced, and the burdens of the people so far lightened.</p>
            <p>In reviewing the conflicts which have taken place between different interests in the United States, and the policy pursued since the adoption of our present form of government, we find nothing that has produced such deep seated evil as the course of legislation in relation to the currency.  The Constitution of the United States unquestionably intended to secure to the people a circulating medium of gold and silver. But the establishment of a national bank by Congress, with the privilege of issuing paper money   receivable in the payment of the public dues, and the unfortunate course of legislation in the several States upon the same subject, drove from general circulation the constitutional currency, and substituted one of paper in its place.</p>
            <p>It was not easy for men engaged in the ordinary pursuits of business, whose attention had not been particularly drawn to the subject, to foresee all the consequences of a currency exclusively of paper; and we ought not, on that account, to be surprised at the facility with which laws were obtained to carry into effect the paper system.  Honest, and even enlightened men, are sometimes misled by the specious and plausible statements of the designing.  But experience has now proved the mischiefs and dangers of a paper currency, and it rests with you to determine whether the proper remedy shall be applied.</p>
            <p>
               <add place="top, middle">9</add> The paper system being founded on public confidence, and having of itself no intrinsic value, it is liable to great and sudden fluctuation: thereby rendering property insecure, and the wages of labor unsteady and uncertain.  The corporations which create the paper money cannot be relied upon to keep the circulating medium uniform in amount.  In times of prosperity, when confidence is high, they are tempted, by the prospect of gain, or by the influence of those who hope to profit by it, to extend their issues of paper beyond the bounds of discretion and the reasonable demands of business.  And when these issues have been pushed on, from day to day, until public confidence is at length shaken, then a reaction takes place, and they immediately withdraw the credits they have given; suddenly curtail their issues; and produce an unexpected and ruinous contraction of the circulating medium, which is felt by the whole community.  The banks, by this means, save themselves, and the <choice>
                  <orig>mischievious</orig>
                  <reg>mischievous</reg>
               </choice> consequences of their imprudence or cupidity are visited upon the public.  Nor does the evil stop here.  These ebbs and flows in the currency, and these indiscreet extensions of credit naturally engender a spirit of speculation injurious to the habits and character of the people.  We have already seen its effects in the wild spirit of speculation in the public lands, and various kinds of stock, which, within the last year or two, seized upon such a multitude of our citizens, and threatened to pervade all classes of society, and to withdraw their attention from the sober pursuits of honest industry.  It is not by encouraging this spirit that we shall best preserve public virtue and promote the true interests of our country.  But if your currency continues as exclusively paper as it now is, it will foster this eager desire to amass wealth without labor; it will multiply the number of dependents on bank accommodations and bank favors; the temptation to obtain money at any sacrifice will become stronger and stronger, and inevitably lead to corruption, which will find its way into your public councils, and destroy at no distant day, the purity of your government.  Some of the evils which arise from this system of paper, press with peculiar hardship upon the class of society least able to bear it.  A portion of this currency frequently becomes depreciated or worthless, and all of it is easily counterfeited, in such a manner as to require peculiar skill and much experience to distinguish the counterfeit from the genuine note.  These frauds are most generally perpetrated in the smaller notes, which are used in the daily transactions of ordinary business; and the losses occasioned by them are commonly thrown upon the laboring classes of society, whose situation and pursuits put it out of their power to guard themselves from these impositions, and whose daily wages are necessary for their subsistence.  It is the duty of every government so to regulate its currency as to protect this numerous class as far as practicable from the impositions of avarice and fraud.  It is more especially the duty of the United States, where the government is emphatically the government of the people; and where this respectable portion of our citizens are so proudly distinguished from the laboring classes of all other nations, by their independent spirit, their love of liberty, their intelligence, and their high tone of moral character.  Their industry in peace is the source of our wealth; and their bravery in war, has covered us with glory; and the Government of the United States will but ill discharge its duties if it leaves them  a prey to such dishonest impositions.  Yet it is evident that their interests cannot be effectually protected, unless silver and gold are restored to circulation.</p>
            <p>These views alone, of the paper currency, are sufficient to call for immediate reform; but <choice>
                  <orig>their</orig>
                  <reg>there</reg>
               </choice> is another consideration which should still more strongly press it upon your attention</p>
            <p>Recent events have proved that the paper money system of this country may be used as an engine to undermine your free institutions; and that those who desire to engross all power in the hands of the few, and to govern by corruption or force, are aware of its power and prepared to employ it. Your banks now furnish your only circulating medium, and money is plenty scarce, according to the quantity of notes issued by them.  While they have capitals not greatly disproportioned to each other, they are competitors in business, and  no one of them can exercise dominion over the rest; and although, in the present state of the currency, these banks may and do operate injuriously upon the habits of business, the pecuniary concerns, and the moral tone of society; yet, from their number and dispersed situation, they cannot combine for the pur-<pb n="7" facs="sl003g.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top, middle">10</add> pose of political influence; and whatever may be the dispositions of some of them, their power of mischief must necessarily be confined to a narrow space, and felt only in their immediate neighborhoods.</p>
            <p>But when the charter for the Bank of the United States was obtained from Congress, it perfected the schemes of the paper system, and gave to its advocates the position they have struggled to obtain, from the commencement of the Federal Government down to the present hour. The immense capital, and peculiar privileges bestowed upon it, enable it to exercise despotic sway over the other banks in every part of the country.— From its superior strength, it could seriously injure, if not destroy, the business of any of them which might incur its resentment; and it openly claimed for itself the power of regulating the currency throughout the United States.  In other words, it asserted (and it undoubtedly possessed) the power to make money plenty or scarce, at its pleasure, at any time, and in any quarter of the Union, by controlling the issues of other banks, and permitting an expansion, or compelling a general contractions of the circulating medium, according to its own will.  The other banking institutions were sensible   of its strength, and they soon generally became its obedient instruments, ready at all times, to execute its mandates; and with the banks necessarily went, also that numerous class of persons in our commercial cities, who depend altogether on bank credits for their solvency and means of business; and who are, therefore, obliged, for their own safety, to propitiate the favor of the money power by distinguished zeal and devotion in its service.  The result of the ill-advised legislation which established this great monopoly was, to concentrate the whole moneyed power of the Union, with its boundless means of corruption, and its numerous dependents, under the direction and command of one acknowledged head; thus organizing this particular interest as one body, and securing to it unity and concert of action throughout the United States, and enabling it to bring forward, upon any occasion, its entire and undivided strength to support or defeat any measure of the government.  In the hands of this formidable power, thus perfectly organized, was also placed unlimited dominion over the amount of the circulating medium, giving it the power to regulate the value of property and the fruits of labor in every quarter of the Union; and to bestow prosperity, or bring ruin, upon any city or section of the country, as might best comport with its own interest or policy.</p>
            <p>We are not left to conjecture how the moneyed power, thus organized, and with such a weapon in its hands would be likely to use it.  The distress and alarm which pervaded and agitated the whole country, when the Bank of the United States waged war upon the people, in order to compel them to submit to its demands, cannot yet be forgotten.  The ruthless and unsparing temper with which whole cities and communities were oppressed, individuals impoverished and ruined, and a scene of cheerful prosperity suddenly changed into one of gloom and despondency, ought to be indelibly impressed upon the memory of the people of the United States.  If such was its power in a time of peace, what would it not have been in a season of war, with an enemy at your doors?  No nation but the freemen of the United States could have come out victorious from such a contest; yet, if you had not conquered, the government would have passed from the hands of the many to the hands of the few; and this organized money power, from its secret conclave, would have dictated the choice of your highest officers, and compelled you to make peace or war, as best suited their own wishes.  The forms of your government might, for a time, have remained; but its living spirit would have departed from it. </p>
            <p>The distress and sufferings inflicted on the people by the bank, are some of the fruits of that system of policy which is continually striving to enlarge the authority of the Federal Government beyond the limits fixed by the Constitution.  The powers enumerated in that instrument do not confer on Congress the right to establish such a corporation as the Bank of the United States; and the evil consequences which followed, may warn us of the danger of departing from the true role of construction, and of permitting temporary circumstances, or the hope of better promoting the public welfare, to influence in any degree our decisions upon the extent of the authority of the General Gov- <add place="top, middle">11</add> ernment. Let us abide by the Constitution as it is written, or amend it in the constitutional mode if it is found to be defective.  </p>
            <p>The severe lessons of experience will, I doubt not, be sufficient to prevent Congress from again chartering such a monopoly, even if the Constitution did not present an insuperable objection to it.  But you must remember, my fellow citizens, that eternal vigilance by the people is the price of liberty; and that you must pay the price if you wish to secure the blessing.  It behooves you, therefore, to be watchful in your States, as well as in the Federal Government.  The power which the moneyed interest can exercise when concentrated under a single head, and with our present system of currency, was sufficiently demonstrated in the struggle made by the Bank of the United States.  Defeated in the General Government, the same class of intriguers and politicians will now resort to the States, and endeavor to obtain there the same organization which they failed to perpetuate in the Union; and with specious and deceitful plans of public advantages, and State interests and State pride, they will endeavor to establish in the different States, one moneyed institution with overgrown capital and exclusive privileges, sufficient to enable it to control the operations of the other banks.  Such an institution will be pregnant with the same evils produced by the Bank of the United States, although its sphere of action is more confined, and in the State in which it is chartered, the money power will be able to embody its whole strength, and to move together with the undivided force to accomplish any object it may wish to attain.  You have already had abundant evidence of its power to inflict injury upon the agricultural, mechanical, and laboring classes of society; and over those whose engagements in trade or speculation render them dependent on bank facilities, the dominion of the State monopoly will be absolute and their obedience unlimited.  With such a bank and a paper currency, the money power would in a few years govern the State and control its measures; and if a sufficient number of States can be induced to create such establishments, the time will soon come when it will again take the field against the United States, and succeed in perfecting and perpetuating its organization by a charter from Congress.</p>
            <p>It is one of the serious evils of our present system of banking, that it enables one class of society—and that by no means a numerous one—by its control over the currency, to act injuriously upon the interests of all the others, and to exercise more than its just proportion of influence in political affairs.  The agricultural, the mechanical, and the laboring classes, have little or no share in the direction of the great moneyed corporations; and from their habits and the nature of their pursuits, they are incapable of forming extensive combinations to act together with united force.  Such concert of action may sometimes be produced in a single city, or in a small district of country, by means of personal communications with each other; but they have no regular or active correspondence with those who are engaged in similar pursuits in distant places; they have but little patronage to give to the press and exercise but a small share of influence over it; they have no crowd of dependents about them, who hope to grow right without labor, by their countenance and favor, and who are, therefore, always ready to execute their wishes.  The planter, the farmer, the mechanic and laborer all know that their success depends upon their own industry and economy, and that they must not expect to become suddenly rich by the fruits of their toil.  Yet these classes of society form the great body of the people of the United States; they are the bone and sinew of the country; men who love liberty and desire nothing but equal rights and equal laws, and who, moreover, hold the great mass of our national wealth, although it is distributed in moderate amounts among the millions of freemen who possess it.  But, with overwhelming numbers and wealth on their side, they are in constant danger of losing their fair influence in the government, and with difficulty maintain their just rights against the incessant efforts daily made to encroach upon them.  The mischief springs from the power which the moneyed interest derives from a paper currency, which they are able to control; from the multitude of corporations, with exclusive privileges, which they have succeeded in obtaining in the different States, and which are employed altogether for their benefit; and unless you become more watchful in your states and check this spirit of monopoly and thirst for exclusive privileges, you <pb n="8" facs="sl003h.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top, middle">12</add> will in the end, find that the most important powers of government have been given or bartered away, and the control over your dearest interests has passed into the hands of these corporations.</p>
            <p>The paper money system, and its natural associates, monopoly and exclusive privileges, have already struck their roods deep in the soil; and it will require all your efforts to check its further growth, and to eradicate the evil.  The men who profit by the abuses, and desire to perpetuate them, will continue to besiege the halls of legislation in the General Government as well as in the States, and will seek, by every artifice, to mislead and deceive the public servants.  It is to yourselves that you must look for your safety, and the means of guarding and perpetuating your free institutions.  In your hands is rightfully placed the sovereignty of the country; and to you every one placed in authority is ultimately responsible.  It is always in your power to see that the wishes of the people are carried into faithful execution, and their will, when once made known, must sooner or later be obeyed.  And while the people remain, as I trust they ever will, uncorrupted and incorruptible, and continue watchful and jealous of their rights, the government is safe, and the cause of freedom will continue to triumph over all its enemies.</p>
            <p>But it will require steady and persevering exertions on your part to rid yourself of the iniquities and mischiefs of the paper system, and to check the spirit of monopoly and other abuses which have sprung up with it, and of which it is the main support.  So many interests are united to resist all reform on this subject that you must not hope the conflict will be a short one, nor success easy.  My humble efforts have not been spared, during my administration of the government to restore the constitutional currency of gold and silver, and sometimes I trust, has been done towards the accomplishment of this most desirable o<gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>b</unclear>ject. But enough yet remains to require all your energy and perseverance.  The power, however, is in your hands, and the remedy must and will be applied, if you determine upon it.</p>
            <p>While I am thus endeavoring to press upon your attention the principles which I deem of vital importance in the domestic concerns of the country, I ought not to pass over, without notice, the important considerations which should govern your policy towards foreign powers.  It is, unquestionably, our true interest to cultivate the most friendly understanding with every nation, and to avoid, by every honorable means, the calamities of war; and we shall best attain this object by frankness and sincerity in our foreign intercourse, by the prompt and faithful execution of treaties, and by justice and impartiality in our conduct to all.  But no nation, however desirous of peace, can hope to escape occasional collisions with other powers; and the soundest dictates of policy require that we should place ourselves in a condition to assert our rights, if a resort to force should ever become necessary.  Our local situation, out long line of seacoast, indented by numerous bays, with deep rivers opening into the interior, as well as our extended and still increasing commerce, point to the navy as our natural means of defence.  It will, in the end, be found to be the cheapest and most effectual; and now is the time, in a season of peace, and with an overflowing revenue, that we can, year  after year, add to its strength, without increasing the burdens of the people.  It is your true policy.  For your navy will not only protect your rich and flourishing commerce in distant seas, but will enable you to reach and annoy the enemy, and will give to defence its greatest efficiency, by meeting danger at a distance from home.  It is impossible, by any line of fortifications, to guard every point from attack against a hostile force advancing from the ocean and selecting its object; but they are indispensable to protect cities from bombardment; dock yards and naval arsenals from destruction; to give shelter to merchant vessels in time of war, and to single ships or weaker squadrons when pressed by a superior force.  Fortifications of this description cannot be too soon completed and armed, and placed in a condition of the most perfect preparation.  The abundant means we now possess cannot be applied in any manner more useful to the country; and when this is done and our <choice>
                  <orig>navel</orig>
                  <reg>naval</reg>
               </choice> force sufficiently strengthened, and our militia armed, we need not fear that any nation will wantonly insult us, or needlessly provoke hostilities.  We shall more certainly preserve peace, when it is well understood that we are prepared for war.</p>
            <p>
               <add place="top, middle">13</add> In presenting to you, my fellow citizens these parting counsels, I have brought before you the leading principles upon which I endeavored to administer the government in the high office with which you twice honored me.  Knowing that the path of freedom is continually beset by enemies, who often assume the disguise of friends, I have devoted the last hours of my public life to warn you of the dangers.  The progress of the United States, under our free and happy institutions, has surpassed the most sanguine hopes of the founders of the Republic.  Our growth has been rapid beyond all former example, in numbers, in wealth, in knowledge, and all the useful arts which contribute to the comforts and convenience of man; and from the earlier ages of history to the present day, there never have been thirteen millions of people associated together in one political body, who enjoyed so much freedom and happiness as the people of these United States.  You have no longer any cause to fear danger from abroad; your strength and power are well known throughout the civilized world, as well as the high and gallant bearing of your sons.  It is from within among yourselves, from cupidity, from corruption, from disappointed ambition, and inordinate thirst for power, that factions will be formed and liberty endangered.  It is against such designs, whatever disguise the actors may assume, that you have especially to guard yourselves.  You have the highest of human trusts committed to your care. Providence has showered on this favored land blessings without number, and has chosen you as the guardians of freedom to preserve it for the benefit of the human race.  May He, who holds in his hands the destinies of nations, make you worthy of the favors he has bestowed, and enable you, with pure hearts and pure hands, and sleepless vigilance, to guard and defend to the end of time, the great charge he has committed to your keeping.</p>
            <p>My own race is nearly run; advanced age and failing health warn me that before I must pass beyond the reach of human events, and cease to feel the vicissitudes of human affairs.  I thank God that my life has been spent in a land of liberty, and that he has given me a heart to love my country with the affection of a son.  And filled with gratitude for your constant and unwavering kindness, I bid you a last and affectionate farewell.</p>
            <p>ANDREW JACKSON</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="sl003i.small.jpg"/>
            <p>PROCLAMATION</p>
            <p>BY ANDREW JACKSON, PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES</p>
            <p>―</p>
            <p>Whereas, A convention assembled in the State of <name type="place">South Carolina</name> have passed an ordinance, by which they declare "that the several acts and parts of acts of the Congress of the United States, purporting to be laws for the imposing of duties and imposts on the importation of foreign commodities, and now having actual operation and effect within the United States, and more especially" two acts, for the same purposes, passed on the <date when="1828-05-29">29th of May, 1828</date>, and on the <date when="1832-07-14">14th of July, 1832</date>, "are unauthorized by the Constitution of the United States, and violate the true meaning and intent thereof, and are null and void, and no law," nor binding on the citizens of that State or its officers: and by the said ordinance it is further declared to be unlawful for any of the constituted authorities of the State, or of the United States, to enforce the payment of the duties imposed by the said acts within the same State, and that it is the duty of the Legislature to pass such laws as may be necessary to give full effect to the said ordinance:</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">And whereas</hi>, By the said ordinance it is further ordained, that, in no case of law or equity, decided in the courts of said State, wherein shall be drawn in question the validity of the said ordinance, or of the acts of the Legislature that may be passed to give it effect, or of the said laws of the United States, no appeal shall be allowed to the supreme court of the United States, nor shall any copy of the record be permitted or allowed for that purpose; and that any person attempting to take such appeal shall be punished as for a contempt of court:</p>
            <p>And, finally, the said ordinance declares that the people of South Carolina will maintain the said ordinance at every hazard; and that they will consider the passage of any act by Congress abolishing or closing the ports of the said State, or otherwise obstructing the free ingress or egress of vessels to and from the said ports, or any other act of the Federal Government to coerce the State, shut up her ports, destroy or harass her commerce, or to enforce the said acts otherwise than through the civil tribunals of the country, as inconsistent with the longer continuance of South Carolina in the Union; and that the people of the said State will thenceforth hold themselves absolved from all further obligation to maintain or preserve  their political connection with the people of the other States, and will forthwith proceed to organize a separate government, and do all other acts and things which sovereign and independent States may of right do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="i">And whereas</hi>, The said ordinance prescribes to the people of South Carolina a course of conduct, in direct violation of their duty as citizens of the United States, contrary to the laws of their country, subversive of its Constitution, and having for its object the destruction of the Union—that Union, which, coeval with our political existence, led our fathers, without any other ties to unite them than those of patriotism and a common cause, through a sanguinary struggle to a glorious independence—that sacred Union, hitherto inviolate, which, perfected by our happy Constitution, has brought us, by the favor of heaven, to a state of prosperity at home, and high consideration abroad, rarely, if ever, equalled in the history of nations.  To preserve this bond of our political existence from destruction, to maintain inviolate this state of national honor and prosperity, and to justify the confidence my fellow citizens have reposed in me, I, <hi rend="sc">Andrew Jackson</hi>, <hi rend="i">President of the United States</hi> have thought proper to issue this <add place="top, middle">15</add> my PROCLAMATION, stating my views of the Constitution and laws applicable to the measures adopted by the convention of South Carolina, and to the reasons they have put forth to sustain them, declaring the course which duty will require me to pursue, and, appealing to the understanding and patriotism of the people, warn them of the consequences that must inevitably result from an observance of the dictates of the convention.</p>
            <p>Strict duty would require of me nothing more than the exercise of those powers with which I am now, or may hereafter be, invested, for preserving the peace of the Union, and for the execution of the laws.  But the imposing aspect which opposition has assumed in this case, by clothing itself with State authority, and the deep interest which the people of the United States must all feel in preventing a resort to stronger measures, while there is a hope that any thing will be yielded to reasoning and remonstrance, perhaps demand, and will certainly justify, a full exposition to South Carolina and the nation of the views I entertain of this important question, as well as a distinct enunciation of the course which my sense of duty will require me to pursue.</p>
            <p>The ordinance is founded, not on the indefeasible right of resisting acts which are plainly unconstitutional, and too oppressive to be endured, but on the strange position that any one State may not only declare an act of Congress void, but prohibit its execution—that they may do this consistently with the Constitution—that the true construction of that instrument permits a State to retain its place in the Union, and yet be bound by no other of its laws than those it may choose to consider as Constitutional.  It is true, they add, that, to justify this abrogation of a law, it must be palpably contrary to the Constitution; but it is evident, that to give the right of resisting laws of that description, coupled with the uncontrolled right to decide what laws deserve that character, is to give the power of resisting all laws.  For, as by the theory there is no appeal, the reasons alleged by the State, good or bad, must prevail.  If it should be said that public opinion is a sufficient check against the abuse of this power, it may be asked why it is not deemed a sufficient guard against the passage of an unconstitutional act by Congress.  There is, however, a restraint in this last case, which makes the assumed power of a State more indefeasible, and which does not exist in the other.  There are two appeals from an unconstitutional act passed by Congress—one to the judiciary, the other to the people and the States.  There is no appeal from the State decision in theory; and the practical illustration shows that the courts are closed against an application to review it, both judges and jurors being sworn to decide in its favor.  But reasoning on this subject is superfluous when our social compact in express terms declares, that the laws of the United States, its Constitution, and the treaties made under it, are the supreme law of the land; and, for greater caution, adds, "that the judges in every State shall be bound thereby, any thing in the Constitution or laws of any State to the contrary notwithstanding."  And it may be asserted, without fear of refutation, that no federative government could exist without a similar provision.  Look for a moment to the consequence.  If South Carolina considers the revenue laws unconstitutional, and has a right to prevent their execution in the port of <name type="place">Charleston</name>, there would be a clear constitutional objection to their collection in every other port, and no revenue could be collected any where; for all imposts must be equal.  It is no answer to repeat that an unconstitutional law is no law, so long as the question of its legality is to be decided by the State itself; for every law operating injuriously upon any local interest will be perhaps thought, and certainly represented, as unconstitutional, and, as has been shown, there is no appeal.</p>
            <p>If this doctrine had been established at an earlier day, the Union would have been dissolved in its infancy.  The excise law in <name type="place">Pennsylvania</name>, the embargo and nonintercourse law in the eastern States, the carriage tax in <name type="place">Virginia</name> , were all deemed unconstitutional, and were more unequal in their operation than any of the laws now complained of; but fortunately, none of those States discovered that they had the right now claimed by South Carolina.  The war into which we were forced, to support the dignity of the nation and the rights of our citizens, might have ended in defeat and disgrace, instead of victory and honor, if the States, who supposed it a ruinous and unconstitutional measure, had thought they possessed the right of nullifying the act <pb n="10" facs="sl003j.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top, middle">16</add> by which it was declared, and denying supplies for its prosecution.  Hardly and unequally as those measures bore upon several members of the Union, to the Legislatures of none did this efficient and peaceable remedy, as it is called, suggest itself.  The discovery of this important feature in our Constitution was reserved to the present day.  To the statesmen of South Carolina belongs the invention, and upon the citizens of that State will unfortunately fall the evils of reducing it to practice.</p>
            <p>If the doctrine of a State veto upon the laws of the Union carries with it internal evidence of its impracticable absurdity, our constitutional history will also afford abundant proof that it would have been repudiated with indignation, had it been proposed to form a feature in our government.</p>
            <p>In our colonial state, although dependent on another power, we very early considered ourselves as connected by common interest with each other.  Leagues were formed for common defence, and before the Declaration of Independence, we were known in our aggregate character as the <hi rend="sc">United Colonies of America</hi>.  That decisive and important step was taken jointly.  We declared ourselves a nation by a joint, not by several acts; and when the terms of our confederation were reduced to form, it was in that of a solemn league of several States, by which they agreed that they would, collectively, form one nation for the purpose of conducting some certain domestic concerns, and all foreign relations.  In the instrument forming that Union, is found an article which declares that "every State shall abide by the determinations of Congress on all questions which by that confederation should be submitted to them."</p>
            <p>Under the confederation, then, no State could legally annul a decision of the Congress, or refuse to submit to its execution; but no provision was made to enforce these decisions. Congress made requisitions, but they were not complied with.  The government could not operate on individuals.  They had no judiciary, no means of collecting revenue.</p>
            <p>But the defects of the confederation need not be detailed.  Under its operation, we could scarcely be called a nation.  We had neither prosperity at home nor consideration abroad.  This state of things could not be endured, and our present happy Constitution was formed; but formed in vain, if this fatal doctrine prevails.  It was formed for important objects that are announced in the preamble made in the name and by the authority of the people of the United States, whose delegates framed, and whose conventions approved it.  The most important among these objects, that which is placed first in rank, on which all the others rest, is, "<hi rend="i">to form a more perfect Union</hi>." Now, is it possible that, even if there were no express provision giving supremacy to the Constitution and laws of the United States over those of the States, it can be conceived, that an instrument made for the purpose of "<hi rend="i">forming a more perfect Union</hi>" than that of the confederation, could be so constructed by the assembled wisdom of our country as to substitute for that confederation a form of government dependent for its existence on the local interest, the party spirit of a State, or of a prevailing faction in a State? Every man of plain unsophisticated understanding, who hears the question will give such an answer as will preserve the Union.  Metaphysical subtlety, in pursuit of an impracticable theory, could alone have devised one that is calculated to destroy it.</p>
            <p>I consider, then, the power to annul a law of the United States, assumed by one State, <hi rend="sc">incompatible with the existence of the Union, contradicted expressly by the letter of the Constitution, unauthorized by its spirit, inconsistent with every principle on which it was founded, and destructive of the great object for which it was formed</hi>.</p>
            <p>After this general view of the leading principle, we must examine the particular application of it which is made in the ordinance.</p>
            <p>The preamble rests its justification on these grounds: It assumes as a fact, that the obnoxious laws, although they purport to be laws for raising revenue, were in reality intended for the protection of manufactures, which purpose it asserts to be unconstitutional—that the operation of these laws in unequal—that the amount raised by them is greater than is required by the wants of the government—and, finally, that the proceeds are to be applied to objects unauthorized by the Constitution.  These are the <add place="top, middle">17</add> only causes alleged to justify an open opposition to the laws of the country, and a threat of seceding from the Union, if any attempt should be made to enforce them.  The first virtually acknowledges that the law in question was passed under a power expressly given by the Constitution, to lay and collect imposts; but its constitutionality is drawn in question from the motives of those who passed it.  However apparent this purpose may be in the present case, nothing can be more dangerous than to admit the position that an unconstitutional purpose, entertained by the members who assent to a law enacted under a constitutional power, shall make that law void; for how is that purpose to be ascertained? Who is to make the scrutiny? How often may bad purposes be falsely imputed? in how many cases are they concealed by false professions? in how many is no declaration of motive made? Admit this doctrine, and you give to the States an uncontrolled right to decide, and every law may be annulled under this pretext.  If, therefore, the absurd and dangerous doctrine should be admitted, that a State may annul an unconstitutional law, or one that it deems such, it will not apply to the present case.</p>
            <p>The next objection is, that the laws in question operate unequally.  This objection may be made with truth to every law that has been or can be passed.  The wisdom of man never yet contrived a system of taxation that would operate with perfect equality.  If the unequal operation of a law makes it unconstitutional, and if all laws of that description may be abrogated by any State for that cause, then indeed is the Federal Constitution unworthy of the slightest effort for its preservation.  We have hitherto relied on it as the perpetual bond of our Union.  We have received it as the work of the assembled wisdom of the nation.  We have trusted to it as to the sheet anchor of our safety, in the stormy times of conflict with a foreign or domestic foe.  We have looked to it with sacred awe as the palladium of our liberties, and, with all the solemnities of religion, have pledged to each other our lives and fortunes here, and our hopes of happiness hereafter, in its defence and support.  Were we mistaken, my countrymen, in attaching  this importance to the Constitution of our country? Was our devotion paid to the wretched, inefficient, clumsy contrivance, which this new doctrine would make it? Did we pledge ourselves to the support of an airy nothing—a bubble that must be blown away by the first breath of disaffection? Was this self-destroying, visionary theory, the work of the profound statesmen, the exalted patriots, to whom the task of constitutional reform was entrusted? Did the name of Washington sanction, did the States deliberately ratify, such an anomaly in the history of fundamental legislation? No.  We were not mistaken! The letter of this great instrument is free from this radical fault; its language directly contradicts the imputation; its spirit—its evident intent contradicts it.  No, we did not err! Our Constitution does not contain the absurdity of giving power to make laws, and another power to resist them.  The sages, whose memory will always be reverenced, have given us a practical, and, as they hoped, a permanent constitutional compact.  The Father of his Country did not affix his reverend name to so palpable an absurdity.  Nor did the States, when they severally ratified it, do so under the impression that a veto on the laws of the United States was reserved to them, or that they could exercise it by application.  Search the debates in all their conventions—examine the speeches of the most zealous opposers of federal authority—look at the amendments that were proposed.  They are all silent—not a syllable uttered, not a vote given, not a motion made, to correct the explicit supremacy given to the laws of the Union over those of the States—or to show that implication, as is now contended, could defeat it. No, we have not erred! The Constitution is still the object of our reverence, the bond of our Union, our defence in danger, the source of our prosperity in peace.  It shall descend, as we have received it, uncorrupted by sophistical construction, to our posterity; and the sacrifices of local interest, of State prejudices, of personal animosities, that were made to bring into existence will again be patriotically offered for its support.</p>
            <p>The two remaining objections made by the ordinance to these laws are, that the sums intended to be raised by them are greater than are required, and that the proceeds will be unconstitutionally employed.  The Constitution has given expressly to Congress the right of raising revenue, and of determining the sum the public exigencies <pb n="11" facs="sl003k.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top, middle">18</add> will require.  The States have no control over the exercise of this right, other than that which results from the power of changing the representatives who abuse it, and thus procure redress.  Congress may undoubtedly abuse this discretionary power, but the same may be said of others with which they are vested.  Yet the discretion must exist somewhere.  The Constitution has given it to the representatives of all the people, checked by the representatives of the States, and by the Executive power.  The South Carolina construction gives it to the Legislature or the convention of a single State, where neither the people of the different States, nor the States in their separate capacity, nor the Chief Magistrate elected by the people, have any representation.  Which is the most discreet disposition of the power? I do not ask you, fellow citizens, which is the constitutional disposition—that instrument speaks a language not to be misunderstood.  But if you were assembled in general convention, which would you think the safest depository of this discretionary power in the last resort? Would you add a clause giving it to each of the States, or would you sanction the wise provisions already made by your Constitution? If this should be the result of your deliberations when providing for the future, are you—can you—be ready to risk all that we hold dear, to establish, for a temporary and a local purpose, that which you must acknowledge to be destructive, and even absurd, as a general provision? Carry out the consequences of this right vested in the different States, and you must perceive that the crisis your conduct presents at this day would recur whenever any law of the United States displeased any of the States, and that we should soon cease to be a nation.</p>
            <p>The ordinance, with the same knowledge of that future that characterizes a former objection, tells you that the proceeds of the tax will be unconstitutionally applied.  If this could be ascertained with certainty, the objection would, with more propriety, be reserved for the law so applying the proceeds, but surely cannot be urged against the laws levying the duty.</p>
            <p>These are the allegations contained in the ordinance.  Examine them seriously, my fellow citizens—judge for yourselves.  I appeal to you to determine whether they are so clear, so convincing, as to leave no doubt of their correctness; and even if you should come to this conclusion, how far they justify the reckless, destructive course, which you are directed to pursue. Review these objections, and the conclusions drawn from them, once more.  What are they? Every law, then, for raising revenue, according to the South Carolina ordinance, may be rightfully annulled, unless it be so framed as no law ever will or can be framed.    Congress have a right to pass laws for raising revenue, and each State has a right to oppose their execution—two rights directly opposed to each other; and yet is this absurdity supposed to be contained in an instrument drawn for the express purpose of avoiding <choice>
                  <orig>collissions</orig>
                  <reg>collisions</reg>
               </choice> between the States and the General Government, by an assembly of the most enlightened statesmen and purest patriots ever embodied for a similar purpose.</p>
            <p>In vain have these sages declared that Congress shall have power to lay and collect taxes, duties, imposts, and excises—in vain have they provided that they shall have power to pass laws which shall be necessary and proper to carry those powers into execution; that those laws and that Constitution shall be the "supreme law of the land; and that the judges in every State shall be bound thereby, any thing in the constitution of laws of any State to the contrary notwithstanding." In vain have the people of the several States solemnly sanctioned these provisions, made them their paramount law, and individually sworn to support them whenever they were called on to execute any office.  Vain provisions! ineffectual restrictions! vile profanation of oaths! miserable mockery of legislation! If a bare majority of the voters in any one State may, on a real or supposed knowledge of the intent with which a law has been passed, declare  themselves free from its operation—say here it gives too little, there too much, and operates unequally—here it suffers articles to be free that ought to be taxed, there it taxes those that ought to be free—in this case the proceeds are intended to be applied to purposes which we do not approve, in that the amount raised is more than is wanted.  Congress, it is true, are invested by the Constitution with the right of deciding these questions according to their sound discretion.  Congress is composed of the representatives of all the States, and of all the people of all the States; but <hi rend="sc">we</hi>, part of the people of one <add place="top, middle">19</add>  State, to whom the Constitution has given no power on the subject, from whom it has expressly taken it away—<hi rend="i">we</hi>, who have solemnly agreed that this Constitution shall be our law—<hi rend="i">we</hi>, most of whom have sworn to support it—<hi rend="i">we</hi>, now abrogate this law, and swear, and force others to swear, that it shall not be obeyed—and we do this, not because Congress have no right to pass such laws; this we do not allege; but because they have passed them with improper views.  They are unconstitutional from the motives of those who passed them, which we can never with  certainty know, from their unequal operation; although it is impossible from the nature of things that they should be equal—and from the disposition which we presume may be made of their proceeds, although that disposition has not been declared.  This is the plain meaning of the ordinance in relation to laws which it abrogates for alleged unconstitutionality. But it does not stop there. It repeals, in express terms, an important part of the Constitution itself, and of laws passed to give it effect, which have never been alleged to be unconstitutional.  The Constitution declares that the judicial powers of the United States extend to cases arising under the laws of the United States, and that such laws the Constitution and treaties shall be paramount to the State Constitutions and laws. The judiciary act prescribes the mode by which the case may be brought before a court of the United States, by appeal, when a State tribunal shall decide against this provision of the Constitution. The ordinance declares there shall be no appeal; makes the State law paramount to the Constitution and laws of the United States; forces judges and jurors to swear that they will disregard their provisions; and even makes is lawful for the authorities of the United States, or of that State, to enforce the payment of duties imposed by the revenue laws within its limits.</p>
            <p>Here is a law of the United States, not even pretended to be unconstitutional, repealed by the authority of a small majority of the voters of a single State.  Here is a provision of the Constitution which is solemnly abrogated by the same authority.</p>
            <p>On such expositions and reasonings, the ordinance grounds not only an assertion of the right to annul the laws of which it complains, but to enforce it by a threat of seceding from the Union, if any attempt is made to execute them.</p>
            <p>This right to secede is deduced from the nature of the Constitution, which, they say, is a compact between sovereign States, who have preserved their whole sovereignty, and, therefore, are subject to no superior; that, because they made the compact, they can break it when, in their opinion, it has been departed from by the other States.  Fallacious as this course of reasoning is, it enlists State pride, and finds advocates in the honest prejudices of those who have not studied the nature of our government sufficiently to see the radical error on which it rests.</p>
            <p>The people of the United States formed the Constitution, acting through the State Legislatures in making the compact, to meet and discuss its provisions, and acting in separate conventions when they ratified those provisions; but the terms used in its construction, show it to be a government in which the people of all the States collectively are represented.  We are <hi rend="sc">one people</hi> in the choice of the President and Vice President.  Here the States have no other agency than to direct the mode in which the votes shall be given.  The candidates having the majority of all the votes are chosen.  The electors of a majority of States may have given their votes for one candidate, and yet another may be chosen.  The people, then, and not the States, are represented in the Executive branch.</p>
            <p>In the House of Representatives there is this difference, that the people of one State do not, as in the case of President and Vice President, all vote for the same officers.  The people of all the States do not vote for all the members, each State electing only its own representatives.  But this creates no material distinction.  When chosen, they are all representatives of the United States, not representatives of the particular State from which they come.  They are paid by the United States, not by the State; nor are they accountable to it for any act done in the performance of their legislative functions; and, however they may in practice, as it is their duty to do, consult and prefer the interests of their particular constituents when they come in conflict with any other <pb n="12" facs="sl003l.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top, middle">20</add> partial or local interest, yet it is their first and highest duty, as representatives of the United States, to promote the general good.</p>
            <p>The Constitution of the United States, then, forms a <hi rend="i">government</hi>, not a league; and whether it be formed by compact between the States, or in any other manner, its character is the same.  It is a government in which all the people are represented, which operates directly on the people individually, not upon the States; they retained all the power they did not grant.  But each State having expressly parted with so many powers as to constitute, jointly with the other States a single nation, cannot from that period possess any right to secede, because such secession does not break a league, but destroys the unity of a nation; and any injury to that unity is not only a breach which would result from the contravention of a compact, but it is an offence against the whole Union.  To say that any State may at pleasure secede from the Union, is to say that the United States are not a nation; because it would be a solecism to contend that any part of a nation might dissolve its <choice>
                  <orig>connexion</orig>
                  <reg>connection</reg>
               </choice> with the other parts, to their injury or ruin, without committing any offence.  Secession, like any other revolutionary act, may be morally justified by the extremity of oppression; but to call it a constitutional right is confounding the meaning of terms; and can only be done through gross error, or to deceive those who are willing to assert a right, but would pause before they made a revolution, or incur the penalties consequent on a failure.</p>
            <p>Because the Union was formed by compact, it is said the parties to that compact may, when they feel themselves aggrieved, depart from it: but it is precisely because it is a compact that they cannot.  A compact is an agreement or binding obligation.  It may, by its terms, have a sanction or penalty for its breach, or it may not.—If it contains no sanction, it may be broken with no other consequence than moral guilt: if it have a sanction, then the breach incurs the designated or implied penalty.  A league between the independent nations, generally, has no sanction other than a moral one; or, if it should contain a penalty, as there is no common superior, it cannot be enforced.  A government, on the contrary, always has a sanction, expressed or implied; and, in our case, it is both necessarily implied and expressly given.  An attempt by force of arms to destroy a government, is an offence, by whatever means the constitutional compact may have been formed; and such government has the right, by the law of self-defence, to pass acts for punishing the offender, unless that right is modified, restrained, or resumed, by the constitutional act.  In our system, although it is modified in the case of treason, yet authority is expressly given to pass all laws necessary to carry its powers into effect, and under this grant, provision has been made for punishing acts which obstruct the due administration of the laws.  </p>
            <p>It would seem superfluous to add any thing to show the nature of that union which connects us; but as erroneous opinions on this subject are the foundation of doctrines the most destructive to our peace, I must give some further development to my views on this subject.  No one, fellow citizens, has a higher reverence for the reserved rights of the States, than the Magistrate who now addresses you.  No one would make greater personal sacrifices, or official exertions, to defend them from violation; but equal care must be taken to prevent on their part an improper interference with, or resumption of, the rights they have vested in the nation.  The line has not been so distinctly drawn as to avoid doubts in some cases of the exercise of power.  Men of the best intentions and soundest views may differ in their construction of some parts of the Constitution: but there are others on which dispassionate reflection can leave no doubt.  Of this nature appears to be the assumed right of secession.  It rests, as we have seen, on the alleged undivided sovereignty of the States, and on their having formed in this sovereign capacity a compact which is called the Constitution, from which because they made it, they have the right to secede.  Both of these positions are erroneous, and some of the arguments to prove them so have been anticipated.</p>
            <p>The States severally have not retained their entire sovereignty. It has been shown that in becoming parts of a nation, not members of a league, they surrendered many of  their essential parts of sovereignty.  The right to make treaties—declare war—levy taxes—exercise exclusive judicial and legislative powers—were all of them functions of sovereign power.  The States, then, for all these important purposes, were no longer <add place="top, middle">21</add> sovereign. The allegiance of their citizens was transferred, in the first instance, to the government of the United States—they became American citizens, and owed obedience to the Constitution of the United States, and to laws made in conformity with the powers vested in Congress.  This last position has not been, and cannot be denied.  How then can that State be said to be sovereign and independent, whose citizens owe  obedience to laws not made by it, and whose magistrates are sworn to disregard those laws, when they come in conflict with those passed by another?  What shows conclusively that the States cannot be said to have reserved an undivided sovereignty, is, that they expressly ceded the right to punish treason—not treason against their separate power—but treason against the United States.  Treason is an offence against <hi rend="i">sovereignty</hi>, and sovereignty must reside with the power to punish it.  But the reserved rights to the States are not less sacred, because they have for their common interest made the General Government the depository of these powers.  The unity of our political character (as has been shown for another purpose) commenced with its very existence.  Under the royal government we had no separate character—our opposition to its oppressions began as <hi rend="sc">United Colonies</hi>.  We were the <hi rend="sc">United States</hi> under the confederation, and the name was perpetuated, and the Union rendered more perfect, by the Federal Constitution.  In none of these stages did we consider ourselves in any other light than as forming one nation.  Treaties and alliances were made in the name of all.  Troops were raised for the joint defence.  How, then, with all these proofs, that under all changes of our position we had, for designated purposes and with defined powers, created national governments—how is it, that the most perfect of those several modes of union should now be considered as a mere league, that may be dissolved at pleasure? It is from an abuse of terms.  Compact is used as synonymous with league, although the true term is not employed, because it would at once shew the fallacy of the reasoning.  It would not do to say that our Constitution was only a league; but, it is labored to prove it a compact, (which in one sense it is) and then to argue that as a league is a compact, every compact between nations must of course be a league, and that from such an engagement every sovereign power has a right to recede.  But it has been shown, that in this sense the States are not sovereign, and that even if they were, and the National Constitution had been formed by compact, there would be no right in any one State to exonerate itself from its obligations.</p>
            <p>So obvious are the reasons which forbid this secession, that it is necessary only to allude to them.  The Union was formed for the benefit of all.  It was produced by mutual sacrifices of interests and opinions.  Can those sacrifices be recalled? Can the States who magnanimously surrendered their title to the territories of the west, recall the grant? Will the inhabitants of the inland States agree to pay the duties that may be imposed without their assent by those on the <name type="place">Atlantic</name> or the gulf, for their own benefit? Shall there be a free port in one State, and onerous duties in another? No one believes that any right exists in a single State to involve all the others in these and countless other evils, contrary to the engagements solemnly made.  Every one must see that the other States, in self-defence, must oppose at all hazards.</p>
            <p>These are the alternatives that are presented by the convention: a repeal of all the acts for raising revenue, leaving the government without the means of support; or an acquiescence in the dissolution of the Union, by the secession of one of its members.  When the first was proposed, it was known that it could not be listened to for a moment.  It was known if force was applied to oppose the execution of the laws, that it must be repelled by force—that Congress could not, without involving itself in disgrace, and the country in ruin, accede to the proposition; and yet, if this is not done in a given day, or if any attempt is made to execute the laws, the State is, by the ordinance, declared to be out of the Union.  The majority of a convention assembled for  the purpose have dictated these terms, or rather this rejection of all terms, in the name of the people of South Carolina.  It is true that the Governor of the State speaks of the submission of their grievances to a convention of all the States; which, he says, they "sincerely and anxiously seek and desire." Yet this obvious and constitutional mode of obtaining the sense of the other States on the construction of the federal compact, and amending it, if necessary, has never been attempted by those who have urged <pb n="13" facs="sl003m.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top, middle">22</add> the State on this destructive measure.  The State might have proposed the call for a general convention to the other States; and Congress, if a sufficient number of them concurred, most have called it.  But the first magistrate of South Carolina, when he expressed a hope that, "on a review by Congress and the functionaries of the General Government of the merits of the controversy," such a convention will be accorded to them, must have known that neither Congress nor any functionary of the General Government has authority to call such a convention, unless it be demanded by two-thirds of the States.  This suggestion, then, is another instance of the reckless inattention to the provisions of the Constitution with which this crisis has been madly hurried on; or of the attempt to persuade the people that a constitutional remedy had been sought and refused.  If the Legislature of South Carolina "anxiously desire" a general convention to consider their complaints, why have they not made application for it in the way the Constitution points out?  The assertion that they "earnestly seek" it is completely negatived by the omission.</p>
            <p>This, then, is the position in which we stand.  A small majority of the citizens of one State in the Union have elected delegates to a State convention: that convention has ordained that all the revenue laws of the United States must be repealed, or that they are no longer a member of the Union.  The Governor of that State has recommended to the Legislature the raising of an army to carry the secession into effect, and that he may be empowered to give clearances to vessels in the name of the State.  No act of violent opposition to the laws has yet been committed, but such  a state of things is hourly apprehended, and it is the intent of this instrument to <hi rend="sc">proclaim</hi> not only that the duty imposed on me by the Constitution "to take care that the laws be faithfully executed," shall be performed to the extent of the powers already vested in me by law, or of such other as the wisdom of Congress shall devise and entrust to me for that purpose; but to warn the citizens of South Carolina, who have been deluded into an opposition to the laws, of the danger they will incur by obedience to the illegal and disorganizing ordinance of the convention,—to exhort those who have refused to support it to persevere in their determination, to uphold the Constitution and laws of their country, and to point out to all the perilous situation into which the good people of that State have been led,—and that the course they are urged to pursue is one of ruin and disgrace to the very State whose rights they affect to support.</p>
            <p>Fellow citizens of my native State!—let me not only admonish you, as the First Magistrate of our common country, not to incur the penalty of its laws, but use the influence that a father would over his children whom he saw rushing to certain ruin. In that paternal language, with that paternal feeling, let me tell you, my countrymen, that you are deluded by men who are either deceived themselves, or wish to deceive you.  Mark under what <choice>
                  <orig>pretences</orig>
                  <reg>pretenses</reg>
               </choice> you have been led on to the brink of insurrection and treason, on which you stand! First, a diminution of the value of your staple commodity, lowered by over production in other quarters, and the consequent diminution in the value of your lands, were the sole effect of the tariff laws.  The effect of those laws are confessedly injurious, but the evil was greatly exaggerated by the unfounded theory you were taught to believe, that its burthens were in proportion to your exports, not to your consumption of imported articles.  Your pride was roused by the assertion that a submission to those laws was a state of vassalage, and that resistance to them was equal, in patriotic merit, to the opposition our fathers offered to the oppressive laws of <name type="place">Great Britain</name>. You were told that this opposition might be peaceably—might be constitutionally made—that you might enjoy all the advantages of the Union and bear non of its burthens.</p>
            <p>Eloquent appeals to your passions, to your State pride, to your native courage, to your sense of real injury, were used to prepare you for the period to when the mask which concealed the hideous features of DISUNION should be taken off.  It fell, and you were made to look with complacency on objects which, not long since, you would have regarded with horror. Look back at the arts which have brought you to this state—look forward to the consequences to which it must inevitably lead! Look back to what was first told you as an inducement to enter into this dangerous course.  The great political truth was repeated to you, that you had the revolutionary right of resist-<add place="top, middle">23</add>ing all laws that were palpably unconstitutional and intolerably oppressive—it was added that the right to nullify a law rested on the same principle, but that it was a peaceable remedy! This character which was given to it, made you receive, with too much confidence, the assertions that were made of the unconstitutionality of the law, and its oppressive effects.  Mark, my fellow citizens, that by the admission of your leaders, the unconstitutionality must be <hi rend="i">palpable</hi>, or it will not justify either resistance or nullification! What is the meaning of the word <hi rend="i">palpable</hi>, in the sense in which it is here used?—that which is apparent to every one; that which no man of ordinary intellect will fail to perceive.  Is the unconstitutionality of these laws of that description? Let those among your leaders who once approved and advocated the principle of protective duties, answer the question; and let them choose whether they will be considered as incapable, then, of perceiving that which must have been apparent to every man of common understanding, or as imposing upon your confidence, and endeavoring to mislead you now.  In either case, they are unsafe guides in the perilous path they urge you to tread. Ponder well on this circumstance, and you will know how to appreciate the exaggerated language they address to you.  They are not champions of liberty, emulating the fame of our Revolutionary fathers; nor are you oppressed people, contending, as they repeat to you, against worse than colonial vassalage.  You are free members of a flourishing and happy Union.  There is no settled design to oppress you.  You have indeed felt the unequal operation of laws which may have been unwisely, not unconstitutionally passed; but that inequality must necessarily be removed.  At the very moment when you were madly urged on the unfortunate course you have begun, a change in public opinion had commenced.  The nearly approaching payment of the public debt, and the consequent necessity of a diminution of duties, had already produced a considerable reduction, and that too on some articles of general consumption in your State.  The importance of this change was understood, and you were authoritatively told, that no further alleviation of your burthens was to be expected, at the very time when the condition of the country imperiously demanded such a modification of the duties as should reduce them to a just and equitable scale.  But, as if apprehensive of the effect of this change in allaying your discontents, you were precipitated into the fearful state in which you now find yourselves.</p>
            <p>I have urged you to look back to the means that were used to hurry you on to the position you have now assumed, and forward to the consequences it will produce.  Something more is necessary.  Contemplate the condition of that country on which you still form an important part! Consider its government, uniting in one bond of common interests and general protection so many different States, giving to all their inhabitants the proud title of <hi rend="sc">American citizens</hi>, protecting their commerce, securing their literature and their arts, facilitating their intercommunication, defending their frontiers, and making their name respected in the remotest parts of the earth! Consider the extent of its territory, its increasing and happy population, its advance in arts, which render life agreeable, and the sciences which elevate the mind! See education spreading the lights of religion, humanity, and general information into every cottage in this wide extent of our Territories and States! Behold it as the asylum where the wretched and the oppressed find a refuge and support! Look on this picture of happiness and honor, and say—<hi rend="sc">we, too, are citizens of America</hi>; Carolina is one of these proud States: her arms have defended, her best blood has cemented this happy Union! And then add, if you can, without horror and remorse, this happy Union we will dissolve—this picture of peace and prosperity we will deface—this free intercourse we will interrupt—these fertile fields we will deluge with blood—the protection of that glorious flag we renounce—the very names of Americans we discard.  And for what, mistaken men!—for what do you throw away these inestimable blessings—for what would you exchange your share in the advantages and honor of the Union?  For the dream of a separate independence—a dream interrupted by bloody conflicts with your neighbors, and a vile dependence on a foreign power.  If your leaders could succeed in establishing a separation, what would be your situation? Are you united at home—are you free from the apprehension of civil discord, with all its fearful consequences? Do our neighboring republics, every day suffering some new revolution, or contending with some new <pb n="14" facs="sl003n.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top, middle">24</add> insurrection—do they excite your envy? But the dictates of a high duty oblige me solemnly to announce that you cannot succeed.</p>
            <p>The laws of the United States must be executed.  I have no discretionary power on the subject—my duty is emphatically pronounced in the Constitution.  Those who told you that you might peaceable prevent their execution, deceived you—they could not have been deceived themselves.  They know that a forcible opposition could alone prevent the execution of the laws, and they know that such opposition must be repelled.  Their object is disunion; but be not deceived by names; disunion, by armed force, is <hi rend="sc">treason</hi>. Are you really ready to incur its guilt? If you are, on the heads of the instigators of the act be the dreadful consequences—on their heads be the dishonor, but on yours may fall the punishment—on your unhappy State will inevitably fall all the evils of the conflict you force upon the government of your country.  It cannot accede to the mad project of disunion of which you would be the first victims—its First Magistrate cannot, if he would, avoid the performance of his duty—the consequence must be fearful for you, distressing to your fellow citizens here, and to the friends of good government  throughout the world.  Its enemies have beheld our prosperity with a vexation they could not conceal—it was a standing refutation of their slavish doctrines, and they will point to our discord with the triumph of malignant joy.  It is yet in your power to disappoint them.  There is yet time to show that the descendants of the  <name type="person">Pinckneys</name>, the <name type="person">Sumpters</name>, the <name type="person">Rutledges</name>; and of the thousand other names which adorn the pages of your revolutionary history will not abandon that Union to support which, so many of them fought, and bled, and died.  I adjure you as you honor their memory—as you love the cause of freedom, to which they dedicated their lives—as you prize the peace of your country, the lives of its best citizens, and your own fair fame, to retrace your steps.  Snatch from the archives of your state the disorganizing edict of its convention—bid its members to re-assemble and promulgate the decided expressions of your will to remain in the path which alone can conduct you to safety, prosperity and honor—tell them that compared to disunion, all other evils are light, because that brings with it an accumulation of all—declare that you will never take the field unless the star spangled banner of your country shall float over you—that you will not be stigmatized when dead, and dishonored and scorned while you live, as the authors of the first attack on the Constitution of your country!—Its destroyers you cannot be.  You may disturb its peace—you may interrupt the course of its prosperity—you may cloud its reputation for stability—but its tranquility will be restored, its prosperity will return, and the stain upon its national character will be transferred, and remain an eternal blot on the memory of those who caused the disorder.</p>
            <p>Fellow citizens of the United States! The threat of unhallowed disunion—the names of those, once respected, by whom it is uttered—the array of military force to support it—denote the approach of a crisis in our affairs on which the continuance of our unexampled prosperity, our political existence, and perhaps that of all free governments may depend.  The conjunction demanded a free, a full, and explicit enunciation, not only of my intentions but of my principles of action; and as the claim was asserted of a right by a State to annul the laws of the Union, and even to secede from it at pleasure, a frank exposition of my opinions in relation to the origin and form of our government, and the construction I give to the instrument by which it was erected, seemed to be proper.  Having the fullest confidence in the justness of the legal and constitutional opinion of my duties which has been expressed, I rely with equal confidence on your undivided support in my determination to execute the laws—to preserve the Union by all constitutional means—to arrest, if possible, by moderate but firm measures, the necessity of a recourse to force; and, if it be the will of Heaven that the recurrence of its primeval curse of man for the shedding of a brother's blood should fall upon our hand, that it be not called down by any offensive act on the part of the United States.</p>
            <p>Fellow citizens! the momentous case is before you. On your undivided support of your government depends the decision of the great question it involves, whether your sacred Union will be preserved, and the blessing it secures to us as one people shall be perpetuated.  No one can doubt that the unanimity with which that decision will be expressed, will be such as to inspire new confidence in republican institutions, and that <add place="top, middle">25</add> the prudence, the wisdom and the courage which it will bring to their defence, will transmit them <choice>
                  <orig>umimpaired</orig>
                  <reg>unimpaired</reg>
               </choice> and invigorated to our children.</p>
            <p>May the Great Rule of nations grant that the signal blessings with which He has favored ours, may not, by the madness of party or personal ambition, be disregarded and lost: and may His wise Providence bring those who have produced this crisis, to see the folly, before they feel the misery of civil strife: and inspire a returning veneration for that Union which, if we may dare to penetrate His designs, He has chosen as the only means of attaining the high destinies to which we may reasonably aspire.</p>
            <p>In testimony whereof , I have caused the seal of the United States to be hereunto affixed, having signed the same with my hand.</p>
            <p>Done at this city of <name type="place">Washington</name> this <date when="1832-12-10">tenth day of December, in the year of our Lord, one thousand eight hundred and thirty-two</date>, and of the independence of the United States the fifty-seventh.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ANDREW JACKSON.</signed>
               <signed>By the President:</signed>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <hi rend="sc">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Edw.</abbr>
                           <expan>Edward</expan>
                        </choice> Livingston</hi>
                  </name>, <hi rend="i">Secretary of State</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
