<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0248">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Claim] 1836 Dec. 16, McMinn County [to] State of Tennessee / John Austin  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Austin, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0248</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 45959459</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Claim] 1836 Dec. 16, McMinn County [to] State of Tennessee / John Austin</title>
               <author> Austin, John</author>
               <date when="1836-12-16">December 16, 1836</date>
               <extent> 2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This note, dated December 16, 1836 is in reference to a murder trial in McMinn County, Tennessee.  The accused murderers, James Foreman and Anderson Springstin were both Cherokee Indians.  The victim, John Walker Jr. was also a native.  Springstin and Foreman employeed E.M. Churchill and Spencer Jarnigan to defend them and the case was sent to the United States Supreme Court.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> pa0248</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Claims</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Claims against</term>
               <term>McMinn County (Tenn.)</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Creator http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/cre">Austin, John</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0248a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>State of Tennessee <lb/> McMinn County</addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>Be it known that I <name>John Camp</name>  a justice of the Peace for the County aforesaid have called before <add>me</add> at my house in said County on this  the <date>16th day of December 1836</date>  and proceed to take the Deposition of <name>John Austin</name> a citizen of <name>Calhoun</name> in <unclear>P county</unclear> who after being duly sworn according to Law <unclear>departh</unclear> and says__ that Question 1st <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Austin are you acquainted with <name>James Foreman</name> &amp; <name>Anderson Springstin</name> native <name>Cherokees</name> of the Cherokee nation who were charged with the murder of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jno</abbr>
                     <expan>John</expan>
                  </choice> Walker <choice>
                     <abbr>Jr</abbr>
                     <expan>Junior</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> &amp; held at <name>Athens</name> Court <name>Tennessee</name>, in 1834__ If so state if the notes here presented in the note given by them to <name>G.W. Churchill</name>   &amp; Spencer <unclear>Jasuagin</unclear> __ and what was it given for__ &amp; state all about it__</p>
            <p>
               <gap agent="damage"/> I am acquainted with the <unclear>Foreman</unclear>
               <gap agent="damage"/> , and was present when the <unclear>note</unclear> here <gap agent="damage"/> me, &amp; answered to this paper, for twelve hundred Dollars dated <date>31st October 1834</date>__ &amp; signed by <name>James C. Foreman</name> &amp; Anderson springstine payable to GW Churchill &amp; <name>spencer Jarnagin</name>, was executed and I signed my name as a witness to said note__ after they signed &amp; acknowledged it in my presence__ They employed Churchill &amp; Jarnagin as Lawyers to defend them against a charge of the state as them for the murder of <unclear>Jus Tralker </unclear> as a native, &amp; executed this note in my presence to Lawyers for their fees <choice>
                  <orig>incase</orig>
                  <reg>in case</reg>
               </choice> and I was present in the Court house and heard Lawyers defend their case.  upon a plea to the jurisdiction of <pb n="2" facs="pa0248b.small.jpg"/> Court, and they labored hard in Cause for the Indian question, &amp; argued the cause for several days and succeeded, in sustaining thier plea__and the judge gave his opinion in faver of the pleas that the Courts of Tennessee had no jurisdition of the case said note is just, &amp; the Indians aforesaid <gap agent="damage"/> value for __ note as aforeaid__ The attorney General appealed ffrom the Judges opinion, to the Supreme Court of Tennessee where the cause was again argued as I have understood__ but the Supreme Court decided against the Indians pleas &amp; the cause is now gone to the Supreme Court of the <unclear>U</unclear>  I have no knowledge of the fact nor do I believe the <choice>
                  <abbr>U states</abbr>
                  <expan>United States</expan>
               </choice>__.  further this Defenent saith not note was ever paid.__</p>
            <closer>
               <name>John Austin</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>State of Tennessee McMinn County</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>I <name>John Camp</name> a justice of the Peace for County, do hereby certify that John Austin signed &amp; swore to this Deposition &amp; note described &amp; enclosed as stated above before me this <date>16th day of December 1836</date>__ and I certify that I am acquainted with the Character of john Austin the <choice>
                     <orig>Defenant</orig>
                     <reg>defendant</reg>
                  </choice>, and state that he is a respectable man &amp; entitled to <add>full</add> credit__ <lb/>
                  <name>Jno Camp</name> justice of the peace for the County aforesaid</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
