<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc165">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1807 Dec. 20, Knoxville [to] Return J. Meigs, Highwassee / John Sevier : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Sevier, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc165</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1807 Dec. 20, Knoxville [to] Return J. Meigs, Highwassee / John Sevier</title>
               <author>Sevier, John</author>
               <date when="1807-12-20">December 20, 1807</date>
               <extent> 3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter from Governor John Sevier to Return J. Meigs, Agent to the Cherokee Indians. Sevier responds to Meigs letter about the murders of two men presumably by the Creek Indians.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">John Sevier Letters</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-368</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc165</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Government relations</term>
               <term>Creek Indians -- Claims against</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr89016779"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Sevier, John, 1745-1815</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc165a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Knoxville</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>20 December 1807</date>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letter <choice>
                  <orig>immeadiatly</orig>
                  <reg>immediatly</reg>
               </choice> on your return from <name>Elk River</name> containing information respecting the murders of <name>Cash</name> &amp; <name>Prigmore</name>, I have been duly honored with_ It appears from the information you have collected that the crimes have been perpetrated by the <name>Creeks</name>, who never hesitate much at such shocking aggressions_ I am much <choice>
                  <orig>surprized </orig>
                  <reg>surprised</reg>
               </choice> at the <name>Cherokees</name> suffering such an intercourse with that savage <choice>
                  <orig>bandittee</orig>
                  <reg>banditti</reg>
               </choice>, who will sooner or later involve their Nation in ruin &amp; extermination. Inclosed is a copy of a letter from <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Cap</abbr>
                     <expan>Captain</expan>
                  </choice>. Surk</name>, who complains of some ill treatment from an Indian fellow at the <name>Shomake Village</name>: Several other complaints have been made respecting the rudeness of the Indians on the Georgia Road_ Their insolence towards <name>Captain Armstead</name> and others rather evinces a hostile and malignant temper_ I seriously wish that tribe may keep themselves within the bounds of moderation_ The people are not disposed to always bear such frequent insults and <pb n="2" facs="sc165b.small.jpg"/>
               <sic>and</sic> probably may teach them to understand they will not always be suffered to pass off with impunity. Inclosed is a letter to the <name>Fox</name>, and also one to the Creek Superintendent_ I deemed it proper to leave the one for the Cherokees unsealed, in order you may be acquainted with the contents, after which you will please to forward it to the <choice>
                  <orig>Cheif</orig>
                  <reg>Chief</reg>
               </choice>: Also by the first opportunity that to the Creek agent, who I have written to, requesting an Enquiry into the murder alleged to be committed by some persons belonging to that Nation, and if found guilty, to have the perpetrators punished_ I deeply deplore the loss of your amiable companion, but no doubt she is in the mansions of bliss_ happy state_ We are traveling the same road with rapidity a very short space in the rear_</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have the honor to be Sir, with sincere &amp; great esteem Your Most <choice>
                     <abbr>obed.t </abbr>
                     <expan>obedient</expan>
                  </choice> &amp; Humble <choice>
                     <abbr>Sert</abbr>
                     <expan>Servant</expan>
                  </choice>.</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>John Sevier</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Col</abbr>
                        <expan>Colonel</expan>
                     </choice> Return J. Meigs</name>
               </add>
            </closer>
            <pb n="3" facs="sc165c.small.jpg"/>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1">
            <p>Governor Sevier's letter 20: Dec 1807 Indian Affairs</p>
            <p>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Colonel Return J. Meigs</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Agent of Indian affairs</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <add>Mail</add>
                     <name>Highwassee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Miscellaneous math calculations</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
