<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl649">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1836 Dec. 10, Oakland, Tennessee [to] Newton Cannon, Nashville, Tennessee / Jacob Peck : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Peck, Jacob</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl649</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1836 Dec. 10, Oakland, Tennessee [to] Newton Cannon, Nashville, Tennessee / Jacob Peck</title>
               <author> Peck, Jacob</author>
               <date when="1836-12-10"> 
			 December 10, 1836</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Judge Jacob Peck to Governor Newton Cannon, dated December 10, 1836. Peck wants to be hired as an engineer on the Charleston-Cincinnati-Louisville Rail Road. He writes to notify Cannon of some of his qualifications.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Newton Cannon Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">4</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl649</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Rail Roads Design and construction</term>
               <term>Engineering</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr2001040541"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Peck, Jacob, 1779-1869</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl649a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Oakland</name>
                     <date>10th <choice>
                           <abbr>Decr.</abbr>
                           <expan>December</expan>
                        </choice>1836</date>.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>A number of my friends have expressed to me their desire that I would undertake the survey of the <name>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Charlston</orig>
                     <reg>Charleston</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> &amp; <name>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Cincinati</orig>
                     <reg>Cincinnati</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> Rail road route through <name>Tennessee</name>; their reasons I am told they have expressed in a petition or address to your Excellency which will be forwarded in due time</p>
            <p>As it is probable you are unacquainted with my abilities as a mathematician, and as it is not probable that much will be said on that subject except what may appear in the address <choice>
                  <orig>refered</orig>
                  <reg>referred</reg>
               </choice> to, I beg leave to say for myself that in the various <add>pursuits</add> of life this branch of science has with me been a favorite study, and with it I have had much to do in practice</p>
            <p>In short there is no part of the duty that will present the least difficulty with me unless in estimate of the cost of construction which at best can but be an approximation to the truth, so that this part of the duty in any hands would be the least certain_ This however like the other parts of the service has its rules which govern others (found in books) and by which I can also be governed.</p>
            <p>But in this I will have the aid of the principal and other sub Engineer and am not as you see afraid to take upon myself at <pb n="2" facs="sl649b.small.jpg"/> at least a part of the responsibility; Every part of the Compass and level lines are not only easy but familiar with me.</p>
            <p>I have mentioned this rail road for several reasons_ It will no doubt be the first to survey it is expected to pass somewhere in this vicinity either by <name>Dandridge</name> or <name>Newmarket</name> to <name>Knoxville</name>__ I am intimately acquainted with the country to be traversed__ I <choice>
                  <orig>oregenally</orig>
                  <reg>originally</reg>
               </choice> furnished <name>Mr Lucas</name> with all the materials for East Tennessee when <choice>
                  <orig>compeling</orig>
                  <reg>compelling</reg>
               </choice> his map of the state; this <choice>
                  <orig>contrebution</orig>
                  <reg>contribution</reg>
               </choice> of mine was the basis also of <name>Mr Rhea</name>s map.</p>
            <p>In Lillimans Journal of Science <choice>
                  <abbr>No</abbr>
                  <expan>Number</expan>
               </choice> 47 <choice>
                  <abbr>v</abbr>
                  <expan>volume</expan>
               </choice>23 / you will find a map of my constructing <name>Mr. Fogg</name> or <name>Mr Bell</name> late <name>Mr Yeatman</name> can furnish you with it, and which I beg you will examine_ It <add>will</add> furnish you with <add>an idea of</add> my powers in topographical drawing, and the article from my <unclear> pen</unclear>, which accompanies the map of the minuteness of my observations upon the country delineated_</p>
            <p>I do not aspire to the head of the <unclear>corpse</unclear> or board if you choose to confer upon me the office of assistant engineer I can only pledge myself that the duty shall be faithfully and impartially executed so far as the execution may depend upon myself, and at as little cost as if <choice>
                  <orig>commited</orig>
                  <reg>committed</reg>
               </choice> to another, for I <pb n="3" facs="sl649c.small.jpg"/> I shall be content with such compensation as the other assistant whoever he may be may agree upon_ Or if you deem it more proper that I should state terms a letter from you so advising me shall be answered.</p>
            <p>I do not know that I need add more than to say I shall be gratified in serving my friends and the public but above all that you may be found to entertain as high an opinion of me as you see I entertain of myself__</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Yours Respectfully</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Jacob Peck</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>His Excellency</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Newton Cannon</name>_</addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl649d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Mossy</abbr>
                           <expan>Mossey</expan>
                        </choice> Creek</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>17th Decr 1836</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>His Excellency</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Newton Cannon</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Judge Peck</add>
               <add>Judge Peck</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
