<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl268">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1843 Mar. 9 [to] George W. House, Nashville, Tenn[essee] / J. P. Williams   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Williams, J. P.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl268</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51238358</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1843 Mar. 9 [to] George W. House, Nashville, Tenn[essee] / J. P. Williams</title>
               <author>Williams, J. P.</author>
               <date when="1843-03-09">March 9, 1843</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from J. P. Williams to George W. House, dated March 9, 1843. Williams is trying to convince House to give him some medicine. The medicine is some kind of pill that House has declared he would not give out for moral reasons. Williams swears that if House will allow him to take some, he will not let anyone else know. He also promises to pay whatever is asked to House if the pills cure him.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">12</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl268</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Medical care</term>
               <term>Pills</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Williams, J. P.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl268a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1843-03-09">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Mar</abbr>
                           <expan>March</expan>
                        </choice> the 9th 1843</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Mr House</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I again write you a few lines asking of you if it is in your power to let me have the pills to take at home. I would not ask it of you if my situation was such that I could stay in <name type="place">nashville</name> I dont think that I <choice>
                  <orig>posibly</orig>
                  <reg>possibly</reg>
               </choice> could confine myself to a room in Nashville. in my low state of health. here at home I can as I have my relations with me to cheer me up, and all the necessary attention paid me that I would wish. There the medicine might operate before day and I would be caught without <unclear>fire</unclear> or attention and you know from experience how an invalid suffers without attention.</p>
            <p>If you possibly can let me have the medicine I will come down and get it and will be <choice>
                  <orig>wiling</orig>
                  <reg>willing</reg>
               </choice> to obligate myself in a bond of five thousand dollars that know one shall ever see the pills. I have waited and studied upon it since you wrote me that you were <choice>
                  <orig>moraly</orig>
                  <reg>morally</reg>
               </choice> bound <choice>
                  <orig>knot</orig>
                  <reg>not</reg>
               </choice> to give them out. whether I would come down and put myself under you or knot but have come to the determination not to do so as I think I would be <choice>
                  <orig>runing</orig>
                  <reg>running</reg>
               </choice> a great risk to take them in nashville. I would knot Mr House ask them of you if it was not for my low situation and you have had the feelings of one in my situation and I hope it will induce you to let me have them you may think it a little strange <unclear>in me</unclear> to ask it of you since you wrote to me what you did. I have <unclear>such</unclear> strong confidence in it <pb n="2" facs="sl268b.small.jpg"/> curing me that I am anxious to give it another trial at home which I know if I then fail it will not be my fault as I should use all possible means to take care of myself. write to me and let me know if you can let me have them and if you can I will come down immediately. and if the medicine should cure me I will give you one hundred dollars or as much <unclear>money</unclear> as you should ask.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Yours</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">J. P. Williams</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mr <name type="person">George W House</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left of address">by <name type="person">W Jon Childress</name>
               </add>
               <add place="down right margin">J. P. Williams <lb/> March 9. 1843 <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Recd</abbr>
                     <expan>Received</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <date when="1843-03-11">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Mch</abbr>
                        <expan>March</expan>
                     </choice> 11 / 43</date>
                  <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Answd</abbr>
                     <expan>Answered</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <unclear/> 11 / 43</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
