<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl093">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1847 April 9, Elizabethton, Carter County, TN, [to] Tho[mas] E. Abernathy, Elkton, Giles County, TN /  A. W. Taylor   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Taylor, A. W.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl093</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50179080</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1847 April 9, Elizabethton, Carter County, TN, [to] Tho[mas] E. Abernathy, Elkton, Giles County, TN /  A. W. Taylor</title>
               <author>  Taylor, A. W.</author>
               <date when="1847-04-09">April 9, 1847</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from A. W. Taylor to T. E. Abernathy dated April 9, 1847. Taylor is trying to sell Abernathy about 480 acres of land in Giles County,  TN   for $5000.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Abernathy Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">II-H-3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">folder 12</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl093</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Real Property</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Taylor, A. W.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl093a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Carter County </name>
                     <date when="1847-04-09">April 9th 1847</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>your letter withdrawing your proposition as to my land was duly <choice>
                  <abbr>rec'd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> also shortly thereafter your letter reinstating your original proposition was <choice>
                  <abbr>rec'd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> Shortly before I <choice>
                  <abbr>  rec'd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice>  these letters I had written to you, a letter in which I declined your proposition, but made <emph>you one</emph> To this letter I have <choice>
                  <abbr>rec'd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> no answer,  your two letters above spoken of were not answered  because of my having shortly before their arrival written to you,  Having come to the conclusion, that my letter probably miscarried from the fact, there was very high waters about the time it started, I feel that it is due to you that I should again write to you, and inform you what my proposition was, I was not certain as to the precise number of  acres of land that I own<del type="overstrike">ed</del> in <name type="place">Giles</name>, But suppose there is  about four hundred and eighty acres, My proposition was to sell you the whole tract <unclear>Be</unclear> the sum   <choice>
                  <orig>mor</orig>
                  <reg>more</reg>
               </choice> or less  than Four hundred and Eighty acres for Five Thousand Dollars two thousand five hundred payable on the<date when="--06-01"> first of June</date>, the other half on the<date when="--03-01"> first of March</date>next, provided however that you should comply with the contract made by my agent with the <choice>
                  <orig>Tennants</orig>
                  <reg>Tenants</reg>
               </choice> in possession and with the persons that had leased my land, also do Justice by a man by the name of <name type="person">Rainey</name>who <pb n="2" facs="sl093b.small.jpg"/> had made an improvement on my land without any special contract upon the doing of which I proposed to Convey my entire interest in the<name type="place">Giles</name> land with a Warranty of the title, and that my Wife would give me, I also suggested that if it was not convenient to pay twenty five hundred Dollars  on the <date when="--06-01">first of June</date>, two thousand  dollars would do, and the balance in the spring.</p>
            <p>  In your letter last <choice>
                  <abbr>rc'd</abbr>
                  <expan>recieved</expan>
               </choice> you ask if you was to  fail as to payment of a part of the money at the time stipulated if I would   extend indulgence  upon the payment of interest, upon this subject I  presume if you knew me you would have  no fears.  The honest energetic man who is trying to pay his debts can <choice>
                  <orig>allways</orig>
                  <reg>always</reg>
               </choice> get any reasonable indulgence at my hands  I seldom sue any person and hope I will not treat you worse than others. It is true if I trade with you, I may need part of the money for I may vest some in  land near me, Hence I say  to you if we trade I wish to make a trade by which we can both live &amp; prosper. I will therefore   expect you to pay me the price for my land, yet if it is not convenient for you to pay at the times stipulated you may expect any reasonable indulgence at my hands, your interest would be as good as any other mans. I of course will expect an early answer from you, <pb n="3" facs="sl093c.small.jpg"/> If    we do not trade I wish to improve this land for some of my family to live on, will you please give me your advice as to the propriety of having  timber deadened  what it will cost per acre, and when it ought to be done <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c &amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera, et cetera</expan>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Yours Very Respectfully </salute>
               <signed>
                  <emph>
                     <name type="person">A. W. Taylor</name>
                  </emph>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl093d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top left hand corner" rend="different hand, ink">
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Elizabethton <choice>
                              <abbr>Tn</abbr>
                              <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </name>
                        <date when="--04-13"> April 13</date>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
               <add place="top right corner">10</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Tho</abbr>
                           <expan>Thomas</expan>
                        </choice> E Abernathey <choice>
                           <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                           <expan>Esquire</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Elkton</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Giles County</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left of address">mail }</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
