<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl126">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 10 April [18]48, Shelbyville, [TN] [to] Mrs. A[nn] J[ane] Bell, Charlotte, Tenn[essee] / Theodore A. Bell     : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Bell, Theodore A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl126</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51106157</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 10 April [18]48 Shelbyville, [TN] [to] Mrs. A[nn] J[ane] Bell, Charlotte, Tenn[essee] / Theodore A. Bell</title>
               <author>Theodore, A. Bell</author>
               <date when="1848-04-10">April 10, 1848</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Theodore Bell to his mother Jane Bell dated April 10, 1848. He writes that he would be willing to take up a profession, but that he is unable. He lets Jane know that despite the rumors, he is not married. He informs her that he is still poor, with no hope yet of improving his situation.  He reports of cholera in Nashville and Murfreesboro. He also writes about a fire that almost destroyed the business district.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">B:1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">F:15</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl126</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Cholera</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Bell, Theodore A.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl126a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Shelbyville</name>
                     <date when="1848-04-10">April 10th / 48</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I could not think what was the <choice>
                  <orig>couse</orig>
                  <reg>cause</reg>
               </choice> of your delay in writing to me, but you will think I have no doubt that I ought to be the last one to complain. Since I last wrote to you I have collected very little that is new or would be interesting to you. If  I could express my ideas as prettily as I would wish I would try to comply with your request — after reading a work then is many parts of it may strike me as sublime or beautiful yet I lack words to express my ideas as they ought to be — this prevents me from making an effort. I do not for one moment question the sincerity of your motives &amp; would cheerfully do any thing to gratify you <del type="overstrike">that</del> if I felt competent to do ⁁ <add place="linear">so</add> even to commence the profession of law though arduous as it is — <pb n="2" facs="sl126b.small.jpg"/> I am sure if I was able or felt that I could accomplish any profession I would have been willing to have attempted it, you know that my thirst for more than a mere pittance would be a very great inducement aside from any other <del type="overstrike">if nothing</del> else It is true I ought to be very thankful that I have health &amp; have been spared thus far without mourning over my condition;  <choice>
                  <orig>their</orig>
                  <reg>there</reg>
               </choice> are many whose situation is much more deplorable than mine. from this thought &amp; the mercies bestowed upon us every day that we live;  we ought to be contented in whatever situation we may be placed. I was some what surprised to hear that the folks of <name type="place">Montgomery</name> had me married. I did not think that you would be troubled at all for I am sure if   <del type="overstrike">I</del> such had have been the case you certainly would have Known something about it. I would <choice>
                  <orig>neve</orig>
                  <reg>never</reg>
               </choice> ⁁ <add place="supralinear">have</add> concealed this from you if <choice>
                  <orig>ther</orig>
                  <reg>there</reg>
               </choice> had been any thing of it —: as you remarked if my purse was large enough I dont Know but what their would be some danger, but the prospect of an enlargement of my purse is so gloomy that I dont think you need be alarmed yet a while. The only thing I regret is that I have all necessary preparations yet to make. It has been reported that the Cholera is in <name type="place">Nashville</name> &amp; <pb n="3" facs="sl126c.small.jpg"/> has been for sometime it is nearer than that at least reported to be in <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Murfreesborough</orig>
                     <reg>Murfreesboro</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> which is 25 miles from this. The panic has in a great degree worn off the citizens of this place: I have me doubt that if the cholera would make its <choice>
                  <orig>apperance</orig>
                  <reg>appearance</reg>
               </choice> here that they would all flee to the country for refuge — &amp; desert the place entirely as they done in <emph>38</emph> or when it visited them before</p>
            <p>A few nights since we <del type="overstrike">had</del> were aroused from sleep by the cry of fire a <choice>
                  <orig>fram</orig>
                  <reg>farm</reg>
               </choice> house <del type="overstrike">was</del> used for a grocery which stood near the business side of the <choice>
                  <orig>squre</orig>
                  <reg>square</reg>
               </choice> had taken fire from negligence: the night was storm<gap agent="damage"/> the wind blew very hard and all the <gap agent="damage"/>orce on our side took fire. I never saw such a dismal sight. Their was no person that saw the fire but <add place="supralinear">what</add> give up every thing as lost, but by the exertions of the young men principally, the buildings were all saved except the grocery — that we dont miss much. The damage from fire was about twelve hundred dollars. a great <del type="overstrike">deal</del> many goods was stolen &amp; abused very much by <choice>
                  <orig>moveing</orig>
                  <reg>moving</reg>
               </choice> them out of the stores — No person was injured though their was some very narrow escapes from powder — they were so much excited that several Kegs of powder were scattered about every where &amp; the air filled with fire — but all escaped without harm to any person</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Theodore A Bell</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl126d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mrs. <choice>
                           <abbr>A. J.</abbr>
                           <expan>Ann Jane</expan>
                        </choice> Bell</name> .</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Charlotte</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address">Answered May 18<gap agent="damage"/>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
