<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl767">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> [Letter] 1825 Jun. 6, Murfreesboro, Tennessee [to] George M. Troup, Millidgeville, Georgia / W[illia]m Carroll : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Carroll, William</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl767</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1825 Jun. 6, Murfreesboro, Tennessee [to] George M. Troup, Millidgeville, Georgia / W[illia]m Carroll</title>
               <author>Carroll, William</author>
               <date when="1825-06-06">June 6, 1825</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Governor William Carroll to George M. Troup, dated June 6, 1825. Troup is governor of Georgia. The Tennessee legislature has proposed that a canal be built to connect the Hiwassee River to the Coosa River, and also for one to bypass the muscle shoals. Carroll writes Troup for information about undertaking such a project and to secure Georgia's cooperation.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor William Carroll Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl767</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Georgia</term>
               <term>Alabama</term>
               <term>Canals</term>
               <term>Law and legislation</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Carroll, William, 1788-1844</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl767a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <add>(A Copy)</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Executive office <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Murfreesboro</name>
                     <date>June 6 1825</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I am directed by an act of the legislature of this state passed at their session of 1823, "to commence a written correspondence with the government of the state of <name>Alabama</name> and <name>Georgia</name> on the subject of connecting the waters of <name>Hiwassee</name> with the waters of <name>Coosa</name> by means of a canal, as well as the practicability of a canal around the <name>muscle shoals</name> in the Tennessee and through what is called the Tennessee valley on the south side of said river."</p>
            <p>The object to which our legislature expected that the attention of Georgia would be most particularly drawn, was doubtless that of a canal from Hiwassee to Coosa___ allow me therefore to request, that you will be pleased to communicate any information you may have on the following points</p>
            <p>Is it probable that Georgia would <choice>
                  <orig>co-operate</orig>
                  <reg>cooperate</reg>
               </choice> with Tennessee in making the canal spoken?</p>
            <p>Have you any correct information of the probable expense of <del type="overstrike">making</del> completing a canal from Hiwassee to Coosa?</p>
            <p>Have you any knowledge of the ground through which a canal would have to be cut, the quantity of water that may be commanded with convenience and the practicability of the plan? Do you know of a skillful engineer who could be procured to make the necessary examining of the ground? Is it likely that <pb n="2" facs="sl767b.small.jpg"/> Georgia would take any interest in the canal around the muscle shoals, or would give her aid in the enterprize?</p>
            <p>Upon the foregoing points as well as others touching the matter, I shall be happy to hear from you as early as convenient; it being important that the subjects with all its lights should be laid before our Legislature at its fall session.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Receive assurances of the respect <lb/> with which I have the honor to be, <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>yr obt servt</abbr>
                     <expan>your obedient servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Wm Carroll</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>His Excellency</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>George M Troup</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Governor of Georgia</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Milledgeville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Georgia___</addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl767c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>To Governor Troupe</add>
               <add>Gov <unclear>Carroll</unclear>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
