<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm011">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Drawing of the mid-18th century Cherokee village of Chota] /
			 [by Gerald F. Schroedl] : a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Schroedl, Gerald F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Catherine Michelle Love</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Tara Hottenstein</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. 3k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>mm011</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 45076445</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Museum, University of
				Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Drawing of the mid-18th century Cherokee village of Chota] /
				[by Gerald F. Schroedl]</title>
               <author>Schroedl, Gerald F.</author>
               <date/>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This drawing depicts the layout of Chota or
				Echota, an 18th century Overhill Cherokee village. It shows a central village
				plaza with both a circular winter council house and rectangular summer council
				house, which were used for public, social, and political events. Shown also are
				domestic dwellings with the same set-up, a circular winter house alongside a
				rectangular summerhouse. Also drawn are areas of dense refuse-filled pits.
				Archeological studies by the University of Tennessee from 1969 -1974 indicate
				that in the mid -1700's Chota had a population of around 300-500. There were
				approximately 60 domestic houses surrounding the village plaza that extended
				along the river for about a mile. Chota was recognized by Europeans as well as
				other Indians for its powerful social and economic influence and was regarded
				as the capital of the Cherokee nation. The excavations were conducted under
				contract with the National Park Service and the Tennessee Valley Authority
				(TVA). Principal investigator, Alfred K. Guthe. Field Directors, J. Worth
				Greene, Duane H. King, and Gerald F. Schroedl</note>
               <note type="collection">Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note type="document">mm011</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Architectural drawing</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</term>
               <term>Salvage archaeology</term>
               <term>Historic sites</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Chota Site (Tenn.)</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n78090514"
                        role="Artist http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/art">Schroedl, Gerald F.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mm011.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Plan of Chota, mid 18th century Cherokee village, shows
				  townhouse, domestic dwellings, village plaza, and areas of dense refuse-filled
				  pits, based on archaeological excavations by University of Tennessee 1969-1974.
				  Drawing by Gerald F. Schroedl. This information was provided by the Frank H.
				  McClung Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
