<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl122">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1837, Dec 1, Clover Dale, TN [to] Mrs. Ann Jane Bell, Oil Creek, Venango Co., PA / Sarah B. Bell   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Bell, Sarah B.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl122</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50590815</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1837, Dec 1, Clover Dale, TN [to] Mrs. Ann Jane Bell, Oil Creek, Venango Co., PA / Sarah B. Bell   </title>
               <author>Bell, Sarah B.</author>
               <date when="1837-12-01">December 1, 1837</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Sarah Bell to her sister Mrs. Ann Jane Bell, dated Dec. 1, 1837. Sarah describes the reactions of family and friends to the news of Anne Jane's recent and unexpected marriage. She also writes that the Cumberland Presbyterians have formed a church in Charlotte, and she comments on who has converted or  professed religion. She thanks Jane for the many presents the family has just received from her. Sarah further writes a bit about the farm and the neighbors.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl122</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Marriage</term>
               <term>Religious facilities</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Bell, Sarah</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl122a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Clover Dale</name>. <date when="1837-12-01">Dec 1st 1837</date>.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Sister</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We were all very much surprised two weeks since on receiving a letter from brother <choice>
                  <orig>anouncing</orig>
                  <reg>announcing</reg>
               </choice> your marriage, your last letter to my Father gave us to hope you would soon be a member of our family again. Little did I think when we parted you would take a step, that would <choice>
                  <orig>seperate</orig>
                  <reg>separate</reg>
               </choice> us so far, yet I cannot bear the idea we are <choice>
                  <orig>seperated</orig>
                  <reg>separated</reg>
               </choice> for ever, but hope you will yet visit<name type="place">Clover Dale</name>. It is impossible to describe the astonishment it created in <name type="place">Charlotte</name> and the <choice>
                  <orig>neighbourhood</orig>
                  <reg>neighborhood</reg>
               </choice>. <name type="person">Margaret</name> and I attended a two days meeting in Charlotte this week, they had heard of it the week before but did not believe it, the first question was is your sister Jane married, <name type="person">Mr. <unclear>Varies</unclear>
               </name> says one consolation, you have not changed your name, if he had known <name type="person">Mr. Bell</name> was to be your husband, he would have noticed him more particularly. <name type="person">Mr. <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm.</abbr>
                     <expan>William</expan>
                  </choice> Guthrie</name> laugh ⁁<add place="supralinear">ed</add>  when he heard it, and said he <choice>
                  <orig>allways</orig>
                  <reg>always</reg>
               </choice> thought you would get married he had understood you lived at home to educate your sisters and that was accomplished you done right. <name type="person">Mary Caldwell</name> says she <add place="supralinear">never</add> knows the reason why you could not write to her, she will excuse <add place="supralinear">you</add> and is going to write to you. All your acquaintances and friends send love and congratulations to you with out measure. <name type="person">Mrs. Collier</name> sends her love to you and says the book you sent her was the first thing that <pb n="2" facs="sl122b.small.jpg"/> ever made <name type="person">
                  <add place="supralinear">Mr.</add> Colier</name> think seriously of religion, of which he is now a sincere seeker. <name type="person">Major Bell</name> is still quite anxious to obtain religion  him and <name type="person">Eveline</name> speak of going on to see you in a year or so. The <name type="place">Cumberland</name> Presbyterians formed a church in Charlotte last week consisting of 40 members, there were three elders ordained, <name type="person">Christopher Dickson</name> was one of them, There is still a warm interest expressed among the people on the subject of religion, and a great many converts since I wrote you, <name type="person">Miss Sally Walker</name> has professed religion.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Ellennora</name> is now in <name type="place">Nashville</name>, her Father intends living there so I expect we will not see her often, she wished to stay with us till after <choice>
                  <orig>Christmass</orig>
                  <reg>Christmas</reg>
               </choice> but her Father would not consent. <name type="person">Amanda Napier</name> was married last week to <name type="person">Mr. Lee</name>, there were none <choice>
                  <orig>presant</orig>
                  <reg>present</reg>
               </choice> except the attendants who were<name type="person"> Elizabeth Bell</name>, <name type="person">James Gould</name>, Ellennora and <name type="person">Mr. B Collier</name>. We did not receive our box till this week every thing pleases us very much, you may know there is a change wrought in Margaret when she thinks the  <choice>
                  <orig>scarfs to</orig>
                  <reg>scarves too</reg>
               </choice> fine for our present circumstances.</p>
            <p>Mother says her braid was quite an unexpected presant she is very much pleased with the book you sent her.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Mrs. Davis</name> is very much pleased with the Souvenir you sent her, and the beautiful slip of paper that was in it with her name on it, as she expressed it, <name type="person">Orvill Caldwell</name> is quite anxious to see you since he professed religion, he says you are as well acquainted with his disposition as any other person, he has one favor to ask of you, which he wishes ⁁ <add place="supralinear">you</add> to grant, that is to send him a book that you think will suit him. <pb n="3" facs="sl122c.small.jpg"/> Wm. would have <choice>
                  <orig>writen</orig>
                  <reg>written</reg>
               </choice> to you before this, but has been so much <choice>
                  <orig>ingaged</orig>
                  <reg>engaged</reg>
               </choice> in the corn <choice>
                  <orig>buisiness</orig>
                  <reg>business</reg>
               </choice> this fall he has not thought of any thing but corn, with the help of  <name type="person">Mr. Young</name> 4 months he made 280 <unclear>lbs</unclear> which he thinks will bring him in some money next Spring. <name type="person">Mr. Cunningham</name> will leave us some time this winter, we do not know yet who will be our next <choice>
                  <orig>neighbour</orig>
                  <reg>neighbor</reg>
               </choice> I am fearful we never will get as good a one. <name type="person">Mr. Scot</name> is now clerk at the furnace below us, he has been up several times to see us he is as full of flattery as ever. We have the same circuit Preachers we had last year one of them, <name type="person">Mr. Marshal</name> was married last week to a sister of <name type="person">John L. Smith</name> whom you have heard Preach. Presbytery will hold in Charlotte next spring. Several of your friends wish you had been here three or four months past, to witness the warm excitement there is on the subject of religion a great many of the old Presbyerians now believe strongly in camp meetings, religion is now almost the only subject of conversation. <name type="person">Mrs. Adkinson</name>
               <name type="person">
                  <unclear>Arrabellar</unclear> West</name> that was died last week of a lingering consumption. I hoped you would have written to us before this, but as you did not I thought I would write you a few lines, which you must excuse. Tell cousin <name type="person">Samuel</name> we hope he has not <choice>
                  <orig>forgoten</orig>
                  <reg>forgotten</reg>
               </choice> us but will now visit us, we will <choice>
                  <orig>promis</orig>
                  <reg>promise</reg>
               </choice> ⁁ <add place="supralinear">to</add> do all that lays in our power to render your visit agreeable. you now  have some thing else to think about, so you will not be offended if I do not   name Wm. he will write you soon. They all join me in love to you and cousin <choice>
                  <abbr>S.</abbr>
                  <expan>Samuel</expan>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Ever your affectionate sister</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Sarah B. Bell.</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl122d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top, right of address">25</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Charlotte <choice>
                        <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1837-12-08">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Decr</abbr>
                           <expan>December</expan>
                        </choice> 8th 1837</date>
                     <add place="right of return address">}</add>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mrs. Ann Jane Bell</name>.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Oil Creek Venango County</name>.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Cornplanter</name> Post Office.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Pen.</abbr>
                           <expan>Pennsylvania</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
