<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl374">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1850 Jan. 14, Hendersonville Ten[nessee] [to] A[ndrew] J[ackson] Donelson, Fort Larimie, Oregon Route / Dan[ei]l S. Donelson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Donelson, Daniel S.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl374</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1850 Jan. 14, Hendersonville Ten[nessee] [to] A[ndrew] J[ackson] Donelson, Fort Larimie, Oregon Route / Dan[ei]l S. Donelson</title>
               <author>Donelson, Daniel S.</author>
               <date when="1850-01-14">January 14, 1850</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to Lieutenant Andrew Jackson Donelson, son of Andrew Jackson Donelson. It is from his uncle   Daniel S. Donelson, dated January 14, 1850. Daniel writes that Andrew's father has arrived home safely from a trip. Daniel informs Andrew that the family heard rumors that he had been killed by Indians, and were relieved to find it not true. Daniel hopes that Andrew will be allowed home on furlough soon.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bettie M. Donelson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">III-E-2-3, b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl374</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Donelson, Andrew Jackson 1799-1871</term>
               <term>Financial, personal</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Donelson, Daniel S.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl374a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Hendersonville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Janry</abbr>
                           <expan>January</expan>
                        </choice> 14th 1850</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Jackson</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Inclosed you have a letter from your Father, which he sent from <name>South hampton</name>, in one inclosed to me___ I would have forwarded this sooner, had I known the address,, your Father accompanied by all the family reached <name>Nashville</name> on thursday last the 10th, all in fine health except had cold from exposure in Travelling. It gives me pleasure to say that he has means with him, together with proceeds of cotton crop to relieve pressing debts, I hope sincerely that by economical living he will yet <add>be able</add> to get along without a sale of much if any property, it is my advice, however to square off even though it should require a sale of some portion of his property,  such as can be best spared, and <pb n="2" facs="sl374b.small.jpg"/> and have it in his <unclear>power</unclear> to say I am a freeman.</p>
            <p>We were filled with apprehension about your fate, based upon a report going the rounds of the <choice>
                  <abbr>N.</abbr>
                  <expan>Nashville</expan>
               </choice>
               <choice>
                  <orig>pappers</orig>
                  <reg>papers</reg>
               </choice> that you had been murdered by the Indians, in this state of uncertainty I addressed a letter to the <unclear>Add,, Genrl</unclear> to know the truth in the case, in his answer he stated that he presumed the report <unclear>came</unclear> from the fact of your having communicated the murder of two mail carriers by the Indians on the oregon route- I need not say that  we were rejoiced on <choice>
                  <orig>recieving</orig>
                  <reg>receiving</reg>
               </choice> this explanation.</p>
            <p> Some changes have taken place since you left, you have been advised of the manner and death of mary D_ an unfortunate affair Report says that <name>John Donelson</name> is courting miss <name>Wila Harding</name>. The times would seem to be improving, Lands, Negroes, and almost every <unclear>species</unclear> of property rising in value <pb n="3" facs="sl374c.small.jpg"/> owing to the rise in Cotton, and the great increase in gold from <name>California</name> which if it should continue will have the  <unclear>fleet to unsittle</unclear> prices throughout the world.</p>
            <p>I hope in the spring you  will be permitted by the Department, to have a more desirable station, and at the same time be permitted to pay us a visit on a furlough of some months. I would <add>not</add> now advise you to resign unless you had a positive certainty  of doing something <gap/> which your prospects in life would be greatly advanced.</p>
            <p>Our relatives are all well as far as I am <unclear>devised</unclear> __ my family desires to be remembered to you in most affectionate terms.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am yours affectionately</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Danl</abbr>
                        <expan>Daniel</expan>
                     </choice> S. Donelson</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P.S</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> since you left my health has been <add>and</add> is now bad owing to Cholera. <choice>
                     <abbr>DS. D</abbr>
                     <expan>Daniel S. Donelson</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl374d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Hendersonville <choice>
                        <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice> 10</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Jay</abbr>
                        <expan>January</expan>
                     </choice> 14</addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Lieut. A. J.</abbr>
                           <expan>Lieutenent Andrew Jackson</expan>
                        </choice> Donelson</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Fort <choice>
                           <orig>Larimie</orig>
                           <reg>Laramie</reg>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Oregon Route</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Danl S. Donelson <lb/>1850</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
