<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl593">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1846 Jun. 30, Dresden, Tennessee [to]    Aaron Brown, Nashville, Tennessee / William Blakemore: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Blakemore, William</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl593</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1846 Jun. 30, Dresden, Tennessee [to]    Aaron Brown, Nashville, Tennessee / William Blakemore</title>
               <author>Blakemore, William</author>
               <date when="1846-06-30">June 30, 1846</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated June 30, 1846 from William Blakemore, the coroner of Weakley County, Tennessee,  to Governor Aaron V. Brown in Nashville.  In the letter, Blakemore describes a brutal murder committed by William Dunn, who has since fled the county, and he requests the  governors assistance in his apprehension.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Aaron V. Brown Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl593</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Crime &amp; Justice in American history</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Brown, Aaron V. (Aaron Venable), 1795-1859</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Blakemore, William</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl593a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Dresden <choice>
                        <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>30th June 1846</date>
               <salute>His Excellency Aaron V. Brown, <choice>
                     <abbr>Govr</abbr>
                     <expan>Governor</expan>
                  </choice>.Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>On the 24th <choice>
                  <abbr>inst</abbr>
                  <expan>instant</expan>
               </choice>, a most cruel and brutal murder was committed in this (<name>Weakley <choice>
                     <abbr>Co</abbr>
                     <expan>County</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>) by <name>William Dunn</name> on the body of <name>Benjamin M Travis</name>__ the particulars are briefly these__Dunn (in company with a third person) met Travis (aged about 20) in a neighborhood road, and in a very friendly manner requested Travis to drink with him, which the latter did__ Dunn again insisted  that Travis would take another drink, which the latter proceeded to do, when Dunn, immediately announced his interests on to whip Travis__ Travis had set a <unclear>gun</unclear> by the side of a tree, which he happened to have with him__ which Dunn seized and broke Travis' skull, and otherwise brutally mangled him__  Dunn then cut his throat__ and mounted his horse and fled.  These are the facts, as found at the inquest.  Previous malice was also proved.  the jury of inquest returned a verdict of murder__ Dunn has fled the county, and as the relatives of the deceased are poor; it is respectfully submitted whether  a <unclear>reward</unclear> should not be offered by your Excellency for Dunns, apprehension.</p>
            <p>Said William Dunn is about 28 years of age, 5 feet, 9 or 10 inches in height heavy built weighs about 175 pounds.  has a round face and a smiling countenance, light hair, gray or hazel eyes, swarthy complexion__ talks and laughs freely, and is very profane</p>
            <closer>Very Respectfully <signed>William B. Blakemore</signed> coroner of <name>Weakley County</name>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl593b.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <name>Dresden <choice>
                        <abbr>Te</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name> 29th June</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To His Excellency Aaron V Brown Govr. Nashville <choice>
                        <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>.</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
