<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tl045">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1798 July 4, [to] James Robertson, James Stuart,
			 Lochlen [i.e. Lachlan] McIntosh / John Sevier : a machine-readable
			 transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Sevier, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Holly Adams</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno>tl045</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 47832429</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, Tennessee. It may be used freely by individuals for
				research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability
				is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1798 July 4, [to] James Robertson, James Stuart,
				Lochlen [i.e. Lachlan] McIntosh / John Sevier : a machine-readable
				transcription of an image</title>
               <author>Sevier, John</author>
               <date when="1798-07-04">July 4, 1798</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This document is a letter of instructions
				written by the Governor of Tennessee, John Sevier (1796-1801,1803-1809) to
				state agents James Robertson, James Stuart, and Lachlan McIntosh. The letter is
				dated July 4, 1798. Sevier stated that he appointed the agents to represent the
				interests of the state of Tennessee on the issues of a treaty to be made
				between the United States and the Cherokee. Among the issues Sevier noted for
				the three men to pay close attention to were the Indian boundary lines and the
				state districts in close contact with those boundaries. Sevier also commanded
				the men to examine the grounds of the Cherokee, to question the
				constitutionality of Cherokee land claims whenever possible, and to try to get
				more roads, rivers, and ports in the possession of the state.</note>
               <note type="Collection"> Governor John Sevier Papers</note>
               <note type="Box">1</note>
               <note type="Folder">6</note>
               <note type="Document">tl045</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Treaties</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Government relations</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Land tenure</term>
               <term>Boundaries</term>
               <term>Indian agents</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr89016779"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Sevier, John, 1745-1815</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tl045a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Messrs 
				  <name type="person">James Robertson</name>, 
				  <name type="person">James Stuart </name>and 
				  <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <orig>Lochlen</orig>
                           <reg>Lochlan</reg>
                        </choice>
					 McIntosh</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Gentlemen</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Having appointed you as Agents on the part of this State, to attend
			 the <choice>
                  <orig>insuing</orig>
                  <reg>ensuing</reg>
               </choice> treaty now about to be held between the 
			 <name type="place">United States</name> and the 
			 <name type="person">Cherokee</name> indians.</p>
            <p>You will therefore please to repair to 
			 <name type="place">Tellico Blockhouse</name>, at which place you will
			 be on the 
			 <date when="---06">sixth</date> instant prepared to attend the
			 negotiations, at whatever point they may open.</p>
            <p>It will be impossible to instruct you in the minutia of those
			 interests, to which you are called to attend; as an outline, you will
			 understand the State to require as extensive an extension of the indian claim
			 North of the 
			 <name type="place">Tennessee</name>, as may be obtained.</p>
            <p>The communication of the 
			 <name type="place">Holston</name> and 
			 <name type="place">Clinch</name> with the 
			 <name type="place">Tennessee</name>, and the right bank of the last
			 river from our <choice>
                  <orig>south east</orig>
                  <reg>southeast</reg>
               </choice> boundary to its
			 confluence with the 
			 <name type="place">Clinch</name>, are points to which you will direct
			 your attention, as also to secure from future molestation the settlements so
			 far as they have progressed, on the northern and western borders of the State,
			 the connecting the districts of 
			 <name type="place">Mero</name> and 
			 <name type="person">Hamilton</name>, now separated by a space of
			 unextinguished hunting grounds of near eighty miles in <choice>
                  <orig>wedth</orig>
                  <reg>width</reg>
               </choice>, will be considered by you Gentlemen as an object of
			 great importance, as the inconveniencies resulting from the present state of
			 our Settlements must be obvious to every mind conversant with the geography of
			 the country, and is certainly too irksome to be continued when the facts are
			 fairly represented.</p>
            <p>Among your duties will be an examination of
			 <add place="bottom right">the</add>
               <pb n="2" facs="tl045b.small.jpg"/> the ground of the Cherokee
			 claim, either as derived from original rights, or founded on treaties, and if
			 on investigation you shall find such right settle into a mere temporary use,
			 antecedent to the 
			 <name type="place">Holston</name> treaty, it may perhaps be proper to
			 question the constitutionality of that measure, that prostrated the guaranteed
			 rights of the whole people of the State, and to show the act of Cession
			 operative on the government, prior to this treaty. In all appointments
			 however of this kind much must necessarily be left discretionary, and perhaps
			 there is no instance where that <choice>
                  <orig>disscretion</orig>
                  <reg>discretion</reg>
               </choice> must
			 be suffered to assume a wider range, than on the present occasion.
               </p>
            <p>Accept the assurances of my belief, that it cannot be better placed,
			 and will in no instance be used more to the advantage of the State you
			 represent. I trust it is unnecessary to remind you, that your duties,
			 and your objects will be so connected with the Commissioners on the part of the
			 
			 <name type="place">United States</name>; that you will yield
			 <choice>
                  <orig>every thing</orig>
                  <reg>everything</reg>
               </choice> short of the interest and dignity of
			 the State you represent to preserve yourselves well with them; please advise me
			 frequently of the features your negotiations assume.</p>
            <p>Roads opened from this State, to any of the adjacent ones, and to
			 settlements in various parts of our own State, will be of much utility and
			 convenience, and also to have the privilege of the unmolested navigation of all
			 rivers, and waters within the chartered bounds of the State, and particularly
			 to obtain where it may be necessary, suitable ports for deposit, and carrying
			 places from river to river, so as to facilitate, and make easy as possible the
			 importation and exportation of all the articles necessary for the commercial
			 intercourse of the State.</p>
            <p>You will please engage some suitable person to supply you with
			 necessary stores for your support, during your attendance at the treaty, and
			 for the discharge of the same I will grant a <add place="bottom right">warrant</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="tl045c.small.jpg"/> warrant or warrants on the
			 treasury for the necessary sum to be expended on that occasion, which is to be
			 understood, not to exceed in the whole expenditure relative to the objects of
			 your agency, one thousand dollars.
               </p>
            <p>Wishing you every success compatible with the interest of the
			 State.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have the honor to be respectfully <lb/> Your 
				<choice>
                     <abbr>Mo Obedt and Huml.</abbr>
                     <expan>Most Obedient and Humble</expan>
                  </choice>
				Servant
                  </salute>
               <lb/> / signed /; 
			 <signed>
                  <name type="person">John Sevier</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="bottom, left">
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Knoxville</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <date when="1798-07-04">4 July 1798</date>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="tl045d.small.jpg"/>
            <p> / Copy / <lb/> Letter of Instructions, from <lb/> the Governor, to
			 the State <lb/> Agents  
			 <date when="1798-07-04"> 4 July 1798</date>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
