<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl338">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1840 Oct. 20, Gallatin, T[ennessee] [to] Mr. Stephens or A. Fergusson, Carthage, T[ennessee] / J. R. A. Tarnking   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Tarnking, J. R. A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl338</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1840 Oct. 20, Gallatin, T[ennessee] [to] Mr. Stephens or A. Fergusson, Carthage, T[ennessee] / J. R. A. Tarnking</title>
               <author>Tarnking, J. R. A.</author>
               <date when="1840-10-20">October 20, 1840</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to Mr. Stephens or Adam Fergusson from J. R. A. Tarnking, dated October 20, 1840. Tarnking has enclosed another letter from Felix Robertson dated September 25, 1840. Robertson is concerned that the Federalist party [aka as the Whig Party] will give the Democratic Republicans a run for their money in the upcoming election. He accuses the Federalists of misconduct in regards to the election of 1939, and warns that they have been threatening to use force. Robertson instructs Fergusson to make tickets for each Democratic voter, in order to  reduce the chance of voter fraud. In Tarnking's letter, he reports that he has made tickets for Smith County.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> IV-G-1 b5</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl338</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Tarnking, J. R. A.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl338a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name>, <name>
                        <abbr>Ten.</abbr>
                     </name>, <date>Sept. 25, 1840</date>. }</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir: _</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>As the Presidential contest approaches its close, the importance of vigilant and united action on the part of the Democratic Republicans becomes more and more manifest. The Federalists' conscious that their existence as a party depends on the election of <name>General Harrison</name>, are resorting to all the means which talent and money can command to secure a majority of votes for him; and if their exertions are not counteracted by timely efforts on our part to guard the freedom and purity of the ballot box, they may be successful.</p>
            <p>Under these circumstances, we think it our duty to remind you of the necessity of watching the polls on the day of the election so as to prevent frauds. For this purpose, we recommend the appointment of a committee at each precinct in every county, whose duty shall be to have printed Tickets for the use of every Democratic Voter, containing the names of the Democratic Electors; and on whom should be enjoined the task of visiting as far as practicable every voter friendly to our cause, and of urging upon him the necessity of vindicating his principles at the ballot box.</p>
            <p>The outrages practised at the polls in <name>New Jersey</name>, at <name>Philadelphia</name>, and other portions of the Union, in the elections of the year <date>1839</date>, teach us what we are to expect when Federalists have control of the ballot box. Even force is already threatened by some of the prominent leaders of that party, under the hope, doubtless, that there are Democrats who may be deterred by such means from appearing at the polls.</p>
            <p>Let it be our pride to teach these myrmidons of the Money Power that it is impossible thus to stifle the voice of American Freemen. In the language of the immortal <name>Jefferson</name> let us teach the Federalists once more that corruption is as harmless now as it is was in his day when "Truth was free to combat errors of opinion."</p>
            <p>From a conviction that the present crisis calls for all our energies, our most talented and efficient Speakers will be engaged in visiting the various portions of the State until the day for voting arrives. We must therefore look to them for the employment of the proper means to keep up spirited discussion in their neighborhoods, and wherever they go in the various portions of the State; the effect of which will be to satisfy every Democrat that he will not do his duty to himself or his country unless he goes to the polls and there gives his vote boldly and fearlessly for the Electors pledged to the support of <name>Martin Van Buren</name>, the candidate of the Republican Party.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>Felix Robertson</name>
               </signed>
               <lb/> Chairman of the Corresponding Central Committee.</closer>
         </div>
         <pb n="2" facs="sl338b.small.jpg"/>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Gallatin</name>
                     <gap agent="damage"/>
                     <unclear/>
                     <date>20th 1840</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>
                  <unclear>Gent</unclear>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>On the other page you will see letter of Felix Robertson chairman <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>and etcetera</expan>
               </choice> the importance of the contents you will at once perceive</p>
            <p>I have made at <name>Dixons Springs</name> a deposit of 1000 tickets for the middle &amp; South part of <name>Smith County</name> take Some pains to have them <choice>
                  <orig>destributed</orig>
                  <reg>distributed</reg>
               </choice> if <choice>
                  <orig>moore</orig>
                  <reg>more</reg>
               </choice> is needed write there was also a great many documents Sent there which I hope you have received</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>yours &amp;c</salute>
            </closer>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>J R A Tanking</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl338c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Gallatin <choice>
                           <abbr>Tn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <date>Oct 21</date>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
               <add>Free<address>
                     <addrLine>J. R. A. Tanking <unclear>
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>PM</abbr>
                              <expan>Post Master</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </unclear>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Gallatin Tn</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Messrs</abbr>
                        <expan>Misters</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <unclear>N</unclear>
                     <name>Stephens</name> or</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <del type="overstrike">A Stephens</del>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>A</abbr>
                           <expan>Adam</expan>
                        </choice>
                        <choice>
                           <orig>Furgasan</orig>
                           <reg>Fergusson</reg>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Carthage</name> Tn</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
