<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl191">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1847 Oct., Knoxville [TN]  [to] Mary House, Nashville, Tennessee / Mary Broyles   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Broyles, Mary</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl191</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51196278</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1847 Oct., Knoxville [TN]  [to] Mary House, Nashville, Tennessee / Mary Broyles</title>
               <author>Broyles, Mary </author>
               <date when="1847-08">October 1847</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Mary Broyles to Mary House, dated October 1847. Broyles has been travelling, and has stopped in Knoxville for the day. She writes about the people she has been meeting. She mentions the health of her family members. Because the weather is good, she will not be going through Nashville, which is not agreeable to her. Broyles is afraid she may never get  the chance to see her Nashville friends again.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl191</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Description and travel</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Broyles, Mary</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl191a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Knoxville</name>
                     <date when="1847-10-06">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Oct</abbr>
                           <expan>October</expan>
                        </choice>
                        <unclear>6</unclear> th 1847</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear Friends</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I for the first time, realize the pleasure of writing to one who has long since <unclear>secured</unclear> the love and esteem of your sincere friend. I would have written from <name type="place">Greenville</name> but ⁁ <add place="supralinear">nearly</add> the whole of my time was occupied in visiting our friends</p>
            <p>Be assured it was not for want of inclination that I did not write but an opportunity. We were disappointed in leaving Greenville as soon as we designed in consequence of all the seats being occupied in the "vast coach" which accommodates the surprising number of persons "Two" This disappointment however was very agreeable. It was the means of procuring a much more comfortable conveyance to this place where we arrived on yesterday afternoon will take the Stage again this <choice>
                  <orig>evning</orig>
                  <reg>evening</reg>
               </choice>. Thank fortune ! we will be only one night in the 'dear' little thing before we get to Bon <unclear>Air</unclear> . Well really we have passed the time since we left home very pleasantly. On the evening we arrived ⁁ <add place="supralinear">at</add> Greenville I attended a party given by one <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Doct</abbr>
                     <expan>Doctor</expan>
                  </choice> Williams</name> "a very worthy gentleman" but remarkable for not having seen his feet for many years. which you will not think at all wonderful when I tell you that the famous picture of <name type="person">John Barleycorn</name> is an exact representation of his person and his lady (a woman of the highest excellence) is not inferior in size to her unfortunate husband but what is very astonishing to me is that these enormous personages are the parents of one of the nicest little fellows I have met with for some time <pb n="2" facs="sl191b.small.jpg"/> he is not at all handsome but very agreeable a fine musician plays splendidly on the Violin an pretty well on the Guitar!  Ask <name type="person">Miss Hudley</name> what she would think of such a gentleman. I could give her opinion but you will enjoy it much more from her. well his name is "Bill" but he is honored with the more  dignified appellation  of "Prince". — and is related to the <name type="person">Irvin</name>s of <name type="place">Nashville</name> is on his way to that city now will be here in the  stage this evening.</p>
            <p>Several Greenville gentlemen have gone to Nashville. two of whom are slight acquaintances of mine one <name type="person">
                  <unclear>Mr Bemple</unclear>
               </name> a lawyer of considerable repute very talented and rather good looking. the other that abominable <name type="person">Bob Campbell</name>who prevailed on me last summer to accept as a keepsake his miniature I know he is the greatest tease I ever saw though exceedingly polite yet disagreeably attentive. If you should see a gentleman walking about the Streets with a  <unclear>crutch</unclear> (he is very lame) and a white hat on you may Know it is 'Bob' they Say he is a very clever fellow and I believe he is but unfortunately he has a very amorous disposition and in all his love <unclear>scrapes</unclear> (which have been very numerous) he has never ! never ! had the consolation of  being "loved". Our latest news from home was not very pleasant Uncle Irvine is very ill with <unclear>conjestive fever</unclear> Aunt  has almost  recovered from the attack under which she was laboring when we left home and something that <unclear>surprises</unclear> me very much , is that I am now "Aunt Mary (how old maidish that sounds) Bell imprudently rode several miles in a <unclear>folding</unclear> carriage over very rough road which caused premature birth  though the "little 'ren" is doing very well they call it Cornelias' for one of my deceased Sisters We will not return through Nashville the weather being fine and the roades good  superceeds the necessity of so <unclear>doing</unclear>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl191c.small.jpg"/> but I had rather  much rather the <choice>
                  <orig>roades</orig>
                  <reg>roads</reg>
               </choice> were hard for they deny me the pleasure of seeing my  friends in Nashville which  privilege may never again be afforded. Yet I hope for better things!</p>
            <p>Uncle Sevier has also been very ill, since I should not be surprised if he does not visit <name type="place">Savannah</name> this fall though he designs leaving home for our town on the tenth if his <unclear>health</unclear> permits. You are very lonely now' in the absence of your Ma. Mrs Pope &amp; Jane are gone too. I wrote to Jane while in Greenville but learned through <name type="person">Miss Hudley </name>that she was about leaving the city. therefore did not send my letter. I should like to be with you now' very much indeed have a great many things to talk about a great many questions to ask and some secrets to tell you. I heard from your Cousin<name type="person"> Sally Hamilton</name> the <unclear>morning</unclear> we left Greenville cousin <unclear>Mary Jones</unclear> received a letter from her containing the news of the death of her Uncle Martin, the family was well and Sally particularly well I think she is to be married soon. I have not had the pleasure of seeing any of your relations in East Tennessee, though I have heard from them frequently. Father's health continues good. he <unclear>desires</unclear> his compliments to you '&amp; the captain' <unclear>also</unclear> to <name type="person">Mrs Hamilton</name> and cousin Joe. Present the same for me. My love to your Ma. Mrs P. and Jane also to Miss Hudley. tell her she may expect a letter from me as soon as I get home. I hope you will write soon and direct to Savannah. I shall always be happy to hear from you.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Yours Sincerely</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Mary Broyles</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl191d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mrs <name type="person">Mary House</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
