<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0323">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> [Deposition of Margaret Carmichal] 1838 Dec. 31, Roane County, Tennessee : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0323</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>  [Deposition of Margaret Carmichal] 1838 Dec. 31, Roane County, Tennessee </title>
               <date when="1838-12-31"> 
			 December 31, 1838</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a deposition given by Margaret Carmichal on December 31, 1838. Her deposition concerns The Pathkiller, a Cherokee Indian who was removed from his land on the Tennessee River. The Pathkiller made several attempts in the court system to regain his land to no avail.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> pa0323</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Legal documents</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Land tenure</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0323a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>State of <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Roane County</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>Personally appeared before me <name>John Blair</name> on acting Justice of the Peace for <choice>
                  <abbr>sd</abbr>
                  <expan>said</expan>
               </choice> County <name>Margaret Carmichal</name> with whom I am personally acquainted &amp; she is a respectable woman_ she made oath that she was living on the north bank of <name>Tennessee River</name> opposite what is now called <name>Blairs Ferry</name>_ from 1809 up to this time and that in 1819, PathKiller took a Reservation on the south bank of sd river including the now Blairs ferry_ that in 1818 she Kept her cows over in sd land &amp; milked there. <name>PathKiller</name> was living there then &amp; <name>Cavas</name> his tenant then took possession of the place and 1819_ my husband  Carmichal got hold of a lease &amp; attempted to set it up &amp; Cavas or Blair sent for PathKiller &amp; he came there &amp; moved into the house with Cavas &amp; lived there a short time this was in the spring of 1819_ Carmichal quit the premises because his case said he was not have it if any Indian resided in it_ PathKiller after remaining with Cavas his Tenant for some time built a little <add>camp &amp; then</add>
               <choice>
                  <orig>cabbin</orig>
                  <reg>cabin</reg>
               </choice> on the reserve &amp; lived there &amp; continued there <choice>
                  <orig>untill </orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice>
               <unclear>removed by</unclear> the sheriff after the land sales- he had a little old  boat he ferried some his wife some &amp; <name>Nicholas</name> his son some- PathKiller like other Indians were frequently hunting- &amp; therefore I cannot say that PathKiller was on the place himself on the 1st day of January 1820- but believe he was I knew his family was there .&amp; his Tenant Cavas was there &amp; PathKillers home was there. my husband started a <unclear>drive</unclear>of hogs about Christmas 1819_ to <name>Georgia</name> PathKiller &amp; family was there then as I believe <pb n="2" facs="pa0323b.small.jpg"/> and I have no doubt Path &amp; family was there living on the 1st January 1820_ &amp; lived there &amp; during that spring untill removed by the sheriff__</p>
            <p>Madam was, it likely  a stranger passing would get acquainted with Path__</p>
            <p>Answer I think not he was retaining in his manners, &amp; could speak but say little English and as to travellers or strangers, I hardly think he would notice them__ he Path suing for his land &amp; Kept it in Court from 1821- till 1838___ when he lost the land at Kingston_  Path next to <name>Eldnidys</name> place 4 or 5 miles from the ferry in the year 1818 &amp; <choice>
                  <orig>staid </orig>
                  <reg>stayed</reg>
               </choice> awhile but returned __ again Path had a little place at the muddy branch, but the ferry place was his home &amp; he Kept his Tenant lease on it, &amp; remained on it as aforesaid and further this deponent saith not</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>Margaret <add>her x mark</add> Carmichal</name>
               </signed>
               <add>sworn to &amp; subscribed <lb/> before me this 31st of <lb/> December 1838-</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <orig>atest </orig>
                        <reg>attest</reg>
                     </choice>
                     <name>John Blair</name> acting</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Justice of the <choice>
                        <orig>pease</orig>
                        <reg>peace</reg>
                     </choice> for</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Roane County</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>60 <lb/> 4th <choice>
                     <abbr>comm</abbr>
                     <expan>Commission</expan>
                  </choice>. <lb/> Deposition of <lb/> Margaret Carmichal <lb/> PathKillers Case</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
