<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch001">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1829 Aug. 29, New Town, Cherokee Nation [to] Jno. [i.e., John] Ross / William Carroll: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Tennessee. Governor (1829-1835 : Carroll)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch001</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:44743253</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville,TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1829 Aug. 29, New Town, Cherokee Nation [to] Jno. [i.e., John] Ross / William Carroll</title>
               <author>Carroll, William, 1788-1844 [Tennessee. Governor (1829-1835 : Carroll)]</author>
               <date when="1829-08-29">August 29,1829</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter from William Carroll, Governor of Tennessee (1821-1827, 1829-1835), to John Ross, Principal Chief of the Cherokee Nation, dated August 29, 1829.  Carroll informs Ross that the President is very interested in the removal of the Cherokees to a territory west of the Mississippi River, specifically in light of recent decisions by certain states to extend their jurisdiction over the Cherokee Nation.  Carroll requests a meeting with the principal chiefs and impresses on them the importance of settling these matters peacefully.</note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville,TN</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true"> 2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch001</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Relocation</term>
               <term>Ross, John, 1790-1866</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr90023816"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Carroll, William, 1788-1844</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch001a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">New town</name>, <name>Cherokee Nation</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <date when="1829-08-29">August 29. 1829.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Dear Sir;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have come into the Nation by appointment of the <choice>
                  <abbr>Secy </abbr>
                  <expan>Secretary</expan>
               </choice> of War, to see you and other principal men on a subject interesting to the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> as well as the the <name type="place">United States</name>.</p>
            <p>It is scarcely necessary to say that the President of the <name type="place">U States</name> feels a deep interest in the removal of the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> West of the <name type="place"> 
                  <reg>River</reg> Mississippi</name>.  This you have been informed of by himself.  He believes that it will tend to the permanent advancement of the prosperity of the nation, and will prevent those unpleasant bickerings that are sure to arise from the extension of Jurisdiction by the adjoining States over that part of the nation within their respective chartered limits.   Without entering further into a train of reasoning upon this subject, permit me to say that I am directed to make the plain, simple proposition to you.  Will you agree to meet commissioners to be appointed by the President, at such time as might best suit the convenience of both parties, for the purpose of discussing the subject of the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> removing West of the <name type="place"> 
                  <reg>River</reg> Mississippi</name>.  You will then have the opportunity of hearing the propositions of the government.  If they are such as meet the approbation of the nation, you will, of course agree to them.  If<pb n="2" facs="ch001b.small.jpg"/>they are not you will reject them.  It is to me a source of much satisfaction to find that the best feelings exist every where towards the <name type="place">US</name> in the nation, and that the circulation of tales of hostile intentions on their part is wholly without foundation.  This pleasing intelligence I shall not fail to communicate immediately to the President.
               </p>
            <p>I trust that you will readily agree to meet commissioners for the purpose above mentioned.  It is granting nothing on your part, and will evince a disposition to keep up those friendly relations which have so long happily subsisted between the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> and the <name type="place">US</name> and which I trust will not be lessened by any circumstances to come.  Receive assurances of my best wishes for the future happiness of the nation over which you preside, and of the regard, with which I am most respectfully </p>
            <closer>Your friend <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                        <expan>William</expan>
                     </choice> Carroll</name>
               </signed>
               <lb/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mr. <choice>
                           <abbr>Jno</abbr>
                           <expan>John</expan>
                        </choice> Ross</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Principal Chief of the</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Cherokee Nation</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
