<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mc041">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1836 Dec. 21, Mouth of Poplar Creek [to] Charles F. Welcker / Catharine F. Welcker : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Welcker, Catharine F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">mc041</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1836 Dec. 21, Mouth of Poplar Creek [to] Charles F. Welcker / Catharine F. Welcker</title>
               <author>Welcker, Catharine F.</author>
               <date when="1836-12-21">December 21, 1836</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a correspondence amongst the Welcker family, a prominent landholding family of Roane County.  The letter, dated December 21, 1836, is from Catherine F. Welcker to her brother Charles F. Welcker.  Catherine gives her brother news of  the mill he owns, which was situated on the mouth of Poplar Creek.  She also relays business advice and proposals from their father, Henry Welcker, and talks of their brother Monroe going to school in Knoxville, most likely to East Tennessee College.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Welcker Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1836</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mc041</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Financial, Personal</term>
               <term>Tennessee, East</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Welcker, Catharine F.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mc041a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mouth of <name>Poplar Creek</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Dec.</abbr>
                           <expan>December</expan>
                        </choice> 21 1836</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>As I expect you are desirous of hearing about the <choice>
                  <orig>mil</orig>
                  <reg>mill</reg>
               </choice> I will relate a few particulars about it.  Father was up there a few weeks since and he says if you do not sell it soon there will be nothing to sell as it looks like a few more high waters would carry it away.  Cook does not saw any for people he did not even saw the stocks that Nail delivered <choice>
                  <orig>ther</orig>
                  <reg>there</reg>
               </choice>. he said that they were not worth sawing and so they laid there until the high water Came and carried the most of them away</p>
            <p>Cook has got the rent corn <choice>
                  <orig>halled</orig>
                  <reg>hauled</reg>
               </choice> he thinks that there is 300 bushels but Father says that there is not more than half so much if that. I suppose Henry told you that <name>Major Burris</name> and <name>Monroe</name> were buying hogs. Father will have about 3000 weight of bacon to sell and he says if you can give him 10 cents per pound that he will send it to you by some of the <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>botsmen</orig>
                     <reg>boatsmen</reg>
                  </choice>
               </unclear> the <choice>
                  <orig>meet</orig>
                  <reg>meat</reg>
               </choice> is small <pb n="2" facs="mc041b.small.jpg"/>  the hogs weighing from 100 to 150 each if you take the bacon you must write immediately and let Father know where it is to be delivered at and he is obliged to have the money early next fall so that he can make another trip to <name>kentucky</name>   as Monroe made a very bad <choice>
                  <orig>bargin</orig>
                  <reg>bargain</reg>
               </choice> this fall Mr Burris will take all of his bacon down the river early next <choice>
                  <orig>Febuary</orig>
                  <reg>February</reg>
               </choice> and Father says that he would advise you to come immediately and try to sell the mill and if you can not sell it to put it in better hands for Cook <choice>
                  <orig>dos</orig>
                  <reg>does</reg>
               </choice> nothing but live on the <unclear>tole</unclear> and if you are here when Burris starts you can probably have a better chance than at an other time of carrying the bacon down and indeed I know of no other way to do as Father is <choice>
                  <orig>harly</orig>
                  <reg>hardly</reg>
               </choice> able to manage his own business and he has no help  for Monroe is at school in <name>Knoxville</name> he started last Month and it is likely he will go <unclear>3</unclear> sessions we received a letter from Frederick a few days since he was well and at that time in <name>Asheville <choice>
                     <abbr>N.C.</abbr>
                     <expan>North Carolina</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> we also got one from Lewis last evening- he was in good health he says that he has <pb n="3" facs="mc041c.small.jpg"/> written to you and received no answer he wants you to write to him and let him know where to direct his letter so that you can get <choice>
                  <orig>then</orig>
                  <reg>them</reg>
               </choice> for he said that he expected that you had not got them or you <choice>
                  <orig>shurely</orig>
                  <reg>surely</reg>
               </choice> would have written to him.  we have not heard from Henry since he wrote to us while in <name>Taladego</name>.</p>
            <p>we intended to have sent this by <name>Mr Nail</name> but he has just sold his boat to <name>Mr Blain</name> a son in law to <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Gillespie</name> he gave $2 per foot and has just left here to go to the mill to get it Father again insists that you should come immediately.</p>
            <p>the family are all well and send <choice>
                  <orig>there</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice> love to you and please receive a large portion from your sister</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>Catharine F Welcker</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>to <name>Charles F Welcker</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
