<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl218">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1843 Mar. 13, Nashville [TN] [to] Mary House, Russellville, Kentucky / George House   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>House, George</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl218</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51217041</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1843 Mar. 13, Nashville [TN] [to] Mary House, Russellville, Kentucky / George House</title>
               <author>House, George </author>
               <date when="1843-03-13">March 13, 1843</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from George House to his wife Mary House, dated March 13, 1843. He is upset that she does not want to write to him more often. He writes that he will not go to Alabama as it would increase the distance between them. He writes about seeing the Great Comet of 1843. He mentions that astronomers have predicted another  comet will also be visible soon. Because the comet which became known as the Great Comet of 1843 was unknown and unexpected, he believes the Millerites will make something of it. Finally, he gives some local news.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl218</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Religios thought -- 19th century</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Comets</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">House, George W.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl218a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                     <date when="1843-03-13">March 13. 1843</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Wife</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have just received yours of 8th <choice>
                  <abbr>inst</abbr>
                  <expan>instant</expan>
               </choice> which should have reached me on Saturday last</p>
            <p>The reasons you advance for not writing are not good, — as applying to your husband — they are perfectly inadmissible for if they hold good as to a definite period of time they are <choice>
                  <orig>equaly</orig>
                  <reg>equally</reg>
               </choice> so why you should not write at all — You also Say "<unclear>That</unclear> I should prize your letters very highly" Certainly I should, and do or else why should I press the request that you should write to me at least Weekly — An hour once in a Week, is Certainly a  very small portion of time to devote to your husband, particularly when you have so much leisure — There is One <unclear>Maxim time</unclear> in life that which we esteem, love and prize the most, will Certainly share the greatest amount of attention — and on the other hand objects we Care Nothing ⁁ <add place="supralinear">for</add> are neglected — now if I admit my Mary's excuse for not Writing to me — I shall have to admit also (very much against my will, however) that she cares nothing for me — Do you see the <choice>
                  <orig>dilema</orig>
                  <reg>dilemma</reg>
               </choice> in which You place me — I cannot think the spell that bound me to thee; has lost its Witchery — <pb n="2" facs="sl218b.small.jpg"/> If so, Then words are not what they seem — nor professions of Woman tine — You are not very explicit in regard to the boarding business but have left it entirely to Me— then I shall do what I esteem (taking all things together) to be for our interest — I have no Idea of going to <name type="place">Alabama</name> — and if I had not without you and James — you are too far from me now and to increase the distance over a hundred miles, is what never entered into my brain —</p>
            <p>I am about paying <choice>
                  <orig>expences</orig>
                  <reg>expenses</reg>
               </choice> here — and Cannot do much until I see Bank which I hope will not be long first — There is no one to whom I would be willing to leave James with more <unclear>cheerfulness</unclear>
               <add place="supralinear">cheerfulness</add> than your Mother — but I cannot reconcile it to my feelings to do so — and so soon as the weather and roads will permit — I shall send over or Come for You both — Have you seen the Comet in the West — it has not been mentioned by any astronomer, and Consequently its appearance is a matter of much speculation — We have an account of one which is ti make its appearance in the East on the 16th of this month — but the stranger in the West we Know nothing of — the Millerites will make Capitol, no doubt out of it — <pb n="3" facs="sl218c.small.jpg"/> If You have not seen it before when you get this — after sundown take a look into the West and you Will see the longest Comet we have any Knowledge of — its tail is estimated to be, above one hundred and fifty-million of miles in length — <name type="person">Thos. L. Budd </name> has been set at liberty and is now, somewhere a free man again — <name type="person">Maria Davis</name> Was down One day last Week, to get Wedding apparel, for the Celebrating of hers and Packs Nuptials— and if she Can get ready will be married before her father leaves home for the <unclear>south</unclear> if not  she will Wait for his return — The Weather has been so bad, that I have not been to Church for Three Weeks — <name>Mr <unclear>Cruarbins</unclear>
               </name> Workshop opposite <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Doct.</abbr>
                     <expan>Doctor</expan>
                  </choice> Edgars</name> Was burnt down last night between 8 and 9 oclock — all of his lumber together with a Considerable quantity of ready made Work was entirely Consumed — It is supposed to be the Work of an incendiary — all Well — when I see Em, the children <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;C</abbr>
                  <expan>and etcetera</expan>
               </choice> I will make Your love — are You Anxious to return or not — say in your next — If You are <choice>
                  <orig>indiferent</orig>
                  <reg>indifferent</reg>
               </choice> about it — as the river is in good order I may as well cut out at Once as to Wait longer — <pb n="4" facs="sl218d.small.jpg"/> Make my love to Mother and all relatives — Kiss Jim for me and make my <unclear>respects</unclear> to all friends — I write in haste — <add place="in center of page, rotated">single<address>
                     <addrLine>Mrs <name type="person">Mary House</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Care if <name type="person">Mrs <choice>
                              <abbr>S.</abbr>
                              <expan>Sally</expan>
                           </choice> B. Hamilton</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Russellville</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Kentucky</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
               <add place="above address"> paid <unclear/> J. B. H.</add> Cast a strong thought upon me occasionally and remember me in your prayers —</p>
            <p>May You ever enjoy <unclear>peace</unclear> comfort and happiness — Without You I Can not —</p>
            <closer>
               <salute> yours forever</salute>
               <signed>George</signed>—</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
