<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl379">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1838 Aug. 8, St. Louis [to] Governor Newton Cannon, Tennessee / Edmund P. Gaines   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Gaines, Edmund P.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl379</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1838 Aug. 8, St. Louis [to] Governor Newton Cannon, Tennessee / Edmund P. Gaines   </title>
               <author>Gaines, Edmond P.</author>
               <date when="1838-08-08">August 8, 1838</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Edmond P. Gaines to Newton Cannon, Governor of Tennessee. Major General Gaines requests three to five thousand volunteers from Tennessee to help fight due to a possible threat by  Mexicans and Cherokee Indians.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Gaines Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">I-C-3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl379</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Claims against</term>
               <term>Gaines, Edmond Pendleton, 1777-1849 Correspondence. </term>
               <term>Frontier Patrols</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n88277194"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Gaines, Edmund Pendleton, 1777-1849</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl379a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Hd Qr</abbr>
                        <expan>Headquarters</expan>
                     </choice> Western Division</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>St. Louis</name>
                     <date>August 8th 1838</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I do myself tthe honor to transmit herewith for your information a copy of a letter which I have just now received from <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Lt.</abbr>
                     <expan>Lieutenent</expan>
                  </choice> Colonel  R. B. Mason</name> , 1st Dragoons commanding at <name>Fort Leavenworth</name>; reporting to me the well ascertained fact that the <name>Cherokee Indians</name> of the <name>Arkansas</name> have invited all the chiefs together with all <gap/> principle Braves of all the tribes (excepting the <name>osages</name> and <name>Kansas</name>) residing near our western frontier north of the <name>Red river</name> to meet them in council in the cherokee country on the <choice>
                  <orig>Illionois</orig>
                  <reg>Illinois</reg>
               </choice> river a few miles above the mouth of the Barren fork about the 11th of september next month.</p>
            <p>The object of the council   and the reason for excluding the osages and Kansas, are unknown; but the <choice>
                  <abbr>Lieut</abbr>
                  <expan>Lieutenent</expan>
               </choice> Colonel states that there is no doubt in his mind that the object of the council is to effect a union of the different tribes preparatory to striking a simultaneous blow upon the settlements of Arkansas and <name>missouri</name> from the Red River to the upper Mississippi.</p>
            <p>concuring as I do in this opinion &amp; being convinced that the cherokees of <name>Texas</name> and Arkansas have been instigated by the agents of <name>Mexico</name>, who have been endeavoring for more than two years past to organize a combination of cherokees with all the nations west of Arkansas and the state of Missouri a combination capable of bringing into action upon our frontier <pb n="2" facs="sl379b.small.jpg"/>  over twenty thousand mounted warriors ___ a force that under enterprizing leaders, would lay waste the whole line of their settlements from the mouth of the sabine to the falls of St Anthony, including the richest cotton growing section of america, on Red river with some of the most valluable sugar Districts of <name>Louisiana</name> if indeed the enemy is suffered to commence the work of destruction before our measures of protection  are matured. __ with these impressions I cannot but anticipate authority to concentrate upon the Arkansas frontier a sufficient force to enable me to check the incipient movements of the Indians. five thousand mounted Kentuckyans and <unclear>Tennesseans</unclear> added to our present Regular forces, among which is the 1st Regiment of Dragoons (the best I have ever seen) would enable me effectually to <unclear>thwart</unclear> the designs of the enemy and givve better protection to the frontier than five times that force would accomplish, after the concentration of <add>the</add> enemy &amp; his successful commencement in his savage work of destruction.</p>
            <p>I have therefore respectfully to request of your Excellency the promulgation of authority <pb n="3" facs="sl379c.small.jpg"/> for the formation of volunteer companies ___ to be organized and held ready to march by the first of september, or as soon thereafter as they shall receive orders ___ to serve the united states six months unless sooner discharged. Should the apprehended  combination of most of the different tribes of Indians invited take place, I shall need for the <choice>
                  <orig>defence</orig>
                  <reg>defense</reg>
               </choice> of the western  frontier from three thousand to five thousand men from your state. And I shall hold myself in honor and in duty bound to make every requisite provision for their health and comfort preparatory to meeting the enemy, ___ and above all to afford them every proper opportunity to sustain the chivalry of their state ___ and to take care of the sick &amp; wounded I am with very great respect.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your Excellency's most obedient <choice>
                     <abbr>st</abbr>
                     <expan>servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Edmund P. Gaines </name>
                  <lb/> major General <name>US</name> Army <lb/> commanding</signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>His Excellency</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Newton Cannon</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Governor of Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl379d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Genl.</abbr>
                        <expan>General</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>E. P.</abbr>
                        <expan>Edmond Pendleton</expan>
                     </choice> Gaines</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Western Indians</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
