<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl663">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1840 Dec. 1, Columbia [to] James K. Polk, Nashville, Tennessee / Gideon J. Pillow : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Pillow, Gideon J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl663</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1840 Dec. 1, Columbia [to] James K. Polk, Nashville, Tennessee / Gideon J. Pillow</title>
               <author> Pillow, Gideon J.</author>
               <date when="1840-12-01"> 
			 December 1, 1840</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Gideon J. Pillow to Governor James K. Polk, dated December 1, 1840. Pillow is President of the Board of Directors for the Columbia Central Turnpike Company. He is writing to inform Polk who the rest of the Directors are. Pillow also advises that they are ahead of schedule in the construction of the turnpike.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor James K. Polk Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl663</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Turnpike roads</term>
               <term>Business enterprises</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n89103775"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Pillow, Gideon Johnson, 1806-1878</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl663a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Columbia</name>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Decr</abbr>
                           <expan>December</expan>
                        </choice> 1st 1840</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To His Excellency</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>James K Polk</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>Yours of the 30th ultimo convey a commission for new director on behalf of the state in the Columbia Central Turnpike Company is received The Stockholders of the company have regularly elected Directors on their behalf annually since the organization of the company At the elections, (immediately preceding your election to the Executive of the state) I advised <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Gov</abbr>
                     <expan>Governor</expan>
                  </choice> Cannon</name>, that the private stockholders had re-elected the former board of Directors on their behalf_ This communication was made in order that he might appoint the state Directors, but he took no notice of my communication. <name>Hugh Kirkpatrick</name> has never met the Board of Directors and has informed me long since that he would not act__ So has <name>William Welch</name>_ though I am not advised that they have formerly resigned <name>Lewis P Speece</name>has been dead for 18 months I advised Gov Cannon of the Death of the Latter Gentleman death of the fact that the Two former would not act All the other State Directors have regularly attended the meeting of the Board</p>
            <p>The Directors on behalf of the stockholders elected this year are Gid J Pillow (<choice>
                  <abbr>Prest</abbr>
                  <expan>President</expan>
               </choice>) <pb n="2" facs="sl663b.small.jpg"/>
               <name>James Walker</name>, <name>Evan Young</name>
               <name>Lucus J Polk</name>
               <name>Granville A Pillen</name>
               <name>James B Pillen</name>
               <name>Will J Polk</name>
               <name>Mathew D Cooper</name> &amp; <name>James Booker</name>_</p>
            <p>The Two last named Gentlemen have resigned since a regular meeting of the Board and their places have not yet been filled by the election of others</p>
            <p>I am fully sensible of the requirements of the charter of our company_ In no instance have the stockholders failed promptly to comply with previsions</p>
            <p>We commenced receiving toll at 3 Gates on our road on yesterday morning &amp; will at the 4th  gate as soon as we can have the Tollhenge, gate <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>etcetera</expan>
               </choice> put up Its now nearly in state of readiness Though we have certified a completed but 16 miles of our road, we have 18 miles completed I mention this to show you the energy with which we are pushing the work. we confidently expect to have the whole road ready for the erection of gates in Two more years</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your Friend <lb/> &amp; <choice>
                     <abbr>obt sert</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Gid J Pillow</name>
               </signed>
               <add>Prest <choice>
                     <abbr>C. C. L Co</abbr>
                     <expan>Columbia Central Turnpike Company</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl663c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To His Excellency </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>James K Polk</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Nashville</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Gideon J. Pillow <lb/> Prest of the Colum <lb/> bia Central Turn <lb/> pike Company _ <lb/> giving list of names <lb/> of the <unclear>present</unclear>                           Direc <lb/> tors on the part of  <lb/> the stockholders and <lb/>of the death of one <lb/> of the State Directors_ <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Recd</abbr>
                     <expan>Received</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <date>Decr 3rd 1840</date>_<lb/> Nathaniel Willis _ appoin <lb/> ted a State Director <unclear>view</unclear>
                  <lb/> Lewis P Speece resign <lb/> ed  <date>Decr 4th 1840</date> (see <lb/> letter Book p. 125) ___</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
