<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl201">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1833 Dec. 23, Williamson County, Tn. [to] John Claybrooke / John S. Claybrooke   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Claybrooke, John S.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl201</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51197070</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1833 Dec. 23, Williamson County, Tn. [to] John Claybrooke / John S. Claybrooke</title>
               <author>Claybrooke, John S. </author>
               <date when="1833-12-23">December 23, 1833</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated December 23, 1833 to John Claybrooke of Virginia from his son John     S. Claybrooke in Tennessee. John S. writes about various business deals that he and his brother Thomas are involved in and announces his engagement to Mary A. Perkins.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection, IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl201</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Claybrooke, John S.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl201a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Williamson <choice>
                           <abbr>Cty. Tenn.</abbr>
                           <expan>County Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date when="1833-12-23">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Decb.</abbr>
                     <expan>December</expan>
                  </choice> 23d 1833</date>
               <salute>My Dear Father,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>It is with no small degree of pleasure that I take my pen to write you this epistle. It will contain many important facts, some of which are connected with my future happiness, prosperity <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>and et cetera</expan>
               </choice> in this life, but one  of which counties I have some land business to do, but it will not take me long to accomplish it. I shall remain with Thomas three days and will get him to accompany me for a few days, having some business in <name type="place">Haywood</name>, that will detain me that length of time. I shall get back to <name type="place">Nashville</name> by the 29th of January and start on the 29th for <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Va.</abbr>
                     <expan>Virginia</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>  I shall not ride my present riding horse to Va. but will ride a young bay horse, which I own and would like to exchange him with you for a good riding horse, when I get there. My horse is a very good horse, but he will be much fatigued going through the mud, therefore I would like to exchange him with you or brother for a fine horse. Please keep it in mind, for I shall not have time to rest my horse while there.</p>
            <p>I must inform you concerning a matter which I gave you a hint of last spring, and I believe asked your advice, but never received it, or any ⁁<add place="supralinear">en</add> couragement whatever, however I suppose, you reposed much confidence in me, and thought I ought to judge for myself concerning a matter, upon which so much of my prosperity and happiness in life depended, and from your silence, such was your opinion, at least taken by me for granted, that I am engaged to be married to <name type="person">Miss Mary A Perkins</name>, who is not beautiful, but very genteel in her appearance, very modest &amp; <pb n="2" facs="sl201b.small.jpg"/> reserved in her manner, (which is not a very usual <choice>
                  <orig>characteristick</orig>
                  <reg>characteristic</reg>
               </choice> of a <choice>
                  <orig>Tenneseean</orig>
                  <reg>Tennessean</reg>
               </choice>) &amp; of a very highly respectable family. Her father was originally, I think, from <name type="place">Buckingham County</name> in Virginia. It is needless for me to say anything in relation to his wealth, suffice it for the present, to say, that he is in very easy and independent circumstances, for I <unclear>hope</unclear> by industry and <unclear>economy </unclear> and with a little aid from yourself, such as a loan or otherwise, <unclear>we</unclear> shall be enabled to get along comfortably and agreeably through life.</p>
            <p>I would get married previous to my coming to Va and bring Mary with me, (as she says, she would take great pleasure in going with me to see you all) but we have thought it most <gap agent="damage"/> or at least I have, to defer our marriage until my return <gap agent="damage"/> would be a very serious undertaking for a lady in <gap/> disagreeable weather in winter to go cross the mountains <gap agent="damage"/> this State to Va. I even myself,  in fine health <gap agent="damage"/> the <choice>
                  <orig>vigour</orig>
                  <reg>vigor</reg>
               </choice> of youth, dread the cold breaking winds, that blow about the tops of the <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Alleghany</orig>
                     <reg>Allegheny</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> in the month of February and March , how much more then ought I to dread it if I had Mary along, and I am compelled to be back here by the 20th of March. </p>
            <p>We have been engaged about six weeks and I have never summed up fortitude enough, to ask <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>words unclear</unclear> permission, and though I am said to possess much firmness and stability and very fluent <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>unreadable</unclear> most subjects, yet this task is far more difficult than I anticipated, previous to my having ⁁<add place="supralinear">it</add> assigned to me to perform, however I think I will talk with him about it in a few days.</p>
            <p>Owing to the condition of my property here, it being real estate.  I wish to make an arrangement with you, so as  to advance the interest of my brother's &amp; sisters⁁<add place="supralinear">as well as myself</add> I will suggest the plan when I come to <pb n="3" facs="sl201c.small.jpg"/> Va. and if you think it practicable, you can adopt it. Thomas is well and is doing very well &amp; very industrious and saving. O, that I could be as economical I could ⁁<add place="supralinear">get</add> well off in a few years. My health is good I weigh 153lbs, fatter than I ever was in my life. My love to them all. Kiss Sally O. &amp; Jim</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your affectionate Son</salute>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">John S. Claybrooke</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mr. John Claybrooke</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="bottom of address page">
                  <note>
                     <p>Dear Brother, I wish you to have the money out of Bank in readiness for me at <name type="place">Brookville</name>, by the <date when="--02-10">10th of February</date> and do not wait until I arrive, for I expect or it is very probable I shall lay it out here before I leave Tennessee in <del type="overstrike">add</del> advantageous manner to us, therefore I say have it in readiness, unless you have already laid it out. I could make out without, but not easy as I never go in debt. <choice>
                           <abbr>JSC</abbr>
                           <expan>John S. Claybrooke</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </add>
               <add place="center of page, rotated">
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>via <name type="place">Washington City</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="person">John Claybrooke <choice>
                              <abbr>Esqr.</abbr>
                              <expan>Esquire</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Pottiesville</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Louisa County</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Virginia</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
