<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl089">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1846 June 16, New Orleans [to] Mrs. Ephraim H. Foster, Nashville, TN/   Robert C. Foster 3.   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Foster, Robert C., III</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>   Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl089</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50178391</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1846 June 16, New Orleans [to] Mrs. Ephraim H. Foster, Nashville, TN/   Robert C. Foster 3 </title>
               <author>Foster, Robert C., III</author>
               <date when="1846-06-16">June 16, 1846</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Robert C. Foster III, son of Tennessee Senator Ephraim Foster, to his mother, dated June 16, 1846. Foster writes from his  station in New Orleans, where he is the captain of a troop of Tennessee Volunteers during the Mexican-American War under the command of Colonel William Campbell. Foster reports that the soldiers are enjoying good health, though there has been one  death, that of a man named McAdams from Shelbyville. He also talks extensively about public parades in New Orleans and how the Tennessee Volunteers are thought of as  the finest troops to have passed through the city.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Foster Family</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">Correspondence Robert C. Foster</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl089</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Mexican War, 1846-1848</term>
               <term>United States</term>
               <term>Military life</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007072331"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Foster, Robert C., 1818-1871</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl089a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <add place="top of page">[Gift of <name type="person">Dr. A.     L. Crabb</name>]</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">New Orleans</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1846-07-16">June 16th 1846</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>This is the 7th day since our arrival here, and believe me it is the first <choice>
                  <orig>oppirtunity</orig>
                  <reg>opportunity</reg>
               </choice> that I have had of writing since that time — My constant engagements in the discharge of my duties, now that I belong to "Uncle Sam", which have so far been very laborious, has only give me time to <unclear>not</unclear> at night —  And now, My Dear Mother,  that I have seated myself for the purpose of writing you, I do not know where to commence, for I have so much to speak of, and so little time to do it in, that it leaves me in doubt  as to what I shall  communicate first.  Well, I am growing very sick of the "Crescent City"  — the weather is very warm, and   <del type="overstrike">our</del> quarters not by any means comfortable — We are in the  French part of the city, opposite  to the lower end of the shipping on the levee,  and are quartered in ⁁<add place="supralinear">an</add> old "lumber yard", about three miles from the <name type="place">St. Charles Exchange</name>— We are greatly annoyed at night,  with these nasty things called <choice>
                  <orig>musquitoes</orig>
                  <reg>mosquitoes</reg>
               </choice>, and without bars to protect ourselves from them constant and <gap agent="damage"/> attacks upon us, and were it not for these troublesome "customers" and  their friends the fleas, we would get along pretty well — All are anxious to leave and <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Campbell</name> has just informed me that we will get off   this <choice>
                  <orig>evning</orig>
                  <reg>evening</reg>
               </choice>,  if not then, most certainly tomorrow <choice>
                  <orig>evning</orig>
                  <reg>evening</reg>
               </choice> — There has been but little sickness amongst the troops — one death however, (the cause of  imprudence in drinking cold ice water) in <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Capt</abbr>
                     <expan>Captain</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <unclear>Fresser</unclear>
               </name>company he had but a few hours   after he was taken and    <unclear>un</unclear>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl089b.small.jpg"/>
               <choice>
                  <orig>buried</orig>
                  <reg>burried</reg>
               </choice> on Sunday <choice>
                  <orig>evning</orig>
                  <reg>evening</reg>
               </choice> with military honors — his name was <name type="person">McAdams</name> from near <name type="place">Shelbyville </name>and has a wife and three children — You will have seen before this the many compliments paid the <name type="place">Tennessee</name>Volunteers by the all the public <unclear>parades</unclear> in the city, and it is <choice>
                  <orig>conceeded</orig>
                  <reg>conceded</reg>
               </choice> on all hands that they are the finest troops that have yet passed here on the way to <name type="place">Texas</name>—<name type="person"> Harry</name>   heard all these things I began to grow proud and <unclear>look</unclear>  big and determined at once to  parade my company, the "flowers of the army" through some of the principal streets of the city — and from the time that we were upon parade  until we returned to the encampment, we were followed by    crowds of citizens — and there it was that I was a foot taller than even before  — The <unclear>"Harsmm Gamass"</unclear> "<name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Capt</abbr>
                     <expan>Captain</expan>
                  </choice> Foster </name>company of        <choice>
                  <abbr> Tenn.</abbr>
                  <expan>Tennesse</expan>
               </choice> Volunteers were noticed  in the papers of the next  day, and most <choice>
                  <orig>higly</orig>
                  <reg>highly</reg>
               </choice> complimented, as the finest and best  drilled company of Volunteers that ever paraded through the streets of <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N.O.</abbr>
                     <expan>New Orleans</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> There was <choice>
                  <orig>scarsly</orig>
                  <reg>scarcely</reg>
               </choice> a <unclear>man</unclear> of  standing   and <unclear>respectability?</unclear> that did not advance and give me his hand, at the same time crowding  me with compliments,— but I did not get <unclear/> and act the <unclear>part</unclear> buy so much <choice>
                  <orig>flater</orig>
                  <reg>flattery</reg>
               </choice> and know that I met it with all <unclear>becoming n?</unclear> —  I never enjoyed better health, and have not been the least sick since I left — The great hurry with which I am compelled to write, make it almost illegible — but my dear Mother know that situated as I am, <del type="overstrike">that</del> I have but little <pb n="3" facs="sl089c.small.jpg"/> time that I can call my own, and will most cheerfully excuse  the haste <del type="overstrike">and</del> with which I write and all mistakes in spelling and composition — Many thanks to my dear Sister<name type="person"> Ellen</name>    for the kind and affectionate letter— Love to all and say to father that my next shall be to him  from the <unclear> army</unclear> of occupation</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>and <choice>
                     <orig>believ</orig>
                     <reg>believe</reg>
                  </choice> me my dear Mother Your most affectionate Son </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <emph>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Robt</abbr>
                           <expan>Robert</expan>
                        </choice> C. Foster 3</emph>
                  </name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl089d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mrs Ephraim H. Foster</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="upside down under address">
                  <date when="1846-06-16">June 16 - 1846</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
