<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tl023">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1795 Sept. 29, Chickasaw Nation / Piomingo : a
			 machine-readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Opy Omingo</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Holly Adams</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno>tl023</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 47822571</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, Tennessee. It may be used freely by individuals for
				research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability
				is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1795 Sept. 29, Chickasaw Nation / Piomingo</title>
               <author>Opy Omingo</author>
               <date when="1795-09-29">September 29, 1795</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This document is a copy of a letter, dated
				September 29, 1795, by Chickasaw chief Piomingo (indicated in this letter as
				Opy Omingo and Opoia mingo) that was written to General James Robertson and
				sent to Colonel David Henley. Piomingo wrote this letter as a plea to the
				United States government for assistance. Hostility existed between the
				Chickasaws and the Creeks, and the letter described an attack by the Creek on
				the Chickasaw Nation. Although the Chickasaw were able to hold off and defeat
				the Creek, they endured considerable losses. Piomingo urged Robertson to think
				of Chickasaws as the brothers of Americans and that brothers should want to
				help each other in times of need. The Chickasaw chief asked for troops and
				provisions to be sent to his nation.</note>
               <note type="Collection"> Henley Papers</note>
               <note type="Box">n/a</note>
               <note type="Folder">11</note>
               <note type="Document">tl023</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Creek Indians--Wars</term>
               <term>Chickasaw Indians--Wars</term>
               <term>Chickasaw Indians--Government relations</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Opy Omingo</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tl023a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Chickasaw Nation</name>
                     <date when="1795-09-29">September 29th 1795</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Friend  Brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>This is to inform you that the people who come against us when you
			 was here. come against us again with their Sharp weapons. when you was here
			 none of us went after them.  there was no blood Spilt. but it is not the
			 case now. I have lost Some of my warriors and Spilt a great <choice>
                  <orig>deel</orig>
                  <reg>deal</reg>
               </choice> of Blood. there was a good many guns fired. but
			 <unclear>my (document damaged)</unclear> times was not come. I am Still alive.
			 there is Blood Spilt but not so much as to run. I told you when I Saw you last
			 that I never expected to see you. I <unclear>write (document damaged)</unclear>
			 you to let you know how times is. I am alive as yet but I have no Case of my
			 life. I have sent you <unclear>(document damaged)</unclear> talk for you to set
			 down and think of. and to let me know. how things is to be. I told you when you
			 was here now you may plainly See <choice>
                  <orig>there</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice> Intentions.
			 they were not <choice>
                  <orig>hear</orig>
                  <reg>here</reg>
               </choice> to <choice>
                  <orig>any
			 thing</orig>
                  <reg>anything</reg>
               </choice> that is good. but if is bad they will <choice>
                  <orig>liston</orig>
                  <reg>listen</reg>
               </choice>  open <choice>
                  <orig>there</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice> ears
			  you told me that it would be good times. but we Sat Still and did not
			 go and hunt them. they come to our Towns  we turn out and fought them like
			 men. and drove them from where they came with a considerable loss, I send you
			 this <unclear>letter (document damaged)</unclear> to think of as a brother. if
			 you think <choice>
                  <orig>any thing</orig>
                  <reg>anything</reg>
               </choice> of your Brothers you will Send
			 one or two Hundred of your warriors to help your brothers hold to their Land. I
			 expect they will come. if you find it <add place="supralinear">not</add> in
			 your heart we must <pb n="2" facs="tl023b.small.jpg"/>
               <unclear>do (document damaged)</unclear> our
			 <choice>
                  <orig>indeavours</orig>
                  <reg>endeavors</reg>
               </choice> to live as long as we can I expect we
			 Shall have hard fighting until the <del type="overstrike">weather</del>
               <add place="supralinear">water</add> rises high If your men Should come let
			 them fetch their guns and long Sword and pistols as you are a people that Can
			 make them, if you think <choice>
                  <orig>any thing</orig>
                  <reg>anything</reg>
               </choice> of your brothers
			 <unclear>and (document damaged)</unclear> Send men to assist us. to send a boat
			 with provisions to 
			 <name type="place">the Bluffs</name> and the rest come by land as
			 provisions is dear here. and the provisions can be packed in from 
			 <name type="place">the Bluffs</name> I have lost my
			 <choice>
                  <orig>Son in law</orig>
                  <reg>son-in-law</reg>
               </choice>
               <name type="person">William Nash</name> and another warrior out of my
			 town one woman. the whole that was killed was Six warriors  one Woman
			 There came about one thousand 
			 <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>creeks</orig>
                     <reg>Creeks</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> in order
			 to take the nation. they camp in the edge of the woods on the back of 
			 <name type="place">Colberts Fort</name> to the west of the Town. they
			 brought <del type="overstrike">with</del> white people with them  Brought
			 their drums and <choice>
                  <orig>amunition</orig>
                  <reg>ammunition</reg>
               </choice> for a long
			 <choice>
                  <orig>Seage</orig>
                  <reg>Siege</reg>
               </choice> there was a great number of them on
			 <choice>
                  <orig>horse back</orig>
                  <reg>horseback</reg>
               </choice> in the morning they killed a woman Just
			 below 
			 <name type="place">Colbert Fort</name> along the 
			 <name type="place">Big Town</name> path, with that they advanced
			 against 
			 <name type="place">Colberts Fort</name> in a half moon their lines
			 extended a half mile. we met them  Gave them battle and beat them Back.
			 and as they Gave Back 
			 <name type="place">Big Town </name> came on their backs and they were
			 all mixed through other and that put them to the <unclear>Loute</unclear> and
			 we fought them about five miles they threw away all <choice>
                  <orig>there</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice>
               <pb n="3" facs="tl023c.small.jpg"/> Baggage and went home in
			 <choice>
                  <orig>there</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice> flaps. they threw away <choice>
                  <orig>there</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice> provisions Blanket <choice>
                  <orig>kittles</orig>
                  <reg>kettles</reg>
               </choice>
			 boots  <choice>
                  <orig>every thing</orig>
                  <reg>everything</reg>
               </choice> they had with them. we
			 winged them on each Side with our horse  our foot brought up the rear. we
			 found <choice>
                  <orig>twenty four</orig>
                  <reg>twenty-four</reg>
               </choice> of them dead and a number that
			 we did not find and a number <add place="supralinear">was wounded</add> that we
			 Saw on their retreat there was not the half of our nation in action. If you
			 Send your men to assist me you may think that the 
			 <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Spanards</orig>
                     <reg>Spaniards</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name>
               <choice>
                  <orig>wont</orig>
                  <reg>won't</reg>
               </choice> allow of it but <choice>
                  <orig>dont</orig>
                  <reg>don't</reg>
               </choice>
			 think it for I shall send to them not to <choice>
                  <orig>interupt any thing</orig>
                  <reg>interrupt anything</reg>
               </choice> that comes nor the people
			 that come for it is my request that you Should come there, if you Send a boat
			 it will not be <choice>
                  <orig>interupted</orig>
                  <reg>interrupted</reg>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>So no more But remains <lb/> your Friend 
				Brother
                  </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Opy omingo</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="below">a
			 Copy</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="tl023d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <orig>Chickesaw</orig>
                           <reg>Chickasaw</reg>
                        </choice>
				  Nation</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1795-09-22">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Sept.</abbr>
                           <expan>September</expan>
                        </choice> 22
				   1795</date>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Opoia mingo</name>s <lb/> Letter
                     </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below">A Copy</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
