<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl325">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] [1849] December 20, Washington [City, D.C.] [to Adam Fergusson] / Andrew Ewing   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Ewing, Andrew</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl325</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[1849] December 20, Washington [City, D.C.] [to Adam Fergusson] / Andrew Ewing</title>
               <author>Ewing, Andrew</author>
               <date when="1849-12-20">December 20, 1849</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Andrew Ewing to Adam Fergusson, dated December 20, presumably in 1849. Ewing writes that the government is in great disorganization over the slavery question. He considers the Northern Democrats and Whigs to be anarchists. He also fears that the chaos in America might lead to an end of the liberty that America stands for. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> IV-G-1 b3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl325</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</term>
               <term>Slavery</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr2001010974"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Ewing, Andrew, 1813-1864</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl325a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Washington</name>
                     <date when="--12-20">December 20 <gap agent="damage"/>
                     </date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I am in receipt of your letter with its enclosure I went immediate <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>ly</unclear> to the Commissioner of Pensions and procured him to carry the case up to <name type="person">Mr Ewing</name> for <choice>
                  <orig>decission</orig>
                  <reg>decision</reg>
               </choice> of the appeal. Upon a personal visit to Mr Ewing he promised to audit the matter and give a speedy decision. this is all that can be done at present and so soon as the decision <add place="supralinear">is made</add> you will be informed and such other steps taken as may be required __ any other business intrusted to me <del type="overstrike">will me</del> from you will receive prompt attention __</p>
            <p>We are still in a state of complete disorganization no Speaker has been or indeed can be elected under the present state of voting. and <choice>
                  <orig>altho</orig>
                  <reg>although</reg>
               </choice> Committees of both Parties are in communication, with a view to a compromise. but little hope is entertained of any <choice>
                  <orig>favourable</orig>
                  <reg>favorable</reg>
               </choice> result we shall probably never be organized until we adopt the plurality rule. this is the last expedient. and altho painful to all of us <del type="overstrike">to</del> as a change from the ordinary rules and in as far revolutionary in its character yet the wheels of Government cannot be stopped. We would in case of a longer failure in organization cause the Government Stocks to fall, trade to be paralyzed and the suffering friends of liberty in every part of the world  to pause with <unclear>mortification</unclear> and anguish. they have suffered and bled for freedom and pointed with pride to our glorious land of freedom. shall we too disorganize our Government and thus quench the last lamp of liberty! I trust in Providence it cannot be so and must therefore risk the danger of innovation __</p>
            <p>The cause of all this disorganization is the Slavery question You have no idea how deeply pledged all the Northern <del type="overstrike">Democrats</del>
               <add place="supralinear">Whigs</add> &amp; many Northern <del type="overstrike">Whigs</del> Democrats are pledged to this unholy crusade against our Southern institutions <pb n="2" facs="sl325b.small.jpg"/> the spirit of anarchy is abroad and the Union is <choice>
                  <orig>threatned</orig>
                  <reg>threatened</reg>
               </choice> on all sides the bonds of Party are loosened and every moment we are afraid that the signal of dissolution will be given and all will be over __</p>
            <p>I shall stand by our Country and <choice>
                  <orig>labour</orig>
                  <reg>labor</reg>
               </choice> for the best. hoping that she will be saved</p>
            <p>Give my respects to friends</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Yrs &amp;c</abbr>
                     <expan>Yours and etcetera</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Andrew Ewing</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
