<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD">
<TEI.2 ID="tl001"> 
  <TEIHEADER> 
	 <FILEDESC> 
		<TITLESTMT> 
		  <TITLE>[Letter] 1802 June 11, Nashville, [Tennessee], [to] Gov[ernor]
			 Archibald Roane of Tennessee / Jim Overton: a machine-readable transcription of
			 an image</TITLE> 
		  <AUTHOR>Overton, Jim</AUTHOR> 
		  <RESPSTMT> 
			 <RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP> 
			 <NAME>Holly Chadwell</NAME> 
			 <NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME> 
			 <NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME> 
			 <NAME>Maha Ayesh</NAME> 
		  </RESPSTMT> 
		</TITLESTMT> 
		<EXTENT>ca. k</EXTENT> 
		<PUBLICATIONSTMT> 
		  <PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER> 
		  <PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE> 
		  <ADDRESS> 
			 <ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE> 
			 <ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE> 
			 <ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE> 
		  </ADDRESS> 
		  <DATE>2001</DATE> 
		  <IDNO>tl001</IDNO> 
		  <IDNO>OCLC: 47783575</IDNO> 
		  <AVAILABILITY> 
			 <P>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, Tennessee. It may be used freely by individuals for
				research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability
				is included in the text.</P> 
		  </AVAILABILITY> 
		</PUBLICATIONSTMT> 
		<SOURCEDESC> 
		  <BIBL> 
			 <TITLE>[Letter] 1802 June 11, Nashville, [Tennessee], [to] Gov[ernor]
				Archibald Roane of Tennessee / Jim Overton</TITLE> 
			 <AUTHOR>Overton, Jim</AUTHOR> 
			 <DATE VALUE="1802-06-11">June 11, 1802 </DATE> 
			 <EXTENT>8p</EXTENT> 
			 <NOTE TYPE="summary">This document is a letter dated June 11, 1802
				from Jim Overton to Tennessee Governor Archibald Roane (1801-1803). Overton
				requests the Governor's help regarding the opening of the Natchez road near the
				Indian Boundary line that would run from Franklin to Davidson County. </NOTE> 
			 <NOTE TYPE="Collection"> Governor Roane Papers</NOTE> 
			 <NOTE TYPE="Box">1</NOTE> 
			 <NOTE TYPE="Folder">5</NOTE> 
			 <NOTE TYPE="Document">tl001</NOTE></BIBL> 
		</SOURCEDESC> 
	 </FILEDESC> 
	 <ENCODINGDESC> 
		<PROJECTDESC> 
		  <P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P> 
		</PROJECTDESC> 
		<EDITORIALDECL> 
		  <P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P> 
		  <P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</P> 
		  <P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</P> 
		  <P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</P> 
		  <P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</P> 
		</EDITORIALDECL> 
		<REFSDECL> 
		  <P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P> 
		</REFSDECL> 
		<CLASSDECL> 
		  <TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"> 
			 <BIBL> 
				<TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL> 
		  </TAXONOMY> 
		</CLASSDECL> 
	 </ENCODINGDESC> 
	 <PROFILEDESC> 
		<TEXTCLASS> 
		  <KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"> 
			 <LIST> 
				<ITEM>Letters</ITEM> 
				<ITEM>Indians of North America--Government relations</ITEM> 
				<ITEM>Roads--Design and construction</ITEM> 
				<ITEM>Boundaries</ITEM> 
				<ITEM>Tennessee</ITEM> 
			 </LIST> 
		  </KEYWORDS> 
		</TEXTCLASS> 
	 </PROFILEDESC> 
  </TEIHEADER> 
  <TEXT> 
	 <BODY> 
		<DIV1 TYPE="letter"><PB N="[1]"> 
		  <OPENER> 
			 <ADDRESS> 
				<ADDRLINE> 
				  <NAME TYPE="place">Nashville</NAME></ADDRLINE> 
				<ADDRLINE> 
				  <DATE VALUE="1802-06-11">June 11th 1802</DATE></ADDRLINE> 
			 </ADDRESS> 
			 <SALUTE>Sir</SALUTE>,</OPENER> 
		  <P>Since the setting of 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Davidson Court</NAME>I received your letter
			 relative to the opening of the 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Natchez</NAME> road. agreeably thereto, the
			 subject was brought before last 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Williamson County</NAME> Court. An order was then
			 and there made for a jury to view a road the nearest and best was from <HI> 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Franklin</NAME></HI> to the 
			 <NAME>Davidson County</NAME> line in the direction to 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Nashville</NAME>, and also order for a jury to
			 view a road the nearest and best way from <HI> 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Franklin</NAME></HI> to the 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Natchez</NAME> road cut by the troops of the 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, where the Indian Boundary
			 line intersects the same or to the North <ADD PLACE="supralinear">&caret;of
			 that</ADD>point. A motion was made at the same court to procure an order for a
			 view of a road from where the 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Natchez</NAME> road intersects the Indian boundary
			 line, the nearest and best way towards 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Nashville</NAME> to the 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Davidson County</NAME> line, but the court
			 unanimously opposed it. Because they said there was now a reduction of the
			 army, and they had received information that the troops were ordered to cease
			 cutting the 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Natchez</NAME> road any further; and then said
			 that road would be an intolerable <UNCLEAR><ORIG
			 REG="burden">burthen</ORIG></UNCLEAR> on the citizens of the said County
			 without any benefit, for it would pass <UNCLEAR><ORIG
			 REG="through">thou</ORIG></UNCLEAR> a County very thinly <PB N="[2]"> settled
			 and that said road would not pass <ORIG REG="through">thro</ORIG> 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Franklin</NAME> and would be against the interest
			 of said Town and its vicinity which they thought they ought to promote; and
			 this last reason appeared to be the only <UNCLEAR>actuating</UNCLEAR> one; the
			 others were <UNCLEAR>ostensible</UNCLEAR>. it had such weight that it was
			 mentioned <DEL TYPE="overstrike">by</DEL> by several and not denied by any that
			 even if the 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> troops were to cut said road
			 they ought not to permit them</P> 
		  <P>If said order had been obtained in 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Williamson</NAME> there would I believe have been
			 no difficulty in <ORIG REG="obtaining">obtaing</ORIG> an order from the County
			 Court of 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Davidson</NAME> for a road from 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Nashville</NAME> the nearest
			 <DEL TYPE="overstrike">way</DEL> and best way to the 
		  <NAME TYPE="place">Davidson County</NAME> line in the direction to the
		  intersection of the 
		  <NAME TYPE="place">Natchez</NAME> road and the Indian boundary</P> 
		  <P>And thereby said viewers viewing said road and marking it in concert
			 with 
			 <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Colonel">Col</ABBR>. Butler</NAME>,
			 the object of the secretary at war might be obtained to wit. the having a road
			 opened the nearest and best way from 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Nashville</NAME> to 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Natchez</NAME>. But now 
			 <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Colonel">Col</ABBR> Butler</NAME>
			 <PB N="[3]"> declines to open the road from 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Nashville</NAME> agreeably to the order of view of
			 Williamson court <ORIG REG="alleging">alledging</ORIG> that it does not accord
			 with the letter spirit nor intent of the order of the secretary at war
			 <DEL TYPE="overstrike">unclear</DEL> for he says the road the nearest and best
			 way from 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Nashville</NAME> to 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Natchez</NAME> road now opened at the Indian
			 boundary would be four miles nearer than any road which could be cut passing
			 through 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Franklin</NAME> to the same places Said road will
			 be of much importance to the citizens of <UNCLEAR>Meroe</UNCLEAR> generally and
			 to <ORIG REG="travellers">travelers</ORIG> to and from 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Natchez</NAME> but unless exertions are used, we
			 shall be deprived of the <ORIG REG="benefit">benifit</ORIG> of it by the local
			 policy of the County of 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Williamson</NAME>; the town of 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Franklin</NAME> and it vicinity, and the narrow
			 interested views of a few individuals.&mdash;</P> 
		  <P>Suffer me to suggest to the consideration of your excellency whether
			 there would not be a propriety in writing to the County court of 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Williamson</NAME> and 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Davidson</NAME>, to make such order as would
			 enable 
			 <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Colonel">Col</ABBR>. Butler</NAME>
			 to cut out said road agreeably to the orders of the secretary at war
			 <PB N="[4]"> Or to write to the secretary at war to permit 
			 <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Colonel">Col</ABBR>. Butler</NAME>
			 to cut said road according to his discretion from 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Nashville</NAME> to where it is already open at
			 the Indian boundary having first obtained permission of the owners of the lands
			 through which it may pass: and permission of your excellency. &mdash;</P> 
		  <P>Or that the secretary will permit 
			 <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Colonel">Col</ABBR>. Butler</NAME>
			 to open such road from 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Nashville</NAME> to the intersection of the 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Natchez</NAME> road and the Indian boundary line
			 as the county Court of 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Davidson</NAME> and 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Williamson</NAME> may respectively
			 direct.&mdash;</P> 
		  <P>I have not a copy by me of the above mentioned order of 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Williamson County</NAME> Court.
			 <ADD PLACE="supralinear">&caret;it</ADD> is merely recited from memory and
			 possibly may not be altogether correct. &mdash;</P> 
		  <P>It is the earnest desire of most of the respectable characters in
			 this district that said road should be opened; and I am confident if it could
			 <PB N="[5]"> be obtained through the intervention of your excellency with the
			 secretary at war, or with the County courts of 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Davidson</NAME> and 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Williamson</NAME> your regard for the interest of
			 this District would be great <ADD PLACE="supralinear">&caret;ful</ADD>ly
			 remembered.</P> 
		  <P>Possibly the most eligible way of effecting it might be by your
			 giving permission immediately to the troops to open away agreeably to the
			 orders of secretary at war with the consent of the County Courts of 
			 <NAME TYPE="person">Davidson</NAME> &amp; 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Williamson</NAME> and with the consent of ye
			 respective owners of the lands, through, which it may pass. &mdash;</P> 
		  <P>And at the same time to provide against the possibility of the
			 courts and individuals not giving said consent, to write to the secretary to
			 permit the said way to be opened as the County courts of 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Davidson</NAME> and 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Williamson</NAME> may respectfully order. 1st 
			 <ABBR EXPAN="Governor">Gov.</ABBR> to write to County courts of 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Davidson</NAME> &amp; 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Williamson</NAME> to permit the <SIC CORR="U.S."> 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">U.S.</NAME> <PB N="[6]"> 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">U.S.</NAME></SIC> to open the road according to
			 orders 2. to write to secretary at war to permit troops to cut the road
			 according to wish of 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Davidson</NAME> &amp; 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Williamson</NAME>, and if they are unwilling to
			 make order 3. <ORIG REG="Then">Thin</ORIG>, to permit the troops to cut the
			 road with permission of the owners of the lands through which it passes.
			 &mdash;</P> 
		  <P>4th. Then to permit the troops to cut the road with the permission
			 of the County Courts <ADD PLACE="supralinear">&caret; and</ADD> of the
			 <DEL TYPE="overstrike">unclear</DEL> owners of the lands</P> 
		  <P>I have got a young man who <UNCLEAR>sits</UNCLEAR> with me to
			 <UNCLEAR>throw</UNCLEAR> three <UNCLEAR>unc</UNCLEAR> together &mdash; I have
			 been sick nearly three weeks and am not now able to sit up long &mdash;The
			 <UNCLEAR>unc</UNCLEAR> are not <UNCLEAR>commenced up</UNCLEAR> I could wish
			 &mdash; The road is of great consequence; and <UNCLEAR>unless an
			 order</UNCLEAR> is obtained from the secretary of <UNCLEAR>war</UNCLEAR>to open
			 it by 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Franklin</NAME>. The <UNCLEAR>troops</UNCLEAR>
			 <PB N="[7]"> will be withdrawn, and the road lost for it would be difficult to
			 get the consent of the owners of land not in the Country &mdash; 
			 <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Colonel">Col</ABBR> Butler</NAME>
			 says an order must be got from the Secretary of War, or he can't <UNCLEAR>do
			 it</UNCLEAR> As an individual let me intreat you to <ORIG
			 REG="endeavor">indeavour</ORIG> to get the order of the secretary of War to
			 open by 
			 <NAME TYPE="person">Franklin</NAME>, by immediate representation</P> 
		  <P>I believe 
			 <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR TYPE="Colonel">Col</ABBR> Butler</NAME>
			 expects such an application will be made</P> 
		  <CLOSER> 
			 <SALUTE>I am exhausted <LB>with great 
				<ABBR EXPAN="respects">resp</ABBR> <LB> I am 
				<ABBR EXPAN="your most obedient servant">yr mo obs</ABBR></SALUTE> 
			 <SIGNED><HI> 
				<NAME TYPE="person"><UNCLEAR><ABBR
				  EXPAN="John">Jim</ABBR></UNCLEAR> Overton</NAME></HI></SIGNED><ADD
			 PLACE="bottom, left"> 
			 <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Governor">Gov</ABBR>
				Roane</NAME></ADD></CLOSER> 
		</DIV1> 
	 </BODY> 
	 <BACK> 
		<DIV1 TYPE="letter"><PB N="[8]"> 
		  <P> 
		  <ADDRESS> 
			 <ADDRLINE><UNCLEAR><ABBR EXPAN="Superior">Sup</ABBR></UNCLEAR>
				officer</ADDRLINE> 
			 <ADDRLINE><UNCLEAR>Fm</UNCLEAR> <HI> 
				<NAME TYPE="person"><UNCLEAR>Jim</UNCLEAR>
				  Overton</NAME></HI></ADDRLINE> 
			 <ADDRLINE> 
				<NAME TYPE="person">Governor Roane</NAME></ADDRLINE> 
			 <ADDRLINE> 
				<NAME TYPE="place">Knoxville</NAME></ADDRLINE> 
		  </ADDRESS></P> 
		</DIV1> 
	 </BACK> 
  </TEXT>
</TEI.2>
