<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="tl211"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1828 Mar. 14 [to] Governor Samuel Houston, Nashville, Ten [nessee] / Residents of Canton County, Kentucky : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Residents of Canton County, Kentucky</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>tl211</idno><idno>OCLC: 49946637</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1828 Mar. 14 [to] Governor Samuel Houston, Nashville, Ten [nessee] / Residents of Canton County, Kentucky</title><author>Residents of Canton County, Kentucky</author><date value="1828-03-14">March 14, 1828</date><extent> 4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter drafted by the residents of Canton County, Kentucky to Samuel Houston (1827-1829) dated March 14, 1828. The  letter asks Governor Houston to use his influence with the Governor of Kentucky to settle a boundary dispute between two counties.  The existing Walker line is in dispute with the citizens. The citizens have put their signatures on the letter requesting the assistance of Governor Houston.</note><note type="collection">Governor Sam Houston Correspondence </note><note type="box">Jackson - Woods, b1</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">tl211</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</item><item>Land tenure</item><item>Boundaries</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>Kentucky</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><salute>To his Excellency <name type="person">Samuel Houston</name> Governor of <name type="place">Tennessee</name></salute></opener><p>The Undersigned beg leave to call your Attention to the subject of settling the state boundary line in that part that <orig reg="separates">seperates</orig> <name type="place">Stuart</name> &amp; <name type="place">Trigg</name> Counties as the Legislature of <name type="place">Kentucky</name> hath passed a resolution on that subject, and as you will be called on by the Executive of that state to <orig reg="cooperate">cooporate</orig> with him in that business. We with due deference would suggest the following remarks, that owing to a line found having the appearance of <name type="person">Walker's</name> marks. Extending from two miles East of Cumberland to the Tennessee River about two miles North and unconnected with the line run by Walker. As directed by the Government of <name type="place">Virginia</name> from the Southeast Corner of the State of Kentucky. Which reputed line hath been a source of much <orig reg="perplexity">perplex &caret; <add place="supralinear">i</add> ty</orig> <orig reg="growing">growin</orig> out of the <orig reg="exercisive">excercisive</orig> power by the officers of both states over a few inhabitants over which each claim jurisdiction that the <orig reg="Territory">Teritory</orig> is small Say 18 or 20 Square miles Which we presume of too little magnitude to be regarded as an Object with either state or Counties adjoining and we suppose the Legislature of Kentucky notice the subject with a special view, to the relief of us that is <unclear>agreed</unclear> and as we are unable to perceive how survey or that may be appointed by the Chief <orig reg="magistrates">majistrates</orig> of the two states with the article of Stipulation of the <date value="1820-02-11">11th of February 1820</date> <orig reg="entered">intered</orig> into by the <pb n="[2]"/> commissioners appointed by both States before them can connect those lines <orig reg="without">with out</orig> doing violence to other parts of the Compact we would further remark that whether those marks north of Walkers general line were made by Walker are <unclear>title?</unclear> to the purpose Walker work out to be a <orig reg="straight">strait</orig> line extending to the Tennessee River this would give uniformity to the boundary between the two States and tranquility to the people immediately interested, With this view of the Subject we would respectfully submit, the following <abbr expan="to wit">(viz)</abbr> that in your <orig reg="correspondence">correspondince</orig> with the Executive of Kentucky You permit him by his surveyors or Survey or" to remark and settle Walkers line from the Southeast corner of Trigg County to the Tennessee River, And where no marks can be found that he shall be governed by the Course of said line. We believe this would be in strict Conformity with the expectation &amp; praise worthy Spirit in which the stipulation was made</p><p>We under those remarks with feelings &amp; views congenial with that vital self governing principle that so <unclear>iminently</unclear> adorns our system of Government</p><p><table><row><cell>Names</cell><cell>Names</cell></row><row><cell><unclear><name type="person">Jsain <add place="suprallinear">her</add> Sells <add place="infralinear">mark</add></name></unclear></cell><cell> <name type="person">Thomas G Downs</name></cell></row><row><cell><unclear><name type="person">John Acree</name></unclear></cell><cell><name type="person"><abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> C Jones</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Joshua <unclear>Sheec</unclear>Cane</name></cell><cell><name type="person">Elisha McHain</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Robert <unclear>Hamletton</unclear></name></cell><cell><name type="person">Thomas Powell</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Charles Lamlleton</name></cell><cell><name type="person">David Churchill</name></cell></row><row><cell><unclear><name type="person">James Churchill</name></unclear></cell><cell><name type="person"><abbr expan="Thomas">Thos</abbr> S Elliot</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Enous Outland</name></cell><cell><name type="person">Nathan Skinner</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Jowain Champain</name></cell><cell> </cell></row></table><pb n="[3]"/></p><p><table><row><cell><name type="person">Rolin, W, Wells</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">John Skinner</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Ebenezer L Brown</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Lewis H Jernigan</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Jesse Brown</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">James <unclear>Mcdehee</unclear></name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Christopher Brandon</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Joseph Shaw</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Allen Elliott</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Isaac McKinney</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Jonathan Eliott</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person"><unclear><abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr></unclear> Pryor</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">David morris</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">David Grant</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Cornelius Manning</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Abraham Franklin</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Samuel Kennady</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Jonathan Eliott <abbr expan="junior">junr</abbr></name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Samuel Canaday &mdash; Senior</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Henry King</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><unclear><name type="person">G Sam Gurrott</name></unclear></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Lewis Eliott</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Daniel Skinner</name></cell><cell> </cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Henry Dunkin</name></cell><cell> </cell></row></table></p></div1></body><back><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[4]"/><p><address><addrLine><name type="place">Canton <abbr expan="Kentucky">Ky</abbr></name></addrLine></address> &rcub;<lb/><address><addrLine><date value="0000-03-14">14 March</date></addrLine></address> &rcub; <lb/><address><addrLine>His Excellency <name type="person">Samuel Houston</name></addrLine></address>  <lb/><address><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name></addrLine></address>  <lb/><address><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></name></addrLine></address> <add><emph>Paid</emph> 12 &frac12;</add><add place="bottom of page">Walkers Line <lb/> <unclear>Stewart County</unclear></add></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
