<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm081">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Computer generated map of an excavation unit at Chattooga
			 showing post hole pattern of the Chattooga townhouse, created in 1993] / [by
			 Eric Howard and Brett Riggs] : a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Howard, Eric </author>
            <author>Riggs, Brett</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Mays</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno>mm081</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 48040671</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work in the property of the Frank H. McClung Museum,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. All other use is prohibited without the
				express written permission of the copyright holder.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Computer generated map of an excavation unit at Chattooga
				showing post hole pattern of the Chattooga townhouse, created in 1993] / [by
				Eric Howard and Brett Riggs] : a machine-readable transcription</title>
               <author>Howard, Eric</author>
               <author>Riggs, Brett</author>
               <date when="1993">1993</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary"> This is a computer generated map of an
				excavated unit at the Chattooga site, showing the post hole pattern of the
				Chattooga townhouse. Chattooga is a Cherokee archaeological site that was
				formerly called 'Cherokee Town.' Cherokee Town was an 18th century village
				associated with the Lower town Cherokee communities of northern Georgia and
				western South Carolina. The site is thought to have been occupied for only 160
				years and was abandoned by the Cherokees in the 1740s. This site is given
				special attention because it retained early 18th century Cherokee material
				culture. This material culture is difficult to find and distinguish on other
				Cherokee sites of the same time period. The University of Tennessee (UT) and
				the Francis Marion National Forest conducted archaeological excavations at
				Chattooga during 1989-1994. The focus of these excavations was to develop a
				better understanding of the nature of the historical Cherokee occupation at the
				site and compare these findings with those found on other 18th century Cherokee
				sites. As a result of these excavations, archaeologists were able to identify
				and partially excavate the remains of five superimposed council houses. In
				addition, the excavations of two winter structures and one summer domestic
				structure were conducted. Through the use of surface collection, test pit
				excavations, and remote sensing equipment, vast amounts of artifacts and the
				location of additional buildings and features were found with minimal
				disturbance to the site. The excavation of Chattooga is still an active
				research project with additional findings in the process of being
				documented.</note>
               <note type="collection">Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note type="document">mm081</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Maps</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</term>
               <term>Public buildings</term>
               <term>Excavations (Archaeology)</term>
               <term>Chattooga site (Ga. and S.C.)</term>
               <term>Historic sites</term>
               <term>Georgia</term>
               <term>South Carolina</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="https://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86005864"
                        role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Riggs, Brett H.</name>
               </term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Howard, Eric</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mm081.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc> This is a computer generated map of an excavation unit at
				  the Chattooga site showing post hole pattern of the 
				  <name type="place">Chattooga</name> townhouse. Created by 
				  <name type="person">Eric Howard</name> and 
				  <name type="person">Brett Riggs</name> in 1993. This information
				  was provided by the 
				  <name type="person">Frank H. McClung</name> Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
