<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl277">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1829 Mar. 29, Phil[adelphia] P[ennsylvania] [to] Andrew Jackson Donelson, Washington, District of Columbia / C. J. Jack   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Jack, C. J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl277</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1829 Mar. 29, Phil[adelphia] P[ennsylvania] [to] Andrew Jackson Donelson, Washington, District of Columbia / C. J. Jack</title>
               <author>Jack, C. J.</author>
               <date when="1829-03-29">March 29, 1829</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from C. J. Jack to Andrew J. Donelson, dated March 29, 1829. Jack has applied for the job of Marshall. He states that he is qualified for the position and that the people want him to fill it.  Jack complains that other people who helped President Jackson have already been rewarded, whereas he has not. He also writes that he has papers to forward to Donelson, that are for President Jackson.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">A. J. Donelson Papers </note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">I-D-3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl277</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>United States -- Politics and government -- 1815-1861</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr91032360"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Jack, Charles J. (Charles James), 1799?-1873</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl277a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Andrew J <choice>
                           <orig>Donaldson</orig>
                           <reg>Donelson</reg>
                        </choice>
                     </name> Esquire</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I enclosed for the President under cover to you twice papers relating to my application for Marshall of this District which I should like to hear had arrived safely — since then I have had the pleasure of seeing <name type="person">Colonel Armstrong</name> of <name type="place">Nashville</name> and was glad to learn that the President's old and true friends would be attended to — I am anxious to learn what is to be the fate of my application as early as is consistent with the public interest. I cannot however pass over the fact, that many who have not the same claims upon the notice of the President nor the party have already reaped the harvest which we sowed — This circumstance had given rise to many rumors prejudicial to the fame and interest of <pb n="2" facs="sl277b.small.jpg"/> the President  throughout our state  It has strengthened the arms of the enemy and if not speedily removed by some act of definitive disposition, may result in a severe loss to our side — no better argument is wanted by the friends of <name type="person">Clay</name> in our State than they could <unclear>derive</unclear> from the neglect of the original and firm friends of <name type="person">General Jackson</name>. And with their usual art they are already making use of the present posture of affairs — I am thus <unclear>frank</unclear> because I sincerely desire to sustain as I have <unclear>ever</unclear> done, the man of my choice — <unclear>Seven Years</unclear> of bitter strife have passed away, and beheld me laboring for his advancement at all <unclear>jeopardy</unclear> and many sacrifices of a weighty kind, it now remains for him to make the <unclear><?xm-replace_text {unclear}?></unclear> honorable — I ask for no post that I am not fitted to fill — I demand no sacrifice of principle or public interest — I only <pb n="3" facs="sl277c.small.jpg"/> ask for a small situation conceded to me <unclear>even</unclear> by the opposite party as a matter to which I am fully entitled and accorded to me by the unanimous voice of the whole people of my district — And one which  under other circumstances I would not accept — I forbear for there to press my claims to this office upon you a the General Their repetition could not advance me with him if his mind is not already that way disposed — I have several papers which I intended handing to <choice>
                  <abbr>Col</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Armstrong but his hasty departure prevented their delivery — I will forward them to you for the President as soon as you inform me when he will be likely to attend to my business —</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your <choice>
                     <abbr>obt st</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">C. J. Jack</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="right of signature">
                  <name type="place">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Phil</abbr>
                        <expan>Philadelphia</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>
                  <date when="1829-03-29">March 29 1829</date> —</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl277d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Andrew Jackson Donaldson</name> Esquire</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Washington</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">District of Columbia</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="bottom right corner, rotated">March 29 <choice>
                     <abbr>Pll</abbr>
                     <expan>Pennsylvania</expan>
                  </choice>— <lb/> C. J. Jack. desiring <lb/> some reward for <lb/> his services. amends <lb/> honorable. — <lb/> to be answered — <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>AJD</abbr>
                     <expan>Andrew Jackson Donaldson</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>ansd</abbr>
                     <expan>answered</expan>
                  </choice> —</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
