<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl574">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1821 Apr. 25, Dixon Springs, Tennessee [to] James Winchester, Sumner County, Cairo, Tennessee / William Martin   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Martin, William</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl574</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1821 Apr. 25, Dixon Springs, Tennessee [to] James Winchester, Sumner County, Cairo, Tennessee / William Martin</title>
               <author>Martin, William</author>
               <date when="1821-04-25">April 25, 1821</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated April 25, 1821 from William Martin in Dixon Springs, Tennessee to James Winchester in Cairo, Tennessee.  Martin's letter concerns many topics including the appointment of General Andrew Jackson as Governor of Florida.  He also addresses the explosion of the Robertson steam boat and the loss of the majority of its crew.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">James Winchester Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">8</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl574</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845.</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2009202801"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Martin, William, 1765-1846</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl574a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Bellview</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>25th <choice>
                     <abbr>apl</abbr>
                     <expan>april</expan>
                  </choice> 1821</date>
               <salute>Dear <choice>
                     <abbr>Grnl.</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have at length expected an arrangement, by which I become responsible  to you, for the <choice>
                  <orig>ballance</orig>
                  <reg>balance</reg>
               </choice> due from Young for the <name>Carthage</name> lots.  I think you said it was $200__     you also said on being second in this sum, you would convey the title.  One of the lots I have second to myself, at considerable sacrifice.   It is valuable, and somewhat improved I wish you would take it at anything like a fair price for I know not when I shall be able to pay you this money neither the ballance I owe  on the <choice>
                  <orig>acuout</orig>
                  <reg>account</reg>
               </choice> Or if not this lot, take my <name>Drakes creek land</name>.  I have never before been so embarrassed as respects money matters. not my own, but other peoples debts.  the <choice>
                  <abbr>amt</abbr>
                  <expan>amount</expan>
               </choice> is not great, but such is the difficulty in <choice>
                  <orig>geting</orig>
                  <reg>getting</reg>
               </choice> hold of money.  that I as yet know not how to overcome it.  you know I have always been a bad hand this way.  I think I shall visit <add>you</add> in long, to advise <del>ways</del> on ways &amp; means.</p>
            <p>I am glad <pb n="2" facs="sl574b.small.jpg"/> that <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Jackson</name> is <choice>
                  <abbr>appd</abbr>
                  <expan>appointed</expan>
               </choice>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Govr</abbr>
                  <expan>Governor</expan>
               </choice> of <name>Florida</name> he in my opinion is the best <del>appt</del> that could have been made for that service.  The energy of his character will go far in rendering to order the <unclear>discordant</unclear> materials of which <add>the population of</add> that country is composed.  as respects himself; it is probable that his condition will <unclear>bettered</unclear> in point of health.  and at the same time afford him the means of providing for a host of his hangers on, who by the late reduction of the army are <unclear>breadless</unclear>.</p>
            <p>We have just heard with deep sorrow, of the explosion of the <name>Robertson steam boat</name>, with the loss of nearly the whole of the crew &amp; passengers.  Cannot those <choice>
                  <orig>occurancies</orig>
                  <reg>occurrences</reg>
               </choice> which have been frequent be prevented <add>in future</add> ? If they can, no time should be lost in affecting them, by such improvement <sic>as</sic> as experience may dictate.</p>
            <p>You I expect have before now heard of the <unclear>cruel</unclear> murder perpetrated by <name>John Ragland</name>__ on the body of <name>John Duty</name> of this neighborhood some weeks ago.  his trial is continued <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> next__ court__ &amp;  be bailed, notwithstanding a true bill for murder was found by the Grand jury this I believe is a novel proceeding.  I hear that an attempt to murder has been <unclear>lately</unclear>  made in your neighborhood__  and of several <pb n="3" facs="sl574c.small.jpg"/> murders in other quarters, of <unclear>recent</unclear> date.  It appears that society is becoming more &amp; more vicious.  What is or can, be done to correct this inordinate passion?  Legislature  regulations will not do it.  perhaps the highest proof of moral <unclear>turpitude</unclear> in society, is the lax manner in which the penal laws are executed.  the laws themselves are <choice>
                  <orig>sufficeintly</orig>
                  <reg>sufficiently</reg>
               </choice> rigorous.  but there is not virtue enough among the people to execute them.  but enough of this.  <unclear>I  sicken at the reflextion</unclear> I rejoice that I am not doomed to stay here eternally, exposed to the conflicts, &amp; turmoils incident to human life.  but that a little time more will dispose of this liniment of day.</p>
            <p>"But oh the soul that never dies. <lb/> At once it leaves its day <lb/>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Yr</orig>
                  <reg>Your</reg>
               </choice> thoughts pursued it where it flies <lb/> And track its <choice>
                  <orig>wonderous</orig>
                  <reg>wondrous</reg>
               </choice> way. <lb/> Up to the courts where angels dwell. <lb/> It mounts triumphant there <lb/> Or devils plunge it down to hell. <lb/> In infinite <choice>
                  <orig>dispair</orig>
                  <reg>despair</reg>
               </choice>.</p>
            <closer>Farewell my friend think on those things while it is day__ for the night cometh when no man can work.  Respects to your lady &amp; children I still am, as I have for more than thirty years been your friend.__ <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                     <expan>William</expan>
                  </choice> martin</signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl574d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <name>William Martin</name>
                  <date>25th april 1821</date>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Dixon Spring</addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <date>April 30th 1820</date>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                           <expan>General</expan>
                        </choice> James Winchester <choice>
                           <orig>Cario</orig>
                           <reg>Cairo</reg>
                        </choice> Sumner County Tennessee</addrLine>
                  </address> mail</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
