<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl393">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1832 Jan. 29, Washington, District of Columbia [to] E.A. Fitzgerald / William Fitzgerald   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Fitzgerald, William</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl393</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1832 Jan. 29, Washington, District of Columbia [to] E.A. Fitzgerald / William Fitzgerald</title>
               <author>Fitzgerald, William</author>
               <date when="1832-01-29">January 29, 1832</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated January 29, 1832 from William Fitzgerald in Washington, D.C. to E.A. Fitzgerald.  In the letter William complains of the bitter cold weather and the daunting prospect of having to venture outdoors.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fitzgerald - Williams - Greer Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">IV-K-1 B1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl393</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside   tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Fitzgerald, William</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl393a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Washington</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jan</abbr>
                     <expan>January</expan>
                  </choice> 29 1832</date>
               <salute>My Dear</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I tell you what I never felt such cold weather as this in my life before and how I never shall again I have not been out of my room since yesterday 4 <choice>
                  <orig>oclock</orig>
                  <reg>o'clock</reg>
               </choice> and it is now near bedtime and if it keeps cold I shall not go out till monday when I will be forced out to my duties at the House.  you have  no idea of cold here I am in a warm close room with as much fire as can be made in &amp; one side bakes while the other freezes still I was never in better health in my life I see from the Jackson paper that we have fine weather now you wrote me for money never fear we shall have enough.  I must send it in small sums for fear of loss.  I have in all now sent you $35.  three fives &amp; two tens.  and will in a day or two start more.  I wish would try &amp; get old friend Julin to do as much work any how as will come to the $65.  he owes me for the horse.  and when  that much is done.  I shall not be in a Hurry about <pb n="2" facs="sl393b.small.jpg"/> the balance since I have been here when sitting alone thinking about you all  I have thoughts of various plans for our future settlement.    and my best conclusion was to fix up the Two places and either rent or sell them and get a farm not more than a mile from town where we could reuse stack <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>and et cetera</expan>
               </choice>. I shall be able to <unclear>hire</unclear> hands enough to cultivate it I think a mile or 3 quarters from Town would be preferable to a residence at either of our places, however we will talk all this over sitting by the fire with each of us a pipe in our mouth when I get Home for I am resolved  my next move shall be permanent therefore I think we had better have 150 or 200 acres of good land where we can raise hogs, cows, &amp; chickens Ducks geese <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;C</abbr>
                  <expan>etcetera</expan>
               </choice> and then we  wont want money to buy corn <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;C</abbr>
                  <expan>etcetera</expan>
               </choice> You may depend I am saving here,  except that I wear as fine clothes as any man in congress and  that I dont count extravagance.  I have been telling you in my letters of my steady &amp; sober habits and I tell you now it is all true.  I dont believe there is a man in either branch of congress   more regular than myself except Benton of <name>Missouri</name> who is one of the most Laborious  men in America our acquaintance C. Johnson <choice>
                  <orig>tho</orig>
                  <reg>though</reg>
               </choice> not a dissipated man is far from a man of research <pb n="3" facs="sl393c.small.jpg"/> he stands well here is a clever fellow but his position as a man of talent is far from invincible the fact is he can never make any figure here  tho this is his third session he seems to have reconciled himself to <choice>
                  <orig>moove</orig>
                  <reg>move</reg>
               </choice> along smoothly how we are deceived at Home as to the standing of men here.  <name>James K Polk</name> is evidently the most efficient &amp; respectable member from our state.  tho keep all this to yourself.  I dont know what to think of my old friend C. <unclear>Boyle</unclear>, I have written to him several times but have received no answer.  tho I find he writes to Johnson I wrote a letter or two to Moran and forgot then one time to write to him as they hate each other perhaps he did not like this. but the fact is I care not whether he likes it or not. I<choice>
                  <abbr> recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> a letter to day from our old friend <choice>
                  <abbr>Capt</abbr>
                  <expan>Captain</expan>
               </choice> Caudle he and family were well.  Be in good spirits the time glides on pretty fast and I am not only going in a pecuniary point but I am availing myself of every chance of information I am searching into all the observations of government of which I knew less than I supposed the fact is it takes constant application if a man ever expects to make any figure here and as I have resolved to speak to no subject <pb n="4" facs="sl393d.small.jpg"/> unless it be one of importance and not be that <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> I am well acquainted with it. it behooves  me to be industrious. many men of good mind render themselves ridiculous here by entering on debate with <add>out</add> knowing what they are talking about it is the rock on which many <unclear>split</unclear> they become dissatisfied with themselves and surrender themselves to dissipation.  my brother wrote me that his son Will was the largest build of his size he ever saw that he was very much like me with many other particulars of his family which I this moment remember <gap agent="damage"/> wrote to you about before so I will stop  I write to <unclear>you</unclear> so often I expect I shall repeat the same story often however  as the Vicar of Wakefield says a good story cannot be told too often</p>
            <closer>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Yrs</abbr>
                  <expan>Yours</expan>
               </choice> Affectionately <signed>W Fitzgerald</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
