<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um072">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1841 Apr 1, Columbia Female Institute [to] Mrs. Elizabeth Chester, Jackson, Tennessee / M[ary] J[ane] Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um072</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50315797</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1841 Apr 1, Columbia Female Institute [to] Mrs. Elizabeth Chester, Jackson, Tennessee / M[ary] J[ane] Chester</title>
               <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
               <date when="1841-04-01">April 1, 1841</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a letter dated April 1, 1841, from Mary Jane Chester at the Columbia (Tennessee) Female Institute to her mother Mrs. Elizabeth Chester in Jackson, Tennessee.  In the letter, Mary Jane discusses a milieu of topics about life back home and life at school.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers MS-25 (March, April 1841)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">8</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um072</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Mary Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um072a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia</name> Female Institute</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1841-04-01">April 1st 1841</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>
                  <emph>Dearest</emph> Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>You have I know my dear ⁁ <add place="supralinear">Mother</add> sufficient reason to reproach me for my silence I have no excuse to offer to you, but I promise you that I shall be write more regularly hereafter.  I received your very <choice>
                  <abbr>afft.</abbr>
                  <expan>affectionate</expan>
               </choice> letter a day or two since. You do not know how much pleasure it gave me to receive it. If I could receive such letters as that is every week I should be <emph>almost happy</emph>. I also received a very kind and interesting letter from <name type="person">Uncle Will</name>. I need not say how much I was pleased with it.  I am very happy to hear that <name type="person">Aunt Patsy</name> is recovering her health so fast.  I hope that she will be so well that her &amp; Uncle can come up to my Examination.  Tell <name type="person">Aunt Narcissa</name> I wish very much to be at home so that I could go a <emph>fishing</emph> with for we always have so much pleasure.  Why does she not write to me? I shall look for a letter from her next week — if I do not receive it shall be very much disappointed — I have been very <choice>
                  <orig>buisily</orig>
                  <reg>busily</reg>
               </choice> engaged for the last two weeks in writing my French exercises — we have six or eight to write every <pb n="2" facs="um072b.small.jpg"/> evening — I am very much pleased with the study of French.  I was very much astonished, I must confess at hearing of so many marriages, I had no idea that <name type="person">Miss McIver</name>  was going to be married — but "strange things will happen sometimes."</p>
            <p>Mamma you need not be uneasy about my clothes, for I have as many as I have any use for, though I am very glad that you intend sending me a dress, for scarcely any of mine will suit the weather. I want to purchase a Calico dress — but thought I would wait until you would tell what kind I had better get.  all my dresses that I have are too short waisted — If you have any made please have them longer <choice>
                  <sic>in in</sic>
                  <corr>in</corr>
               </choice> that respect only. I do not think that I have grown any in height.</p>
            <p>Mamma you made an earnest request of me in your last letter, that I would not ride on horse back until I see you.  <emph>I will promise you that I will not</emph>. I have discontinued my riding lessons, and have taken Embroidery in the place of it — I like to take it very much.  the most pleasant evening that I have spent since I have been here was in the Embroidery room.  I am very glad to hear that Sis was pleased with her Pants.</p>
            <p>O! how much I should like to see our little <emph>Walking</emph> and <emph>almost talking</emph> brother <name type="person">Sam</name>. I know that he looks very sweet You must let him know that he has such a sister as I am.  it would please me very much if would learn to call my name. You excuse this very short letter.  but as it is the 1st day of April — &amp; most of the girls are writing April fools I concluded that I would have much more pleasure in writing to you, so you see that I have no time to <choice>
                  <orig>writin</orig>
                  <reg>writing</reg>
               </choice> any more.  Give my love to Papa &amp; all my relations kiss the children for.  Tell   <name type="person">Mary Ormand</name> that I want to see her very much.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>your <choice>
                     <abbr>afft.</abbr>
                     <expan>affectionate</expan>
                  </choice> &amp; obedient daughter</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>M. J.</abbr>
                        <expan>Mary Jane</expan>
                     </choice> Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="um072c.small.jpg"/>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>P.S.</abbr>
                  <expan>Post Script</expan>
               </choice>
               <lb/>
               <name type="person">Miss Rachel Easton</name> called on me the other day — I think that she is a very fine girl.  <name type="person">Mrs L Polk</name> also called upon me.  I expect that I shall go out to her house on Friday.  she intends sending her Carriage for me.  Mrs Polk said that she wished me to tell her all about you and the rest of the family.  The <choice>
                  <orig>recolects</orig>
                  <reg>recollects</reg>
               </choice> to Aunt Narcissa perfectly: Every person is very anxious for Aunt <choice>
                  <abbr>N</abbr>
                  <expan>Narcissa</expan>
               </choice> to come up to the Examination.  Mamma dont you think that Mrs Polk was a very long time in coming to see me?  <name type="person">Mrs James Walker</name> is recovering very fast from her illness —  Why does not <name type="person">Cousin Dick</name> answer my letter?  but I expect he is better employed with <name type="person">Miss Lyons</name>. Tell him I say to <emph>persevere</emph> in his <emph>suite</emph>. <lb/> You and all the children must be sure to come up at the examination. <lb/> The letters have just arrived  &amp; I have received a very interesting letter from brother <name type="person">John</name>  &amp; <name type="person">Robert</name>. I shall <gap agent="damage"/> it in a few days.  I need not say how much pleasure  <gap agent="damage"/> gave me.  <choice>
                  <orig>Remmember</orig>
                  <reg>Remember</reg>
               </choice> me <choice>
                  <abbr>afft.</abbr>
                  <expan>affectionately</expan>
               </choice> to all the servants. <salute>Farewell my dear <emph>Mother</emph>.</salute>
               <dateline>1st day of April — —  — —</dateline>
               <pb n="4" facs="um072d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="left of address">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>postmarked for April 8</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mrs. Elizabeth Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left of address">Mail }</add>
               <add place="bottom" rend="different hand, ink">
                  <date when="1841-04-01">1st  April 1841</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
