<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0047">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Legal document] 1806 Aug. 18, Vannsville   [Charter of the Cherokee Turnpike Company]: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0047</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Legal document] 1806 Aug. 18, Vannsville   [Charter of the Cherokee Turnpike Company]</title>
               <date when="1806-08-18">August 18, 1806 
			 </date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document dated August 18, 1806 is the terms of the agreement between the United States and the Cherokee Nation to operate the Cherokee Turnpike Company. The turnpike crosses the mountains of Tennessee into Georgia.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> n/a</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Legal documents</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Government relations</term>
               <term>Turnpikes</term>
               <term>Georgia</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0047a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Vannsville</name>
                     <date>agust 18th 1806</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>1st <lb/> resolved that this company shall be known by the name and Appelation of the <name>Cherokee</name> Turnpike Company on the road from <name>Tennessee</name> to Georgia.</p>
            <p>2nd <lb/> resolved by the aforesaid Company  Shall be Composed of the following persons and <unclear>distances</unclear> whose names and places hereunto annexed</p>
            <p>3rd <lb/> that is to say that <name>John Walker</name> and <name>Cataquaskee</name> shall <del>
                  <unclear/>
               </del> repair the road from <name>southwest point</name>  to the <unclear>Hurricane</unclear> ground on the South side of the <name>Highwassee river</name> ___ 51½ miles</p>
            <p>that <name>David McNair</name> shall repair the road from the <unclear>Harricane</unclear> ground to <name>shoe make Creek</name> ___ 20 ¼</p>
            <p>that <name>Charles Hicks</name> shall repair the road from shoe make Creek to <name>Coosuwattee Defile</name>   to where a toll gate is to be <choice>
                  <orig>Eslished</orig>
                  <reg>Established</reg>
               </choice> 24½</p>
            <p>that <name>Charles Rodgers</name> shall repair the road from <name>Tellico Ferry</name> to the Junction of the <choice>
                  <orig>maine</orig>
                  <reg>main</reg>
               </choice> road aforesaid---45. </p>
            <p>that <name>kela chu la</name> shall repair the road from the <name>osuwatee</name> to a large creek four miles this side of <name>
                  <unclear>mitchel Sandiges</unclear>
               </name>
            </p>
            <p>that <name>Alexander and George Sandiges</name>  shall repair the road <del type="overstrike">the</del> from the big Creek to <name>Georgle Stills</name>------ 10</p>
            <p>that <name>Thomas Buffington</name> shall repair the road from George Stills to the <name>Highwassee river</name>---- 12</p>
            <p>that <name>George Harlin</name>
               <add>&amp; <name>Joseph Vann</name>
               </add> shall repair <del type="overstrike">the</del> from <choice>
                  <abbr>Thos.</abbr>
                  <expan>Thomas</expan>
               </choice> Buffington to <del type="overstrike">the</del> Stewarts at the Divisional line of Georgia and the Cherokees- <add>30</add>
            </p>
            <p>4th <lb/> that each and seperable will obligate themselves to keep the road in good not to be less than fifteen feet wide and make Causeways and bridges not to be less than Twelve feet width sufficient for waggons to pass and repass- and the said Company shall <unclear>mend</unclear> and repair the raod Every three months, Excepting sooner informed of <unclear>to the</unclear>
               <pb n="2" facs="pa0047b.small.jpg"/>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Countrary</orig>
                  <reg>Contrary</reg>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <p>5th Any person or persons failing in repairing his part or their parts shall forfeit one Hundred Dollars to the company for the use and purpose of repairing the road <del type="overstrike">at</del> without  <unclear>he showeth</unclear>
               <choice>
                  <orig>lawfull</orig>
                  <reg>lawful</reg>
               </choice> cause- but he shall be still <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> to his share provided he does not give up his right and Emolument for such for future- which right  and Emolument shall Equally be Divided by the Company or their heirs for the Term of Ten years </p>
            <p>6th the aforesaid Company shall provid a horse and a  gate for toll for the Turn pike keeper and at the Expense of the Company and the said Company shall be governed by the rates and price of toll which the Agent for the Department war may establish and the said Company shall Govern by the majority to any regulation that might made hereafter.  Further that the road be in readiness by the first of october eighteen Hundred and six and the turnpike to be opened for the benefit of the Company &amp; the profits arising from the toll shall equally be divided by the Company</p>
            <p>Where unto we have set our hands and seals the day and year above written</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed <lb/>
                  <name>David McNair</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>John  Walker</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>Cotaqua,skee</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>Charles Rodgers</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>George Sanders</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name> Thomas buffington</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>Ka,la,chula</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>George Harlin</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>Charles Hicks</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>Joseph Vann</name>
               </signed>
               <add>a Copy</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
