<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch039">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter, 1818 July 15, Department of War to Jer[emia]h Evarts [and] Rev. Elias Cornelius / John C. Calhoun, Secretary of War : a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Calhoun, John C. (John Caldwell), 1782-1850</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch039</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44837807</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Letter, 1818 July 15, Department of War to Jer[emia]h Evarts [and] Rev. Elias Cornelius / John C. Calhoun, Secretary of War</title>
               <author>Calhoun, John C. (John Caldwell), 1782-1850</author>
               <date when="1818-07-15"> July 15,1818</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">Copy of a letter wherein John C. Calhoun writes to Jeremiah Evarts and Reverend Elias Cornelius to inform them that Congress is in control of the public land that was once Indian territory and will dictate where the missionary schools may be established after the extinguishment of the Indian title. He informs them that the four youths, which accompany them on their way to a school in Connecticut, will be allowed a sum of one hundred dollars per year for four years, July 15, 1818.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">29</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch039</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Land tenure</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Education</term>
               <term>United States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79137102"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Calhoun, John C.(John Caldwell), 1782-1850</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch039a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>
               <add place="top">
                  <hi rend="o">D.</hi>
               </add> Letter from the <choice>
                  <abbr>Hon.</abbr>
                  <expan>Honorable</expan>
               </choice>
               <name type="person">John C. Calhoun</name>, secretary of War to <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jerh.</abbr>
                     <expan>Jeremiah</expan>
                  </choice> Evarts</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Esq.</abbr>
                  <expan>Esquire</expan>
               </choice>
               <name type="person">Rev. Elias Cornelius</name>, in answer to theirs of<date> 15th. July 1818 dated</date>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Department of War </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <date when="1818-07-15">15 July 1818</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> I am directed by the President to assure you, and through you the Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, that he has the best disposition to afford Every Encouragement in his power to the benevolent Efforts of the society, to diffuse knowledge  civilization among our Indian neighbors;  that he views, with approbation, the judicious measures which have already been adopted by the Board to Effect these objects.</p>
            <p>The public lands, after the Extinguishment of the Indian title, being Entirely under the disposition  control of Congress, that body, only, can give the assurance desired by the Board, as to the disposition which may be made after an extinguishment of the Indian title, of the lands on which the schools of the missionaries may be Established.</p>
            <p>The agent for the <name>Cherokee nation</name> will be directed to furnish as great a number of the ordinary implements of husbandry  of domestic manufactures, as, in his opinion, the exigencies of the school already Established there may require.</p>
            <p>So the four youths which are now with you, on their way to the school in Connecticut, one hundred<pb n="2" facs="ch039b.small.jpg"/>dollars a year will be allowed to Each, while at school, provided the term of their tuition does not exceed four years.
               </p>
            <p>The assistance requested in erecting a corn mill near each station will, if practicable, be afforded.</p>
            <p>As it is the wish of the President that the <name type="place">Arkansas</name> should be the permanent  home of the <name type="person">Cherokees</name>, he would be particularly friendly to the Establishment of schools among the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> there, and will render such aids as the public interest  the state of the Indian appropriation may permit.</p>
            <closer>I have the honor to be, Your <choice>
                  <abbr>obedt.</abbr>
                  <expan>obedient</expan>
               </choice> servant signed<signed>
                  <name type="person">John C. Calhoun</name>
               </signed>
               <lb/>
               <name type="person">Rev. Jerh. Evarts</name>,  <name type="person">Rev. Elias Cornelius</name>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
