<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl690">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1827 Oct. 9, Blountville, Tennessee [to] Sam Houston, Nashville, Tennessee / Thomas White : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> White, Thomas</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl690</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1827 Oct. 9, Blountville, Tennessee [to] Sam Houston, Nashville, Tennessee / Thomas White</title>
               <author>  White, Thomas</author>
               <date when="1827-10-09"> 
			 October 9, 1827</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated October 9, 1827, from sheriff Thomas White of Blountville, Tennessee to governor Sam Houston.  The subject of the letter is a prisoner of the Sullivan County jail, James P. Havron, who had recently escaped from his cell in order to avoid a death sentence by hanging.  White asks the governor to issue a reward for his capture, based on a description provided in the letter.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Sam Houston Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl690</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Houston, Sam, 1793-1863.</term>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">White, Thomas</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl690a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Blountville</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>9 October 1827</date>
            </opener>
            <p>Broke <name>Blountville</name> Jail (<name>Sullivan County</name>) on the night of the 5th Instant <name>James P. Havron</name> who was imprisoned in said jail for murdering <name>William Humphries</name>, said Havrin is about the age of twenty five years, five feet nine or ten inches high, sandy hair rather light, grey eyes, and <add>or down</add> bad countenances, tolerably about made</p>
            <closer>
               <add>His Excellency <name>Samuel Houston</name> Governor <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                     <expan>Dear</expan>
                  </choice>. Sir, I have thought it best to send to you the above description that you might if you think proper, offer a reward for the above described fellow, it is believed that his chance of escaping the gallows could only be affected by his not coming to trial, several persons committed to jails in this District lately for like  offences have, made their escapes or broke jail, and the good of society no doubt requires that some of them at least should be apprehended and punished, I have made great exertions since he broke jail to apprehend him, but have been unsuccessful, Our representatives <unclear>Messieurs</unclear> Gaunnon &amp; McClellan who are acquainted particularly I presumed with the circumstances can relate them to you, and give you more particular accounts of the murder, and character of said Havron than I have__ <lb/> your <choice>
                     <abbr>obt</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient</expan>
                  </choice> Servant <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Thos</abbr>
                        <expan>Thomas</expan>
                     </choice> White</name> Sheriff of <name>Sullivan County</name>
               </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl690b.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Blountville </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>T</abbr>
                     <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                  </choice>    Paid 183<lb/>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>His Excellency Samuel Houston Governor of Nashville Tennessee</addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <lb/> JT Havron Fugitive $50. 29 Oct 1827</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
