<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm058">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Photograph of unexcavated structural ruins at Fort Southwest
			 Point, Kingston, Tennessee] / [by Gerald F. Schroedl] : a machine-readable
			 transcription</title>
            <author>Schroedl, Gerald F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Mays</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno>mm058</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 47997703</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work in the property of the Frank H. McClung Museum,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. All other use is prohibited without the
				express written permission of the copyright holder.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Photograph of unexcavated structural ruins at Fort Southwest
				Point, Kingston, Tennessee] / [by Gerald F. Schroedl] : a machine-readable
				transcription</title>
               <author>Schroedl, Gerald F.</author>
               <date when="1980">1980</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary"> This photograph is of unexcavated structural
				ruins at Fort Southwest Point, located near the city of Kingston, in Roane
				County, Tennessee. The ruins show that the structures were composed of stacked
				mortared and unmortared limestone blocks and, occasionally, river rocks. Fort
				Southwest Point was established in 1792 as a blockhouse post for the
				territorial militia troops that were protecting white settlers from Indian acts
				of hostility. By 1797, the militia was replaced by Federal troops whose goals
				were to maintain peace with the Indians and protect their rights on the
				frontier. During the years between 1801-1807, the fort was established as the
				headquarters for the Cherokee Agency. In 1974, archaeological crews from the
				University of Tennessee unearthed portions of six fort building foundations,
				the remains of a massive stone wall, and many fort-period artifacts. A 1984
				excavation of the site by the Department of Conservation and the City of
				Kingston located the sites of a total of thirteen buildings. These buildings
				include and officer's barracks, four blockhouses, and several buildings that
				are believed to have been barracks. A complementary excavation in 1986 revealed
				the location of two more buildings, bringing the total to fifteen buildings.
				The excavation also produced a more detailed examination of the palisade and
				stone wall enclosures, and uncovered several historic and prehistoric features.
				Additional excavations were conducted at Fort Southwest Point in the 1990s
				yielded new information as to the fort's original layout and functions, as well
				as the life ways of the people who occupied the fort. Fort Southwest Point was
				given to the city of Kingston by the Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA) and is
				now used as a historical and recreational area. </note>
               <note type="collection">Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note type="document">mm058</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Photographs</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</term>
               <term>Fort Southwest Point (Tenn.)</term>
               <term>Fortification</term>
               <term>Historical sites</term>
               <term>Kingston, (Tenn.)</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n78090514"
                        role="Photographer http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/pht">Schroedl, Gerald F.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <p>
               <pb n="1" facs="mm058.small.jpg"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc> This is a photographic image of unexcavated structural
				  ruins at 
				  <name type="place">Fort Southwest Point</name> in 
				  <name type="place">Kingston</name>, 
				  <name type="place">Tennessee</name>. Photograph by 
				  <name type="person">Gerald F. Schroedl</name>. This information
				  was provided by the 
				  <name type="person">Frank H. McClung</name> Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
