<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0252">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Claim] 1843, Rebecca Staritt vs United States [for] improvements  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0252</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 45959477</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Claim] 1843, Rebecca Staritt vs United States [for] improvements</title>
               <date when="1843">1843</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a claim made by Rebecca Starritt to receive the value of improvements made on property she claims to have owned during the Treaty of 1835 and 1836. See also pa0253, pa0254, and pa0255.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> pa0252</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Claims</term>
               <term>Georgia</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Claims</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Land tenure</term>
               <term>Betterments</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0252a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>To <choice>
                     <abbr>Hon</abbr>
                     <expan>Honorable</expan>
                  </choice> Commissioners</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The <choice>
                  <orig>Morial</orig>
                  <reg>Memorial</reg>
               </choice>
               <name>Preston Starritt</name> respectfully represents that in <date>January 1839</date> your Memorials <choice>
                  <orig>Intermaried</orig>
                  <reg>Intermarried</reg>
               </choice> with <name>Rebecca Henson</name> a Woman of 1/0 Cherokee blood before the <choice>
                  <orig>mariage</orig>
                  <reg>marriage</reg>
               </choice> the said Rebecca was <choice>
                  <orig>possesed</orig>
                  <reg>possessed</reg>
               </choice> of an improvement in the <name>Cherokee Nation</name> on <name>Notley River</name>
               <name>Union County</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Ga.</abbr>
                  <expan>Georgia</expan>
               </choice> At a place called <name>Choestoak</name> where she had two Dwelling Houses a smoke House and  Corn Crib also about Twenty Eight acres of River bottom under good fenced. The said Rebecca had a regular transfer from Cherokee of <choice>
                  <orig>whoom</orig>
                  <reg>whom</reg>
               </choice> she had purchased the Improvement which Instrument she placed in the hands of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> S Smith</name> as evidence of her right to a valuation she also <choice>
                  <orig>furished</orig>
                  <reg>furnished</reg>
               </choice> the Superintendent of Cherokee Removals with Satisfactory Proof by the Cherokees of her right to the value of said Improvements on Which Proof the Superintendant Sent agents <choice>
                  <abbr>Messrs</abbr>
                  <expan>Misters</expan>
               </choice> Hair &amp; Love to value the Same they returned a valuation which will appear on Book of valuation Lettered F on Which there is an Endorsement Disallowing but not Signed by any <unclear>lawyer</unclear> your Memorials cannot now produce  the Transfer it having been placed in the Hands of the Superintendant and the <pb n="2" facs="pa0252b.small.jpg"/> Indian from whoom the Purchase was made having been removed west as well as all others residing near the plan having Knowledge of the facts your Memorialist Respectfully asks your Board to Take the Examination of the Said Love now present and to Award to your Memorialist the value of the said Improvement as the Treaty of 1835 &amp; 6 makes the agents the Sole Judges of the Value as well as the right to Improvements</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Preston Starritt</signed>
               <add>945  __ 4th: Commission</add>
               <add>Rebecca Starritt <lb/> claim for <lb/> valuation</add>
               <add>this claim has been <lb/> allowed by a former board <lb/> whom nothing to do with it  <lb/>
                  <unclear>D. H. Thewften</unclear>
               </add>
               <add>Edward Harden</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
