<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl214">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1835 Mar. 23,  Nashville [TN] [to] Sarah B. Hamilton, Russelville, Kentucky / Oscar Hamilton   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Hamilton, Oscar</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl214</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51212867</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1835 Mar. 23,  Nashville [TN] [to] Sarah B. Hamilton, Russelville, Kentucky / Oscar Hamilton</title>
               <author>Hamilton, Oscar</author>
               <date when="1835-03-23">March 23, 1835</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Oscar Hamilton to his mother Sarah Hamilton, dated March 23, 1835. He complaines a lot about how Kentucky is not a fun place to visit. He thinks that the people are too concerned with religion and earning money. He also gives brief updates on family and friends.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl214</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Religious life</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Kentucky</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Hamilton, Oscar</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl214a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                     <date when="1835-03-23">March 23 1835</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>As <name type="person">Mr Roberts</name> is in <unclear>town</unclear> and I Suppose he will leave for <name type="place">Russellville</name> in a few days I take this opportunity of dropping you a few lines <unclear>mearly</unclear> to let you Know that Brother and Myself are well and hearty <name type="person">Mr Lafland</name> has been Elected cashier of the Branch Bank of the Planters &amp; Meca <add place="supralinear">n</add> icks of <name type="place">Tennessee</name> at <name type="place">Memphis</name> and he told <unclear>me</unclear> Some days Since the <unclear>Intended</unclear> writing to you to Know if you would not come and Stay with <unclear>Lucy</unclear> ⁁ <add place="supralinear">to keep her from Running crazy</add> while he was absent to the East on business for the Bank but I suppose as the Spring is Just opening and <gap agent="damage"/> It would not be <gap agent="damage"/>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl214b.small.jpg"/> I Expect If nothing happens I will visit <choice>
                  <abbr>Ky</abbr>
                  <expan>Kentucky</expan>
               </choice> this Summer but what time I cannot Say I should like to visit <name type="place">Kentucky</name> at the Election or some Ball or when there Is more Excitement then common For the People of Ky think so much of making money that they never <choice>
                  <orig>studdy</orig>
                  <reg>study</reg>
               </choice> how to spend it and they are always at work and do not ⁁<add place="supralinear">even</add> take time to have a christmas Frolic or a Party dance but you are all Religious in that Section of country and I must  make <unclear>allowence</unclear> for Christians. But I am In hopes that by the time I visit Kentucky that they will find some more Pleasing amusement for strangers <del type="overstrike"><?xm-replace_text {del}?></del> than sending them to church Every day In the week on Sunday too and gorging them with gospel and <choice>
                  <orig>hymes</orig>
                  <reg>hymns</reg>
               </choice>. I Intend to send <del type="overstrike">some</del> or bring Some western Songsters and <gap agent="damage"/>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl214c.small.jpg"/> give my love to My Brothers and dear Sister Tell them that they must write to me frequently that I am <choice>
                  <orig>alwaws</orig>
                  <reg>always</reg>
               </choice> glad to hear from them If it is only a <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>few</unclear> lines give My love <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>to</unclear> all my <del type="overstrike">Inqui</del> Relations and Inquiring Friends In general Brother Mortimer Sends his love to you and Family. Tell Aunt Mariah that Step wishes to Receive a letter from her <choice>
                  <orig>verry</orig>
                  <reg>very</reg>
               </choice> much Tell Charles that I hope to See the fruits of his <choice>
                  <orig>labours wen</orig>
                  <reg>labors when</reg>
               </choice> I come home and that they may be Plentiful and <unclear>Choice</unclear>  Except of my love as a token of obedience and affection</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>your Dutiful Son</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Oscar Hamilton</name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>M. D.</abbr>
                     <expan>Medical Doctor</expan>
                  </choice>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl214d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mrs. Sarah B. Hamilton</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Russelville</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Kentucky</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left of address">Politeness of <lb/> Mr Roberts</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
