<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc225">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1842 Aug. 24 [to] Honorable Peter D. Vroom / Aaron Brown : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Brown, Aaron</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc225</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1842 Aug. 24 [to] Honorable Peter D. Vroom / Aaron Brown</title>
               <author>Brown, Aaron</author>
               <date when="1824-08-24">August 24, 1842</date>
               <extent> 4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter from Aaron Brown to Peter D. Vroom dated August 24, 1842. Brown discusses his family, a new Tariff Bill, and other political topics.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Aaron Brown Letter</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">New Accessions</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc225</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr90000566"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Brown, Aaron V. (Aaron Venable), 1795-1859</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc225a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>H. Rep</abbr>
                  <expan>House of Representatives</expan>
               </choice>. <date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Augst</abbr>
                     <expan>August</expan>
                  </choice> 24th 1842</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>In a few <del type="overstrike">more</del> days more "the general jail delivery" will come off at this place_ but it will take some two weeks after to secure our release. <name>Mrs <choice>
                     <abbr>B</abbr>
                     <expan>Brown</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>. is yet in her convenient room having made the accession of another fine boy to our family circle_ doing reasonably well, both of them. Poor Waller seems sadly disappointed at times in the withdrawal of the accustomed attention paid to him &amp; often enquires if "Tilly's boy is like his mama".</p>
            <p>I have proposed to Mrs B. to remain on this side of the mountain until after the next session &amp; to pay you &amp; mrs V. a visit_ but she insist that she has too many children either to stay or to visit with_ We therefore expect to take up our travel to the West as soon as her strength will allow. "The Jersey boy" I hope will grow <choice>
                  <orig>fenily</orig>
                  <reg>finely</reg>
               </choice> &amp; realize all the fond hopes of those who so well deserve to be made happy by him.</p>
            <p>I am weary with the strife of party &amp; look with anxiety to the close of  <pb n="2" facs="sc225b.small.jpg"/> "my present engagement"_  that I may devote myself to the care &amp; education of my family &amp; attention to my private affairs_ Every thing deepens my conviction of the soundness of the Democratic creed_ but it is more or less affected by the ambitious aspirating of individuals_ We shall have much trouble on this score_ The pending Tariff bill has created heart burnings amongst us_ The south complaining of the abandonment of us by the Democrats of <name>Pennsylvania </name>&amp; a part of those of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N</abbr>
                     <expan>New</expan>
                  </choice>. York</name>. The idea is that we had fought the battle_gained the victory &amp; that in the very moment of triumph_we were delivered over into the hands of our enemies_ This is rather the sentiment of others than myself_ I have long known that our Northern friends in these states would hazard much to themselves to go with us fully on this subject_ They They long to soften the matter down by saying they will help to redirect the rates hereafter_ but it is <pb n="3" facs="sc225c.small.jpg"/> a poor apology for inflicting a wound that they mean hereafter to help in healing it_ you will make the change in the Bill in the Senate, with regards to the admissibility of members to the 28th Congress. The change will save much trouble &amp; violence &amp; give time for the repeal of the law_ which will certainly be done_</p>
            <p>The Breach between the Clay whigs &amp; the manufacturers, was wide &amp; deep_ but if the bill finally passes it will heal up but if it fail nothing can restore a good understanding between them.</p>
            <p>I think it probable that in your state it will operate well for us that the question has been settled.</p>
            <p>The <unclear>Dancery rabbit</unclear> bill has passed Salaries reduced to $2.500_ The President has nominated <name>Claiborne</name> the old member of C. from <choice>
                  <abbr>Miss</abbr>
                  <expan>Mississippi</expan>
               </choice>. &amp; <name>Starke</name> of <name>Columbus</name> &amp; <name>Graham</name> a loafing Edelton at <name>Cincinnati Ohio</name>_ The two last poorly suited to the business &amp; will be rejected I think. He declined recommending <name>Barlor</name> though strongly recommended by her Mississippi <pb n="4" facs="sc225d.small.jpg"/> members_ <name>Fisher</name> was here when the bill passed_ Your humble servant had much to do in passing it but found that he had not much influence in making the appointments_</p>
            <p>The election never is as you have seen very favorable &amp; I doubt not <name>Tennessee</name> is now securely Democratic for the future</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>most sincerely yours</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>AV </abbr>
                        <expan>Aaron Venable</expan>
                     </choice> Brown</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Honl.</abbr>
                        <expan>Honorable</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr> P</abbr>
                        <expan>Peter</expan>
                     </choice>. D. Vroom</name>
               </add>
               <add>A. V. Brown N. C. Aug. 24</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
