<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl377">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1836 June 28, Camp Sabine [to]    Governor Newton Cannon, Tennessee / Edmund P. Gaines: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Gaines, Edmund P.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl377</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1836 June 28, Camp Sabine [to]    Governor Newton Cannon, Tennessee / Edmund P. Gaines</title>
               <author>Gaines, Edmund P.</author>
               <date>June 28, 1836</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written By General Edmund Gaines to Governor Newton Cannon of Tennessee. Gaines requests that the Governor send him ten regiments of troops to help thwart a possible war with the Mexicans and the Native Americans.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Gaines Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">I-C-3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl377</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Military planning</term>
               <term>Indians of North America</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n88277194"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Gaines, Edmund Pendleton, 1777-1849</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl377a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Head Quarters, Western Department.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Camp Sabine, tuesday morning</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1836-06-28">28th June 1836</date>.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I last night received information from a high official source in <name>Texas</name>, that the mexican army at <name>Matamoras</name>  , under <name>General Urria</name>, had been reinforced to the number of seven thousand men, and was on the 18th <choice>
                  <abbr>Inst</abbr>
                  <expan>Instant</expan>
               </choice>. in its march, and rapidly advancing towards <name>Guadalupe</name>, Victoria, the Head Quarters of the Texian Army undder <name>General Thomas J. Rusk</name>; and that the mexican motto was "Exterminate to the Sabine or Death", to which the soldiery were sworn; and that the motto of the Texian Army was "Liberty or Death"</p>
            <p>This intelligence was preceded by the Report of Major <name>Sterling  C. Robertson</name>, sustained by the depositions of two witnesses to the facts deposed, that two men were recently killed &amp; another wounded on the waters of the Navasota, in Robertson's Colony about 120 miles west of <unclear>Nacodockes</unclear> , by the Indians of several different tribes (Caddoes, Keechies &amp; others) who had taken &amp; carried away several women and children of the families of the men killed.</p>
            <p>The above Intelligence taken in connexion with the history of the bloody conflicts of the months of  march &amp; april last, at the <name>Alamo</name>, at Goliad, of at <name>San Jaciuto</name>, sufficiently indicate the character of the approaching events, as well as the necessity of unceasing vigilance on the part of the United States <pb n="2" facs="sl377b.small.jpg"/> to maintain our neutral relations, &amp; stay the work of devastaion in the disputed Territory, &amp; preserve this frontier from the horrors of Savage war.</p>
            <p>To effect  these important objects mounted force fully equal to that of the principal belligerent is necessary. For this purpose I have to request of your Excellency a Regiment of mounted Gun=men, volunteers if practcable, to consist of Ten companies; to be enrolled and repair ro this place by companies, or in a body, as may be most convenient, via <name>Little Rock</name>, Arkansas_ Transportation, subsistence &amp; forage for the route will be furnished by the Quarter Master Department, similar supplies, with camp-Equipage, arms &amp;c will be furnished at this place, &amp; Fort Jesup.</p>
            <p>The companies to continue in service for six months, from the day they reach their rendezvous, to be discharged at any time by the United States.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have the honor to be with perfect respect, your friend &amp; <choice>
                     <abbr>obtserv</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>Edmund P. Gaines<lb/>Major <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> ensuing</signed>
               <add>note_if there is not in Tennessee a U.S. quarter master your excellency will be pleased to <choice>
                     <abbr>appt</abbr>
                     <expan>appoint</expan>
                  </choice> a regimental one &amp; supply him with funds for his movement to this place</add>
               <signed>E.P. Gaines</signed>
               <add>To His Excellency <name>N. Cannon </name>Governor of Tennessee<pb n="3" facs="sl377c.small.jpg"/>Genl Edmund P. Gaines <date when="1836-06-28">28 June 1836</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
