<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl595">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1846 May 16, Fayettville [to] A.V. Brown, Nashville, Tennessee / F. Farquharson   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Farquharson, F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl595</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1846 May 16, Fayettville [to] A.V. Brown, Nashville, Tennessee / F. Farquharson</title>
               <author>Farquharson, F.</author>
               <date when="1846-05-16">May 16, 1846</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated May 16, 1846 from F. Farquharson to Governor Aaron Venable Brown of Tennessee.  The purpose of Farquharson's letter is to offer the services of a company of mounted riflemen from Tennessee.  He tells the governor the men are ready and eager to participate in the war with Mexico in any way that they are needed. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Aaron V. Brown Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl595</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Brown, Aaron V. (Aaron Venable), 1795-1859</term>
               <term>Mexican War, 1846-1848</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Farquharson, F.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl595a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Fayettville</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>May 16th 1840</date>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>From your letter to the "Blues" and the order of the Adjutant General I think it more than probable that a call will be made on <name>Tennessee</name> for Troops for the <name>Rio del norto</name>__ You seem to be of the same opinion but I presume there is no certainty as yet. </p>
            <p>I write for the purpose of tending the services of a company of mounted Riflemen such men as know how to use that weapon.  The company is now of sufficient strength to be reported but we are receiving accession to the ranks every hour and intend doing so until we reach one hundred__ </p>
            <p>I have seen no account of such troops in the <choice>
                  <abbr>U.S</abbr>
                  <expan>United States</expan>
               </choice>. service in Texas and from the character of the duty there I am satisfied they would be <choice>
                  <orig>emanently</orig>
                  <reg>eminently</reg>
               </choice> useful, and might be mustered in even after the number called for was complete__ We are really mounted rifleman but are ready to do anything that may be required in order to be received.</p>
            <p>Our men are anxious to be entered on your list for service__ we want to go__ we have volunteered expressly for this occasion and without boasting.  the boys (except myself) are such a will not do any discredit to the high character of Tennesseans as marksmen But you know them__ <pb n="2" facs="sl595b.small.jpg"/> You may make up your mind to receive us and have us mustered in__ for nothing short of an absolute flat unconditional refusal will do in case there is a call for anybody__ If they only call for 1000__ a company of mounted riflemen would be needed for sharp shooters and if we were not needed on horseback we could give up our horses for the <choice>
                  <orig>artilery</orig>
                  <reg>artillery</reg>
               </choice> or <choice>
                  <orig>waggons</orig>
                  <reg>wagons</reg>
               </choice> and do as good service on foot as any body </p>
            <p>Please enter our company of mounted Riflemen from <name>Lincoln</name>_ first <del type="overstrike">__</del> for service we will send you the particulars in a few days__ and I claim it as a personal favor that you use your influence with the power that be to have us received under the first call__</p>
            <closer>Very respectfully your <choice>
                  <abbr>obt servt</abbr>
                  <expan>obedient servant</expan>
               </choice> &amp; friend <signed>F. Farquharson</signed>
               <add>To His <choice>
                     <abbr>Exel A.V</abbr>
                     <expan>Excellency Aaron Venable</expan>
                  </choice>. Brown <name>Nashville</name>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>T</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>.  <choice>
                     <abbr>P.S</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice>. of course this is not for the "prints. and you will be pleased to drop me a line by the first mail such as I may read to the boys on parade__ and say we are extend on your roll__ <choice>
                     <abbr>FF</abbr>
                     <expan>F. Farquharson</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <pb n="3" facs="sl595c.small.jpg"/>
                  <name>Lincoln</name> mounted riflemen</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
