<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="gc016"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1831 Mar. 5 [to] Hardy Moore / J.M. King: a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>King, James Moore</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harding</name><name>Bobby Holt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>gc016</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1831 Mar. 5 [to] Hardy Moore / J.M. King</title><author>King, James Moore</author><date value="1831-03-05">March 5, 1831</date><extent> 2p</extent><note type="summary">Letter dates March 5, 1831 from James Moore King  to Hardy Moore.  The letter concerns the exhibition, performance and praise of fine horses, as well as the acquisition of new animals.</note><note type="collection">James Moore King Papers Correspondence 1831</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">8</note><note type="document">gc016</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Horses</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><date value="1831-03-05"><add cert="different hand, ink" place="Before March">5th</add> March 1831 <add cert="different hand, ink" place="under 1831">1831</add></date> <add place="left top side of letter, written vertically" cert="different hand, ink">Col. J.M. King</add><salute>Dear Hardy </salute></opener><p> I take this opportunity of informing you that <name type="place">Hesekiah House</name> Mr Burre <del type="overstrike">has purchased</del> and myself has purchased our half of Sir Richard for which we gave $2000.- he is &caret; <add place="supralinear">a gray</add> 15 hand 3 inches high and one of the most splendid and high formed horses you ever saw, he has run all distances &caret;<add place="supralinear">and never been beat</add> he has had to repeat the 3 mile heats 4 times before winning, tho he was not in order he is full brother to <name type="person">Monsheer Tonson</name> <del type="overstrike">now in <name type="place">virginia</name></del> that run so successful in this state <name type="place"><orig reg="Louisiana">Louisana</orig></name> &amp; <name type="place">Virginia</name>  and now standing in <name type="place">virginia</name>  at $50 &mdash;this season, he is <orig reg="also">aso</orig> full brother to champion that belong to <abbr expan="Colonel">Coln</abbr> <unclear>Kemp</unclear> — <add cert="different hand, ink" place="supralinear">Is this W.R. King</add> There was an <orig reg="exhibition">exabition</orig> of fine horses at <orig reg="Murfreesboro"><name type="place">murfresboro</name></orig> on monday at court, I heard several  saying from account they expected to see a very fine horse, but they <orig reg="were">ware</orig> <orig reg="amazed">amased</orig> in seeing a much finer and a more <orig reg="splendid">splended</orig> horse than they could <orig reg="possible">posible</orig> imagine existed there ware <unclear>11</unclear> or 12 horses exhibited, but richard <pb n="[2]"/> the admirers, and it was a  unanimous exclamation that he was the finest and most splendid horse they ever saw, he will stand the ensuing season at P.J. Burrus, near <name type="place">Murfreesboro</name>, upon the terms stated in the enclosed lines, ( I would have sent you a hand bill if had an <orig reg="opportunity">oportunity</orig>)  If you have any fine mares I should like for you to send them over to him, and leave them with me, and they shall be strictly attended to, I also <orig reg="solicit">solicite</orig> your influence in procuring some of the best <orig reg="blooded">bluded</orig> mares in your section and <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood</orig>, believing  and hoping that all those that <orig reg="patron">patronese</orig> sir richard, &caret; <add place="supralinear">they</add> will be highly gratified with his progeny and abundantly rewarded say to <abbr expan="Colonel">Coln</abbr> King to make all the interest he can for me.  with those that <orig reg="raise">raisee</orig> fine horses and to send 2 or 3 of his own as he is fond of —fine horses — tell Henry to write to me, if you are not two much engaged I <orig reg="should">shoul</orig> be glad to see you here —</p><closer>Yours <orig reg="respectfully">Respectefully</orig> <signed><abbr expan="James">Ja</abbr> M King</signed></closer></div1></body></text> </TEI.2>
