<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="gc013"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] ca. 1831, [to] William / James Moore King  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>King, James Moore</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harding</name><name>Bobby Holt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>gc013</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] ca. 1831, [to] William / James Moore King</title><author>King, James Moore</author><date value="1831-00-00">ca. 1831</date><extent> 2p</extent><note type="summary">This is a  letter written ca. 1831, presumably from James Moore King; the recipient is only identified  by William.  The letter consists of adulation, and highly descriptive language of audience reactions to colts and stallions at an exhibition in Murfreesboro.  </note><note type="collection">James Moore King Papers Correspondence 1831</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">8</note><note type="document">gc013</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Horses</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/>   <salute>Dear William <add place="middle, top, of page" cert="different hand and ink">(Parish?)</add></salute><p>With pleasure I acknowledge  the receipt of your letter of the 19th <abbr expan="February">Feby</abbr> which was gratifying to hear from you and my friends, but with feeling of <orig reg="sympathy">simpathy</orig> I <orig reg="regret">regreted</orig> to see the statement of <add place="supralinear"><del type="overstrike">the death </del>of</add> your <del type="overstrike">infant</del> son., <add place="supralinear">J.K</add> In your former letter you <orig reg="spoke">spok</orig> of an <orig reg="excursion">excurtion</orig> you had taken for the examination of some gold mines I should like to hear what the prospects are.  (the winter has been <orig reg="remarkable">remarcable</orig> <orig reg="severe">sevear</orig>, but I am <orig reg="in hopes">inhopes</orig> it is now broke, as we have had <orig reg="several">seviral</orig> <orig reg="weeks">weeak</orig> of <orig reg="beautiful">butiful</orig> weather,) I have been informed by <name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Coln</abbr> Hing</name>  that he has brought your two <orig reg="mares">maires</orig> with him, to  <del type="overstrike"><add place="supralinear">either</add></del> go  to Richard or Champion, I informed him that I should be much gratified in their going to sir Richard and if he would send them I would take them in charge and use my best <orig reg="endeavour">endeavou</orig> to have them got in fold by Sir Richard, <add place="supralinear">If there be any other person </add>you stated that if your <orig reg="acquaintance">accquaintance</orig> that wishes to send you may assure them that all care <orig reg="will">wil</orig> be set and with measure   your Linolian <orig reg="colt">coalt</orig> died, It was <del type="overstrike">truly</del> a loss <orig reg="indeed">indead</orig> for I believed it &caret; <add place="supralinear">was</add> an <orig reg="uncommon">un common</orig> fine coalt; your Richard coalt mare state <orig reg="comes">come's</orig> on finely, which I am <orig reg="in hopes">inhopes</orig> <del type="overstrike">he</del> <add place="supralinear">it</add> will be able to <orig reg="distinguish">distinguiss</orig>  <del type="overstrike">him</del> itself superior to any nag that &caret;<add place="supralinear">it</add> <del type="overstrike">he</del> may  have to contend with; and should be gratified to see <del type="overstrike">him</del> <add place="supralinear">it</add> on the Harrican Hill Turf making some of <orig reg="those">thois</orig> efforts of distinction, and your <orig reg="presents">preasants</orig>  to  witness it: I am  inhopes, I do not anticipate your presence <orig reg="in vain">invain</orig> at some of our amusement on the <name>Harrican Hill Turf</name> — <add cert="different hand, ink" place="left side of page, written vertically">who W.R. or <name type="person">Has. Devane King</name>?</add><pb n="[2]"/> <gap reason="top of page folded over"/> to comply with your invite, <gap reason="top of page folded over"/> at <name type="place">Tuskaloosa</name> next fall, but it is quite out of — my power <del type="overstrike">to do so</del>, as I am <orig reg="preparing">prepairing</orig> to build, I have some fine <orig reg="colts">coaltes</orig> and I think promising and do expect to train one or 2 this fall.   I cannot forbear giving you a short <del type="overstrike">detail</del> <add place="supralinear"><del type="overstrike">sketch</del></add> of the exhibition of fine stallions a <orig reg="few">feiw</orig> <orig reg="weeks">weeaks</orig> a go at <name type="place">Murfreesboro</name>; — Among there<orig reg="were"> ware</orig> the Jefferson by <name type="place">Virginian</name>, <name type="person">Sir Charles Pinkney</name> by Old Sir Charles, De Foe by <orig reg="conqueror">conquerer</orig>, <name>Traveller</name> by <name><abbr expan="Andrew">A</abbr>  Jackson</name>.    <del type="overstrike">I </del>and Sir Richard,   besides several others —there was a large crowd of — spectators to  view those fine  <add place="supralinear">loaded</add> animals as their <orig reg="were">war</orig> several that had been<del type="overstrike">greatly</del> <add cert="different hand, ink" place="supralinear">much</add> <orig reg=" ">talked</orig> about, and had never been shone there before The spectators formed a circle in which the horse entered, among them Dick <orig reg="moved">mooved</orig>  in with magnificent splendor, his <orig reg="beautiful">butiful</orig> arched neck aloft in the air <orig reg="eyes">exyes</orig> sparkling with excitement, his long and silver glossed tail twirled on his back and with gallant strides moved with exquisite <orig reg="grandeur">grandure</orig> round and <orig reg="through">throug</orig> the admired spectators it was a unanimous tone  among the numerous crowd, that he was the finest and the most <orig reg="splendid">splended</orig> horse they ever saw, that he was the fare paragon of —animals. </p> <p>Our friends about <name><abbr expan="Nevada">N.V</abbr></name>. are generally well.   <add place="supralinear">also</add> Blackman &amp; family Mother is in very good health, so is Walter &amp; Jane, <orig reg="myself">miself</orig> Mark and children are in very good health, tell cousin <name>Ann Washington Lafayette</name> is very fine child, &amp; <name>Jane Helen</name> is <orig reg="too">two</orig> <orig reg="sweet">sweeat</orig>,   and no end to her chattering <add place="left margin of page, written vertically">I sent to you a few day a go a <orig reg="news">newes</orig> paper and hand bell</add></p> </div1></body></text></TEI.2>
