<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="gc039"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1838 Jun. 15  [to] H.D. Jameson / Henry King : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>King, Henry</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harding</name><name>Bobby Holt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>gc039</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1838 Jun. 15  [to] H.D. Jameson / Henry King</title><author>King, Henry</author><date value="1838-06-15">June 15, 1838</date><extent>    2p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated June 15, 1838 from Henry King to his uncle H.D. Jameson.  In the letter King writes to his mother, and expresses his well-being as part of his battalion.</note><note type="collection">James Moore King Papers Correspondence, 1838</note><note type="box">2</note><note type="folder">5</note><note type="document">gc039</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><add cert="different hand, ink">From <name>Henry a. j King</name> 1838-</add> <address><addrLine>H.J. Jamison <abbr expan="Esquire">Esq </abbr><name><orig reg="Murfreesboro">Murfreesborough</orig></name> <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></addrLine></address> <pb n="[2]"/> <date> June the 15th 1838</date> <salute>Dear <orig reg="Uncle">Unkle</orig></salute></opener><p> I wish to write a few lines to Mother.</p><p>Dear Mother I received yours and Cousin <name>Sarah Moors</name> letters <del>I</del> the seventh of June I was truly glad to hear that the family was all well.    But I was <orig reg="very">verry</orig> sorry to hear that ant <name>Sally Gannaway</name> was sick I have heard <del type="overstrike">from</del> by Cousin Williams letter that she is better which I was much pleased We are <orig reg="still">stil</orig> at <name>Rosses landing</name> and expect to remain <orig reg="here">hear</orig> the balance of our time.  Cousin William Albert and myself are all in <orig reg="a mess">amess</orig> to gether and we far verry well <del>the</del> our mess mates are all verry friendly they are <orig reg="principally">principly</orig> from the <orig reg="neighbor">neighbour</orig> hood I have feared that all of <orig reg="those">thoes</orig> things which you informed me to be <orig reg="true">tru</orig> there are a great many <unclear>ceanless</unclear> boys in our battalion some of them have lost a part of their clothing Cousin William Albert and Myself have not <del>los</del> lost the <orig reg="first">firs</orig> thing. our clothing I expect is sufficient to stand us There are some sickly boys in the battalion <orig reg="there">ther</orig> is only me in <abbr expan="Captain">Cap</abbr> <name>john A Macklins</name> company <orig reg="Tell">Tel</orig> <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> snell that <name>Brite Snell</name> is fat as a <orig reg="bear">bare</orig> <del>her</del> Cousin William Albert and myself <orig reg="have">hav</orig> had our <orig reg="health">helth</orig> <orig reg="so far">safir</orig> give my love and respect to all of my friends and relations</p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
