<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="gc036"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1838 May 29, Rural Rest [to] Henry King, Ross Landing, Hamilton County / Mrs. James King: a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>King, Mrs. James</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harding</name><name>Bobby Holt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>gc036</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1838 May 29, Rural Rest [to] Henry King, Ross Landing, Hamilton County / Mrs. James King</title><author>King, Mrs. James</author><date value="1838-05-29">May 29, 1838</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated May 29, 1838 from Mrs. James King to her son Henry King.  She warns her son to take care of himself, and  to observe safety and duty as a young soldier.</note><note type="collection">James Moore King Papers Correspondence, 1838</note><note type="box">2</note><note type="folder">5</note><note type="document">gc036</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><abbr expan="Colonel">Coln</abbr> Henderson Yoakum For Henry A.J. King Ross Landing Hamilton <abbr expan="City">Cty</abbr> <abbr expan="East">E</abbr> <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></addrLine></address> <add>paid 121/2</add> <add cert="different hand, ink"><name><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name> <abbr expan="Misses">Mrs</abbr>. <name><abbr expan="James Moore">JM</abbr>King</name></add> <add><figure><figDesc>Murfreesboro <abbr expan="June">JUN</abbr> 5 <abbr expan="Tennessee">Te</abbr>.</figDesc></figure></add> <pb n="[2]"/> <address><addrLine>Rural Rest </addrLine></address><date>May 29th 1838</date> <salute>My <orig reg="Dear">Deare</orig> Son</salute></opener><p> We received your letter <add>on the</add> 25 <orig reg="which">whitch</orig> were truly gratifying I do assure you; My son I cannot <orig reg="describe">discribe</orig> my feelings on hearing and seeing those lines <orig reg="coming">comin</orig> from you stating you had arrived at <name>calhoon</name> <orig reg="safe">safte</orig> and in good health</p><p>Henry I do miss you William and <add cert="different hand, ink">(Junior)</add> Albert very <orig reg="much">mutch</orig> your Brother seems to be at a great loss.  I do often think of you young boys with feelings that you are not a ware of you are young and unexperienced you are amidst a great many <orig reg="snarls">snairs</orig> that are new to you.  therefore my Dear son I do insist on your <orig reg="bearing">bairing</orig> in mind the advise I gave you the evening before you left me siting on my bedside, Henry My Dear son do think of this, you know not the feelings of your Mother: great many persons says they do not know how I <add>could</add> give my <orig reg="consent">concent</orig> for you to go but you know that I did not object - the first time but <add>you are young it is true</add> leaving your duty my son and act the soldiers part; you now have to see and act for yourself; I do hope and trust the God of <orig reg="heaven">heven</orig> will in <orig reg="encourage">curage</orig> you youths and gave you health and strength and return you <orig reg="safe">saft</orig> home a <orig reg="again">gaine</orig> Henry we have herd that one of your company were <del>shot</del> <orig reg="killed">kiled</orig> accidently by one of the soldiers; <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Loass we herd was <orig reg="killed">kiled</orig> by <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Waide what a dredful accident my <orig reg="Dear">Deare</orig> boys be careful with your guns <pb n="[3]"/> Henry your <orig reg="aunt">ant</orig> <name>Sally Ganaway</name> has been very sick with the pleuricy but is better at this time the rest of your relations and friends are generally well William I saw your Father Mother and the <orig reg="girls">girles</orig> the other day they were all well I sent Henrys letter up for them to read they were very glad to here from you; Cousin John Thomas and his lady has been up to see us </p><p><name>Henry WIlliam</name> and Albert this letter I <orig reg="decipher">desipher</orig> for you all Dear boys we are all very often talking a bout you all; Charly says tell <name>Budy Henry</name> he can shoot the Indians with his fly gun Henry your little sister sits alone and gnaws a piece of bread </p><p>Cousin Lizzy and cousin Mary cousin Martha Sarah are all here they send their best love to you cousin Sarah says she will to you <orig reg="soon">soone.</orig>  you must write to me let <orig reg="me know">menou</orig> all a bout how you are a getting a long let me know what is thought you all will have to do or <del type="overstrike">gal</del> where you will have to <orig reg="go">goe</orig>; write me word how your clothing will hold out, I wish to know whether you three mess to <orig reg="together">geather</orig> or not write me word who messes with you; your Father Brothers and sisters joins me in love to you I must come to close</p> <closer>I <orig reg="remain">remaine</orig> my son your affectionate Mother <signed>Martha King</signed> <add place="bottom of page">Post script that has been erased</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
