<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="gc035"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1838 May 18, Rural Rest [to] Henry King, McMinn County, Tennessee / James King : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>King, James</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harding</name><name>Bobby Holt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>gc035</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1838 May 18, Rural Rest [to] Henry King, McMin County, Tennessee / James King</title><author>King, James</author><date value="1838-05-18">May 18, 1838</date><extent> 4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated May 18, 1838 from James King to his son Henry King.  He instructs his son on the virtues of being a good soldier, as well as his various duties and responsibilities.</note><note type="collection">James Moore King Papers Correspondence,  1838 </note><note type="box">2</note><note type="folder">5</note><note type="document">gc035</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Working Life</item><item>Comfort Letters</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><add cert="different hand, ink">From <name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> J M King</name> aug <name>H.D. Jamison</name> </add> <add cert="different hand, ink">Paid 122</add> <address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> Henderson Yoakum</name> For. <name type="person">Henry A.J. King</name> <name type="place">Calhone</name> <name type="place">McMin County</name> <name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine></address> <add cert="different hand, ink" place="top left corner of envelope"><figure><figDesc><name type="place">Murfreesboro</name><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">TN</abbr></name>May 21</figDesc></figure>  </add> <add cert="different hand, ink">May 1838 —</add> <add cert="different hand, ink">"William" must be "Jamison.</add> <pb n="[2]"/> <address><addrLine>Rural Rest</addrLine></address> <date>18th May 1838</date>.<salute>My Dear Son</salute></opener><p>Before this time you have reached <name>Calhone</name>, the <orig reg="place">plaice</orig> of rendezvous, and by this I presume you have learnt a little of the <orig reg="rudiments">reedements</orig> of a <orig reg="soldier">soaldier</orig> in camps; therefore if I give you a short <orig reg="treatise">treatice</orig> on the duties, acts, and <orig reg="performances">performaces</orig> of a soaldier, it will <add place="supralinear">be</add>  more <orig reg="perceptible">perseptible</orig> to your understanding than would have been on any former occasion.</p><p>It is expected your officers will instruct you on all the various duties of a soaldier in camp; also, the rules &amp; regulations, by law that are necessarily established, to keep good order and <orig reg="discipline">disciplin</orig> in the army.  They will also inform you of the <orig reg="penalties">pennilities</orig> and <orig reg="punishments">punnishmints</orig> annexed by violating and <orig reg="disobeying">disobaying</orig> such laws and regulation.  Whilst learning what the various duties of a soaldier are; you should bear in mind, the soaldier that prides in his duty, will be always ready and <orig reg="cheerfully">chearfully</orig> perform it, whilst health permits,.  therefore <del type="overstrike">in</del> I <orig reg="encourage">incourage</orig> you, by the love of duty to <orig reg="perform">purform</orig> the part of a <orig reg="valiant">valient</orig> <orig reg="soldier">Soaldier</orig>.  In treating on the love of duty I would not have you to think, you are to be at every bodies beck and call, and to do any thing that might call on you to do, no; that would show two much good natured <orig reg="ignorance">ignorence</orig>; </p><p>I would have you to inspire confidence &amp; stability in your self, and courage to suffer no imposition in any way.</p><p>I have been an old soaldier, and have seen, and know, many imprudent acts and deeds by <orig reg="soldiers">soaldiers</orig> in the army; such as many have <orig reg="received">recieved</orig> severe punishment, others, with their <orig reg="characters">carracters</orig> so <orig reg="defamed">defaimed</orig> that they bare <add>Since I come in town I understand you <del>are</del> have all arrived at Calhone <orig reg="safe">saft</orig>, and are all well, In presenting my respects to <abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> Yoakum tell him if I would be pleased he would write to me- <name>JaMKing</name></add><pb n="[3]"/> bare reproach where ever they go.  Those occurrences frequently <orig reg="arise">arrise</orig>, by two often indulging in little <orig reg="mischievous">mischiviolus</orig> acts for amusements, and at length where checked.  Your officers are under the disagreeably <orig reg="necessity">necesity</orig> of forcing them under <orig reg="guard">gard</orig>, and <orig reg="perhaps">purhaps</orig>, with wounded <orig reg="feelings">fealings</orig> <orig reg="sentence">sentince</orig> them to <orig reg="punishment">punnishment</orig></p><p>My <orig reg="son">sone</orig> you are young; and unexperienced, let me treat the to be cautious, and act the part of an honourably <orig reg="Soldier">Soaldier.</orig></p><p>When I parted with you and the company my eyes <orig reg="were">ware</orig> overflowing; not that I was sorry, but overjoyed with the gratification of seeing so much patriotism and <orig reg="valor">valour</orig>, <orig reg="inhaled">inhailed</orig> in the youthful <orig reg="sons">sones</orig> of <name>Tennessee</name>, by the <del type="overstrike">lighted</del> kindled <orig reg="flames">flaimes</orig> of the old heroes of Seventy Six.-</p><p>Your officers are <orig reg="gentlemen">gentllmen</orig> of <orig reg="respectability">respectibility</orig> and I have no doubt but they will use their best efforts to provide for your general welfare, and should any of you be sick, I have no doubt but they would give all <orig reg="possible">posible</orig> attention therefore I <orig reg="feel">feal</orig> not the least uneasy about your <orig reg="welfare">welfair</orig>, and I flatter myself you have prudence and care enough to conduct yourself in a respectable &amp; orderly manner so much so, as to <orig reg="merit">merrit</orig> and <orig reg="receive">recieve</orig> the applause of your officers &amp; good will of the <orig reg="soldiers">Soaldiers</orig></p><p>What I have written I intend for you William &amp; Albert to peruse, and regard it as matter of importance, coming from one who has had <orig reg="considerable">considerably</orig> experience in the service of his country.  If any others wish <del type="overstrike">interested to</del> perusing it let them do so.</p><p>I wish you William &amp; Albert assist each other as occasion requires, and act generously &amp; <orig reg="feelingly">fealingly</orig> towards each other-<pb n="[4]"/> My son, your mother has much feeling for you William and Albert on account of your youthful age, for fear you will be headless and careless, and get in bad habits; this I flatter myself will not be the case; she is <orig reg="perfectly">purfectly</orig> <orig reg="reconciled">reconsiled</orig> at your going, and are proud to think you have the pride of a soaldier, and <orig reg="cherish">cherrish</orig> the hopes that you will never <orig reg="degrade">degrad</orig> it- <del type="overstrike">You</del> Your brothers and sisters are often <add>talking about</add> you and wondering what you are about, and how your are doing, Charley are often talking about brother Henry's <orig reg="going">goin</orig> to shoot the Indians-</p><p>Myself your mother, Brothers &amp; Sisters, Sarah and Martha are all in good health, Your Grandmother's, Your Aunt Jane &amp; friends generally are all well, my respects to Snell &amp; <gap reason="hole in document"/> tell them I hear of no complaining at their homes- My respects and well wishes to <abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> Yocum &amp; Officers, and to the soaldiers generally,-</p><p>Your mother Brothers &amp; sisters, Sarah &amp; Martha <orig reg="joins">joines</orig> me in love and well wishes for your's Williams &amp; Aberts <del type="overstrike">safety</del> welfare and safe return home, write to me let me know where to direct letters to you, and what are the general <orig reg="movements">movemts</orig> of the army</p> <closer>Your affectionate Father <signed>JaMKing</signed> <add>to <name>H.A.J King</name> To all three of you, I have herd this say from farm and have read the <orig reg="forgoing">fogoing</orig> <orig reg="let">lette</orig> us and agree with all the <orig reg="sediments">sittments</orig> therein contained, I say to my <orig reg="seer">sover</orig> that we overall will and that I wish him to do his duty as I told him before he Hasted <name>H D Jamison</name></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
