<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="gc045"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1838 Oct. 3, Rural Rest [to] Henry King, Tuscaloosa, Alabama  / James King: a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>King, James</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harding</name><name>Bobby Holt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>gc045</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1838 Oct. 3, Rural Rest [to] Henry King, Tuscaloosa, Alabama  / James King</title><author>King, James</author><date value="1838-10-03">October 3, 1838</date><extent> 3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated October 3, 1838 from James King to his son Henry King.  He tells his son to finish his business of selling meat, the prices he should expect, and tells him to make plans to come home.</note><note type="collection">James Moore King Papers Correspondence, 1838</note><note type="box">2</note><note type="folder">5</note><note type="document">gc045</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Meat industry and trade</item><item>Alabama</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><add cert="different hand, ink">From <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> <abbr expan="James">J</abbr>.<abbr expan="Moore">M</abbr>. King. <abbr expan="October">Oct</abbr> —1838—</add> <add cert="different hand, ink">18 3/4</add><address><addrLine><name><abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> William G. Parrish</name> or <name>Henry A.J King</name> <name>Tuscaloosa</name> <name>Alabama</name></addrLine></address> <add cert="different hand, ink"><figure><figDesc><name>Murfreesboro</name><name><abbr expan="Tennessee">Te</abbr></name><abbr expan="October">Oct</abbr> 4 postmark</figDesc></figure>  </add> <add cert="different hand, ink">Refers to <name><abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> King</name> also to <abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> R. King</add> <pb n="[2]"/> <address><addrLine>Rural Rest</addrLine></address> <date>3rd <abbr expan="October">Octr</abbr> 1838</date> <salute>Son Henry</salute></opener><p>  I was much pleased to here from you &amp; friend, by your letter to <abbr expan="Major">Majr</abbr> Woods </p><p>From what you <orig reg="write">rite</orig>, bacon must be a dull business, or you must be a bad <orig reg="salesman">sallesman</orig>, bacon is selling from 10 to 13 <abbr expan="cents">cts.</abbr>  hams from 12 1/2 to 15 <abbr expan="cents">cts</abbr> in <name>Nashville</name>,  I am thinking you are most <orig reg="too">two</orig> well satisfied their, and your friends treating you two well, for you to make much exertion; I wish you to sell out soon as practicable, but I do not think it advisable to sell for less than 14 or 15 <abbr expan="cents">cts</abbr>.  as it cant <orig reg="barely">bearly</orig> be afforded for that, <orig reg="though">tho</orig> do the best you can, and come home shortly_ If you can sell your horse for a fair price do so.  and take the <orig reg="stage">staige</orig>_ I wrote to <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Parrish a <orig reg="few">fiew</orig> days ago, and requested him to advise and instruct you <del type="overstrike">about</del> in any way he <orig reg="deem">deam</orig> advisable_ I wish you to act <orig reg="morally">morrally</orig> &amp; <del type="overstrike">preserve</del> be high- minded &amp; honourable, in so doing you will be welcomely received in any company <abbr expan="Major">majr</abbr> Woods tell's me your friends ware glad to see you, and he was much pleased with <orig reg="them">thim</orig>, I <orig reg="feel">feal</orig> much gratified at your being <orig reg="there">their</orig>, and flatter myself you will act prudent, especially as your cousin Parrish has left you and your young friend <unclear>Bud</unclear> to keep <orig reg="house">hous</orig> while they are from home,_ I would like for you to been in some better equipage while among your friends, tho your business did not so much require it_ I am <orig reg="in hopes">inhopes</orig> the trip, and the mixing among different kind of <orig reg="persons">pursons</orig>, the observations and experience, will add greatly to  the cultivation and improvement of your mind <pb n="[3]"/> Tell <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Parrish in all <orig reg="probability">probility</orig> <orig reg="pork">poark</orig> will be very high, I <orig reg="don't">do't</orig> think it can be bought here for $5.- P. Thomas from the . West <orig reg="District">Districk.</orig> ware saying it <orig reg="couldn't">coul'nt</orig> be bought for $8 in <name>Brownsville</name>, bacon is selling for 16 <abbr expan="cents">cts</abbr> <orig reg="there">their</orig>.- Our corn crops are very short in <orig reg="consequence">consiquence</orig> of the <orig reg="drought">drowth</orig>; <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Woods says they have fine crops of corn in Alabama, and corn can be bought cheaper <orig reg="there">their</orig> than here_</p><p>Your mother <orig reg="joins">joines</orig> me in respect to Mr Parrish cousin Ann &amp; family, the <abbr expan="general">genl.</abbr> and family <name><abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> R King</name> and enquiring friends_  Tell cousin Ann I should be pleased to see her and hope I shall next spring, and hope to have <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Parrish and her to spend the summer with us tell Ann <del type="overstrike">to</del> write to me_</p><p>Little<name>James Moore</name> has been very low with the fever, he is some better and a hope of his recovery your grandmother Butler had <orig reg="chills">chils</orig> &amp; fever but are <orig reg="clear">clare</orig> of them and better_ Dunnaway has been very sick but is recovering_ My family are all well_  <abbr expan="Major">Majr</abbr> Woods is quite well__ write to me <orig reg="immediately">imediately</orig> when you <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr> this if you are not ready to start home__</p> <closer>Your affectionate Father <signed><abbr expan="James">Ja</abbr> <abbr expan="Moore">M</abbr> King</signed> <add>To <name>Henry A.J. King</name></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
