<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="gc048"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1839 Jun. 13, Moringo County, McKinley, Alabama [to] Henry King, Rural Rest, Rutherford County, Murfreesboro, Tennessee / James King: a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>King, James </author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name><name>Bobby Holt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>gc048</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1839 Jun. 13, Moringo County, McKinley, Alabama [to] Henry King, Rural Rest, Rutherford County, Murfreesboro, Tennessee / James King</title><author>King, James</author><date value="1839-06-13"> June 13, 1839 </date><extent> 4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated June 13, 1839 from James King to his son Henry King.  James King gives his son several directions  for looking after the plantation, and requests that every thing be well tended to.</note><note type="collection"> James Moore King Papers Correspondence, 1839</note><note type="box">2</note><note type="folder">6</note><note type="document">gc048</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Crops</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><orig reg="McKinley">MKinley</orig> <abbr expan="Massachusetts"><name>Ma</name></abbr> </addrLine></address> <date>June 15</date> <address><addrLine><name><abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Henry A.J. King</name> <name>Rural Rest</name>, <name>Murfreesboro</name> <name>Rutherford County</name> <name><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tene</abbr></name>.</addrLine></address> <add cert="different hand, ink">25</add> <add>We all join in love and respects to you all your beloved father <name><abbr expan="James">Ja</abbr> <abbr expan="Moore">M</abbr> King</name></add> <pb n="[2]"/> <address><addrLine>Moringo County- Mckinley</addrLine></address> <date>13th June 1839</date> <salute>My dear son, Henry-</salute></opener><p> I presume you have understood the progress of our journey to <name>Tuskaloosa</name> by your uncle Gan <add>n</add> away- </p><p>We arrived at<name> Tuskaloosa</name> 31st May- We <orig reg="were">ware</orig> very affectionately <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr> by all our friends they are generally well.  Your Cousin Ann is in better health than she has been But does not enjoy very good health, they all made special enquires about you <orig reg="especially">especiallly</orig> your uncle Thomas and lady, they all speak highly of your civil and <orig reg="moral">morral</orig> deportment, and feel very <orig reg="solicitous">solicituous</orig> for your prosperity- Your uncle Tom son and daughter are going to school, little Dick is going but <orig reg="poor">pore</orig> little fellow cant learn, he is very much attached to us - <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Byrd was with us several days he is going to the university, to school, and has to study very hard, he made considerably <orig reg="inquiry">enquirery</orig> about you, and abut your progress at school-</p><p><abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Ellis opposes <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Crab for congress, it is thought he will be elected-.  I think very highly of <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Ellis, he is very much of a gentleman- After spending quite an agreeably <orig reg="week">weeak</orig> at <name>Tuskaloosa</name> we left for <name>moringo</name> on the 6th of June <pb n="[3]"/> by the way of Cousin <name>Loucrese Bakers</name>, in <name>Green county</name> near <name>Clinton</name>, we met them all in fine health and was much rejoiced to see us we <orig reg="were">ware</orig> all well till saturday the 8th that evening your mother was taken with a violent <orig reg="headache">headake</orig>, ( I suspect by eating Wortleberries)  I gave her labelia and soon relieved her- whilst here I herd from <abbr expan="Colonel">Coln</abbr> <name>Robert Smith</name> at <name>clinton</name> at the <orig reg="races">raises</orig>, I understood he <orig reg="won">wone</orig> two raises <orig reg="there">thier</orig> one 2 mile &amp; repeat, distanced the field the first heat, the other best 3 in 5, run four heats, was very <orig reg="close">clost</orig> contested, run the <orig reg="same">saim</orig> horse both raises he was a Leviathan, not knowing <abbr expan="Colonel">Coln</abbr> smith was their till saturday evening I went <del type="overstrike">there on</del> to clinton on sunday morning but he was <orig reg="gone">gaun</orig> I understand he <orig reg="won">wone</orig> numbers of <orig reg="races">rases</orig>, I understood he had sold or was likely to sell the horse that run for $2500 - on monday the 10th we set out for <abbr expan="Colonel">Coln</abbr> H Kings arrived their the 12t, Your cousin <name>Penelope Carvonis</name> went with us - We found no <orig reg="one">wone</orig> at home but your Cousin Henry, Your Cousin Helen had <orig reg="gone">gaun</orig> to <name>cahauba</name> on a visit I expect her here tomorrow Your Cousin Henry's <orig reg="son-in-law">suninlaw</orig> Croa <add>c</add> hran that married Lucrettea, they are here, we are very well entertained and enjoy, our selves very well Your Mother and the rest of us are all enjoying the very best of health, we will leave here by the 20th of this month for <name>Tuskaloosa</name>, we, shall leave <pb n="[4]"/> their about the 25th for your cousin <name>Tom Moore</name> <del type="overstrike">as Ten</del> near <name>Clays-ville</name> or <abbr expan="Tennessee"><name>Ten</name></abbr>. <abbr expan="River">R</abbr>- I shall aim to get home between the 15 &amp; 20th of July- when you receive this write to me at <name>Hazlegreen</name> I am not certain any of our friends will return with us or not - crops of all sorts are <orig reg="exceedingly">excidingly</orig> fine here , cotton <del type="overstrike">are</del> are <orig reg="blooming">bluming</orig> finely, and corn in <orig reg="roasting ears">ro <add>a</add> stingyears</orig> I have <add>seen</add> the <del type="overstrike">roasnyeas</del> <add>roastingyears</add> corn <orig reg="perfectly">purfectly</orig> dry at Kings, and he has planted some corn that has grown this year, It is very dry and hot hear at present, and are wanting rain. Bacon are <orig reg="offering">offerring</orig> here at 12 1/2 <abbr expan="cents">cts</abbr>; tell your uncle Gannaway to sell mine -</p><p>Henry you and Mr Ship.  I <add>have</add> great reliance in your care and attention about the domestic affaires of the house as well as that of the plantation, and wish every thing to be snugly attended to, I want my year old and suckling <orig reg="colt">coalts</orig> to be well attended to, my wheat and other small grain to be well attended to, my crop I shall expect to <orig reg="find">fine</orig> in good order I want you to stay generally about home, write to me about my crop, I <orig reg="haven't">have'nt</orig> <orig reg="heard">herd</orig> any thing from home since left, <orig reg="show">sho</orig> this letter to your <orig reg="aunt">Ant</orig> Jane cousin Martha, your Grandmother and you uncles as I cant <orig reg="write">rite</orig> to them all- Your Grandmother mother &amp; sister <orig reg="enjoys">enjoyes</orig> themselves very well, and pleased with travelling, - your mother are wanting to see little <unclear>mit</unclear> very much they all, send their love and respects to every body, tell the children all about us, and <orig reg="howdy">houdy</orig>, to be good children, that we will be at home before long, tell James &amp; Charles to <abbr expan="get">gt</abbr> fat &amp; grow big.</p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
