<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um028">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1840 Oct. 28 [to] John Chester, Jackson, Tennessee / Mary Jane Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um028</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50274839</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1840 Oct. 28 [to] John Chester, Jackson, Tennessee / Mary Jane Chester </title>
               <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
               <date when="1840-10-10">October 28, 1840</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated October 28, 1840 to John Chester from his sister Mary Jane Chester at the Female Institute, Columbia Tennessee. Mary Jane describes her daily routine at the institute and how much she misses her family. Included with her letter is a course description for the institute along with a brief note to her brother Robert.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers, MS25</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um028</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Mary Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um028a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mr. John Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Jackson Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left of address">post mark and seal</add>
               <add place="above address">18 ¾</add>
               <add place="below address, upside down">
                  <date when="1840-10-28">28 <choice>
                        <abbr>Octbr</abbr>
                        <expan>October</expan>
                     </choice> 1840</date>
               </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="um028b.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia Female Institute</name>
                     <date when="1840-10-28">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Oct.</abbr>
                           <expan>October</expan>
                        </choice> 28th 1840</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear brother John</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>You cannot imagine how much pleasure your kind and affectionate letter gave me. I had been expecting ⁁<add place="supralinear">one</add> for so long a time, and had not received any that I can assure you I was very agreeably surprised I would have answered it sooner, but I had <name type="person">Aunt Frances's</name> &amp; cousin Richard's to answer as I received theirs first. I could not write home last week because I had to write a composition. <choice>
                  <orig>Yo</orig>
                  <reg>You</reg>
               </choice> know that it is very difficult for me to write a letter—anyhow, for I never wrote one by myself before I came here. Mama would always tell me every word to put down— but here I have no person to show me. Brother John please write me how <name type="person">Aunt Narcissa</name> is—if she is entirely well I feel very anxious to hear. Tell her that she must be sure to answer the letter that I wrote to her. Dear Brother you have no idea how very strict they are here. They censure<pb n="3" facs="um028c.small.jpg"/> but I have not received any yet. We set up until 9 o,clock every night to study. We then ⁁<add place="supralinear">go</add> up in the Dormitory, there is a little  ⁁<add place="supralinear">bell</add> that is rung for us to undress and another for us to go to bed, and if we speak after the second bell rings we are censured in deportment.</p>
            <p>They ring that bell for us to rise in the morning and again for us to go downstairs. O! it would <del type="overstrike">take</del>
               <add place="supralinear">fill</add> 5 or 6 sheets of paper if ⁁<add place="supralinear">I</add> were to tell you all of the rules. Give my love to Mama and Papa, and all of the children, to<sic> Aunt</sic> Aunt P, and all of my relations and accept the love of your</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>affectionate sister</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>M. J.</abbr>
                        <expan>Mary Jane</expan>
                     </choice> Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">John Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="bottom of letter">
                  <note>
                     <p>Dear Brother Robert</p>
                     <p>You have no idea how much pleasure a letter from you would give me. </p>
                     <p>I have not received a letter from any person this week and I begin to feel very <choice>
                           <orig>melanc⁁lly</orig>
                           <reg>melancholy</reg>
                        </choice> letters now are my only pleasure, Tell Mama I have expecting a letter from her all this week and if I do not receive one soon I do not know what I shall. Tell Aunt that she promised to write to but has written yet. Cousin Jane promised and Cousin Martha Ann. Tell them that I <choice>
                           <orig>wis</orig>
                           <reg>wish</reg>
                        </choice> that they would fulfill their promise. <pb n="4" facs="um028d.small.jpg"/>
                        <figure>
                           <figDesc rend="printed material">Page of course descriptions for Female Institute, Columbia, Tennessee</figDesc>
                        </figure>  Give my love to all my schoolmates.</p>
                  </note>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
