<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl420">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1837 Nov. 20, Carthage, Tennessee [to unknown recipient] / Adam Fergusson   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Fergusson, Adam</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl420</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1837 Nov. 20, Carthage, Tennessee [to unknown recipient] / Adam Fergusson</title>
               <author>Fergusson, Adam</author>
               <date when="1837-11-20">November 20, 1837</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Adam Fergusson dated November 20, 1837. The recipient is unknown, but is from Scotland. Fergusson is writing because he wishes information from his parents hometown in Scotland. He gives the names of his relations there, and where they are from. Fergusson requests that the recipient find someone willing to correspond with him.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">IV-G-1, B6</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl420</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Scotland</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Fergusson, Adam</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl420a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <add>Copy</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Carthage</name> State of <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>20th November 1837</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>It has been about 46 or 7 years Since my Parents have  left your country the land of their birth and relations, and Sought in the then wilds of the <name>United States <add>of America</add>
               </name> a country more Suitable to their inclination. Having myself been born and raised in this country it would Seem that I might <add>be</add> content <del type="overstrike">myself</del> with the knowledge of having <choice>
                  <orig>decended</orig>
                  <reg>descended</reg>
               </choice> from the true Highland race: but having heard my Parents Speak of <name>Scotland</name> and the friends and relations they left behind makes me anxious to know Something more about our family <choice>
                  <orig>conections</orig>
                  <reg>connections</reg>
               </choice> at the distance of almost half a century of time it would be idle for me to adress a letter to any one of our friends living at the time my parents left. We have never heard but little about them Since that period and that little has been <choice>
                  <orig>verry</orig>
                  <reg>very</reg>
               </choice> unsatisfactory. Believing that most of them are past away and that their children <choice>
                  <orig>Suply</orig>
                  <reg>Supply</reg>
               </choice> their places and those not known to me I take the liberty to adress you the first letter making you the organ of our communication <add>between</add> until I find who to adress. My mother was raised at <name>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Dalmaley</orig>
                     <reg>Dalmally</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> the place where I am informed <del type="overstrike">you act as a</del>
               <add>your</add> Post office is now established     <add>
                  <del type="overstrike">and you are the Post master</del> before her marriage</add> Her name was <name>Isable McNable</name> her family <pb n="2" facs="sl420b.small.jpg"/> ranks among the oldest in you country The family of McNable had lived on a Small hill close to the <unclear>Cuplick</unclear> Inn <add>at Dalmaley</add> and occupied the farm and its <choice>
                  <orig>priveledges</orig>
                  <reg>privileges</reg>
               </choice> my uncle <name>Alexander McNable</name> was remarkable for his  excelling in making dirks and other cutlery. My fathers family lived about a days Journey I expect as near as I can guess north at a place called <name>ASedale</name> where <del type="overstrike">an ex tensive state query was in operation</del>
               <add>they as well as others were engaged in making State</add> the Small farm <add>on which they lived</add> was named  <del type="overstrike">I think</del> Killride as well as I my <choice>
                  <orig>recolection</orig>
                  <reg>recollection</reg>
               </choice> Serves me my uncles were John <add>and</add>
               <name>Archibald Fergusson</name> my fathers name was <name>Duncan Fergusson</name> the oldest of the Brothers. I have thus given you Some account of my relations left in your country and of whom I have heard my Parents in their lifetime Speak You Sir will do me a great kindness by handing this letter to one of the nearest decendants of either of the above families and also to the one most likely to keep up a <choice>
                  <orig>correspondance</orig>
                  <reg>correspondence</reg>
               </choice> with me I have a great deal to enquire about more than can be contained in a Single letter which I have no doubt would be interesting to them as it would be gratifying to me. I am anxious after So long a lapse of time to renew those ties of blood and affinity that binds friends together even though they live in distant climes and you Sir can be the means of relieving that anxiety by introducing friends and relations to each other who though not forgotten are at this time Strangers. You <pb n="3" facs="sl420c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Sir</add> can remove the Spell that locks up the avenues of <choice>
                  <orig>corespondance</orig>
                  <reg>correspondence</reg>
               </choice> and cause <add>us</add> at least to Speak to each other I have reasons to believe that many of my friends live in the United States but as yet I have found but few <add>of them</add> and those few are none of those left in Scotland at the time my father <add>left and</add> came over. I am induced to believe that they have emigrated many of them to other countries and live like me unknown by their friends. You will be kind enough to write to me an answer to this and let me know what information you can about them. Both families had numerous relations and I am thinking will be easy for you to impart information to them If however any of them are living in you country and Should See this letter I ask of them to commence the correspondance <choice>
                  <orig>imediately</orig>
                  <reg>immediately</reg>
               </choice> by writing to me They will give a general History or account from 1790 the time I think my father and his family embarked to this country to the present <unclear>Stating</unclear> who are yet living who <add>may</add> have died and who may have come to the United States of America <add>or went elsewhere</add> and what part of the United States they may now live in I hope you will pardon the trouble this may give you and hope though a Stranger you will accept the assurances of my great esteem and friendship</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>Adam Fergusson</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
