<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um014"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1849 Apr. 4 Washington, D.C., [to] Alex[ander] D. Coffee, Florence, Alabama / Andrew J[ackson] Coffee : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Coffee, Andrew Jackson</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um014</idno><idno>OCLC: 50199684</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1849 Apr. 4 Washington, D.C., [to] Alex[ander] D. Coffee, Florence, Alabama / Andrew J[ackson] Coffee</title><author>Coffee, Andrew Jackson</author><date value="1849-04-04">April 4, 1849</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written from Andrew Jackson Coffee to his brother Alex Coffee, dated April 4, 1849. Andrew writes the letter from Washington D. C., and speaks of the political atmosphere there at the time.</note><note type="collection">Andrew Jackson Coffee Family Papers 1833-1903 MS 27</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">16</note><note type="document">um014</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>United States -- Politics and government -- 1845-1849</item><item>United States</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><add place="above address"><figure><figDesc>post mark seal</figDesc></figure>  10</add><address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Alexander">Alex.</abbr> D. Coffee</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Florence</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Lauderdale <abbr expan="County">Co.</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Alabama</name></addrLine></address><pb n="[2]"/><address><addrLine><name type="place">Washington D. C.</name> <date value="1849-04-04">April 4th 1849</date></addrLine></address><salute>My <abbr expan="Dear">Dr </abbr>Alex</salute></opener><p>I have but little to write about but you will no doubt be glad to hear from this <unclear><emph>benighted</emph></unclear> country. You will excuse me for writing first about myself as it is generally not considered genteel, but circumstances alter cases. I will leave here in a day or two for the City of <name type="place">New York</name> where I shall remain a day or two or three, and then for home only to stay long enough to say howdy and off again to <name type="place">New Orleans</name>, again to contend with yellow fever and Cholera. It is unfortunate that I am so unlucky but I will have to submit with the best grace possible. I do not believe that <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Gen</abbr> Lawson</name> would have sent me there if he could have avoided it until fall, but just now I have to become a victim to the urgent necessities of <name type="person">Uncle Sam</name>, for myself I do not care, but I am not so well <pb n="[3]"/> pleased on my family's account. I do not want to carry them into danger if there is any. Yet I will hate if possible more to <del type="overstrike">carry</del> <add place="supralinear">leave</add> them behind me, and I have a <orig reg="disagreeable">disagreable</orig> horn of a <orig reg="dilemma">delemma</orig> to seize either way I can fix it. I am sorry I cannot stay longer in <name type="place">North Alabama</name>, as I had anticipated much pleasure this summer. All the gaming and <emph>fishing</emph> will have to be delayed until another spring.</p><p>The political world is as quiet as you can imagine. <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> Taylor</name> does not give satisfaction to his Whig friends he does not make removals enough or rather he will not sanction any removals and hence the office seekers are wonderfully disappointed, many  have left the city grumbling and vowing they will have revenge, others still hang on in hopes that a change will soon take place. I cannot say what will be the result in the end. The president certainly possesses the quality of keeping his own counsel to perfection, up to this time none but his most intimate <pb n="[4]"/> friends know what <del type="overstrike">is</del> his course is to be. It is true that many of his appointments so far have had a singular cast, but that argues more for the Generals want of political knowledge than any thing else. </p><p>I must refer you to the papers for the particulars of what is going on here, and do not put too much faith in Old man <name type="person">Ritchie</name> he is decidedly too much prejudiced against the Whigs to do them justice. I believe the <name type="place">Baltimore</name> "Sun" and the <name type="place">New York</name> "Herald" are the best papers as far as the news is concerned we have, and I shall myself take one of them on that account, probably the "Sun."</p><p><name type="person">Betty</name> joins me in love to <name type="person">Ann</name>, Ma, <name type="person">Rachel</name>, <name type="person">Cate</name>, <name type="person">Joshua</name>, <name type="person">Andrew</name>, Sis and <name type="person">John</name>. We hope soon to see you all if it is only for a few days.</p><p>We all keep well.</p><closer><salute>Your Brother</salute><signed><name type="person">Andrew <abbr expan="Jackson">J.</abbr> Coffee</name></signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
