<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um031"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1840 Nov. 22, Jackson, [Tennessee] [to] Mary Jane Chester, Columbia, Ten[nessee] / Elizabeth Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Chester, Elizabeth</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um031</idno><idno>OCLC: 50274988</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1840 Nov. 22, Jackson, [Tennessee] [to] Mary Jane Chester, Columbia, Ten[nessee] / Elizabeth Chester</title><author>Chester, Elizabeth</author><date value="1840-11-22">November 22, 1840</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written by Elizabeth Chester to her daughter Mary Jane Chester on November 22, 1840. The letter is composed of two entries. The first entry discusses Mary Jane's birthday, family events, and the political climate in Jackson, Tennessee. The second entry, dated November 26, discusses a fire at the Institute where Mary Jane attends and alludes to possible unrest with their slaves if future president William Henry Harrison does not free them. The letter has written on it that Elizabeth Chester died twelve months after writing this letter.</note><note type="collection">Chester Family Papers MS 25</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">4</note><note type="document">um031</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Boarding school students</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Jackson</name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1840-11-22"><abbr expan="November">Nov.</abbr> 22 1840</date></addrLine></address><salute>My Dear Mary Jane</salute></opener><p>This being the <date value="1840-11-22">22 of <emph>November</emph></date> the Birth day of my first born the day that I first experienced the delight of being a Mother I cannot deny myself the pleasure of writing to you and as it is the first birth day you have passed from under the paternal Roof I know that you will be glad to know that you were affectionately remembered by us all, you recollect you asked me what I should do for you on your birth day, you recollect I replied that I would Pray for you, I Pray my Daughter that you may live to see many returns of this day that you may be permitted to return to the Bosom of your Parents the same affectionate and Pure child that you were when you left us, that you may be delivered from temptation and sin and that God may take you in his especial keeping</p><p>I received your very good letter on yesterday it gave me much pleasure I must congratula<add place="supralinear">te</add> you on your improvement in letter writing <pb n="[2]"/> </p><p>I fear my dear daughter you repine too much at being from home you must keep the object <orig reg="steadily">stedily</orig> in view and that will console you, you are now of an age to know the importance of a good Education, <emph>Beauty</emph> and Fortune are nothing with out the refinement of Education that is our only object in keeping you from us, I should like to have our daughter called the accomplished Miss Chester, we were much pleased with your record, your Pa-pa would have acknowledged the receipt of it but for his great press of business I think it an excellent plan to send monthly records your <name type="person">Aunt Narcissa</name>  writes by <orig reg="today's">to days</orig> mail she will tell you about her sickness she will visit you at Christmas your Brother <name type="person">John</name> will go with her your Old Friend <name type="person">Frank patterson</name> wishes to go also, she is anxious to go to school at the Institute she will Board with her relations that lives in <name type="place">Columbia</name>,</p><p>Our Town is dull and gloomy the Democrats in particular on the subject of <orig reg="Politics">Politicks</orig> you are to young to meddle particularly as the Rector of the Institute is a Whig it is important that you should not displease him in any way you know that as republicans that we should submit to the will of the majority</p><p>Present me affectionately to the <name type="person">Walkers</name></p><closer><salute>Your affectionate Mother</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Elizabeth">E</abbr> Chester</name></signed><add place="up left side of page">it is possible you have no winter dresses you must have a common <unclear>musetin delana for</unclear></add></closer></div1><div1 type="letter"><opener><address><addrLine>Thursday Evening</addrLine><addrLine><date value="1840-11-26">26th</date></addrLine></address><salute>My dear Daughter</salute></opener><p>I received your letter bearing date <date value="1840-11-20">20th</date> <abbr expan="ultimo">ulto</abbr> I was greatly shocked to hear that the Institute had been so nearly burned are you still in the third Story! <name type="person">Mr Smith</name> promised your Father that you should have a room in the second Floor I should be much better satisfied if you were in a lower room on the subject of Insurrection I think we need have no present fear but when they find that <name type="person">Harrison</name> cannot free them then we may look for troubles before that time my dear I hope you will be with us do not be disturbed by such <orig reg="nonsense">nonsince</orig>, the Whigs Illuminate Our town to night I had almost forgotten to tell you that <name type="person">Miss Rebecca Moles</name>is to be married <gap reason="hole in document"/> night to <name type="person">Mr Compton</name> the Father of Carol you recollect her she lived at <name type="person">Mrs Thias's</name> he has five Children a good begin<add place="supralinear">n</add>ing for a young Lady the wedding is entirely private all our relations are well and unite in affectionate Love to you Your sister <name type="person">Martha</name> will write next week <orig reg="also">allso</orig> John you shall have letters more regularly hereafter it is getting late you must write your letters give us great pleasure and relieve us from mad</p><p><add place="bottom of page">The</add> <add place="up left side of page">you of course do not any one read my letters</add> <pb n="[4]"/> uneasiness the children and Papa write with me in Love to you,</p><closer><salute>Your affectionate Mother</salute><signed><name type="person">Elizabeth Chester</name></signed><address><addrLine><name type="person">Miss <abbr expan="Mary Jane">M J</abbr> Chester</name></addrLine></address><add place="above address"><name type="place">Jackson</name> <date value="1840-11-27"><abbr expan="November">Novr</abbr> 27</date> <emph>Paid 18 &frac34;</emph> <lb/> <emph>Elizabeth Chester</emph></add><address><addrLine><name type="person">Miss Mary Jane Chester</name></addrLine><addrLine>Female Institute</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Columbia</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></name></addrLine></address><add place="below address, upside down">My Dear Mother <lb/> <date value="1840-11-22">22 Nov 1840</date> <lb/> <emph>Twelve</emph> months from this <emph>day</emph>, She was consigned to the Silent Tomb. &mdash;</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
