<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um042"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1835 Apr. 27, Moor[e]field, Hardy C[oun]ty, V[irgini]a [to] Leroy  B. Gaston Esq[uire] / A. Anderson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Anderson, A.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um042</idno><idno>OCLC: 50281238</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1835 Apr. 27, Moor[e]field, Hardy C[oun]ty, V[irgini]a [to] Leroy  B. Gaston Esq[uire] / A. Anderson </title><author>Anderson, A.</author><date value="1835-04-27">April 27, 1835</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written to Leroy B. Gaston from A. Anderson on April 27, 1835. In the letter, Anderson discusses the political climate in Virginia, financial matters, and social events, including the Winchester Presbytery that is in town.</note><note type="collection">Porter-Rice Family Letters MS154 (letters1830-1839)</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">2</note><note type="document">um042</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Virginia Politics and government 1775-1865</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><name type="place"><orig reg="Moorefield">Moorfield</orig></name>, <name type="place">Hardy, <abbr expan="County Virginia">Cty. Va.</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1835-04-27">April 27th 1835 </date>&mdash;</addrLine></address><salute><foreign rend="lat">Meus Charissimus Amicus</foreign>:</salute></opener><p>Your's of <date value="0000-02-02"><abbr expan="February">Feby.</abbr> 2nd</date> past marked the 13th came to hand in the early part of the present month; an answer to which has been purposely deferred until this moment. You are aware that the month of April is to our profession in <abbr expan="Virginia">Va</abbr> a month of business &mdash; The <abbr expan="Circuit Superior">Cir. Sup.</abbr> Courts throng us &mdash; Our Elections take place &mdash; &amp; all the et ceteras of such like occasions. In addition to all this &mdash; our muddy &mdash; haggard village, has in the providence of God been <orig reg="honored">honoured</orig> with the Session of the Winchester Presbytery &mdash; which took its leave of us this morning. For these reasons &amp; with the expectation of deriving some interesting intelligence from these scenes &mdash; I intentionally <emph>forewent</emph> (will that were pass) my usual promptitude, in replying to your anxiously looked for &amp; welcomely <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr> epistle. It is my purpose now to redeem my pledge &amp; to gratify, in part at least, your wishes &mdash; You emphatically urge me <emph>to write</emph> &mdash; but what shall I write <emph>?</emph> Nothingness &amp; vanity seem inscribed upon every thing around me &mdash; &amp; an incubus of dejection is loading me with its leaden weights. The heavens are shrouded in darkness &mdash; &amp; my mind sympathetically partakes of the gloom &mdash; With such feelings &amp; under such circumstances &mdash; you will realize but little pleasure in the presence of a barren &amp; lifeless epistle. But such as I have I give out thee.</p><p>You express the wish &mdash; that when I started my friend <name type="person">Joe Fellows</name> for the South &mdash; I had stuck to him &amp; thus been dragged out of this slough of despond &mdash; Our wishes are mutual. But dire necessity or the illusions of hope &mdash; have fixed me to the spot &mdash; &amp; <abbr expan="although">altho</abbr> it is any thing other than an <emph>oasis</emph> &mdash; I can not tear myself from it &mdash; <emph>as yet</emph>. True I am not of the seed-royal &mdash; Either by descent or adoption nor will I ever be by matrimonial amalgamation. But having a little of the old roman spirit in me &mdash; I cannot but assert my rights &mdash; nor shall it e'er be said of me &mdash; "He was banished the land of his birth or adoption" &mdash; In plain English &mdash; you know <emph>Efforts</emph> have ever been making by some of the <emph>line</emph> to expel me from their borders &mdash; &amp; to fix the brand of a <emph>stranger</emph> upon my forehead &amp; exclude me from their little <abbr><unclear>comth</unclear></abbr> of privileges &mdash; &amp; the <emph>means</emph> have been as various as their desires. But in all have they been frustrated &mdash; My practice has been flourishing. <pb n="[2]"/> My prospects are daily increasing &amp; the tables are completely turned The spoke of my wheel of fortune is now in the ascendant &mdash; &amp; I have no doubt ere long &mdash; the flag of truce will be hoisted &amp; myself invited to a parley &mdash; An ambassador or two have already <orig reg="honored">honoured</orig> me with their presence &mdash; But I am not to be wooed or won &mdash; Just as soon as I learn that, mine enemies are convinced of the futility of their efforts &amp; designs to expatriate me &mdash; I will pack up my little household &amp; visit your or some other land &mdash; You may think strangely of this course of conduct, but its just me &mdash; I ask no <orig reg="favors">favours</orig> &mdash; I brook no insults &mdash; I stand upon my own hook.</p><p>Our elections are going on &amp; Virginia is becoming herself again &mdash; The newfangled Whiggism is crumbling under the burthen of its own discordant materials &mdash; Hardy has again reelected <name type="person">Mullin</name> &mdash; but under a hard pace &mdash;<name type="person">Mr Leigh</name> will doubtless be instructed out of his illgotten seat in the <name type="place"><abbr expan="United States">U. S.</abbr></name> Senate &mdash; The panic phantom has <orig reg="vanished">evanished</orig> &mdash; &amp; the deluded people are awaking to their senses &mdash; &amp; retrieving their injured rights &mdash; <name type="person">A. J. Cunningham</name> who was a candidate, declined, having ascertained his nullifying doctrines would not take.</p><p>The Presbytery has been in Session a few days &mdash; There is no extraordinary excitement on the subject of religion &mdash; Some good has been done &mdash; but the number of those who come up to the help  <sic corr="of">of of</sic> the Lord against the mighty is small. <orig reg="Moorefield">Moorfield</orig> is something like <name type="place"><unclear>Gilboa</unclear></name> &mdash; Her youth are fonder of the midnight more than the cross &mdash; Your friend &amp; acquaintance <name type="person">Miss Caroline Seymour</name> was married a few weeks ago to <name type="person">Job Hatton</name> of <name type="person">Peter</name> &mdash; Thus they go &mdash; All in the <emph>Friendschoff</emph> &mdash; as the Dutch say &mdash; A. E. W. and L. D. are the only relics of the Creek &mdash; As I seldom get up in that region &mdash; I know but little about them &mdash; And  your hint &mdash;  is malapropos &mdash; I have no <emph>penchant</emph> for either the <emph>oldest</emph> or the <emph>youngest</emph> of either Uncle Job or David &mdash; <emph><orig reg="daughters">darters</orig></emph> !!! <abbr expan="A. J. Cunningham">A. J. C.</abbr> is still in <unclear>status quo</unclear> &mdash; &amp; commodities of this kind are by no means <pb n="[3]"/> in demand here &mdash; A <name type="person">Mr Williams</name> from <name type="place">Shenandoah</name> has taken on of the <name type="person">Miss Craigins</name> to himself &mdash; He had his eye on a fortune but like the chaps who put his finger upon the flea &mdash; when he came to look for it, it <orig reg="wasn't">was 'nt</orig> there. Thus fortune hunters receive hard fare in these parts &mdash; A little <orig reg="avaricious">avaritious</orig> wretch took it in his head a few weeks ago to marry the widow <name type="person">Heath</name> &mdash; soon after the honey moon he became jealous &mdash; &amp; well he might &mdash;  for she <orig reg="always">all ways</orig>  would play second fiddle &mdash; &amp; threatened to shoot her &mdash; for this threat she put him in durance vile; and her creditors are now converting his anticipations of a fortune into all the dire realities of misfortune. Another instance &amp; I have done &mdash; Your kind offices in behalf of <name type="person">D. H. Coyner</name> have gained you a name not soon to be forgotten &mdash; He is an outcast &mdash; &amp; gives hopes of little promise &mdash; Chill penury is staring him in the face &mdash; His name is seldom mentioned &amp; if so &mdash; only with contempt &mdash; Beware in future &mdash; for whom you act as proxy. <name type="person">Mrs Foote</name> is dead &mdash; And this morning all the Physicians were sent for by <name type="person"><abbr expan="George">Geo.</abbr> Cunningham</name> who is dangerously ill &mdash; I have not heard from him since &mdash; The <orig reg="whooping">hooping</orig> cough &amp; scarlet fever have been fatal here during the winter. <name type="person">Mr Scott</name> is teaching &amp; is well <gap reason="hole in document"/> <unclear>nize?</unclear> &mdash; <name type="person">Phil. Williams</name> is married again to a <name type="person">Miss Dunbar</name> of <gap reason="hole in document"/> <orig reg="whether">whither</orig> he has gone to reside. A. J. C. talks of removing westward &mdash; but I shall believe it when I see him start or hear he has gone &mdash; <name type="person">James Heiskell</name> has resumed his mercantile operations at the Burg &mdash; His wife will not leave <abbr expan="Virginia">Va.</abbr>  Thus I have given you a rapid &amp; desultory sketch of what I thought would be most interesting to you &mdash; Now a word for myself. I am still a <emph>single</emph> man: but on the high road to Hymen's Court &mdash; It may be I shall have the pleasure in my next to sing a different song &mdash; But <foreign rend="fre">nous venous</foreign>. According to your request I sent in for mathematical instruments &mdash; &amp; am rapidly increasing my library &mdash; I think I shall during the summer or early in the fall <emph>pack up</emph> &amp; <emph>put</emph> &mdash; Look out for me &mdash; If I dont &mdash; &amp; you come in next winter &mdash; you can have my good company on your return &mdash; should you desire it &mdash; My funds are low &mdash; &amp; some how or other I can't hoard up &mdash; But if I ever make a break &mdash; there is no telling where or when I stop &mdash; I say <emph>write</emph> &mdash; do <pb n="[4]"/> My father is anxious to remove to the west &amp; is making rapid progress in his preparatory measures &mdash; So soon as he has settled down again I shall be contented &amp; free as air &mdash; If I succeed in winning a little <name type="person">Eliza</name> of <name type="place">Woodstock</name> &mdash; who is now wearing her studying cap &mdash; I am off for <name type="place">Illinois</name> &mdash; If defeated &mdash; why then I must look out for a supper somewhere else &mdash; Write to me &mdash; &amp; what thou doest, do quickly &mdash;</p><closer><salute>Yours Affectionately</salute><signed><emph><name type="person">A. Anderson</name></emph></signed><address><addrLine><emph><name type="person"><abbr expan="Leroy">L.</abbr> B. Gaston <abbr expan="Esquire">Esq</abbr></name></emph></addrLine></address><address><addrLine>Moorefield <date value="1835-04-28"><abbr expan="April">Apr</abbr> 28 1835</date> <add place="above address"><emph>25</emph></add></addrLine><addrLine>Leroy B. Gaston <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Litchfield</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Jackson County</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Arkansas Territory</name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
