<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um046"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1838 Dec. 8, Grenada [to] E. H. Porter, Memphis, Tennessee / H. A. Robinson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Robinson, H. A.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um046</idno><idno>OCLC: 50286254</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1838 Dec. 8, Grenada [to] E. H. Porter, Memphis, Tennessee / H. A. Robinson </title><author>Robinson, H. A.</author><date value="1838-12-08">December 8, 1838</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated December 8, 1838 to E. H. Porter of Memphis, Tennessee from H. A. Robinson regarding business that Robinson is attending to for Porter.</note><note type="collection">Porter-Rice Family Letters, MS-154, 1830-1839</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">2</note><note type="document">um046</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Business enterprises</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><add place="supralinear">12&frac12;</add></addrLine><addrLine><name type="person">Mr. <abbr expan="Ethel Henry">E. H.</abbr> Porter</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Memphis <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name></addrLine></address><pb n="[2]"/><address><addrLine><name type="place">Grenada</name><date value="1838-12-08">December the 8th 1838</date><name type="person">Mr. Porter</name></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>I am happy to inform you that I <orig reg="arrived here">arived hear</orig> on Sunday evening after I left there I come twelve <add place="supralinear">miles</add> the first day and <orig reg="stayed">staid</orig> with the <orig reg="wagons">waggons</orig> that night next morning left them and Come on I had a very pleasant trip winding round and over the hills but <orig reg="very lonesome">verny loansome</orig> and <orig reg="tiresome">tiresom</orig> when I got <orig reg="here">hear</orig> I found <orig reg="there">thare</orig> road a great deal of fixing to do before I would be properly fixed to go to work <orig reg="there is">theres</orig> no Shop. I got them to getting timbers they have the wall up and quit it I have got me a work bench<orig reg="made"> maid</orig> and has it render a shelter and a working away as hard as I Can I have not got no handle timber yet when I speak to the overseer about it he <orig reg="don't">dont</orig> appear to give me much <orig reg="satisfaction">Salifaction</orig> about it I have two hundred beams got out we are looking for <name type="person">mr gorian</name> every day when he Come I think he will <add place="supralinear">have</add> things <orig reg="regulated">regalated</orig> I am well and <orig reg="tolerable">tollerable</orig> well pleased with the Country but the prices for Clothing is out of the <orig reg="question">questing</orig> they ask $15 for a pair of <orig reg="boots">bots</orig> <pb n="[3]"/> and <orig reg="everything">evrything</orig> else in <orig reg="proportion">propotion</orig> they charged me eight dollars for <orig reg="hauling">holling</orig> my tools <orig reg="here">hear</orig> I got them the next <orig reg="Wednesday">wednersday</orig> after I got <orig reg="here">hear</orig> <orig reg="we are keeping bachelors">we,are akeeping butcherlors</orig> hall and live well I want you to write to me and let me know how you all are and when you think you will have <orig reg="some">soom</orig> Castings ready for me <orig reg="there">thare</orig> is a small rise in the yellow busher now I want you to send me two or three of your oil stones with the first castings tell <name type="person">mr honsley</name> I think <orig reg="here">hear</orig> would be a very good place for his <orig reg="business">bissiness</orig></p><p><orig reg="please">pleas</orig> excuse my imperfect letter</p><closer><salute>yours with respects</salute><name type="person"><emph>H, A, Robinson</emph></name></closer></div1> </body></text></TEI.2>
