<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um053"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1848 May 22, Watertown [to] E. H. Porter Esq[ui]r[e], Memphis, Tenn[essee] / E[dward] E. Porter : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Porter, Edward E</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um053</idno><idno>OCLC: 50295808</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1848 May 22, Watertown [to] E. H. Porter Esq[ui]r[e], Memphis, Tenn[essee] / E[dward] E. Porter</title><author>Porter, Edward E.</author><date value="1848-05-22">May 22, 1848</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">The following document is a letter from Edward E. Porter to his father Ethel Henry Porter, dated May 22, 1848.  In the letter, Edward discusses his bad health and plans for school, and he sends his love and best wishes to others back home.</note><note type="collection">Porter-Rice Family Letters MS-154 (letters 1846-1849)</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">um053</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Watertown</name>, <date value="1848-05-22">May 22nd/48</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Father</salute></opener>  <p><name type="person">Uncle Hubert</name> <orig reg="received">recieved</orig> yours of the 9th two or three days ago I was glad to hear from you as it has been some time <orig reg="since">scince</orig> you wrote to me  but I suppose you expected me home all the while. But God in his all wise providence has ordered it otherwise and we must  cheerfully submit to his will.</p><p>I came from <name type="place">Bridgeport</name> here last Friday (<date value="0000-05-14">May 14</date>) to <del type="overstrike">enjoy</del> spend a week or ten days but I do not know how long I shall stay but shall be governed entirely by &caret; <add place="supralinear">my</add> health I saw <name type="person"><abbr expan="Doctor">Dr.</abbr> Elton</name> (Mothers favorite) Yesterday he <orig reg="stayed">staid</orig> some time and talked with me and said he did not think it would be safe for me to attempt to travel in my present state of health and thought I had better stay around here this summer and get strong and well before I attempted to travel or study I am very weak <gap reason="bottom of page cut off" desc="at present"/> and what is worse than <pb n="[2]"/> that I have the <emph>rheumatism</emph> in my legs and ankles so much so that it is with great difficulty I can walk around the house, this you know prevents my taking what exercise I should like to and makes it very <orig reg="disagreeable">disagreable</orig> for myself, still Doctor Elton thinks this will only be temporary and I hope it will prove so.  As to the disease in my head there is no change in it as I can <orig reg="perceive">percieve</orig>, and I <orig reg="think">thing</orig> that if this attack has had no effect on it, that nothing can.  Relative to my studies I can only say that I shall  not be able to attend to them this summer and as to <del type="overstrike">takin</del> resuming them in the fall it depends entirely <orig reg="upon">opon</orig> yourself you know my willingness to do what you think best.  but nevertheless I think that we have had pretty clear indications of Providence that it is not the course for me to take I leave the subject entirely to your better judgement = = = = = = </p><p>I do not, nor do any of my friends think it is best for me to come home this summer and although nothing would please me better still I have determined to stay here and at Bridgeport <orig reg="until">untill</orig> I hear from you Uncle Huberts family are all well but still I miss Grandpa and little <name type="person">Henry</name>  They all write <gap reason="bottom of page cut off"/> <pb n="[3]"/> tell <name type="person">aunt Eliza</name>  I do not understand about that baptismal scene but really I did not think that a woman that had arrived at her <emph>Old</emph> age would have been guilty of arranging herself in childish fooleries so much so that <emph>her</emph> own child did not know her tell &caret; <add place="supralinear">her</add> that <name type="person">Richard</name> and his <emph>sweet-tempered</emph> wife do not agree very well, they have parted two or three times this winter and at last came to blows, but I <orig reg="believe">beleave</orig> they are reconciled now</p><p>I saw <name type="person">Mary</name> and <name type="person">Jasman</name>, they send their love to you (Eliza) and wish you would write to them. The crops are all coming on here finely and every thing promises for a bountiful harvest <orig reg="everybody">every body</orig> is going crazy about rail-roads</p><p>They are building a rail road from <name type="place">Waterbury</name>  to join with the <name type="place">New York</name> and <name type="place"><abbr expan="New">N</abbr> Haven</name> rail road &amp; which is being graded and they think will be in operation by the first of January I have money enough I think to last me through the summer and pay my expenses but if you should have occasion to send any one do not send <emph><name type="place">South Carolina</name></emph> money Give my love to all and Mary and write to <name type="person">Ben</name>  and tell him to write to me and give me his direction tell <name type="person">Pres</name> to write often Write me soon and tell me what your plans are</p> <closer><salute>Yours <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;c</abbr></salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Edward">E</abbr> E Porter</name></signed><pb n="[4]"/> <address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Ethel Henry">E. H.</abbr> Porter</name> <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Memphis</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name></addrLine></address></closer> </div1></body></text></TEI.2>
