<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um051"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1848 Mar. 7, Memphis, Tennessee [to] Ed Porter, Bridgeport, Connecticut / B. N. Sawtell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Sawtell, B. N.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um051</idno><idno>OCLC: 50286936</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1848 Mar. 7, Memphis, Tennessee [to] Ed Porter, Bridgeport, Connecticut / B. N. Sawtell </title><author>Sawtell, B. N.</author><date value="1848-03-07">March 7, 1848</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written by Benjamin Sawtell of Memphis Tennessee to his nephew Ed Porter in Bridgeport Connecticut. Benjamin tells his nephew about the latest events at home, including several marriages, and available females.</note><note type="collection">Porter-Rice Family Papers, MS-154, 1846-1849</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">um051</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>Wit and social status</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Memphis</name> <date value="1848-03-07">March 7th 1848</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear <abbr expan="Edward">Ed</abbr></salute></opener><p>Knowing where you are I am going to take time to write you a letter. The last one I wrote I sent by <name type="person">Mr Candee</name> which I hope you have received by this time. I know you are raging because I have not written before but it was because I did not know where to find you the reasons you know.</p><p>There has been considerable going on lately in the shapes of weddings, parties, <abbr expan="and et cetera">&amp;c &amp;c</abbr>  1st <name type="person">Miss Margeret Rudisill</name> has launched forth, she has married a young Doctor,, 2nd <name type="person"><emph>Miss Matilda Miller</emph></name> (alias) <emph>Duck</emph> has taken wings and flew away with <name type="person">Mr Gagg</name>. They were married <abbr expan="February">Feb</abbr> 29th at 7 o'clock in the evening out at her Fathers in the country. I was there, went with <name type="person">Sally Hicks</name>, <name type="person">Bunyan  Miller</name> with <name type="person">Frank Grant</name>. Two young gentleman <name type="person">Mr Taggs</name> friends stroke up with <name type="person">Miss Harriet Miller</name> and <name type="person">Miss Frank</name>. We had rare times I tell you <emph>Bob</emph> I flourished around with Miss Frank extensively, she is as pretty as ever, but she has no charms for me, as my affections lay another quarter, keep dark.. 3rd and last but not least, <name type="person">Miss Sally Hicks</name> to<name type="person"> Mr Wallace</name> the <orig reg="Colporteur">Colpeurteur</orig>. They were &caret;<add place="supralinear">married</add> on the night of the 1st of March by <abbr expan="Reverend">Rev</abbr> <name type="person">G. W. Coons</name>, (who married the others) at our house, it rained like fun, just poured down, nobody here but Mr Coons, <name type="person">Mr &amp; Mrs Garrison</name> and home folks. Nobody knew anything about it until just at sundown, when Aunt Eliza  always ready commenced making the wedding cake, and getting supper. Everything went off fine. I could fill this letter by enlarging on the merits of said marriages but time and paper will not allow, but I am in hopes to give you the particulars by the word of mouth soon. The next night I went to a party <pb n="[2]"/> down in <name type="place">South Memphis</name> given to Mrs Gagg. I went down with Bunyan, all the girls going in a Hack, it was very muddy but we get along very well. I enjoyed myself very well indeed. <orig reg="coming">Comming</orig> home Bunyan fell down and the lantern went out and we had to plod along in the dark, mud something less than knee deep, you know how our mud is. I had to study very hard to make up for the lost time which  I did.&mdash; I am reading Cicero, also <abbr expan="third">3d</abbr> book of Xenphone, Studying Algebra and Euclid. I expect I shall be very deficient in my studies but I am in hopes to get better when I get up there.&mdash; We have some cool weather also pleasant, to day is a fine, <unclear>barnling</unclear>, day, perfectly delightful, a spring day.&mdash; We have had quite a <orig reg="revival">revibal</orig> of  religion here lately 13 joined our Church last communion. <name type="person"><abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr> Cotter</name> and <name type="person">Junuz Means</name> also have professed. <name type="person">Dr Hall </name>preached, an excellent preacher&mdash;There has been a revival at Marys School <name type="person">Miss Kate Palmer</name> has professed. Mary is among the anxious Pray for her, that she may be converted &mdash; I see you are mistaken about my weight and height. I <emph>only</emph> weigh 143 lbs and am some <emph>less</emph> than 6 feet. I am quite healthy but have to keep pouring medicine down me to be so. Memphis has been quite healthy. I am sorry you have been sick but I hope you will get better. We had a letter from <name type="person"><abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr> Hinds</name> a day or two ago&mdash; When you see Frank just tell him if he pleases to answer my letter that I write some 6 months ago&mdash; Pres is going to School, he is well, also his Mother is well, They wished to be remembered by you.&mdash; You must write to Bunyan Miller he wishes to be remembered by you also his sisters. He <orig reg="stayed">staid</orig> with me last night.&mdash; <name reg="person">Tom Phoebes</name> is in <name reg="place">Arkansas</name> at work all the other boys are well, and often speak of you, all send their best respects also the Young <orig reg="laidies">laides</orig> send their compliments <pb n="[3]"/> I wish you would send me a <orig reg="catalogue">catalouge</orig> of  Yale College if you can conveniently, I should like to have one. I hope you <abbr expan="will not">wont</abbr> throw and move cups <orig reg="across">accross</orig> the table or tie any more boys to fence. Excuse my liberty, <emph>but it is a serious</emph> affair, breaking up the crockery and spilling the contents &mdash; There is not much news, only a man shot or stabbed now and then to keep up excitement.&mdash; <abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr><name type="person"> Tom Thumb </name> has been in town some days back I saw him, he is 23 years old weighs <abbr expan="25 pounds">25lbs</abbr> and is <abbr expan="21 inches">21in</abbr> high, monster that, He talks fluently and take him all together he is a smart man and above all a <emph>great</emph> man&mdash; We are going to have plenty of telegraphs here soon &mdash;  All the Family is well both your Father and Mother, also Jessie who is growing pretty very fast <name type="person">Mrs Wallace</name> is well as can be expected from circumstances. Doney is well, Also Father and Mother. <name type="person">Uncle John</name>  and <name type="person">Aunt Silvia</name> also <unclear>Nachez</unclear> fat and hearty, after all, all are well <gap reason="seal covers paper"/> I hope you  will write soon &mdash; Excuse my hand writing I am in a hurry. &mdash; This is a beautiful day, fine day to walk out with the girls, which I think I will improve I wonder if you have any Beauties up there that can compare with those of the Sunny South or <emph>Stars</emph> of the West if  you have, give them my compliments. "Fannie is well, keep dark" My compliments to Miss Julia. Best respects to <name type="person">Mr &amp; Mrs Jones</name>, also to your schoolmates and roommate. Good Bye Please write soon and tell me a heap of news. How is cousin Marian, Charming as a rose and fair as a Lily I reckon. Except the best wishes for your health and <orig reg="success">sucess</orig> in studies and among the girls &mdash;</p><closer><salute>from your friend and Uncle</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Benjamin">Benj</abbr> N. Sawtell</name></signed><address><addrLine><name type="place">Memphis</name></addrLine></address><name type="person"><abbr expan="Edward">Ed</abbr> E. Porter</name><pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine><name><abbr expan="Edward">Ed</abbr> E. Porter</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Bridgeport Fairfield <abbr expan="Connecticut">Co.</abbr></name></addrLine></address><add><figure><figDesc>postmark</figDesc></figure></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
