<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um059"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1850 Jan. 12, New Albany [to] Father [Ethel Henry Porter] / Mary [Porter] : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Porter, Mary C.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um059</idno><idno>OCLC: 50296740</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1850 Jan. 12, New Albany [to] Father [Ethel Henry Porter] / Mary [Porter]</title><author>Porter, Mary C.</author><date value="1850-01-12">January 12, 1850</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written by Mary C. Porter to her father, Ethel Henry Porter, on January 12, 1850. In the letter, Mary discusses social events happening in Connecticut, where she is attending school, and back at home, and she thanks her father for her Christmas gifts.  Mary also briefly mentions her desire to find her daguerreotype, which was an early form of photography.</note><note type="collection">Porter-Rice Family Letters MS 154 (Letters 1850-1851)</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">4</note><note type="document">um059</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Boarding school students</item><item>Southern States</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">New Albany</name> <date value="1850-01-12">12th <abbr expan="January">Jan.</abbr> 1850</date></addrLine></address><salute>My dear Father</salute></opener><p>I <orig reg="received">receved</orig> your letter containing the money for myself &amp; <name type="person">Mr Anderson</name>, I gave the check to him, I will ask him for the excess to send with this, I was very much pleased with the content of my box.</p><p>Did you send the boys a box this Christmas, I know it would be very acceptable, but I do not think they were expecting one,</p><p>I also received the package with the <orig reg="trimming">triming</orig>, and the <emph>litter</emph> which I kept, I will tell you all about it next time I see you.</p><p>I was very much pleased with the <orig reg="trimming">triming</orig>, it was just what I wanted, and I had not been able to get any to <unclear>sent</unclear> me here, I had gotten some <unclear>birt</unclear> it was very narrow and would not seem <unclear>prithy</unclear>, it was very cheap, and will do for some thing else. I have not been able to get my dress made but I will have it done next week. I think it will make up very prettily, and I like it because it is different from all the rest of my dresses, I was very much <pb n="[2]"/> surprised when I opened the package, I expected it was a book paper or something of the kind.</p><p>I <orig reg="received">receved</orig> your letter mailed the 2nd on the the 8th just one day after you expected I would, I was very glad to get it as I had not had a letter for some as <name type="person"><abbr expan="Edward">Ed</abbr></name> &amp; <name type="person"><abbr expan="Benjamin">Ben</abbr></name> have gotten so that they never think of writing to me, or at least very seldom, I wish you would remind them of it, tell them I am still here,</p><p>You say it is very cold down there that you have snow almost 10 <abbr expan="inches">in</abbr> deep,  we are ahead of you there we have had  snow almost two feet deep, and Oh! the coldest weather I <abbr expan="do not">dont</abbr> believe it could be much worse in <name type="place"><abbr expan="Connecticut">Ct.</abbr></name> than it was here for a few days, but we were all better than you we went to church, There were a great many sleighs then in use, and how merry the bells did sound,</p><p>I <orig reg="understood">under stood</orig> also that they had some sleighing in <name type="place">Hanover</name>, I had a call from <name type="person">Miss Helen Ruse</name> and her brother New Years, they told me all about Hanover, You recollect the <name type="person">Miss Finley</name> who was sick all <orig reg="summer">sumer</orig>, she <orig reg="has">hase</orig> died since we left, all the rest are well,</p><p>I <orig reg="received">receved</orig> a letter from <name type="person">Fannie Lanphear</name> when I <orig reg="received">recived</orig> your last. She was very well, and sends her love to you and Mother, she does not go to school any where now, she had just heard from W. H. they are all <orig reg="getting">geting</orig> along finely there.</p><p>Had you heard that Old <name type="person">Mrs Washburn</name> was dead, I do not know when she died, but some time ago I think.</p><p>You did not tell me any thing that was done at home this Christmas, but I almost know that every body enjoyed <orig reg="themselves">themselfs</orig>. What company did Mother have, and did <pb n="[3]"/> she get any handsome presents, what did <name type="person">Jessie</name> get, Oh; I do wish I <orig reg="would">wuld</orig> have been with you all. I did not get any Christmas gifts, but I got a very handsome <orig reg="birthday">Birth day</orig> present, it was a very nice book, The Gem of the Seasons, it was given to me by my roommate, <name type="person">Edna Tanner</name>, she is a very <orig reg="pleasant">plesant</orig> good girl. we get along very well together.</p><p>I am very happy to hear that <unclear>Grant land</unclear> is getting along so well, I know Ben will be so much happier, I suppose she has given up the idea of returning there,</p><p>I am also very happy to hear the news from <name type="person">Uncle Huberts</name> you must give my love to them all, and by the by please send me <name type="person">Harriet's</name> direction as I have forgotten it then I will write to her,</p><p>Do you ever hear from <name type="person">Aunt <unclear>Marria Harills</unclear></name>, are all her family well, give my love to them all next time you write,</p><p>Please ask Mother if <name type="person">Mrs Starr</name> has ever told her that secret she said she was going to, if she has, I should be under very many obligations if she would tell me, and I now <orig reg="promise">promis</orig> perfect se&caret;<add place="supralinear">c</add>recy.</p><p>I do not <orig reg="recollect">reccollec</orig> whether I ever told you that <name type="person">Mr <unclear>Sterdevant</unclear></name> had called to see me, he gave me a very <orig reg="pressing">presing</orig> invitation to come and see his wife, do you wish me to go. Mr L wishes me to give his best respects to you &amp; Mother</p><p><name type="person">Mary Lehevill</name> is in town and has been here most of the winter, she expects to stay <orig reg="until">untill</orig> spring then go on east I believe, she has been to see me once since she came down, her health is not good, but all the family in H &mdash; are just well.</p><p>Last <orig reg="Sabbath">Sabath</orig> <name type="person">Mr Stevenson</name> our minister and a very good one <pb n="[4]"/> gave us an <orig reg="excellent">excelent</orig> New Years <orig reg="sermon">sermond</orig> his text was in the 90th <abbr expan="Psalms">Psl</abbr> 9: 12 verses, and in the afternoon we had an <orig reg="address">adress</orig> from <name type="person"><abbr expan="Reverend">Rev.</abbr> <emph>Mr Lantell</emph></name>, on the exerts of Christianity in the <orig reg="island">iland</orig> of <name type="place">Madara</name>, It did me so much good to see him, it reminded me <orig reg="so much">somuch</orig> of home, he did not recognize me.</p><p>I am very sorry that Mother cannot find my Daguerreotype but indeed I do not know any thing about it. I thought she put it away with the rest, and I can not <orig reg="imagine">imagin</orig> who has it, I am very sorry it is not there. I am afraid some of my friends will forget me if they do not have it to look at,</p><p>I must bring this letter to a close as I have some more letters today. Dear Father you must write to me every time you can, give much love to Mother tell her to write when ever she gets an <orig reg="opportunity">opertunity</orig>, give Jessie many kisses tell her I wish she would write to me, her last writing was very <orig reg="acceptable">acceptible</orig> Give my love to all my friends, and accept a great deal of love your self from</p><closer><salute>your devoted daughter</salute><signed><name type="person">Mary</name>,</signed><add place="below signature"><abbr expan="Post Script">P. S.</abbr> I was very sorry indeed to hear that you had been sick, I hope you are perfectly well long before now, you must let me know if any of you get much sick How does  <name type="person"> Aunt Eliza</name> get along give love to her <name type="person">John</name> and <name type="person"><orig reg="Lizzy">Lizy</orig></name></add><add place="bottom of page, sideways" rend="different hand, ink"><emph>From</emph> <lb/> <emph>Mary</emph> <lb/> <emph><date value="1850-01-12">12 <abbr expan="January">Jan</abbr> 1850</date></emph></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
