<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um062"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1840 Dec. 8,    Columbia F[emale] Institute, [Tennessee] [to] Mrs. Rob[er]t J. Chester / M[ary] J[ane] Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Chester, Mary Jane</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um062</idno><idno>OCLC: 50310256</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1840 Dec. 8,    Columbia F[emale] Institute, [Tennessee] [to] Mrs. Rob[er]t J. Chester / M[ary] J[ane] Chester</title><author>Chester, Mary Jane</author><date value="1840-12-08">December 8, 1840</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written by Mary Jane Chester to her mother, Elizabeth Chester, on December 8, 1840. In the letter, Mary Jane discusses events occurring at the Female Institute, her recent illnesses, and asks about events taking place at home.</note><note type="collection">Chester Family Papers MS 25 (December 1840)</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">5</note><note type="document">um062</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Boarding school students</item><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee -- History</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Columbia</name> <abbr expan="Female">F</abbr> Institute</addrLine><addrLine><date value="1840-12-08">December [8th], 1840</date></addrLine></address><salute>My dear Mama</salute></opener><p>Your long expected letter arrived here on Monday to very welcome hands I can assure you. <orig reg="Oh">O</orig>! I was so very happy to receive one from you and to hear how you <orig reg="honored">honoured</orig> my <emph>Birth Day</emph>. I would rather that you had <orig reg="honored">honoured</orig> it in that way than any other. I hope that you will write to me often now. I am so much pleased to hear that you intend writing more regularly <orig reg="now">nowt</orig>. mind I shall expect you to keep that promise.</p><closer><signed> <name type="person"><abbr expan="Mary Jane">M. J.</abbr> Chester</name></signed><add place="below signature"><abbr expan="Post Script">P.S.</abbr> Do you <orig reg="really">realy</orig> think that I have improved in my letter writing. I am afraid that you will not think so in this one for I have scarcely any time to write in. Tell me what did you think of the first letter I wrote to you. It was about Dusk <pb n="[2]"/> when <name type="person">Mr Brinkley</name> sent word to me that he would carry it for me. You know that I was very weak then. Well I sat down to try to write. I could think of nothing at all to write. I would have given any thing in this world to have had you by me then to show me how. but I had no person. I thought that there was nothing like the little word trying. You know that I had never written a letter in my life without you telling me every word to write. I folded and backed it. <name type="person">Cousin Jane</name> I suppose wanted it to look very nice as <emph>she</emph> had to <orig reg="carry">cary</orig> it. So it was she looks it open and backed it again. I wish that you would burn it up. I know that you did let any one see it. I <orig reg="believe">beleive</orig> that I have given you the History of my first letter. It was as difficult for me to write the second one.</add></closer><closer><add place="below signature">You have no idea how very difficult it is for me to get my things down town. I have not got near all of my Winter Clothing yet, because it so inconvenient to the <name type="person">Walkers</name> &amp; <name type="person">Mr Smith</name> will not permit us to go down town ourselves. So I think that it would be better for me to purchase my things from Mr Smith. He has said that the girls shall not get more than 50$ worth on any account whatever. I will get nothing more than is absolutely <orig reg="necessary">ness &caret; <add place="supralinear">e</add> cary</orig>. He says that rather than the girls should get me he would give them things. I am assure her that I would not accept of any of his presents.</add></closer><closer><add place="below signature">My dear Mother I do not think that you need be <pb n="[3]"/> <sic>be</sic> uneasy <orig reg="about">abut</orig> my sleeping in the 3rd Story as Mr <abbr expan="Smith">S</abbr> has had all the Chimneys burnt o &caret; <add place="supralinear">u</add> t. I do not think that there is any danger now. I <orig reg="believe">beleive</orig> he has no idea of changing my Sleeping Room. <lb/> <orig reg="Oh">O</orig>! I am so glad to hear that <name type="person">Miss Rebecca Moles</name> has got married at last. I think as you say she has a very good beginning for a young Lady. Tell Sister and <name type="person">Brother John</name> that I am looking very anxiously for their letters. Does not Brother R. write well <orig reg="enough">eneough</orig> to write to me. I think that he might answer my letter. I wrote <name type="person">Cousin Jane Rawlings</name> a letter the other day I hope that she will answer it soon I received a letter from <name type="person">Cousin Dick</name> the other day saying that <name type="person">Aunt Narcissa</name> had another of the over lasting Chills. I wish that I was there to help nurse her. <orig reg="Oh">O</orig>! I am so very sorry to hear that she is sick again. <abbr expan="I will">I'll</abbr> tell what I think will cure her (or at least it cured me) On my chill days <name type="person">Cousin Elen</name> made me lie in bed all Day take <emph>Quinine</emph> every <del type="overstrike">half</del> hour and a <add place="supralinear">Wine</add> Glass of Toddy every half hour. I did not want to take so much but they made me. Its true that It made my head very dizzy. but that was nothing compared with being well. Do tell her to try it. perhaps it will do her some good. Tell her that she must come up Christmas any how. I wish you would tell <name type="person">Aunt Butter</name> that she must excuse me for writing that very short letter to her on <name type="person"><unclear>Aunt N. paper</unclear></name>. She must answer it soon. I was very much astonished to hear that <name type="person">Aunt Frances</name> had gone to <name type="place">Shelby</name>. I did not expect that she would go down this winter. did she leave any of her children at our house. Give my love to Papa and my Sister &amp; Brothers <pb n="[4]"/> and one and all of my relations. I remain your ever affectionate Daughter. <abbr expan="Mary Jane">M. J.</abbr> Chester <address><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs <abbr expan="Elizabeth">E.</abbr> Chester</name></addrLine></address></add>  <add place="above address"><figure><figDesc>post mark for December 8</figDesc></figure>18&frac34;</add> <address><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs. <abbr expan="Robert">Robt.</abbr> J. Chester</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Jackson</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine></address> <add place="left of address">Mail &rcub;</add><add place="below address, upside down"><date value="1840-12-08">8 <abbr expan="December">Decr</abbr> 1840</date></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
