<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um069"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>   [Letter] 1841 Feb. 15, Jackson, Tenn[essee] [to] Mary Jane Chester, Female Institute, Columbus, Ten[nessee] / Elizabeth Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Chester, Elizabeth</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um069</idno><idno>OCLC: 50315155</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>   [Letter] 1841 Feb. 15, Jackson, Tenn[essee] [to] Mary Jane Chester, Female Institute, Columbus, Ten[nessee] / Elizabeth Chester</title><author>Chester, Elizabeth</author><date value="1841-02-15">February 15, 1841</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter, dated February 15, 1841, from Elizabeth Chester in Jackson, TN, to her daughter Mary Jane at the Female Institute in Columbia.  Elizabeth writes to inquire about the latest news of her daughter's schooling, and she also talks about visiting the Hermitage, Andrew Jackson's home in Nashville.</note><note type="collection">Chester Family Papers MS-25 (Feb 1841)</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">7</note><note type="document">um069</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Boarding school students</item><item>Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</item><item>Tennessee -- History</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Jackson <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1841-02-15"><abbr expan="February">Feb.</abbr> 15 1841</date></addrLine></address><salute>My Dear Child</salute></opener><p>I have <orig reg="deferred">defered</orig> writing to you <orig reg="until">untill</orig> to day because I knew that you had several letters last week and because I know that mine will give you more pleasure coming alone, I feel extremely anxious to receive a letter from you to hear how you acquitted yourself at the examination if you were first second third or fourth <emph>best</emph> write me all about it, what you were <unclear><emph>arvaid</emph></unclear> in and how you looked my have been with you continually for the last week, hoping and Praying for your success.  I hope at your next examination to be with you it is our present intention to go for you and spend a few weeks at the <name type="place">Hermitage</name> and at <name type="place">Nashville</name> my Old birth place, so you see you must improve while you have the opportunity I should like for you to show to advantage in Nashville give great attention to your walk and manners, an easy graceful carriage is all impor<pb n="[2]"/>tant, we have not received your records for the last two months I hope <name type="person">Mr Smith</name> will send them regularly your Pa, received a letter from him in which he mentions you in very high terms your amiable deportment and conciliating manners among your other good qualities  it was very pleasing to your parents and relations we still hope you will continue to deserve <orig reg="praise">prais</orig> we are all well <name type="person">John</name> <name type="person">Robert</name> &amp;  <name type="person">Martha</name> have commenced school again <name type="person">William</name> &amp; <name type="person">King</name> are as wild as two Mountain Deer their Pa, says that they shall not go to <orig reg="school until">shool untill</orig> the next session, <name type="person">Sam</name>  is decidedly the Flower of the <emph>flock</emph> the first of the fine smart and Beautiful do not be Vain when I say he is very much like his si<add place="supralinear">s</add>ter Mary Jane Martha is trying to teach him to call <orig reg="Sissy">Sisy</orig> Janie your <name type="person">Aunt Narcissa</name>  has had a rising on her right thumb or she would have written to you you must not wait for her to answer your letters I think it would be much better to write oftener to your Mother and Aunts than to write to so many of those foolish and <orig reg="envious">invious</orig> girls <name type="person">Eliza Bigelow</name> <name type="person">Bett Hale</name> and occasionally to <name type="person">Frank Patterson</name> are quite enough to write to be very guarded in what you write to any of them</p><pb n="[3]"/> <p><name type="person">Cousin Dick</name> is <name type="person">Miss Lyons</name> most devoted Bett Hale is expected every stage I like Elizabeth more than any of the Girls I think she is a high minded honorable girl, your Father will be to see you the first week in mar<add place="supralinear">c</add>h I need not say how much I want to see my dear dear child, but your absence must be <orig reg="borne">born</orig> and that we can only pray that the time  may pass happily and to you <unclear>poffitably</unclear> you must write me if you want me to send you any thing by your Papa, remember me affectionately to <name type="person">Jane</name> and <sic corr="and">and</sic> the <name type="person">Walkers</name>  Generally Papa Brothers and Sister Jain we love good wishes and prays for your continued health and happiness</p><closer><salute>your affectionate Mother</salute><signed><name type="person">Elizabeth Chester</name></signed><address><addrLine><name type="person">Miss <abbr expan="Mary Jane">M J</abbr> Chester</name></addrLine></address> <add place="bottom"><abbr expan="Post Script">PS</abbr> aunt <name type="person">Patsey</name> and <name type="person">Narcissa</name> and <name type="person">Mary Ormond</name> send their love Mary says she is going to write Janie a letter and that you must live with her when you come home affectionately <lb/> <abbr expan="Elizabeth Chester">EC</abbr></add><add place="bottom" rend="different hand">I will be in Columbia, <orig reg="about">abot </orig><date value="0000-02-26">26 <abbr expan="February">Feby</abbr></date> &mdash;.  affectionately, Father &mdash;</add> <pb n="[4]"/> <add><emph>Paid</emph> 18&frac34;</add><address><addrLine>Miss Mary Jane Chester</addrLine><addrLine>Female Institute</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Columbia <abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></name></addrLine></address><add>My Dear Mary Jane <lb/> <date value="1841-07-15">15 <abbr expan="February">Feby</abbr> 1841</date></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
