<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um074"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1841 May 14, Jackson, [Tennessee] [to] Mary J[ane] Chester, Female Institute, Columbia, Ten[nessee] / Elizabeth Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Chester, Elizabeth</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um074</idno><idno>OCLC: 50316131</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1841 May 14, Jackson, [Tennessee] [to] Mary J[ane] Chester, Female Institute, Columbia, Ten[nessee] / Elizabeth Chester</title><author>Chester, Elizabeth</author><date value="1841-05-14">May 14, 1841</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written by Elizabeth Chester to her daughter, Mary Jane Chester, on May 14, 1841. In the letter, Elizabeth acknowledges Mary Jane's recent illness, and wishes her better health. Elizabeth also informs Mary Jane of events happening at home and with her family in Jackson, Tennessee.</note><note type="collection">Chester Family Papers MS 25 (May-June 1841)</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">9</note><note type="document">um074</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Boarding school students</item><item>Tennessee -- History</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><date value="1841-05-14">May 14th <abbr expan="1841">41</abbr></date> <name type="place">Jackson</name></addrLine></address><salute>My Beloved Daughter</salute></opener><p>I this moment received your letter saying that you had a Chill it had made me <emph><orig reg="miserable">misirable</orig></emph> I was in hopes that you would be spared from any more sickness at least <orig reg="until">untill</orig> your return home Oh that I were only with you <name type="person">Mary Jane</name> I shall be in wretched <orig reg="until">untill</orig> I again hear from you if you have more Chills we will send immediately for you <abbr expan="although">altho</abbr> we are very anxious for you to stand your examination, I have great pleasure in telling you that <name type="person">Martha</name> has entirely recovered and is going to school <emph>again</emph> She had a very severe attack of <unclear>Bellious Pleurisy</unclear> in her sickness she looked up in my face and said Ma Ma, I do believe it is because I want to see <emph>Sissee</emph> so much that made me sick her Pa Pa promised her that she should go up for you <name type="person">Aunt Narcissa</name> will be certain to go for you bring you home though <name type="place">Nashville</name> stay one week at the <name type="place">Hermitage</name> <pb n="[2]"/> and at Nashville I am anxious that you should see your <name type="person">Uncle Jackson</name> <orig reg="once more">oncemore</orig> and I wish you to get several handsome dresses in <emph>Nashville</emph> your father is still absent on the trip he wrote you he was going to take I expect him <orig reg="tonight">to night</orig> or <orig reg="tomorrow">to morrow</orig> has been absent for nine days <name type="person">Uncle Sam</name> &amp; Family are still at their Farm in <name type="place">Shelby</name> all relations are well <name type="person">Cousin Jane P</name> <name type="person">Cousin Martha-Ann</name> <name type="person">Aunt <abbr expan="Butter">B</abbr></name> and Families all <del type="overstrike">to</del> dined with me today to feast on Strawberries just about dinner I received your letter you can have no <del type="erasure">idea</del> idea what a gleam it cast on all in Particular your Mother still I trust in a kind god that he will be merciful in his <emph>chastening</emph> and that we will all be <orig reg="spared">spaired</orig> to see each other again we must remember he <emph>chasteneth</emph> those <orig reg="whom">whome</orig> he <emph>loveth</emph> put your trust in him my <emph>Child</emph> he will comfort you in sickness guard you in health and save you in Eternity I say <emph>again</emph> my daughter trust in <emph>him</emph> I hope ere you receive this you will be entirely restored to your usual health a cheerfulness all unite in Love to you</p><closer><salute>your ever affectionate Mother</salute><signed><name type="person">Elizabeth Chester</name></signed> <pb n="[3]"/> <abbr expan="Post Script">P S</abbr> I shall write again next mail. I hope that it will bring me another letter from you saying that you are well be certain and write regularly ever your affectionate Mother <signed><abbr expan="Elizabeth">E</abbr> Chester</signed><address><addrLine> <name type="person">Miss <abbr expan="Mary Jane">M J</abbr> Chester</name></addrLine></address><add place="below address">Sam calls Sisy Jane very sweetly the time is drawing near when I hope you will have the pleasure of hearing him</add><pb n="[4]"/> <add place="above address"><figure><figDesc>post mark seal</figDesc></figure></add> <address><addrLine>Miss Mary <abbr expan="Jane">J.</abbr> Chester</addrLine><addrLine>Female Institute</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Columbia</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></name></addrLine></address><add place="left of address">Mail &rcub;</add> <add place="below address, upside down">My Dear Mother <lb/><date value="1841-05-14">14 May <abbr expan="1841">41</abbr></date></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
