<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um080"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1842 Sep. 6, Columbia, Tennessee [to] Col[onel] R[obert] J. Chester, Jackson, Tennessee / Mary Jane Chester      : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Chester, Mary Jane</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um080</idno><idno>OCLC: 50316711</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1842 Sep. 6, Columbia, Tennessee [to] Col[onel] R[obert] J. Chester, Jackson, Tennessee / Mary Jane Chester</title><author>Chester, Mary Jane</author><date value="1842-09-06">September 6, 1842</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">The following document is a letter dated September 6, 1842, written by Mary Jane Chester to her father Colonel Robert J. Chester.  Mary writes the letter after returning to the Female Institute in Columbia, TN, for the commencement of the new school year.</note><note type="collection">Chester Family Papers MS-25 (Jan-Dec 1842)</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">9</note><note type="document">um080</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Boarding school students</item><item>Tennessee -- History</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><add place="top, right" rend="different hand, ink">[<date value="1842-09-06">6 <abbr expan="September">Sept.</abbr> 1842</date>]</add><address><addrLine><name type="place">Columbia, Tennessee</name></addrLine></address><salute>My dear Father,</salute></opener><p>We arrived here safely on Wednesday evening without any accident, had a very pleasant trip up.  I begin to feel at home. Cousins <name type="person">Ellen</name> &amp; <name type="person">Sam</name> are as kind to me as they can possibly be, &amp; indeed all my relations are,&mdash; notwithstanding, I want to see you all <emph>very</emph> much.  I commenced School thursday morning, there are very few of  my old school mates here, I felt completely lost the first day, but have become acquainted with most of the girls now.  We have a very full school, the first day 107 scholars, more than was ever known to have been there so early in the session, they continue to come, three and four <orig reg="carriages">carriges</orig> a day.  <name type="person">Mr. Smith</name> put me in the first Senior, and I intend to try hard to do it justice, I have a great many studies to attend to; tell <name type="person">Aunt Narcissa</name> we have entirely a <emph>new set</emph> of Tutoresses</p><p>Dear Father ten months seems to be a very long time to be away from you all, much longer than before I left home.  I sometimes wish that I had not come, but as I am here <emph>study hard</emph> is the word.</p><p>Cousin <name type="person">William</name> started home yesterday. should have written <pb n="[2]"/> by him but thought that it would to sooner by mail, I believe that he was very much pleased with Mr Smith and the Institution You have no idea how much I disliked seeing him go without me little <name type="person">Alice Bemiss</name> did not like going to the Institution to board, having not one single acquaintance; three or four of the girls promised me to be kind to her, and take notice of her, she cried once or twice the first day but the second she more reconciled to it, I think she will satisfied after she becomes better acquainted.</p><p>Cousin <name type="person">Jane</name> &amp; <name type="person">Mary Eliza</name> seem very happy indeed, they are as gay as ever. the former looks more beautiful.  Cousin <name type="person">Knox's</name> wife is a very handsome and intelligent lady &mdash;</p><p>Give my love to Aunts <name type="person">Patsy</name>, Narcissa, <name type="person">Lydia</name> &amp; <name type="person">Frances</name>, and all of my dear Relations.  Kiss little <name type="person">Sam</name> and all the children.  Write very soon my dear Father and let &caret; <add place="supralinear">me</add> know how you all are.</p><closer><salute>Your ever affectionate Daughter</salute><signed><name type="person">Mary Jane Chester</name></signed><address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel Robert">Col R.</abbr> J. Chester</name></addrLine></address><pb n="[3]"/> <add place="left of address"><figure><figDesc>postmark for Sept. 6</figDesc></figure></add> <address><addrLine><abbr expan="Colonel Robert">Col. R.</abbr>  J. Chester</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Jackson</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine></address> <add place="below address" rend="different hand, ink">My Dear Mary Jane <lb/> <date value="1842-09-06">6 <abbr expan="September">Sep</abbr> 42</date></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
