<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl128">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] January 12, 1840, Clover Dale, Ten[nessee] [to] Mrs.  Ann Jane Bell, Cornplanter, P[ennsylvani]a / William B. Bell    : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Bell, Willliam B.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl128</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50541337</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] January 12, 1840, Clover Dale, Ten[nessee] [to] Mrs.  Ann Jane Bell, Cornplanter, P[ennsylvani]a / William B. Bell</title>
               <author>Bell, William B.</author>
               <date when="1840-01-12">January 12, 1840</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from William Bell to his sister Jane Bell, dated January 12, 1840. William writes that the Temperance Society of which  he is a member,  has elected him to give a public speech on the topic for July the 4th. He describes how much fun people are having due to a great snow fall. He has been sleigh riding and ice skating. He also asks Jane for a remedy for his swollen tonsil and sore throat.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">B:1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">F:19</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl128</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Temperance and religion</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Bell, William</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl128a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Clover Dale</name>
                     <date when="1840-01-12">January 12th 1840</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sister</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <add place="up left margin">Give my love to <name type="person">Martha</name> and say that I will give her a full letter shortly.</add> I received your letter of  <date when="1839-12-19">Dec 19th</date> and being always pleased to hear from you, its kind contents was well received, although I would rather you had delayed writing a few days longer until my last epistle had reached you, and then you would not have had so much cause to censure me. If you would consider for a moment, and see in what circumstances I am placed you would not be so harsh, A farm and a large quantity of stock with only one interested person to attend to it. Father often <choice>
                  <orig>complaines</orig>
                  <reg>complains</reg>
               </choice> of my not allowing sufficient time to converse with him.</p>
            <p> I am also very thankful for the instructions received in my youth, and do not think that the Doctor's kindness has been spent in vain, as a proof to the contrary I intend to deliver an address on temperance at <name type="place">New Hope</name> on the <date when="1840-07-04">fourth of July</date> next, and have the vanity to think that it will be pretty  <pb n="2" facs="sl128b.small.jpg"/> good. Our Temperance Society still prospers, its annual mee<del type="overstrike">t</del>ting was held on Christmas day, the President <name type="person">Mr. McNeilly</name> read an address composed by <name type="person">Dr. Ewing</name> of <name type="place">Nashville</name>, it was very good and applicable to the audience.</p>
            <p>At the close of the meeting a move was made for the President to appoint a committee of five to select one member of the Society, who should be compelled either to deliver an address, or procure a speaker in his place at the next meeting, I was selected as a suitable person. <name type="person">Abiram Caldwell</name> and <name type="person">James McNeilly</name> concluded to bear me company if I would make a public <emph>exposure</emph> on the <date when="1840-07-04">4th</date>
            </p>
            <p>You will be surprised to hear that <name type="person">Mrs. Robert Collier</name> was married on the <date when="1840-01-02">2nd</date> of this month to <name type="person">Mr. T  Gilbert</name>  brother in law to <name type="person">Sarah Walker</name>.</p>
            <p>I am pleased to say that you are mistaken respecting <name type="person">Mr. J Cunningham</name>, he professed religion five years since, and died very happy.</p>
            <p>Christmas week the snow fell to the depth of 15 inches, which is deep enough for your northern climate. We all  enjoyed ourselves more in the last two weeks <pb n="3" facs="sl128c.small.jpg"/> than we usually do in the holidays There was a select company of near twenty invited to <name type="person">Squire Caldwell</name>'s on Christmas evening, as the greater part of the young people were professors of religion, the evening was spent in innocent amusements and instructive conversation. The <choice>
                  <orig>ensueing</orig>
                  <reg>ensuing</reg>
               </choice> day I invited the company to my Fathers, where they spent the time very agreeably, in this way we paid our annual associated visits to the most of our <choice>
                  <orig>neighbours</orig>
                  <reg>neighbors</reg>
               </choice>. New Year's day I made a sleigh (not such a one as you are in the habit of seeing) but for this part of the <gap agent="damage"/> very genteel. I geared up two <choice>
                  <orig>waggon</orig>
                  <reg>wagon</reg>
               </choice>  horses, and accompanied by <name type="person">Margaret Mary Smith</name> and <name type="person">Mary Mills</name>, we took a circuitous route of seven miles to <name type="person">Squire Caldwell</name>s, the next day we increased our number to eight, and had a few upsets for a variety  . The pond in front of the house was frozen three inches deep, and in fine order for skating. I had received a present of a pair of skates from <name type="place">Nashville</name> a few days before, and had fine amusement, as it was the first evolutions I had performed on the ice in several years, it was quite a novelty and like <pb n="4" facs="sl128d.small.jpg"/> the backwoodsman's glass they congregated all the <choice>
                  <orig>neighbourhood</orig>
                  <reg>neighborhood</reg>
               </choice>.</p>
            <p>I have written to Brother for facts respecting the temperance societies in the <name type="place">United States</name>, if you have any pamphlets on the subject they would be gladly received, I think that speaking in public, will be serviceable to me at some <add place="center of page, rotated 90 deg." rend="different hand, ink">
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Charlotte <choice>
                              <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                              <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <date when="1840-01-15">
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Jany</abbr>
                              <expan>January</expan>
                           </choice> 15th </date>
                        <add place="right of return address">} 25</add>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="person">Mrs. Ann Jane Bell</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Cornplanter</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Venango County</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Pa</abbr>
                              <expan>Pennsylvania</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add> future period. You were so good in prescribing for <name type="person">Sarah</name>, I wish you would tell me how to reduce the <choice>
                  <orig>inflamation</orig>
                  <reg>inflammation</reg>
               </choice> in my th⁁<add place="supralinear">r</add>oat you know one of the tonsils is considerably swelled.</p>
            <p>The family join with me in love to you all</p>
            <closer>
               <salute> I remain you affectionate Brother</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">William B Bell</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
