<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl266">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1800 Jul. 17, Greenville [to] Joseph Hamilton, Russellville, K[entuck]y /  Joshua L.Wilson   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Wilson, Joshua L.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl266</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51237649</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1800 Jul. 17, Greenville [to] Joseph Hamilton, Russellville, K[entuck]y /  Joshua L.Wilson</title>
               <author>Wilson, Joshua L.</author>
               <date when="1800-07-17">July 17, 1800</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Joshua L. Wilson to Joseph Hamilton, dated July 17, 1800. Wilson laments his money troubles. He just lost some court cases that caused him to lose some of his land. Wilson asks Hamilton if he would be willing to trade land for horses. Wilson writes about the upcoming election. He is concerned for the reputation of Hamilton's area if an undesirable candidate, whom Wilson calls the King of Beasts, is elected. Apparently this man came to office by nefarious means, and it is proving difficult to remove him.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">12</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl266</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Real property</term>
               <term>Horse trading</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Wilson, Joshua L.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl266a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Greenville</name>
                     <date when="1800-07-17">July 17th 1800.</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I am now within one days ride of you and should be <choice>
                  <orig>extreemly</orig>
                  <reg>extremely</reg>
               </choice> glad to see you but cannot venture farther from home at this time.</p>
            <p>I received two letters from you, for which I thank you, but  have had no opportunity of returning answers. As to money I can assure you it is hard times, so much so indeed that I should think myself acting improperly should I fix upon any time for you to expect the money I owe you. If you could purchase land for horses I would let you have one or two very low, even at your own price. Judgments were obtained against me at the last term in Nelson for upwards of $400, for which much of my property I expect will be sacrificed, unless preserved by the <choice>
                  <orig>interposetion</orig>
                  <reg>interposition</reg>
               </choice> of friends, and they are scarce. My school is not large a <choice>
                  <orig>consederable</orig>
                  <reg>considerable</reg>
               </choice> part, of the proceeds of which, goes to support my little family; the balance to my <unclear>creditors</unclear> . What is the meaning of all this? "Have patience with me and I will pay you all."</p>
            <p>With this letter I send you two pamphlets. Accept of them as a small token of my regard; read them, and then write to me your opinion upon the performances — <pb n="2" facs="sl266b.small.jpg"/> With regard to our election I have not much to say. From the best information I am able to get upon the subject in our bounds the contest will lie between Lewis and Rowan. You may <choice>
                  <orig>easyly</orig>
                  <reg>easily</reg>
               </choice> Conceive for whom I shall vote when I tell you that laying aside personal attachments and personal enmities I feel myself bound in conscience to vote for the man whom I believe to be best qualified to fill the office, <choice>
                  <abbr>Viz.</abbr>
                  <expan>Videlicet</expan>
               </choice> to serve my country. — I hope, my dear Sir, that in <choice>
                  <orig>politicks</orig>
                  <reg>politics</reg>
               </choice> as well as religion you will dare to think for yourself. Form principles by extensive investigation and mature deliberation and give no man reason to hope that he can allure you, flatter you or force you out of the <choice>
                  <orig>pathes</orig>
                  <reg>paths</reg>
               </choice> of rectitude. Test men by measures and not measures by men.</p>
            <p>I am informed <name type="person">Mr Edwards</name> has declined his pole and the King of Beasts of course will be elected in your district. What a pity that your district is in a dilemma. Either elect the King destitute of decency, talents and good principles or by electing his opponent ruin your own reputation as a district both in point of morals and good sense. You may thank Mr. <choice>
                  <abbr>E</abbr>
                  <expan>Edwards</expan>
               </choice> 's declinature for this doleful situation. The people in the Atlantic states now <pb n="3" facs="sl266c.small.jpg"/> believe that the King of Beasts in the first instance imposed himself upon the people by <choice>
                  <orig>electionering</orig>
                  <reg>electioneering</reg>
               </choice> tricks and the very charming name Republicanism and that now it is difficult <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>is difficult</unclear> to get him shut out, but shut out by a man of no more respectability than Mr W the dignity of your district will be gone forever and a day.</p>
            <p>Amidst all that hustle through which we <gap agent="damage"/> pass through life let us never forget that "One thing is <choice>
                  <orig>needfull</orig>
                  <reg>needful</reg>
               </choice>." How altered would our world be if all men were using even as much diligence to make their heavenly calling and election sure as our candidates for congress are to secure their election to that house where a number of great, wise and sensible <gap agent="damage"/> consult about earthly things.</p>
            <p>I left my family in health last Sabbath <choice>
                  <orig>eve'ning</orig>
                  <reg>evening</reg>
               </choice>. Mackey is beginning to spell off the book tolerable well and to read in the ⁁<add place="supralinear">easy</add> places in the spelling book. I cast <name type="person">Mr. Downs</name> in my suit at <name type="place">Hartford</name> and of course will  be clear of one troublesome wreck so soon as I get my costs out of him.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Often write to</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Joshua L Wilson</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl266d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mr <name type="person">Joseph Hamilton</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Russellville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Ky</abbr>
                           <expan>Kentucky</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left of address">
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                        <expan>Doctor</expan>
                     </choice> Jones</name> }</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
