<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc105">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1839 May 3, Alexander, New York [to] George W. Sevier, Forest Hill, West Tennessee / Lyman C. Draper: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Draper, Lyman C.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc105</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1839 May 3, Alexander, New York [to] George W. Sevier, Forest Hill, West Tennessee / Lyman C. Draper</title>
               <author>Draper, Lyman C.</author>
               <date when="1839-05-03">May 3, 1839</date>
               <extent> 4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated May 3, 1839 from Lyman C. Draper in Alexander, New York to George W. Sevier of West Tennessee.  Draper is preparing biographical literature on "noble and daring" men of the Revolutionary War period.  This is Draper's second letter to Sevier seeking information on prominent figures of the early United States historical period.  This specific correspondence is in solicitation of information on General John Sevier, George W.'s father and who Draper calls the "patriarchal father of Tennessee."</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">John Sevier Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-1941 b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">17</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc105</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Sevier, John, 1745-1815</term>
               <term>Revolutionary War leaders</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50026255"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Draper, Lyman Copeland, 1815-1891</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc105a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Alexander, Genesee <choice>
                           <abbr>Co</abbr>
                           <expan>County</expan>
                        </choice>: <choice>
                           <abbr>N.Y.</abbr>
                           <expan>New York</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>May 3d 1839</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir, -</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your valued communication of the 9th February last was duly <choice>
                  <abbr>recd.</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice>, &amp; for the kindness you have done me I beg you will accept my grateful acknowledgments.  Were all, to whom I have applied for similar information, equally attentive, I should have less reason to regret many an important biographical desideratum.  The sketch you have so kindly furnished, places me in possession of many interesting facts hitherto unknown to myself, and such, I trust, as will prove serviceable to present and future generations.  I fondly hope you will not consider the tax upon your time and patience too great, should I venture to ask the favor of a second communication from you, giving me additional information.  I flatter myself, my dear sir, you will not think me importunate, when you reflect, that the pious labor in which I am engaged, is to rescue from forgetfulness and neglect the memory of meritorious individual- one, whose whole life was  undividedly devoted to his country's weal: And although his services were <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>prominantly</orig>
                     <reg>prominently</reg>
                  </choice>
               </unclear> conspicuous, I find only a solitary biographical work (-and I have consulted many-) in which <add>his name</add> is mentioned, and even that work disposes of the subject in less than three niggardly lines!</p>
            <p>I may not, in this instance, be deemed impertinent nor egotistical in volunteering the remark, that although a young man, I have paid no small attention to American biographical literature; and, finding it lamentably deficient, I formed the design of collecting the necessary materials, and supplying this deficiency to the best of my ability.  As instances of this  deficiency,  I may here observe, that of full a hundred and twenty continental and militia general officers, who served during the whole or a part of the Revolutionary war, our biographical works give a respectable notice of less than forty; and, with apparent reluctance, devote not more than half a dozen lines to each of, perhaps, ten or a dozen others!  The gallant and fearless pioneers of the West have been ungratefully neglected almost to a man.  Relative to many of them I have collected scattering facts; and in but a few instances have I any thing like regularly connected sketches. Gallant fellows they were who composed that hardy band; and, to gratify my own passionate predilections as a biographical  antiquary, I can afford to take especial pains to collect the scattering facts and incidents in the career of these men of iron nerve, and record for the instruction and admiration of future generations, their deeds of noble daring.</p>
            <p>Let me add one other explanatory remark before entering upon the subject- matter of my present inquiry.  I had thought perhaps, beside my chief biographical work which I design preparing for the press, I might be induced to attempt a "Biographical Memoir of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Gen.</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> John Sevier</name>, the patriarchal father of <name>Tennessee</name>, interspersed with incidents in the early annals <pb n="2" facs="sc105b.small.jpg"/> of that state."  I am inclined to think from what you have already communicated, added to the historical facts previously within my knowledge, that quite an interesting duodecimo volume of well nigh 250 pages might be prepared, somewhat resembling in character Flint's Life of Boone.  But in order to insure success to such a work, interest and usefulness must be combined - hence it would be indispensably necessary in my view, that further facts, incidents, characteristic anecdotes, <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> should be brought together and judiciously averaged.  To this end, your father's journal subsequent to the year 1796, his unpublished papers and letters if such there <add>are</add>, together with such additional information as yourself, brother and others might be able to furnish, would be of the greatest importance.  And pertinent sketches of some of the distinguished precursors in the settlement of Tennessee might very appropriately be appended to such a work - for instance of  <name>General James Robertson</name>,  <name>General Thomas Butler</name>,  <name>Colonel John Tipton</name>,  <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Gov.</abbr>
                     <expan>Governor</expan>
                  </choice> William Blount</name>,  <name>Gov. W.C.C. Claiborne</name>, <name>Judge William Cocke</name>, and  <name>Judge Joseph Anderson</name>  Be pleased to express without reserve your views in regard to the propriety and feasibility of such an undertaking.  I shall place great reliance upon your opinion in this matter.</p>
            <p>Soon after <choice>
                  <orig>recieving</orig>
                  <reg>receiving</reg>
               </choice> your letter, I wrote to <name>Judge White</name>, requesting a copy of his sub-Treasury speech, containing, as you informed me, a notice of the short lived <name>Republic of Franklin</name>; but in his reply he expressed his regret in not having a single copy remaining:  Have you a spare copy? - if so, please send it to me; and if you desire it, I will return it to you.  In my letter to the Judge, I intimated the use I intended to make of that historical incident; and he, in reply, took occasion to speak in general terms of your late father; and pardon me for introducing a quotation from his letter: "<name>George W. Sevier</name>, who lives near <name>Nashville</name> in  <name>West Tennessee</name>, is a son of Governor John Sevier by a second wife.  His eldest son, by a first wife, is also alive, and in  <name>Major James Sevier</name> residing near <name>Jonesborough</name> in  <name>East Tennessee</name>.  They are both highly respectable and will tell you nothing, respecting even their father, which they do not believe to be true."  I have just written to your brother, soliciting a variety of information - about the <name>American</name> leaders in command at <name>King's Mountain</name>, the Indian wars, General Butler &amp;c - and concluded with a string of queries which I will here introduce with some others - the two in reference to the battles at <name>Long- Island Flats</name> and <name>Nickajack</name>, Haywood's History would probably answer in a satisfactory manner, if I had that work.  But to the interrogatories:</p>
            <p>I learn from 'Flints Indian Wars of the West,'   that your father, in 1774, held the commission of Captain under <name>Earl Dunmore</name>, governor of <name>Virginia</name>, - was he engaged in the sanguinary battle of <name>Point Pleasant</name> fought <pb n="4" facs="sc105d.small.jpg"/> that year?- and, in 1777. Gov. <name>Richard Caswell</name>, of <name>North Carolina</name>, gave him the commission of lieutenant-colonel of the <name>Washington</name> regiment of militia under <name>Colonel Carter</name>- who was this <choice>
                  <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Carter?- Who commanded the <name>Tennesseeans</name> in the battle with the <name>Cherokees</name> fought at Long-Island Flats, in June, 1776?- and at Nickajack in 1794?- When you say Gen. Sevier was engaged in "about 36 campaigns", I infer that you use that word in the sense of Expeditions?- According to your account, your father could have been only about thirty-five years of age when the battle of King's Mountain occurred, and yet he had several sons in that engagement.  It would seem to me he must have been somewhat older; perhaps you can tell me more definitely, and also the number of brothers you had engaged in that action.  How many brothers had you, were any of them killed in the Indian wars, and how many yet survive?  How many sisters had you, and how many of them are yet living?- Your grandfather, <name>Valentine Sevier</name>- was he a planter in <name>Virginia</name>, and when did he die?- Tell me, too, if you please, when or near what time your father married his first and second wives, their maiden names, and when they respectively died?- What were Gen. Sevier's religious and political sentiments?- Have you, your brother, or any one else, a portrait of  your father, from which I might procure a miniature copy, should I desire one?- Are there any historical works extant besides <name>Haywood</name>'s, treating of the early annals of Tennessee?- if so, be kind enough to name them.  Is it a difficult matter to obtain a copy of Haywood's History?     </p>
            <p>Pardon, my dear sir, the trouble I give you; and <add>when</add> it best suits your convenience, let me beg of you the favor of a communication.  I care not however rough and unpolished it might be; substantially the facts would be what I should esteem of the highest importance.  And, as I said to your brother-if you have any old letter of your father's, or any other writing containing his original signature, I should be thankful if you would enclose it.  I may here add, I made no allusion to a separate and extended life of your father, in my letter to your brother.  Be pleased, in conclusion, to accept my cordial good wishes for your health, happiness and prosperity.</p>
            <closer>Most truly yours, <signed>
                  <name>Lyman C. Draper</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <name>George W. Sevier</name>, <choice>
                     <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                     <expan>Esquire</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sc105d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Alexander <choice>
                        <abbr>NY</abbr>
                        <expan>New York</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>May 4</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Paid 25</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>George W. Sevier, <choice>
                        <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Forest Hill</name>, near Nashville,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>West- Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <name>L.C. Draper</name>
                  <unclear>and</unclear>
                  <date>28th July 1839</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
