<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc207">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1827 Oct., Yorkville [to] Mrs. Sarah McClung, Huntsville, Alabama / Mrs. F. Taylor : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Taylor, F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc207</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1827 Oct., Yorkville [to] Mrs. Sarah McClung, Huntsville, Alabama / Mrs. F. Taylor</title>
               <author>Taylor, F.</author>
               <date when="1827-10">October 1827</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by Mrs. F. Taylor to Mrs. Sarah McClung in 1827. Mrs. Taylor writes on various topics, such as religion, parties, mutual friends, and family.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Taylor Letter</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-1019</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc207</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Social life</term>
               <term>Religion</term>
               <term>Alabama</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Taylor, F.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc207a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Yorkville</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Octbr</abbr>
                     <expan>October</expan>
                  </choice> 1827</date>
               <salute>My Dear Sarah!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I promised to write you when I returned to <choice>
                  <abbr>Baltr</abbr>
                  <expan>Baltimore</expan>
               </choice> but as that will not be for two months to come_ I see no reason why the correspondence may not commence from this same , paradise, of <name>Mrs. Smiths</name>,_ Where I certainly have much more leisure if not a greater variety of interesting matter to fill my paper_ as I make it  a point of conscience to give my friends the value of postage in the quantity, if not <del type="overstrike">the</del>
               <add>in</add> quality.</p>
            <p>As a frank may now be obtained, from the Judge, at Uncle Sams expense_ I shall_ notwithstanding my amor patrie, save you freight upon this precious cargo__</p>
            <p>I left <name>Huntsville</name> with regret_ I had, in a short time, made many agreeable <del type="overstrike">acqua</del> acquaintances, and, I hope, some friends, whom it saddens my heart to think I may never see more, until the resurrection morn, when there will be an eternal union or <choice>
                  <orig>seperation</orig>
                  <reg>separation</reg>
               </choice> of all we most loved on earth_</p>
            <p>Since it was not convenient, without putting others to an inconvenience, to spend the time I must necessarily remain in this state, amongst my husbands family in <name>Pendleton</name>_ I could wish for Alladdin's Lamp, a fairy's ring_ or the wings of a zephyr, to convey me with all speed into your comfortable hall, which beguiled me of many pleasant hours, and where I could forget or leave behind me the cold hearted selfishness and unsocial air that infested_ <name>Spring Grove</name>_</p>
            <p>The roads through the <name>Cherokee Nation</name> were pronounced by the Judge &amp; Mrs. Smith much worse than the <name>Knoxville</name> route_ and those who recommended the first <choice>
                  <orig>recieved </orig>
                  <reg>received</reg>
               </choice> neither thanks or blessings But there was one, and only one <del type="overstrike">which</del> pleasing ingredient which with them, make up all other deficiencies, and that was_ cheapness_ which should be a primary consideration with us all_ <pb n="2" facs="sc207b.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>Mary continues in good health, but, to her delight is somewhat <choice>
                  <orig>thiner</orig>
                  <reg>thinner</reg>
               </choice>,_ and to my sorrow be it known, I have gained many pounds and am daily adding to my weight_ The Judge takes his rations with the best of us_and therefore, <add>may</add> be pronounced convalescent_ His better or rather larger half is in bed with her usual complaint headache, and for a week, we have been gliding upon tip-toe about the house, and living with closed doors, few very few venturing to disturb the solemn stillness which surrounds this <del type="overstrike">hospo</del> hospitable mansion_ However I must <add>do</add> the good citizens the justice to say that we have been invited to one ball_ and that a sister widow has taken compassion on my solitude and invited us to spend this evening with her_ Which like hungry beggars Mary &amp; I greedily, accepted_ pray keep this scandal to yourself, for you know <name>Mr McClung</name> cannot keep any thing from his <unclear>other</unclear> self <name>Mr. White</name>, and then it may get into the religious world that the religious Mrs. T_ instead of reading her Bible, as she now has ample <choice>
                  <orig>oportunity</orig>
                  <reg>oppurtunity</reg>
               </choice> is back-biting her dear friends_</p>
            <p>I received a long letter from Juliana, which with one from <name>Mrs Bolles</name> followed me from Huntsville, both sent their love and some other messages to you_ I received here pleasing accounts of a revival of religion in <name>Baltimore</name>, a sister and many acquaintances were amongst the number added unto the Lord_ What a blessed change_ forty-eight members joined the church (<choice>
                  <orig>presbeterian</orig>
                  <reg>Presbyterian</reg>
               </choice>) of <name>Mr. Nevins</name> at one communion_ <name>Mr. Allan</name> would rejoice at  the good tidings_ Don't forget when you see him to make my most respectful compliments to him_ <choice>
                  <orig>Aslo</orig>
                  <reg>Also</reg>
               </choice> to <name>Mrs. Brein</name> &amp; <name>Hutchin's</name>_ <name>Mrs. Dibb</name>_ and <name>Clay</name> with any others to whom may think them acceptable_ Above all give <add>my</add> love to <name>Mrs. Toby</name> &amp; family_ I do not forget my friend <name>Mr Harris</name> and the carnage break_ thank him for sending on my letters with his name endorsed on them, it assured one he was still in the land of the living_ I wish I could have the same assurance of all I left behind_</p>
            <p>Do write immediately on the receipt of this, or employ Mr. McClung who I recollect proffered his services on the occasion. I feel very anxious to learn how his trial has terminated_</p>
            <p>You did not give me any commissions, if I can serve you, fail not to command me.  If Mary knew I was writing to you she would add her love_ take it for granted that you and Mr McClung are in high in her estimation as well as your <lb/> Friend <lb/>
            </p>
            <signed>
               <name>F Taylor</name>
            </signed>
            <pb n="3" facs="sc207c.small.jpg"/>
            <closer>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Mrs. Sara McClung</name>Huntsville <lb/>
                     <name>Alabama</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <name>Mrs F. Taylor</name>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Yorkville </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <date>Oct 1827 </date>
                  <name> To Mrs. Sarah McClung</name>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
