<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl081">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Legal agreement] 1819 Feb. 10 [between] Lafayette Sanders [and] Richard Alexander : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl081</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50171165</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Legal agreement] 1819 Feb. 10 [between] Lafayette Sanders [and] Richard Alexander </title>
               <date when="1819-02-10"> February 10, 1819</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a land indenture between Richard Alexander and Lafayette Sanders dated February 10, 1819. Sanders sold approximately 180 acres in Smith County, Tennessee to Alexander for two thousand two hundred dollars.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Alexander Papers Outgoing</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">VI-G-2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl081</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Real property</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl081a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>This Indenture made this <date when="1819-02-10">tenth day of February one thousand eight hundred and nineteen</date>, between <name type="person">Lafayette Sanders</name> of the <name type="place">County of Sumner</name> and State of <name type="place">Tennessee</name> of the one part &amp; <name type="person">Richard Alexander </name>
               <sic>Alexander</sic>  of <name type="place">Smith County</name> and state aforesaid of the other part, witnesseth, that the said Lafayette Sanders for and in consideration of the sum of two thousand &amp; two hundred Dollars, to him in Sum paid, by the said Richard Alexander, the, receipt whereof is hereby acknowledged, hath sold, and by these presents doth bargain, <choice>
                  <orig>seel</orig>
                  <reg>seal</reg>
               </choice>, confirm, and convey, unto the said Richard Alexander, his heirs &amp; assigns forever, a certain tract or parcel of land lying and being in the county of Smith, being that part of the Service right of <name type="person">William Sanders</name>, Deceased, that fill to the lot of Lafayette Sanders aforesaid; where the division and distribution of said service right was made between the legatees, by the commissioners appointed for that purpose. Bounded as follows (Viz) Beginning at a Stone North West of the Spring at which Will Sanders first settled in <date when="1796">1796</date> thence cast along a marked line one hundred and twenty poles to a stake in <name type="person">James Bradleys</name> line near a large White Oak, thence South, with Bradleys line, one hundred and sixty four poles to a black walnut, corner to Bradly on <name type="person">Isham Beasly</name>, thence west with Beasly's line one hundred and thirty four poles to a beech, said Beaslys corner, thence North sixty eight, West fifty seven poles, to a back corner of the town lots marked <choice>
                  <abbr>No</abbr>
                  <expan>Number</expan>
               </choice> 60 , thence North thirty four degrees West with the line of said town lots, thirty six poles to two <pb n="2" facs="sl081b.small.jpg"/> — beeches, thence North thirty four degrees, East one hundred and forty poles to the beginning, containing one hundred and eighty acres, be the same more or less, with all the woods, mines, <choice>
                  <orig>heredetanments</orig>
                  <reg>hereditaments</reg>
               </choice> and appurtenances thereunto belonging or in any wise appertaining. — To have and to hold  the aforesaid tract of land and bargained promises to the said Richard Alexander his heirs and assigns forever, and the said Lafayette Sanders for himself his heirs and assigns doth covenant and agree to warrant and defend the above bargained premises, against the lawful claim or claims of all persons whatever. In testimony whereof I have hereunto set my hand, and seal the day and year above written.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Lafayette Sanders <add>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>Seal</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </add>
               </signed>Signed sealed &amp; delivered in presence of   <signed>
                  <name type="person">Wilson Cage</name> Juror</signed>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">W Goodall</name> Juror</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>State of Tennessee</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Smith County}</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>February Term 1819</addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>Then the within deed of Conveyance was duly proven in open court by the oaths  of Wilson Cage &amp; W. Goodall Witnesses thereto and ordered to be certified for registration</p>
            <closer>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Test </abbr>
                  <expan>Testimony</expan>
               </choice>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Robert Alexander</name>
               </signed>
               <name type="place">Smith County</name>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <pb n="3" facs="sl081c.small.jpg"/>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>State of Tennessee</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Smith County }</addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>  I, <name type="person">Jonathan Pickett</name> Register of the County aforesaid do certify that the within deed of conveyance &amp; order of Registration are duly registered in my office in Book F folio 504 Given under my hand at Office this <date when="1819-04-12">12th day of April 1819</date>.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. Pickett Register</signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Smith County </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="middle of page">Lafayette Sanders <lb/> To <lb/> Richard Alexander } Deed</add>
               <add place="bottom of page">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Miscellaneous calculations</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
