<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch079">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Orders] 1836 Nov. 22, Headquarters, New Echota, Geo[rgia] / Brig[adier] Gen[era]l John E. Wool : a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Wool, John Ellis, 1784-1869</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch079</idno>
            <idno>oclc: 44864938</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Orders] 1836 Nov. 22, Headquarters, New Echota, Geo[rgia] / Brig[adier] Gen[era]l John E. Wool </title>
               <author>Wool, John Ellis, 1784-1869</author>
               <date when="1836-11-22">November 22, 1836</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a copy of military orders from Brigadier General John E. Wool at the army headquarters in New Echota, Georgia (the capital of the Cherokee Nation), dated November 22, 1836.  Wool transmits twelve regulations governing the distribution of rations among the Cherokees.  The amount of rations delivered is to be based on the age of the recipient, and close account is to be kept.  In addition, Wool orders that any Cherokee suspected of intemperance shall receive no issues.</note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true"> State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">9</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch079</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Cherokee Indians</term>
               <term>Survival and emergency rations</term>
               <term>Georgia</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86141979"
                        role="Associated name http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/asn">Wool, John Ellis, 1784-1869.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch079a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Head Quarters Army</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>of the <name>Cherokee Nation</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">New Echota</name>
                        <name type="place">
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Geo.</abbr>
                              <expan>Georgia</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <date when="1836-11-22">November <choice>
                        <abbr>22d</abbr>
                        <expan>22nd</expan>
                     </choice> 1836</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>The following regulation will hereafter govern the Agents appointed to issue subsistence and clothing to the poor and needy of the <name type="person">Cherokee Indians</name> (viz)</p>
            <p>1st Issues will be made only to the poorer classes of the <name type="person">Cherokee</name> people referred to in the 10th Article of the late treaty entered into with the Nation upon the recommendation of the Committee or some one of the Committee appointed under the 12th Article of said treaty or by Agents regularly appointed by them and approved by the Commanding General</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>2d.</abbr>
                  <expan>2nd</expan>
               </choice> No issues shall be made for a longer period than three days at a time to any one person or family</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>3d.</abbr>
                  <expan>3rd</expan>
               </choice> Provision returns will be drawn for each family stating the number of men, women and children.  On the back of the return the name of the head of the family will be endorsed.  The return will exhibit the number of days for which rations have been issued and the commencement  termination of the period for which the issue is made<pb n="2" facs="ch079b.small.jpg"/>4th. The abstract of issues will be accompanied by the roll exhibiting the number and names of the Heads of families to which issues have been made and also showing the number of rations issued to each family
               </p>
            <p>5  The ration will consist of one pound of fresh beef or three fourths of a pound of salt pork or bacon, and of three fourths of a quart of corn or corn meal or of one pound of wheat flour to each grown person and four quarts of salt to every one hundred grown persons over the age of 14 and for persons under 14 one half the amount allowed to grown persons.</p>
            <p>6th  When the age of the person cannot be ascertained the issuing Agent shall be the judge and issue accordingly</p>
            <p>7th  No blanket; clothing or articles for clothing will be issued except upon the  recommendation of the Committee or some one of the Committee or Agent appointed by the Committee as authorized in the 1st Paragraph of these regulations.</p>
            <p>8th  The recommendations will state the causes which render the issues necessary, the number of persons to whom issues are to be made making a distinction between grown persons  children with the name of the Head of the family and the articles that may be required.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="ch079c.small.jpg"/>
            <p>9th  Upon these recommendations a return will be made exhibiting the number of persons, making a distinction between men, women, boys  girls with the names  numbers of the articles required; upon the back of which the name of the Head of the family will be endorsed</p>
            <p>10th  <hi>No clothes or articles of clothing will be delivered except to the person or persons for whom they were intended</hi>
            </p>
            <p>11th  <hi>No issues will be made to persons who are addicted to intemperance , or who would be likely to sell the rations or articles of clothing which they might draw; and Agents will not fail to make it known to all those who may draw either rations or articles of clothing that, should they sell either they will not be allowed again to draw either.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>12th  The abstract of issues <hi>for clothing</hi> will be accompanied with a roll containing the names of every person of each family to whom clothing or articles may have been issued also showing the article and the cost of each.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">John E. Wool</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Brig. Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>Brigadier General</expan>
                  </choice>
               </signed>
               <lb/>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Comms.</abbr>
                  <expan>Commissioner</expan>
               </choice> in the <name type="person">Cherokee</name> Country.
                  </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
