<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc237">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1829 Mar. 22, [to] William Donelson / Andrew Jackson, Washington, D.C. : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Jackson, Andrew</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc237</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1829 Mar. 22, [to] William Donelson / Andrew Jackson, Washington, D.C.</title>
               <author> Jackson, Andrew</author>
               <date when="1829-03-22"> 
			 March 22, 1829</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated March 22, 1829 from Andrew Jackson to William Donelson.  The subject of the letter is Jackson's son Andrew Jackson Hutchings, who came under Jackson's supervision after the death of his father John Hutchings.  The tone of the letter is one of regret at Hutchings' poor performance as a student, and the resignation that he will not be a classical scholar, but may be more aptly suited to life as a farmer.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Andrew Jackson Letters</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">New Accessions</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc237</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845.</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79088888"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc237a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Washington</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>March 22d 1829</date>
               <salute>My <choice>
                     <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                     <expan>Dear</expan>
                  </choice> Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have just received from <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Coffee a letter inclosing one from Doctor Lindsley to him informing that Hutchings has been suspended from College, &amp; is now at the Hermitage Idle.  This intelligence is a sore grief to me, and one from his pledge to me, of good behaviour, &amp; application to his Book, and strict adherence to the rules of the university, &amp; the orders of the professors, I was not prepared to hear, I was not prepared you may say to him to hear of his disgrace, which I had taken so much pains, by my frequent admonitions to prevent, nor did I believe he would so far forget himself, as to inflict such a wound on my feelings, if he was regardless of his own__  But it is so, and I must adopt such measures, as will yet preserve him from ruin, &amp; myself from disgrace.</p>
            <p>On the receipt of this my dear friend can I ask the goodness of you, forthwith to take him &amp; enter him with Mr. Otey at Franklin, &amp; advise <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Coffee thereof, &amp; draw upon him for the amount of his Tuition &amp; Board in favour of <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice>. Otey.  I have this day wrote Genl Coffee that I would thus direct you, &amp; he will be prepared to meet your draft for Hutchings board &amp; tuition.</p>
            <p>Say to Mr. Otey I wish him instructed in writing &amp; arithmetic so that he may become a good Book keeper, as I find it <pb n="2" facs="sc237b.small.jpg"/> useless to attempt to make him a good classic scholar; and all I now hope for is, to give him an education to fit him for a farmer.  If he can be restrained &amp; governed, I would wish him to study algebra &amp; some branches of mathematics, with Belle letters, &amp; natural &amp; moral philosophy, and review his greek &amp; latin which he has read.</p>
            <p>My Dr Sir write me on the receipt of this and let me know how your dear little Elisabeth is, &amp; whether poor poll the favourite bird of my dear wife is still living.  present me affectionately to Elisabeth to your father &amp; mother, and all our relations.  Say to them that we are all well &amp; all send their love to them &amp; believe me respectfully your friend</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Andrew Jackson</signed>
               <add>
                  <name>William Donelson</name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                     <expan>Esquire</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
