<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm003">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Photograph of assemblage of artifacts, from Overhill Cherokee
			 villages, Tennessee, taken 1967], / W. Miles Wright: a machine-readable
			 transcription</title>
            <author>Wright, W. Miles</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. 3k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>mm003</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44394322</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Museum, University of
				Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Photograph of assemblage of artifacts, from Overhill Cherokee
				villages, Tennessee, taken 1967], / W. Miles Wright.</title>
               <author>Wright, W. Miles</author>
               <date/>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This is a photograph of mid-18th century
				Cherokee artifacts, animal bones, and plant food remains. It is from
				excavations of Overhill Cherokee Villages which were conducted by the
				University of Tennessee between 1967 and 1983 as part of the Tellico
				Archaeological Project. Excavations continued until 1983, and laboratory
				studies and report preparation continued until 1987. The excavations were
				conducted in anticipation of the flooding of the Lower Little Tennessee River
				Valley, in eastern Tennessee, by the Tellico Dam Reservoir. The excavations
				were conducted under contract with the National Park Service and the Tennessee
				Valley Authority (TVA). </note>
               <note type="collection">Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note type="document">mm003</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Photographs</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</term>
               <term>Salvage archaeology</term>
               <term>Historic sites</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Photographer http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/pht">Wright, W. Miles</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mm003.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Assemblage of mid-18th century Cherokee artifacts, animal
				  bones, and plant food remains. European made ceramics and stone artifacts,
				  metal stirrup, beads, mouthharp, scissors, buckle, hoe, deer bones and charred
				  plant remains, Cherokee made ceramics. Photo by W. Miles Wright. This
				  information was provided by the Frank H. McClung Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
