<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl688">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1849 Jan. 8, Tazwell [to] Neill Brown, Nashville, Tennessee / O.P. Temple : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Temple, O.P.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl688</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1849 Jan. 8, Tazwell [to] Neill Brown, Nashville, Tennessee / O.P. Temple</title>
               <author>  Temple, O.P.</author>
               <date when="1849-01-08"> 
			 January 8, 1849</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated January 8, 1849 from O.P. Temple to governor Neill S. Brown of Tennessee.  The subject of the letter is the upcoming gubernatorial race.  Temple tells the governor that a group of Whigs in East Tennessee have vowed to only support a candidate from their part of the state.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Neill S. Brown Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl688</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor (1845-1847 : Brown)</term>
               <term>Election campaigns</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n96051924"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Temple, Oliver Perry, 1820-1907</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl688a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Tazwell</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>January 8, 1849</date>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Gov</abbr>
                     <expan>Governor</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>NS </abbr>
                     <expan>Neill Smith</expan>
                  </choice>Brown</add>
               <salute> Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The Subject of a candidate for Governor is beginning to excite some interest in certain circles in this end of the State.  There is a strong disposition on the part of a portion of the people to get a candidate from <name>East Tennessee</name>.  The movement, I apprehend, will secure the <unclear>conscience</unclear> of a large and respectable portion of the people.  Those who advocate it do so on the ground that we have been deprived of our Senator.  A writer in the Knoxville Tribune of last week goes so far as to say that the Whigs of this end of the State will not support any person but an East Tennessean for that office.  But I am confident that the writer is mistaken, and that no such disposition exists in the great mass of the Whigs A few may have such feelings the common people never have been dissatisfied with the election of Bell to half the extent that a person at a distance would <unclear>imagine</unclear> from certain articles in the news papers.  Indeed I  <pb n="2" facs="sl688b.small.jpg"/> have always believed that a majority of the people were,  under the then existing circumstances, in favor of the election of John Bell.  Nearly all the complaint has been made by politicians.</p>
            <p>But be that as it may the present movement will have considerable popularity and strength.  There are, however, Some here who think that you are entitled to the track if you desire it. For one I have openly declared on all occasions that there is but one <unclear>contingency</unclear> that will prevent me from supporting you over the head of any more in the State.  That contingency is if <choice>
                  <abbr>Col</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Sneed,  whose name has  been mentioned for that office, Should desire the position, I shall feel bound to advocate his claims.  The relations which exist between us, as well as ties of friendship of the strongest kind, would force me to do so.  I could not act otherwise from a thousand considerations.  But at present I am sure he does not desire to be a candidate unless, there, he should change his mind and desire the position, I shall support your <unclear>claimes</unclear> in preference to those of any other person.  I know not what your desire is upon the subject; but I am most clearly of the opinion that if you desire a re-election, you are entitled to the track.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Nelson is the strongest man whose name has been mentioned in East-Tennessee. I have understood, though I <choice>
                  <orig>dont</orig>
                  <reg>don't</reg>
               </choice> know how true it is, that he thinks you are entitled to the race if you wish it.  Indeed I think <pb n="3" facs="sl688c.small.jpg"/> that he and Crozier are the only two, whose names have been mentioned, who would, under any ordinary state of circumstances, desire to be a candidate.  I am certain that Col Sneed and Col Netherland do not.</p>
            <p>This movement in East Tennessee does not, I am sure, arise from any opposition to you It arises from the cause I first mentioned.  Others may be introduced in the discussion of the Subject to give struggle to that, but that is the primary one.</p>
            <p>I have deemed it proper to make these statements to you, not with the wish or hope of influencing you in making a decision one way or an other; but solely with the view of letting you have a  <unclear>candid</unclear>   statement of the condition of things here__ a thing you are not very likely to get from <unclear>heated partisans</unclear>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <add>most truly Your Friend</add>
               <signed>
                  <name>OP Temple</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl688d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Gov N S Brown Nashville Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
