<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl491">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter]    1844 Jun. 30, Paris, Ten[nessee, to] Gideon B. Black, Lewisburg, Ten[nessee] / W.W. Herron: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Herron, W.W.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl491</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1844 Jun. 30, Paris, Ten[nessee, to] Gideon B. Black, Lewisburg, Ten[nessee] / W.W. Herron</title>
               <author>Herron, W.W.</author>
               <date when="1844-06-30">June 30, 1844</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from W.W. Herron to Gideon Black, dated June 30, 1844. Herron writes about daily events, such as his health, the weather, and that he recently courted someone.  Herron writes about the upcoming election. He refers to the Democrats as "Locos". He also mentions some of the places he has been, and that if his health is willing, he will be visiting Black soon.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">James Winchester Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">8</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl491</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Politics, society, and economy</term>
               <term>Travel</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Herron, W.W.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl491a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Paris</name>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                     <date>30 June 1844</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Gideon</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>To give wings to a few dull Moments and Promote another object I now attempt writing your a few lines. I am in the enjoyment of tolerable health &amp; so are the <choice>
                  <abbr>Cols</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel's</expan>
               </choice> family &amp; the people generally about here. I have been at home about two weeks. I spent several days in <name>
                  <name>Davidson</name>
               </name> on my way from  <name>Marshall</name> and I thought I done some decent courting, at any rate, I know I courted at a decent looking girl; but I was in the worst fix for doing anything of the kind that I ever was on any life, The weather as you will probably remember, was oppressively hot &amp; I generally lead two of the worst sort of boils under one or the other arm: there causes kept <add>me</add> a little more than half sick &amp; at last forced me off a little sooner than I would have left under other circumstances. But not with standing all these difficulties I think I got along tolerably well. The business of selling goods is with us, at this time, quite dull; people generally have  tolerable prospects for crops of corn &amp; tobacco- very little excitement about the <choice>
                  <abbr>Govs</abbr>
                  <expan>Governor's</expan>
               </choice> election. Ours you know is a modern democrat county_ we have two democrats out for the lower branch, is <name>Frazier</name> &amp; <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Copeland</name>, both in favor of repealing the <unclear>"?pling act"</unclear> we have one whig opposed to it should the locos continue to run we will lay <pb n="2" facs="sl491b.small.jpg"/> it on them. tho' I think the whiskey law will be more the question than federal polities <add>at</add> any rate it will divide each party against themselves <name>Polk</name> &amp; <name>Jons</name> are to be in town next week and will have a good crowd. I see that the union! <choice>
                  <orig>correspent</orig>
                  <reg>correspondent</reg>
               </choice> from <name>Shelbyville</name> says that <name>Long</name> corners your man <name>Baxter</name> at every point, the Col says if this be true, your men cant be much. The Locos all here had little or nothing to say against the message &amp; until they saw what the union and its correspent from <name>washington</name> said of <name>webster's</name>letter to <name>Fox</name> they admired it very much__ Since that they dont think so well of it. <choice>
                  <abbr>Gid</abbr>
                  <expan>Gideon</expan>
               </choice> , If I live &amp; am well I intend visiting Nashville again on the <date>1 <choice>
                     <abbr>Aug</abbr>
                     <expan>August</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date> __ &amp; if I can wind up my matters there as I think I can I will be out to see you in the last of the first week of that month and I want you to hold yourself in readiness to go with me. I think I can shine. If I can I will depend on you for the first pig <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>etcetera</expan>
               </choice> after myself. You <choice>
                  <orig>remmember</orig>
                  <reg>remember</reg>
               </choice> that I told you I wanted to do the raking myself. But I think you will be well suited if blood will suit you <choice>
                  <abbr>ie</abbr>
                  <expan>id est</expan>
               </choice> if you call <name>Bell</name> blood <unclear>Paris.</unclear> We have a good deal of rain for the last two weeks,  it now looks like being dry and very warm &amp; I fear that we  will be sickly again this Season tho if I Keep up a few days <pb n="3" facs="sl491c.small.jpg"/> longer I will leave here and only be here occasionally until fall. I have not been to <name>Carroll</name> Since I got home and dont Know much <choice>
                  <abbr>abt</abbr>
                  <expan>about</expan>
               </choice> the people in that region. As I remarked above should I live &amp; keep well &amp; nothing happens I will See you at the time mentioned and hope to find you well. Should you See <name>Miss King</name> say Something good to her for me If I were going to stay at one place long at once I would request you to write but as it is it is not wor<gap/> your while now</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Very Respectfully</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>W.W. Herron</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>G</abbr>
                           <expan>Gideon</expan>
                        </choice> B Black</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl491d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>G.B Black Esqr</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Lewisburg</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Marshall <choice>
                           <abbr>Co</abbr>
                           <expan>County</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Tn</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
