<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="ch029">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1835 July 9, Red Clay, C[herokee] Nation, [to] Col[onel] W[illia]m Y. Hansell and S[amuel] Rockwell, Milledgeville, Georgia / Jno. [i.e., John] Ross: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Cherokee Nation. Principal Chief (1828-1866 : Ross)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch029</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44803890</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1835 July 9, Red Clay, C[herokee] Nation, [to] Col[onel] W[illia]m Y. Hansell and S[amuel] Rockwell, Milledgeville, Georgia / Jno. [i.e., John] Ross</title>
               <author>Cherokee Nation. Principal Chief (1828-1866 : Ross)</author>
               <date value="1835-07-09">July 9, 1835</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This document is a letter from John Ross, Principal Chief of the Cherokee Nation, to Colonel William Y. Hansell and Colonel Samuel Rockwell, lawyers for the Cherokee Nation, dated July 9, 1835.  Ross complains to the two attorneys regarding the controversy of the payment of the Cherokee annuity.  A vote is to be held under the direction of Major Benjamin F. Currey to determine to which Cherokee faction, the Ridge party or the Ross party, the annuity is to be paid.  Ross complains about slanderous depictions of him in local newspapers and also mentions the arrival of Reverend John F. Schermerhorn to submit treaty proposals to the Cherokees.</note>
               <note type="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box"> 1</note>
               <note type="folder">23</note>
               <note type="document">ch029</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>Letters</item>
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Relocation</item>
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Claims</item>
                  <item>Southern States</item>
               </list> 
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[1]"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <address>
                        <addrLine>
                           <name type="place">Red Clay</name> 
                           <name type="place person">
                              <abbr expan="Cherokee">C</abbr> Nation</name>
                        </addrLine>
                     </address> 
                     <date value="1835-07-09">July 9th. 1835.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>Gentlemen</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>The Govt. Agents in this Nation has been maneuvering, so as to get a pretext to shuffle our annuity for this year into the hands of <name type="person" reg="Major?">Ridge</name>'s party. and will not pay it over until the votes of the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> are taken at the time and place designated by <name type="person">Major Currey</name> in the vicinity of the <name type="place">Head of Coosa</name>; Consequently I have been induced to notify the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> of the Several Districts to attend in order that the disorganizers might be voted down in the presence of the <name type="place">United States</name> Commissioners who are expected to be there merely to see and judge of matters and things for themselves  The meeting will take place on the 20th <abbr expan="instant">inst.</abbr> when I wrote you a few days since, I did not know that we should have been<pb n="[2]"/>reduced to the necessity of attending there and should it meet with your convenience to come there, I shall be happy to meet with you, It is the only opportunity which will present itself for some time to come thereafter to enable me to meet you any where else than, at this place The <abbr expan="Reverend" type="contraction">Revd.</abbr> 
                     <name type="person">Mr. Schermarhorn</name> has arrived and is now in the Country It is not Known as yet, when himself and colleagues will call the expected Council for the Submission of the <hi>treaty propositions</hi> before the <name type="person">Cherokee</name> people for their acceptance or rejection  I do hope that it may suit your Convenience to meet me in the vicinity of <name type="place">Rome</name> on the 20th <abbr expan="instant">inst.</abbr>  I am secluded here in the forests of <name type="place">Red Clay</name> and cut off from all regular communications of the mail for the want of a Convenient Post Office And my papers are <abbr expan="received">recd.</abbr> after the news of the day becomes Stale consequently I Know little of<pb n="[3]"/>passing events, until they are almost forgotten at the place where they transpire.  I take no <name type="place">Georgia</name> papers at all a friend of mine called a day or two since and handed me one called <bibl>
                           <title>"The Standard of Union"</title>
                        </bibl> dated the 27th <abbr expan="Ultimo">Ulto.</abbr> containing an article headed <name type="person">"Cherokees"</name> copied from the <bibl>
                           <title>"Georgia Telegraph"</title>
                        </bibl> a paper I never before heard of and do not know where it is published  If the Editors of those papers truly consult their "conscience" love God and fear the judgements of Heaven and have resided any length of time in <name type="place">Georgia</name> and do not Know my general character better than the writer of the article has represented it.  I pity their ignorance and credulity and despise the slanderous falsehoods  epithets which have been wantonly fabricated and published against me for the edification of their gentle readers
                  
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Very respectfully yours truly</salute> 
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="John">Jno</abbr> Ross</name>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[4]"/>
               <p>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Cols. <name type="person" reg="Colonel">Wm Y. Hansell</name>  
                        <name type="person" reg="Colonel">S. Rockwell</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <abbr expan="attorneys" type="suspension">attos.</abbr> at Law</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Milledgeville</name> 
                        <name type="place">Georgia</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </p>
            
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
