<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="ch033">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter, 1839 July 13, Illinois Camp Ground to Brev[e]t Brig[adie]r Gen[era]l M[atthew] Arbuckle / George Lowrey ... [et al.] : a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch033</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44804927</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Letter, 1839 July 13, Illinois Camp Ground to Brev[e]t Brig[adie]r Gen[era]l M[atthew] Arbuckle / George Lowrey ... [et al.]</title>
               <date value="1839-07-13">July 13, 1839</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary">Copy of a letter dated July 13, 1839 from members of the Cherokee Convention to General Matthew Arbuckle regarding Arbuckle's suspicions about the nature of the convention. Arbuckle is assured by the members of the convention that they were called to assemble by the Cherokee people and that there is no cause for concern among any group of Cherokees or others. The undersigned include George Lowrey, George Guess (Sequoyah), John Ross and many others.</note>
               <note type="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box">1</note>
               <note type="folder">23</note>
               <note type="document">ch033</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>Letters</item>
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Government relations</item>
                  <item>United States</item>
               </list> 
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[1]"/>
               <opener>
                  <hi>No. 57.</hi> 57<lb/>In National Convention<lb/>
                        <dateline>
                           <address>
                              <addrLine>
                                 <name type="place">Illinois</name> Camp Ground</addrLine>
                           </address> 
                           <date value="1839-07-13">July 13th. 1839</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <salute>To/ <name type="person">
                              <abbr expan="Brevet Brigadier General Matthew" type="contraction">Brevt. Brigr. Genl. M.</abbr> Arbuckle</name> 
                           <name type="place">U.S.</name>  
                           <abbr expan="Army Commanding">A. Commdg.</abbr> 
Sir/</salute>
                     
                  
               </opener>
               <p>Since our communication of yesterday to yourself  We have been honored with the receipt of yours of the 10th <abbr expan="instant">inst.</abbr> but we had not the satisfaction of seeing the officer <orig reg="through">thro'</orig>  whom it was dispatched, nor, do we know <del type="overstrike">the source <unclear>Thro</unclear> which</del> 
                  <add place="supralinear">by whom</add> it was delivered   In justice to ourselves we beg leave to remark, that it appears you have mistaken the true character of this convention; in order, therefore, that it may be fully understood; we will state, that, this convention has been called by the <name type="person">Cherokee</name> people  and not by the chiefs or people of the late emigrants alone. Consequently, the Undersigned Members have derived their appointment and authority directly from the people in the exercise of their Plenary Power, and not <orig reg="through"> thro'</orig> the limited authority vested in any of the chiefs or other delegated functionary  There is no just cause for any uneasiness to any portion of the <name type="person">Cherokee</name> people, <del type="overstrike">or others</del> and much less to others.  <del type="overstrike">And </del> We <del type="overstrike">
                     <unclear/>
                  </del> are not aware, <del rend="overstrike">of there being <add place="supralinear">any uneasiness</add> among the <add place="supralinear">any</add> peaceable and orderly any such feelings apprehensions and there <unclear>if</unclear>
                  </del> 
                  <add place="supralinear">of</add> any uneasiness <del type="overstrike">among</del> 
                  <add place="supralinear">in</add> the <add place="supralinear">minds of </add> the <name type="person">Chero<del type="overstrike">kee peop</del>kee</name> Community, <add place="supralinear">That by</add> 
                  <del type="overstrike">
                     <unclear/>
                  </del> the <del type="overstrike">
                     <unclear>continued</unclear>
                  </del> sitting of this convention, <del type="overstrike">that</del>  the peace and good order on this frontier can be disturbed.<pb n="[2]"/>
                     <del type="overstrike">by it   Having full confidence <del type="overstrike">in</del> However, in the sincerity of your disposition not to interfere in the concerns of the <name type="person">Cherokee</name> people - and that your motive is honorably confined to the preservation of peace and good order on this frontier - <del type="overstrike">It affords as much</del> We take great pleasure in saying that we hope soon to be prepared to convince <del type="overstrike">the</del> yourself and the <abbr expan="Government">Govt.</abbr> and people of the <name type="place">U States</name> by the Acts of this convention, that the <name type="person">Cherokee</name> people fully appreciate the blessings of peace and good order</del> and that every thing in our power will be done to insure these desirable objects.
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>We have the honor to be Sir, very respectfully <abbr expan="Your Obedient and Humble Servants" type="contraction">Yr Obt  Hble Servts</abbr>
                  </salute>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="George">Geo.</abbr> Lowrey</name>
                  </signed> 
                  <abbr expan="President" type="contraction">Prest.</abbr>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="George">Geo.</abbr> Guess</name>
                  </signed> 
                  <abbr expan="Vice President" type="suspension">V. Pt.</abbr>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Edward">Edwd.</abbr> Gunter</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">R. Taylor</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">Luney Riley</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">Young Wolf</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="George">Geo.</abbr> Hicks</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">Jesse Bushyhead</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">G. M Gunter</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Thomas">Thos.</abbr> Foreman</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="James">Jas.</abbr> Brown</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">Thomas Candy</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">Moses Parris</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">Riley Keys</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">John Benge</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="George">Geo.</abbr> Brewer</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">John F. Boot</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Archibald">Archd.</abbr> Campbell</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Charles">Chas.</abbr> Goard</name>
                  </signed>
                  <lb/>Stop-<signed>
                        <name type="person">Ahstoletah</name>
                     </signed>
                     <signed>
                        <name type="person">Small Back</name>
                     </signed>
                     <signed>
                        <name type="person">Crying Bird</name>
                     </signed>
                     <signed>
                        <name type="person">Tobacco Will</name>
                     </signed>
                     <signed>
                        <name type="person">Bark</name>
                     </signed>
                     <signed>
                        <name type="person">Elijah Hicks</name>
                     </signed> 
                     <abbr expan="Secretary" type="contraction">Secry.</abbr>
                     <lb/>By order of the Convention <signed>
                           <name type="person">John Ross</name>
                        </signed>
                     
                  
               </closer>
            
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[3]"/>
               <p>No. 57 <unclear/> 
                  <del type="overstrike">
                     <unclear/>
                  </del>
                  <lb/>Copy of a letter to <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Brevet Brigadier General Matthew" type="contraction">Brevt. Brigr Genl. M.</abbr> Arbuckle</name> from the members of the Convention <date value="1839-07-13">July 13th 1839</date>
                  
               </p>
            
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
