<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="ch034">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter], 1837 Feb. 18, Cherokee Agency [to John Ross ?] / [Lewis Ross ?]: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch034</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44805296</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter], 1837 Feb. 18, Cherokee Agency [to John Ross ?] / [Lewis Ross ?]</title>
               <date value="1837-02-18">February 18, 1837</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary">Letter dated February 18, 1837 from (Lewis Ross ?) to his brother (John Ross, Principal Chief of the Cherokee Nation ?) relating recent events in the Cherokee Nation. He informs his brother of an election that took place in New Echota concerning the distribution of annuity payments from the United States to the Cherokees. A large group of people crossed on ferry to take part in the election and chose George Lowrey, Cherokee leader, to receive the funds. (Lewis Ross ?) suspects that the true amount due the Nation is more than was reported and asks his brother to check on this. During the time of the election General John E. Wool gave a speech translated by Jesse Bushyhead, a Cherokee interpreter, explaining the terms of the recent treaty (Treaty of New Echota, 1835), advising the people to prepare to remove, and offering to supply certain provisions. (Ross ?) also reports that men who were accused of attacking an officer were whipped, and Bridge Maker and Tom Foreman were arrested for speaking out against the treaty.  He says that emigrants have been passing through and there is much sickness.</note>
               <note type="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box">1</note>
               <note type="folder">24</note>
               <note type="document">ch034</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>Letters</item>
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Legal status, laws, etc.</item>
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Social conditions</item>
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Politics and government</item>
                  <item>United States</item>
               </list> 
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[1]"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <address>
                        <addrLine>
                           <name type="place">Cherokee Agency</name>
                        </addrLine>
                     </address> 
                     <date>
                        <abbr expan="February" type="contraction">Feby.</abbr> 18. 1837</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>Dear Brother</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>In my last letter I wrote you that our Agent had given notice that on the 15th <abbr expan="Instant">Inst.</abbr> a vote would be taken at <name type="place">New Echota</name> 
                  <del type="overstrike">on the 15th <abbr expan="Instant">Inst</abbr>
                  </del> to <orig reg="ascertain">assertain</orig> what disposition the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> 
                  <abbr expan="wished" type="contraction">wishd.</abbr> to be made of the monies due them under former treaties.  I got home from the election yesterday, the votes were taken on the 15<add place="supralinear">th</add>  for paying the Money into the hand of Mr. <name type="person">George Lowrey</name> there were 1269.  for paying it into the hands of <name type="person" reg="Major?">Ridge</name>s Committee 97. and not one of that number was given in <unclear/> the day of the Election they having been taken previously by the Agent.  we met on the river bank on the evening of the <date value="0000-00-14">14th</date> in the rain which <orig reg="fell">feel</orig> incessantly all night. we thought it was best to vote that <name type="person" reg="George">Mr. Lowrey</name> should receive the money. believing it was there, and that it would be paid as soon as the election was over.  It was agreed on that I should cross the river that night and see the Agent and Know of him what arrangement was made about crossing the river and also to know at what hour the election would open.  I went across, in the mean time the people were to be <abbr expan="informed">informd.</abbr> of <add place="supralinear">the</add> manner in which it was thought best the votes should be given.  I called on the Agent that night he informed me that no arrangement had been made about the ferriages <hi>but</hi> that if the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> wished it he could pay all of the ferriages of those who were unable to do so out of their fund.  I also met with <name type="person">Mr. Kennedy</name> one of the Commissioners from him I was <abbr expan="informed">informd.</abbr> that the money was in <name type="place">Washington</name>.  that the result of the election would be reported, and the money would be then sent on.- the next morning I <abbr expan="returned">returnd.</abbr> to the river and hired a ferry boat for the day of one dollar for the foot Men to cross in. the horse men who <abbr expan="wished">wishd</abbr> to take their horses over paid their own ferriages.  I reported what I had been informed about the money. <del rend="overstrike">
                     <unclear/>
                  </del> we<pb n="[2]"/>might have voted it to be paid to the delegation at <name type="place">Washington</name> but as the thing was already agreed on to pay to <name type="person" reg="George">Lowrey</name> and <orig reg="there">their</orig> might be some delays about a report being forwarded.  We concluded to make no change in the way we had agreed on to vote.
               </p>
               <p>The election <add place="supralinear">was</add> to Commence at 11. <abbr expan="O'clock">Ocl.</abbr> we got all across the river, being a very fine day after the rain and <abbr expan="proceeded">proceed.d</abbr> on to the place in a solid body throu<gap desc="gh" reason="document edge"> the Town, <abbr expan="passed">passd</abbr>, our old council house about 300 yards   It was <orig reg="apparent">apparrant</orig> that our numbers Struck <del type="overstrike">
                        <unclear/>
                     </del> every body there with astonishment. <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Doctor">Doct.</abbr> 
                        <unclear>Lyle</unclear>
                     </name> 
                     <name type="person">Thos. Lyon</name> and <name type="person">Elijah Hicks</name> were appointed Judges of the Election <name type="person">Spencer Jarnagin</name>.  <name type="person">Lovely Rogers</name>, Clerks, the election then commenced. after the election had <abbr expan="proceeded">proceedd</abbr> some time <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Wool</name> Said he <abbr expan="wished">wishd.</abbr> to make a speech to <del type="overstrike">them</del> the people, but that they need not suspend going on with the votes. <unclear>Mr.</unclear> 
                     <name type="person">E. Gunter</name> notified the people of the <abbr expan="Generals" type="contraction">Genls.</abbr> wish they collected as close to him as <unclear>they</unclear> could get <name type="person" reg="Jesse?">J. Bushyhead</name> got up on a stump and interpreted; the <abbr expan="General" type="contraction">Genl.</abbr> was on his horse.  The substance of his speech was that he had been sent here to see that the Treaty should be faithfully executed and that a treaty had been made <add place="supralinear">by</add> which they would all have to remove by <date value="1838-06-00">June 1838</date>. that the president would make no alterations. and if <add place="supralinear">any</add> persons told them that there was no treaty they told them that which was not true. and he did not wish to deceive them, that if they did not remove by the time <add place="supralinear">stipulated by the Treaty <unclear/>
                     </add> 
                     <name type="place">United States</name> 
                     <orig reg="Troops">Tropps</orig> would be used to compel their removal, he said the Country was a good Country, there was plenty of game there Buffaloes. Deer <abbr expan="et cetera">c</abbr> - and he wished them when they went home to make <orig reg="preparations">preperations</orig> for removal. he also stated that there <add place="supralinear">was</add> 
                     <orig reg="Clothing">Cloathing</orig> on <add place="supralinear">hand</add> at that place for them also provisions, which they could get if they wanted any.  the speech was but short and did not seem to make much impression.  Some of the people remarked after the Speech was concluded that when they wanted<pb n="[3]"/>blankets they <orig reg="generally">gener<add place="supralinear">a</add>ly</orig> bought them and others that they did not care about Shoes, that Shoes would blister their toes in walking. by night the election closed and the great body had quietly left the ground and were but few to be seen, not one application was made   <unclear>for any</unclear> of the articles offered.  thus closed the <date value="0000-02-15">15th day of February</date>.  <name type="person">
                           <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Wool</name> requested that Several of the leading men should pay him a visit that evening at his Quarters.  <name type="person" reg="George">Mr. Lowrey</name>. <name type="person">Gunter</name>, <name type="person">White Path</name>, <name type="person">Money <unclear>Cryer</unclear>
                        </name> and Several others went I did not go having some other business to attend to that evening, they had Considerable talk pretty <add place="supralinear">much</add> in Substance of the Speech that he had made, I understood and in the winding up of the talk the General proposed to make <name type="person">White Path</name> a present of a blanket.  he replied that he was now getting old and Was there <add place="supralinear">on</add> 
                        <del type="overstrike">
                           <unclear/>
                        </del> foot had considerable baggage to carry, and did not wish to increase his load, and must decline receiving the present.  the <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> then asked him if he would receive it for his wife, he said he could not take it. I am told the <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> was very much amused with his manner of refusal  You had best call at the department and find out the exact amount due the Nation, as I believe there is more due the Nation than was reported to us.  <name type="person">
                           <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> Smith</name> had an extract from a letter <abbr expan="received" type="contraction">receivd.</abbr> by the Commissioner from the department which States there is due the Nation". (the <abbr expan="Amount" type="contraction">Amt</abbr> I do not recollect exactly, but something over $12000-) this must be far short of the <orig reg="amount">amout</orig>, and ought to be looked into before the money is sent out to the Commission who I understand are to pay it over   The three men that I wrote you were taken in the mountains <add place="supralinear">under a charge</add> for having made an attack on one of the Officers I understand has been punished by Whipping of them. without the knowledge of <name type="person">
                           <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Wool</name>, he is very much exasperated<pb n="[4]"/> at the commanding officer at that part, and I understand has given orders for him to be dismissed from Service.  <name type="person">Bridge Maker</name> 
                           <add place="supralinear">
                              <unclear>was</unclear>
                           </add> 
                           <del type="overstrike">has</del> also <del type="overstrike">been</del> arrested about a week since and is yet confined at <name type="place">Ross's Landing</name> under a charge of opposing the Treaty and exciting the people against it by making Speeches <abbr expan="et cetera">c</abbr> 
                           <name type="person">Tom Foreman</name> was also arrested the Same day <name type="person">Bridge Maker</name> was, he happened to be in that neighborhood and met with the men who arrested <name type="person">Bridge Maker</name> he in speaking of the the Treaty Said he did not consider it a Treaty for which expression he was arrested and taken out as far as <name type="place" reg="TN?">Cleaveland</name>, and was there released and that <name type="person">Bridge Maker</name> was taken on.  <name type="person" reg="George">Mr. Lowrey</name> asked <name type="person">
                              <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Wool</name> What Charges <del type="overstrike" cert="appears to be different ink">was</del>  
                           <add place="supralinear" cert="appears to be different ink">were <del type="overstrike" cert="appears to be different ink">then</del> preferred</add> against <name type="person">Bridge Maker</name>; he said he had been reported as using his influence in exciting hostilities against the Treaty. and that he had reported the case and that he would be kept until further order. the Troops who arrested him were those stationed at <name type="place">Ross's Landing</name>. these Measures are very severe to the feelings of free men  but when a people has their hands in the Lyons Mouth prudence requires them to take it out with great care  we have great hopes that when you return home that a course will be shaped that will give some partial relief at least.  I believe as far as I can learn the people are anxious to know their final doom, be it good or be it bad.  I have no Suggestion to make that would be of any Service to you in your Mission at <name type="place">Washington</name>; you know our situation. but can only do the best you can for us, we know that the power of giving us relief is not with you. but with the <abbr expan="Government">Govmt</abbr> of the <name type="place">U. States</name>.   There are probably about 200 Emigrants at this place awaiting for a tide, Some has gone on to <name type="place">Ross's landing</name> in all probably about 300 from the best information, they intend going in a steam boat from this place to <name type="place">Decatur</name> and so on  there has been good deal of Sickness amongst them
                     
                  </gap>
               </p>
            
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
