<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="ch030">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1835 Jan. 14, Washington [to Thomas G.] Barron and [David] Irwin, Cassville, Cherokee Nation / Jno. [i.e., John] Ross: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Cherokee Nation. Principal Chief (1828-1866 : Ross)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch030</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44804095</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1835 Jan. 14, Washington [to Thomas G.] Barron and [David] Irwin, Cassville, Cherokee Nation / Jno. [i.e., John] Ross</title>
               <author>Cherokee Nation. Principal Chief (1828-1866 : Ross)</author>
               <date value="1835-01-14">January 14,1835</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This is a letter from John Ross, Principal Chief of the Cherokee Nation, to Thomas G. Barron and David Irwin, attorneys for the Nation, dated January 14, 1835.  Ross informs them that a small sum will be forwarded to assure them of the Nation's intention to pay for legal services.  In addition, he mentions recent acts passed by the state of Georgia, and upcoming judicial proceedings involving Cherokee plaintiffs.</note>
               <note type="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box">1</note>
               <note type="folder"> 23</note>
               <note type="document">ch030</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>Letters</item>
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Legal status, laws, etc.</item>
                  <item>Southern States</item>
               </list> 
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[1]"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <address>
                        <addrLine>
                           <name type="place">Washington City</name>
                        </addrLine>
                     </address>
                     <date value="1835-01-14">
                        <abbr expan="January" type="contraction">Janry</abbr> 14th 1835</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>
                     <abbr expan="Messieurs" type="contraction">Messrs.</abbr> 
                     <name type="person" reg="Mr.">Barron</name>  
                     <name type="person" reg="Mr.">Irwin</name>
                     <lb/>Gentlemen,,
                  </salute>
               </opener>
               <p>Under the appropriations make by the <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Council at <name type="place">Red Clay</name> last fall, for the <abbr expan="Attorneys">Attos.</abbr> of the Nation; the Treasurer Mr. <name type="person">John Martin</name> has been instructed to pay to your order the sum of Two hundred dollars.  And in making the payment, I am <del type="overstrike">assured</del> 
                  <add place="supralinear">authorized</add> by the Council, to assure you that this sum, <q>is only an earnest of what the Nation will do for you, when its ability shall be increased</q>.  The Delegation have submitted to the President <orig reg="through">thro'</orig> the <abbr expan="Secretary" type="contraction">Secry</abbr> of War, the late Act of <name type="place">Georgia</name>; and will also present it before Congress, as soon as practicable.  The Act of <date value="1833-00-00">1833</date> and the late Amendatory One are <add place="supralinear">also</add> before the <name type="person">Cherokee</name> Council here, for legal advice the cases of <name type="person">Lynch</name>'s  <name type="person">
                     <unclear>Pipe</unclear>
                  </name>'s are expected to come up before the Supreme Court, some time next month  <name type="person">
                     <unclear>Mr</unclear> Sergeant</name>  
                  <name type="person">
                     <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Walter Jones</name> will appear for them.</p>
               <closer>In great haste, I am Gentlemen, Your <abbr expan="Obedient Servant" type="acronym">Obt. Servt.</abbr>
                  <lb/>
                     <signed>
                        <name type="person">
                           <abbr expan="John">Jno</abbr> Ross</name>
                     </signed>
                  
               </closer>
            
         </div1>
         <div1 type="letter">
            <p>PS. Do, pray let me hear from you of passing events if you have nothing consoling to communicate, let <add place="supralinear">the</add> worst come; my mind is prepared to hear and bear any thing.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[2]"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <head>
                        <name type="place">WASHINGTON</name> 
                        <unclear>
                           <date value="0000-01-15">JAN 15</date>
                        </unclear>
                     </head>
                     <figDesc>A postmark appears on the left of this page.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            
         </div1>
         <div1 type="letter">
            <p>No. 8</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="letter">
            <p>25</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="letter">
            <p>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <abbr expan="Messieurs" type="contraction">Messrs.</abbr> 
                     <name type="person" reg="Mr.">Barron</name>  
                     <name type="person" reg="Mr.">Irwin</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <abbr expan="attorneys" type="contraction">Attos.</abbr> at Law.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Cassville</name>, <name type="place person">Cherokee Nation</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Georgia</name>,</addrLine>
               </address>
            </p>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
