<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="ch050">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Account of S[amuel] A. Worcester's second arrest, 1831 July 18 / S[amuel] A. Worcester: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Worcester, S. A. (Samuel Austin), 1798-1859</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch050</idno>
            <idno>oclc: 44845987</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is the property of The University of Tennessee Special Collections Library.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Account of S[amuel] A. Worcester's second arrest, 1831 July 18 / S[amuel] A. Worcester</title>
               <author>Worcester, S. A. (Samuel Austin), 1798-1859</author>
               <date value="1831-07-18">July 18, 1831</date>
               <extent>12p</extent>
               <note type="summary">Account dated July 18, 1831 of the second arrest of Samuel A. Worcester, Moravian missionary to the Cherokees.  Worcester outlines the events of his arrest and the arrest of others by Sergeant Brooks, Colonel Nelson and their men, including the harsh treatment received by the prisoners.</note>
               <note type="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box">1</note>
               <note type="folder">29</note>
               <note type="document">ch050</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>Prisoners</item>
                  <item>Missionaries</item>
                  <item>Georgia</item>
               </list> 
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="letter legal military">
            <pb n="[1]"/>
               <p>
                  <add place="top" cert="appears to be different ink and hand">
                     <unclear/> 
                     <name type="person">Mr. Worcester</name>s account of his second arrest, and of the treatment which himself, <name type="person">Dr. Butler</name>,  other prisoners <orig reg="received">recieved</orig> from the guard, contained in a letter dated <date value="1831-07-18">July 18th, 1831</date>
                  </add>
               </p>
               <p>Early on Friday morning, <date value="0000-07-08">July 8</date> I with my guard Joined <name type="person">Sergeant Brooks</name> at a the house of a near neighbor and rode <orig reg="thence">thense</orig> ten miles to where <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> was with a detachment of which that under <name type="person">Mr. Brooks</name> by which I was arrested, was only apart.  There I found the <name type="person">Rev. Mr. Trott</name>, a methodist missionary who has a <name type="person">Cherokee</name> family, and a <name type="person">Cherokee</name> by the name of <name type="person">Proctor</name>, <name type="person">Proctor</name> was chained to the wall of the house by the neck  had another chain around his <orig reg="ankle">ancle</orig>. He had been arrested on Tuesday, on the charge of digging for gold, chained the first night by the <orig reg="ankle">ancle</orig> only, the second  third by the neck to the wall  by the <orig reg="ankle">ancle</orig> to <name type="person">Mr. Trott</name>.  <name type="person">Mr. Trott</name> was arrested on Wednesday  taken on horseback about ten miles to where <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> then was.  He had been before arrested,  was under bonds to answer at Court for the offence of residing in the nation without licence  now was taken again,  having committed the second offence by returning to his family while the cause was pending.  On Thursday, he  <name type="person">Proctor</name> were marched on foot 22 miles, to the place where I found them, <name type="person">Proctor</name> being chained by the neck to the <orig reg="wagon">waggon</orig>. This manner of treatment, I suppose, was occasioned by his having resistance when arrested and afterwards attempted to escape.</p>
               <p>When I was arrested, <name type="person">Sergeant Brooks</name> enquired the state of my family,  when told that <name type="person">Mrs. Worcester</name> was still confined to her bed, remarked<pb n="[2]"/>that he regretted that <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> was not himself present, <sic corr="implying">implying implying</sic>, as I understood him, that if he were, he probably would not arrest me under such circumstances.  When we arrived where <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> was, I requested <name type="person">Mr. Brooks</name>, to mention to him the state in which he found us, which he very readily promised to do, but certainly had not fulfilled his promise when I heard him say that I was to go on to Head Quarters ie. to this place.  Perceiving, therefore that the state of my family was not to be regarded, I said no more.
               </p>
               <p>We were then marched on foot 22 miles to the same place from which <name type="person">Mr. Trott</name>  
                  <name type="person">Mr. Proctor</name> were taken the day before,  <name type="person">Proctor</name> being again chained to the <orig reg="wagon">waggon</orig>.  We had proceeded about three miles, When we met <abbr expan="Messieurs"> Messrs.</abbr> 
                  <name type="person" reg="Mr.">McLeod</name>  
                  <name type="person" reg="Mr.">Wells</name>, <orig reg="two">tow</orig> Methodist clergymen, not residing within the charter of <name type="place">Georgia</name>.  With leave of <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name>, they turned  rode along some distance in our company.  In conversation, <del type="erasure">
                     <unclear/>
                  </del> 
                  <name type="person">Mr. McLeod</name> asked <name type="person">Mr. Trott</name> whether he had been chained the <orig reg="preceding">preceeding</orig> night,  being answered in the affirmative, asked if it were according to law to chain a prisoner who manifested no disposition to escape.  <name type="person">Mr. Trott</name> said he thought not, but that we ought not to blame those under <orig reg="whose">who</orig> charge we were, as they were obliged to act according to orders.  <name type="person">Mr McLeod</name> remarked <q>It seems they proceed more by orders than by laws</q> This gave offence.  A few words had passed between <name type="person">Mr. McLeod</name>  some of the guard, when <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> rode up  being told of the remark, asked <name type="person">Mr.  McLeod</name> where he <unclear>rides</unclear>.  He replied <unclear>to</unclear> 
                  <name type="place">Tennessee</name>.  <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name>, with a curse, ordered him to <q>flank of</q> Mr.<pb n="[3]"/> 
                     <name type="person" reg="Mr.">McLeod</name>, turning his horse, said I will sir, if it your command" but added, hastily as he afterwards said <q>You will hear from me again.</q>  He was then riding away, when the Col. ordered him to halt,  then to dismount  lead his horse along in the rear.  He then inquired of <name type="person">Mr. Trott</name> whether this was one of their circuit riders"  <name type="person">Mr. Trott</name> answered <q>yes</q>  
                     <name type="person">Mr. McLeod</name>'s horse was then taken from him  delivered to <name type="person">Mr. Wells</name>, and he was declared a prisoner  ordered to walk on with the rest.  For a short distance, <name type="person">Brooks</name> compelled him to keep the center of the road, through mire  water threatening to thrust him through with the<orig reg="bayonet"> bayonette</orig> if he turned aside.  In the meantime he was heaping upon all our heads a load of tremendous curses,  reviling missionaries and all ministers of the Gospel in language, which for profaneness and obscenity, could not be exceeded.  The words of our Savior he turned into ridicule   <add place="supralinear">"Fear not- said he tauntingly </add> Fear not" little flock, for it is you Father's good pleasure to give you the kingdom."  The manner in which these words were uttered did not prevent me, at least from rejoicing in the consolation they afford.  <name type="person">Brooks</name> was the chief speaker,  exceeded all, though some others joined him in his <orig reg="revelings">revilings</orig>.
               </p>
               <p>Another circumstance afterwards occurred, which was related to me by <name type="person">Mr. Thompson</name>, who was eye witness.  <name type="person">Mr. Wells</name>, after <name type="person">Mr. McLeod</name>'s arrest, pursued his journey in the opposite direction till he met <name type="person">Mr Thompson</name> riding in the same direction with the guard.  He then turned  rode in company with Mr. T. intending to see what should become of <name type="person">Mr. McLeod</name>,  to render him any assistance in his power.  After some time they came up with the guard.  When <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> saw <name type="person">Mr. Wells</name>, he ordered him to ride<pb n="4"/>out of his sight either before or behind, threatening violence if he did not.  <name type="person">Mr. Wells</name>, without replying fell back a little  followed on.  <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> cut a stick and making up to <name type="person">Mr. Wells</name> gave him a severe blow on the head.  <name type="person">Mr. Wells</name> then said he had a right to travel the public road  should do it.  He persevered accordingly  rode on till he came to a house where <name type="person">Mr. McLeod</name> requested him to stop.  I know not what offence <name type="person">Mr. Wells</name> had given, unless that, in conversation with me, he had expressed strong disapprobation of the policy of the state of <name type="place">Georgia</name>,  the course pursued by the Executive of the <name type="place">United States</name>.
               </p>
               <p>Towards the end of our days Journey, <name type="person">Mr. McLeod</name> was afflicted with a severe pain in the hips  knees, to which he had been subject,  requested the privilege of riding.  <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> sent him answer, that <name type="person">Proctor</name> at first thought that he could not walk, but afterwards got along very well.</p>
               <p>
                  <orig reg="At">A</orig> night the four prisoners were chained together by their <orig reg="ankle">ancle</orig> in pairs.</p>
               <p>Some time after we lay down, a small detachment arrived with <name type="person">Doctor Butler</name>.  He had been arrested at <name type="place">Haweis</name> on the <orig reg="preceding">preceeding</orig> day.  After crossing a river three or four miles from home, a chain was fastened by a padlock around his neck, and at the other end to the neck of a horse, by the side of which he walked  Night soon came on.  The horse was kept walking at a quick pace, and <name type="person">Doctor Butler</name> unable to see any obstruction which a rough<pb n="[5]"/>road might present, and liable at any moment to fall, and so to be dragged by the neck till the horse should stop.  After walking some distance in the dark, on representing the danger of his situation, he was taken up behind the saddle, his chain being still fastened to the horse's neck,  short enough to keep his neck close to the shoulder of the guard.  In this situation the horse fell both his riders fell under him, and neither the horse nor either of the men could rise, till others could come and, after ascertaining their situation by the sense of feeling, roll the horse over.  <name type="person">Dr. Butler</name> was considerably hurt, but the soldier none, having two ribs broken.  After this, till they came to their lodgings, <name type="person">Dr. Butler</name> was permitted to ride, while a soldier walked.  In the mean time they lost their way in the woods.  However, they found a pine knot, of which they made a torch by striking fire; and by this means recovered their way.  Their lodging place was only 11 miles from <name type="person">Dr. Butlers</name>, but it was midnight when they arrived, well drenched with rain.  When they lay down, the prisoner was chained to his bedstead by the <orig reg="ankle">ancle</orig> the officer, however, putting a handkerchief around under the chain.  The next day they had 35 miles or more to travel.  <name type="person">Dr. Butler</name> wore the chain on his neck, but no longer fastened to a horse.  He was occasionally permitted to ride, one or another of the soldier's walking in his stead.  At night he was chained to <name type="person">Mr. McLeod</name> and me.
               </p>
               <p>On Friday morning we had to cross the <name type="place">Hightower river</name> in boat.  As the prisoners, with a part of the guard, were crossing<pb n="[6]"/>
                     <name type="person">Mr. Thompson</name> was observed on the opposite side waiting to speak with us.  At the same time <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name>  
                     <name type="person">Sergeant Brooks</name> were observed in conversation.  <name type="person">Brooks</name> then called to those who were with us, charging them that no person should be allowed to speak with a prisoner privately, and no letter to be delivered unexamined.  <name type="person">Proctor</name> was now mounted on his own horse (which had been taken as a prize when he was arrested) wearing a chain, as <name type="person">Dr. Butler</name> had worn it the day before.  He had a bag of clothes for a saddle, and a rope halter instead of a bridle.  No other one was chained.  When we had travelled a considerable distance, four of the soldiers were so kind as to walk four or five miles  allow the prisoners to ride for which we were told they were afterwards abused by <name type="person">Brooks</name>, who now had the command of the detachment.  <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> having parted from them.  Afterwards <name type="person">Mr. Trott</name>, being likely to fail , was mounted on <name type="person">Proctor</name>'s horse in his stead.  Still later <name type="person">Mr. McLeod</name>, having become so lame that he could scarcely walk, solicited the privilege of riding, <name type="person">Brooks</name> with much cursing compelled him to walk on.  Afterwards, however, he ordered <name type="person">Mr. Trott</name> to dismount, and placed <name type="person">Mr. McLeod</name> in his stead.  Our days journey was 35 miles
               </p>
               <p>At night only <name type="person">Proctor</name> was chained.  <name type="person">Brooks</name> having retired without giving any orders, on the subject, and the officer who had the charge of us not being disposed to chain us. </p>
               <pb n="[7]"/>
                  <p>The sabbath came  we had 22 miles to travel.  Remonstrance would <orig reg="only">on</orig> have irritated.  We were under the command of armed men,  must travel on.  <name type="person">Mr. McLeod</name> being utterly unable to walk, was  mounted on <name type="person">Proctor</name>'s horse.  <name type="person">Mr. Trott</name> was allowed to ride part of the way in the <orig reg="wagon">waggon</orig> and <name type="person">Dr. Butler</name>   myself two or three miles on horse back.</p>
                  <p>Arrived here, we were, as a matter of course, marched into camp under sound of fife and drum.  We were then introduced to the jail, <name type="person">Brooks</name> saying, as we entered <q>There is <orig reg="where">were</orig> all the enemies of <name type="place">Georgia</name> have to land,  there and in Hell</q>  Happily man has not the <orig reg="keys">keyes</orig> of the everlasting prison.  At night a white man who has a <name type="person">Cherokee</name> family was added to our number.</p>
                  <p>On monday <name type="person">Mr. Thompson</name> 
                     <del type="overstrike">was admitted</del>  
                     <name type="person">Mr. Wells</name> came  requested an interview with us.  <name type="person">Mr. Thomas</name> was admitted under the restriction that no one would have any private conversation with us, or receive any papers from us without their being inspected by <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name>, who has the present command.  <name type="person">Col. Sanford</name> being absent, <name type="person">Mr. Wells</name> was refused admittance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <name type="person">Mr. McLeod</name> sent a note to <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> on Monday, requesting a personal interview.  On Tuesday morning <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> sent for him,  dismissed him.  He was not permitted to return  bid us farewell.</p>
                  <p>On Saturday evening, <date value="0000-07-16">July 16</date> perceiving that we should probably spend the sabbath here, we sent to <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> the following request.</p>
                  <pb n="[8]"/>
                     <q>
                        <text>
                           <body>
                              <div1 type="letter">
                                 <opener> 
                                    <salute>
                                       <name type="person">Col. <unclear>Ch</unclear> H Nelson</name>
                                       <lb/>Sir
                                    </salute>
                                 </opener>
                                 <p>If it be consistent with necessary regulations it would be a high gratification to some of your prisoners, if <name type="person">Mr. Trott</name>  
                                    <name type="person">Mr. Worcester</name> might be permitted to hold a meeting tomorrow evening at some place where such of the guard  of the neighbors as are disposed might attend.  If the favor can be granted, be so kind as to give us an answer as soon as convenient.   We wish to be understood that we should all greatly desire the privilege of attending.</p>
                                 <closer>(Signed) <signed>
                                       <name type="person">
                                          <abbr expan="Samuel">S.</abbr> A. Worcester</name>
                                    </signed>
                                    <signed>
                                       <name type="person">gg Trott</name>
                                    </signed>
                                    <signed>
                                       <name type="person">Elizur Butler</name>
                                    </signed>
                                    <signed>
                                       <name type="person">Samuel Mayes</name>
                                    </signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div1>
                           </body>
                        </text>
                     </q>
                     <p>This note was presently returned with the following written on the outside.</p>
                     <q>
                        <text>
                           <body>
                              <div1 type="letter">
                                 <p>We view the within request as an impertinent one.  If Your conduct  be evidence of your character  the doctrines you wish to promulgate, we are sufficiently enlightened as to both.  Our object is to restrain, not to facilitate their promulgation.  If you object be true piety you can enjoy it where you are were we hearers we would not be <orig reg="benefitted">benefited</orig>, devoid as we are of confidence in your honesty.</p>
                                 <closer>Signed <signed>
                                       <name type="person">C H Nelson</name>
                                    </signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div1>
                           </body>
                        </text>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="[9]"/>
                        <p> From most of the individuals of the guard we have received no ill treatment; from some of them kindness.  As was, however, <add place="supralinear">perhaps</add> to be expected in our circumstances, we have received some insults, which it is trying for the spirit to bear: But we regard it as a testimony in our favor, that when the desire is to torture us, it is taken for granted that this case be best effected by uttering profane  obscene expressions in our ears.</p>
                        <p>
                           <date value="0000-07-19">July 19</date> Yesterday <name type="person">Mr. Thompson</name>  Mr. <name type="person">William Rogers</name> a <name type="person">Cherokee</name> who acts as agent for the nation, arrived,  presented to <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> a writ of <hi>habeas corpus</hi>, which they had procured to remove us from this place.  This would have been sooner done, but <name type="person">Dr. Butler</name> and I thought it best for <name type="person">Mr. Thompson</name> first to consult <name type="person">Mr. Underwood</name> our counsel, who lives at considerable distance, whether that was the best course to pursue in reference to the final result.  When the writ arrived, we supposed we should be immediately taken before a court, but we still remain here.</p>
                        <p>
                           <name type="place">New Echota</name>. <date value="0000-06-28">June 28</date> After I had written the above we still remained in Jail till thursday morning <date value="0000-07-21">July 21</date>.  The reason afterwards assigned by <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> in court for our detention was, that <name type="person">Col. Sanford</name> who returned on Wednesday evening from a Journey to <name type="place">Milledgeville</name>, had important testimony in his possession.  On thursday morning, we were furnished with horses  set out for <name type="place">Lawrenceville</name>.  On the way we were taken before a Justice of the peace  committed to Jail, although the writ of habeas Corpus required <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> to present us before the county court at <name type="place">Lawrenceville</name>.</p>
                        <pb n="[10]"/>
                           <p>It was understood that the constable into whose <unclear>han</unclear> we were committed would wait upon the Col. til he could attend the court.  We arrived at <name type="place">Lawrenceville</name> late at night.  Friday was spent in a vain attempt to convene the court.  On Saturday morning, <name type="person">Dr. Butler</name> had a very violent  dangerous attack of bilious <orig reg="colic">colick</orig>, and although by prompt  vigorous medical assistance he was relieved in a few hours, he was by no means able to attend court.  The <name type="person">Cherokee</name> also was unable to attend.</p>
                           <p>The court convened  we were presented before them I think at about 11 o'clock A.M.  I will not attempt to describe the proceedings.  They appeared to me as singular as the attitude in which we were presented, in the hands of a constable already committed to jail  at the same time in the hands of <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> to be presented before the court to which he was required to render the reasons of our capture  detention.  In the result, we were ordered to give security for our appearance at the next term of the superior court, or be anew committed to Jail.  We all gave bail for our appearance except the <name type="person">Cherokee</name>, who could not, at that time, find any one to be his security.</p>
                           <p>
                              <add place="left">Insert here the paragraph on the following page</add>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <name type="person">Dr. Butler</name>  myself left <name type="place">Lawrenceville</name> on monday morning, after experiencing several acts of distinguished kindness from some of the most respectable citizens, which we shall gratefully remember.  </p>
                           <p>I arrived at home last night,  had the satisfaction to find that <name type="person">Mr. Worcester</name>s health had considerably improved during my absence.</p>
                           <closer>I remain with much affection  respect (Signed)<signed>
                                 <name type="person">
                                    <abbr expan="Samuel">S.</abbr> A. Worcester</name>.</signed>
                              <pb n="[11]"/>
                                 <add place="top">(insert this paragraph as marked on the preceding page)</add> In the course of the trial, <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name>'s counsel produced as evidence in the case of <name type="person">Dr. Butler</name>  myself a letter of the Post master General to the Governor informing him of my removal from office.  A letter from the Secretary of war disavowing missionaries as agents of the General Government.  <name type="person">Dr. Butler</name>'s answer  mine to the governor's letter to us,  a letter from the governor to <name type="person">Col. Sanford</name>, directing him to have us arrested forthwith, and <emph>if we should be released by the courts</emph> or give bail  return home to have us arrested again.  These letters I suppose were the important testimony referred to by <name type="person">Col. Nelson</name> as having been in the hands of <name type="person">Col. Sanford</name>
                              
                           </closer>
                        
                     
                  
               
            
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 type="letter legal military">
            <pb n="[12]"/>
               <p>Papers in relation to the arrest of the <name type="person">Cherokee</name> missionaries </p>
            
         </div1>
         <div1 type="letter legal military">
            <p>
               <date value="1816-00-00">1816</date>
            </p>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
