<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="ch066">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Correspondence between commissioners on the part of the United States and the Council of the Cherokee Nation, 1823 Oct., Newtown : a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch066</idno>
            <idno>oclc: 44854395</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Correspondence between commissioners on the part of the United States and the Council of the Cherokee Nation, 1823 Oct., Newtown</title>
               <date value="1823-10-04">October 4, 1823</date>
               <date value="1823-10-18">October 18, 1823</date>
               <extent>17p</extent>
               <note type="summary">Copy of correspondence between United States Commissioners Duncan G. Campbell and James Meriwether, appointed to treat with the Cherokee Nation, and the Council of the Cherokee Nation. All minutes and correspondence occur within October 1823. Also includes letters between the U.S. Commissioners and Joseph McMinn, U.S. Agent to the Cherokee Nation (and former Governor of Tennessee) and the U.S. and Georgia Commissioners, Wellborn and Blair, sent to take part in the same negotiations. The commissioners did not achieve their purpose.</note>
               <note type="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box">3</note>
               <note type="folder">5</note>
               <note type="document">ch066</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Treaties</item>
                  <item>Southern States</item>
               </list> 
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div1 type="legal council minutes letter">
            <pb n="[1]"/>
               <p>Copy of a Correspondence between Commissioners on the part of the <name type="place">United States</name>; and the Council of the <name type="place person">Cherokee Nation</name>
                  <lb/>
                     <address>
                        <addrLine>
                           <name type="place">Newtown</name>
                        </addrLine>
                     </address> 
                     <date value="1823-10-00">
                        <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr> 1823.</date>
                  
               </p>
            
         </div1>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div1 type="legal council minutes letter">
            <pb n="[2]"/>
               <head>
                  <name type="place person">Cherokee Nation</name> 
               </head>
               <p>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Newtown</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address> 
                  <date>4th <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr> 1823</date>
               </p>
               <p>The commissioners on the part of the <name type="place">United States</name> commissioned to hold a treaty with the <name type="place person">Cherokee Nation</name> of Indians arrived at this place, where they found the National council in Session.  The Board organized but found it impracticable to proceed to business without first making some improvements for their accommodation, which they determined to do with as little delay as possible.</p>
               <p>
                  <date value="00-10-05">Monday 5th <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr>
                  </date>
               </p>
               <p>On this day the board were notified by the Agent of the Nation, that the Grand council were disposed to receive and be introduced to the Board according to the "custom  ceremonial" of the Nation   Whereupon the Board, accompanied by the Agent, and State Commissioners, attended at the Council House and were presented to the King, Council  Committee.  The Speaker, <name type="person">Major Ridge</name>, addressed the Board in <pb n="[3]"/>terms of congratulation and friendship, and was answered by one of the Board, <name type="person">Mr. Campbell</name>, in like terms 
               </p>
               <p>The Board addressed to the Agent <name type="person">
                     <abbr expan="Governor" type="contraction">Govr. </abbr> McMinn</name> the following note</p>
               <q>
                  <text>
                     <body>
                        <div1 type="legal council minutes letter">
                           <opener>
                              <salute>Sir,</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>We take this, the earliest <del type="overstrike">opportunity</del> convenient occasion which has offered since our arrival to inform you that we have proceeded hither for the purpose of submitting to the <name type="place person">Cherokee Nation</name> Subjects of interest to the general government</p>
                           <p>The commissions under which propose to act and the instructions subjoined by the War Department we deem proper to be submitted to you, having been led to expect your cooperation in all matters relating to our Mission.  Permit us to request that you will designate an hour, most convenient to yourself, for us to Submit our Commissions and instructions to your perusal.</p>
                           <p>The absence of our Secretary at present, we hope<pb n="[4]"/>will be accepted as an apology for not furnishing you copies
                           </p>
                           <closer>With Sentiments of consideration  esteem We are<abbr expan="your obedient Servants" type="contractions"> yr obt Serts</abbr>
                              <signed>
                                 <name type="person">Duncan G. Campbell</name>
                              </signed>
                              <signed>
                                 <name type="person">James Meriwether</name>
                              </signed> 
                              <name type="place">U.S.</name> 
                              <abbr expan="Commissioners" type="contraction">Comrs.</abbr>
                              <lb/>
                                 <address>
                                    <addrLine>
                                       <name type="person">Joseph McMinn</name> 
                                       <abbr expan="Esquire" type="suspension">Esq.</abbr> Agent</addrLine>
                                 </address>
                              
                           </closer>
                        </div1>
                     </body>
                  </text>
               </q>
               <p>The Agents reply</p>
               <q>
                  <text>
                     <body>
                        <div1 type="legal council minutes letter">
                           <opener>
                              <dateline>
                                 <address>
                                    <addrLine>
                                       <name type="place">Newtown</name>
                                    </addrLine>
                                 </address> 
                                 <date value="1823-10-07">7th <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr> 1823</date>
                              </dateline>
                              <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>Your polite note of yesterday morning is before me, and would have been answered without loss of time had not the ceremonies of yesterday occupied public attention.  I will do myself the honor to attend at my office at any time after early candle light</p>
                           <closer>With sentiments of great esteem <abbr expan="et cetera your obedient Servant" type="contractions"> c yr obt Sert.</abbr>
                              <signed>
                                 <name type="person">
                                    <abbr expan="Joseph">Jos.</abbr> McMinn</name>
                              </signed>
                              <lb/>
                                 <address>
                                    <addrLine>
                                       <abbr expan="Honorable" type="contraction">Honble.</abbr> 
                                       <name type="person">
                                          <abbr expan="Duncan">D.</abbr> G. Campbell</name>  
                                       <name type="person">James Meriwether</name> 
                                       <name type="place">U.S.</name> Commissioners</addrLine>
                                 </address>
                              
                           </closer>
                        </div1>
                     </body>
                  </text>
               </q>
               <pb n="[5]"/>
                  <p>
                     <name type="person">Governor McMinn</name> to the Board</p>
                  <q>
                     <text>
                        <body>
                           <div1 type="legal council minutes letter">
                              <opener>
                                 <dateline>
                                    <date value="1823-10-08">8th <abbr expan="October">Octr</abbr> 1823</date>
                                 </dateline>
                                 <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>I enclose you the copy of an order from the National Committee <orig reg="agreeable">agreable</orig> to request</p>
                              <closer>Your <abbr expan="Obedient Servant" type="contractions">Obt Sert.</abbr> 
                                 <signed>
                                    <name type="person">Joseph McMinn</name>
                                 </signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div1>
                        </body>
                     </text>
                  </q>
                  <p>Copy </p>
                  <q>
                     <text>
                        <body>
                           <div1 type="legal council minutes letter">
                              <opener>
                                 <dateline>
                                    <address>
                                       <addrLine>Committee Chamber</addrLine>
                                    </address> 
                                    <date value="1823-10-08">8th <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr> 1823</date>
                                 </dateline>
                                 <salute>
                                    <name type="person">Joseph McMinn</name> Agent <abbr expan="et cetera">c.</abbr>
                                    <lb/>Sir,
                                 </salute>
                              </opener>
                              <p>I am directed by the Committee  Council to request you to inform the <name type="place">United States</name> commissioners, that the General Council when convened tomorrow morning, will be in readiness to receive the Commissioners touching the objects of their mission hither under instructions from the President of the <name type="place">United States</name>.  It is desired that the communication Should embrace fully all the instructions they may have received from the President relative thereto.</p>
                              <closer>I am Sir Respectfully<signed>
                                    <name type="person">John Ross</name>
                                 </signed>
                              </closer>
                           </div1>
                        </body>
                     </text>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="[6]"/>
                     <p>The Boards reply to the Council</p>
                     <q>
                        <text>
                           <body>
                              <div1 type="legal council minutes letter">
                                 <opener>
                                    <dateline>
                                       <date value="1823-10-08">8th <abbr expan="October">Octr</abbr> 1823</date>
                                    </dateline>
                                 </opener>
                                 <p>The undersigned, Commissioners on the part of the <name type="place">United States</name>, have received through the agent a communication, by which they are notified,</p>
                                 <p>
                                    <q>That the general Council when convened tomorrow morning will be in readiness to receive their (the commissioners) communications touching the object of their mission</q> to which we reply, that we will do ourselves the pleasure to appear before the general council tomorrow morning at 10 oclock, for the purpose of exhibiting the commission under which we propose to commence negotiations.  The want of Suitable accommodations since our arrival will place it beyond our power to submit a communication as early as suggested by the committee  council in their note to the agent </p>
                                 <closer>With sentiments of due consideration We are yours <abbr expan="et cetera et cetera et cetera">c. c. c.</abbr>
                                    <signed>
                                       <name type="person">Duncan G. Campbell</name>
                                    </signed>
                                    <signed>
                                       <name type="person">James Meriwether</name>
                                    </signed>
                                    <lb/>
                                       <address>
                                          <addrLine>To the National Council</addrLine>
                                       </address>
                                    
                                 </closer>
                              </div1>
                           </body>
                        </text>
                     </q>
                     <pb n="[7]"/>
                        <p>
                           <date value="1823-10-09">9th <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr> 1823</date>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Board attended the Council pursuant to appointment and submitted their commission which was read and interpreted, and they then retired </p>
                        <p>
                           <date value="0000-10-10">10th <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr>
                           </date>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Board convened and notified the council that they would lay a communication before them <orig reg="today">to day</orig> at 2 oclock </p>
                        <p>The following is a copy of the communication </p>
                        <q>
                           <text>
                              <body>
                                 <div1 type="legal council minutes letter">
                                    <opener>
                                       <salute>To the Grand Council of the <name type="place person">Cherokee Nation</name> 
                                          <lb/>Friends  Brothers,
                                       </salute>
                                    </opener>
                                    <p>By the commission which we laid before you yesterday under the hand of your father, the President you discover that we have authority to "hold conference with you, of and con-<pb n="[8]"/>cerning, all matters interesting to the <name type="place">United States</name> and the <name type="place person">Cherokee Nation</name>.  From the powers conveyed to us it becomes our duty to bring to <add place="supralinear">your </add> notice the Commissioners on the part of the State of <name type="place">Georgia</name>.  These Gentlemen have accompanied us today for the purpose of showing their credentials.  They are commissioned by the Governor of <name type="place">Georgia</name>, but their business has been made Known to our father the President and he has directed us to cooperate with them and give them our aid.  In some of the writings which have passed between us, we are sorry to discover that the business of these commissioners is treated lightly and but little attention given to the Subject.  For the Sake of good understanding and justice we ask you to listen with patience to what these commiss<add place="supralinear">ioners</add> 
                                          <del type="overstrike">
                                             <unclear/>
                                          </del> may have to Say.  After taking a deliberate view of all the treaties heretofore made, you will be able to make up a decision.  It is better they should be closed in one way or another.  As soon as this part of our joint business is settled and<pb n="[9]"/>adjusted, the <name type="place">United States</name> commissioners will take occasion to Submit matters of interest and importance to the government and to the Nation.
                                       
                                    </p>
                                    <closer>We renew our wishes that all our negotiations may be calm and friendly <signed>
                                          <name type="person">Duncan G. Campbell</name>
                                       </signed>
                                       <signed>
                                          <name type="person">James Meriwether</name>
                                       </signed> 
                                       <name type="place">U.S.</name> 
                                       <abbr expan="Commissioners" type="contraction">Comrs.</abbr>
                                       <lb/>Ordered that a copy of the foregoing be handed to the <name type="place">Georgia</name> Commissioners and that they be requested to attend this board, this day at 2 Oclock for the purpose of appearing before the Council jointly 
                                    </closer>
                                 </div1>
                              </body>
                           </text>
                        </q>
                        <p>
                           <date value="1823-10-13">13th. <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr> 1823</date>
                        </p>
                        <p>The Board accompanied the State Commissioners to the Council House, where a talk was delivered to the council by that Board setting forth the grounds of the <name type="place">Georgia</name> claims as arising under the different treaties with this Nation</p>
                        <pb n="[10]"/>
                           <p>
                              <date value="1823-10-14">14th <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr> 1823</date>
                           </p>
                           <p>On this day the council returned an answer to the communication of yesterday and the Board were called on by the State Commissioners to cooperate with them in pursuing, the negotiation and did so in the preparation of a further address</p>
                           <p>
                              <date value="1823-10-15">15th <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr> 1823</date>
                           </p>
                           <p>The Board again accompanied the <name type="place">Georgia</name> Commissioners to the Council where a talk was delivered</p>
                           <p>
                              <date value="0000-10-16">16th <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr>
                              </date>
                           </p>
                           <p>The following, note was received, from, the council.</p>
                           <q>
                              <text>
                                 <body>
                                    <div1 type="legal council minutes letter">
                                       <opener>
                                          <dateline>
                                             <address>
                                                <addrLine>
                                                   <name type="place">Newtown</name>
                                                </addrLine>
                                             </address> 
                                             <date value="1823-10-18">
                                                <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr> 18th 1823</date>
                                          </dateline>
                                          <salute>In <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Council<lb/>Friends  Brothers,
                                          </salute>
                                       </opener>
                                       <p>The General Council now embrace the opportunity of informing you that their correspondence with the commissioners on the part of <name type="place">Georgia</name> is brought to a close, and that the General Council now convened is ready to receive your communication on all subjects relating to your instructions from the President of the <name type="place">United States</name> 
                                       </p>
                                       <pb n="[11]"/>
                                          <closer>With consideration of respect and esteem; we take you by the right hand as friends  Brothers<signed>
                                                <name type="person">Path Killer</name>
                                             </signed> 
                                             <abbr expan="principal" type="contraction">pl</abbr> Chief his <signed>X</signed> mark <signed>
                                                <name type="person">Major Ridge</name>
                                             </signed>- Speaker of the Council  <signed>
                                                <name type="person">John Ross</name>
                                             </signed> 
                                             <abbr expan="President of the National Committee" type="suspension">Prest. N. Comt.</abbr>
                                             <signed>
                                                <name type="person">
                                                   <abbr expan="Alexander">A.</abbr> McCoy</name>
                                             </signed>, <abbr expan="clerk" type="contraction">clk</abbr>  
                                             <abbr expan="National" type="suspension">N.</abbr> Committee<signed>
                                                <name type="person">Elijah Hicks</name>
                                             </signed> 
                                             <abbr expan="Clerk National" type="contraction">Clk, N.</abbr> Council</closer>
                                       
                                    </div1>
                                 </body>
                              </text>
                           </q>
                           <p>Copy of a note received from the <name type="place">Georgia</name> 
                              <abbr expan="Commissioners" type="contraction">Comrs.</abbr>
                           </p>
                           <q>
                              <text>
                                 <body>
                                    <div1 type="legal council minutes letter">
                                       <opener>
                                          <dateline>
                                             <address>
                                                <addrLine>
                                                   <name type="place">Newtown</name>
                                                </addrLine>
                                             </address>
                                             <date value="1823-10-16">16th <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr> 1823</date>
                                          </dateline>
                                          <salute>Gentlemen </salute>
                                       </opener>
                                       <p>We have this moment received a communication from the National Council of the <name type="place person">Cherokee Nation</name> in answer to ours to them of yesterdays date, a copy of their communication to us of this days date you herewith receive  We solicit a conference with you upon this subject as soon, as it may comport with your convenience.</p>
                                       <closer>We remain <abbr expan="Gentlemen" type="suspension">Gent.</abbr> with great respect and esteem, your<abbr expan="obedient Servants" type="contactions"> obt Serts</abbr>
                                          <signed>
                                             <name type="person">Johnson Wellborn</name>
                                          </signed>
                                          <signed>
                                             <name type="person">James Blair</name>
                                          </signed>
                                          <lb/>
                                             <abbr expan="Georgia Commissioners" type="contraction">
                                                <name type="place">Ga.</name> Comrs.</abbr>
                                          
                                       </closer>
                                    </div1>
                                 </body>
                              </text>
                           </q>
                           <pb n="[12]"/>
                              <p>Reply to the <name type="place">Georgia</name> Commissioners</p>
                              <q>
                                 <text>
                                    <body>
                                       <div1 type="legal council minutes letter">
                                          <opener>
                                             <dateline>
                                                <address>
                                                   <addrLine>
                                                      <name type="place">Newtown</name>,</addrLine>
                                                </address> 
                                                <date value="1823-10-15">15th, <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr> 1823</date>
                                             </dateline>
                                             <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                                          </opener>
                                          <p>In reply to your note of this days date the answer, that <add place="supralinear">we</add> will be prepared to have an interview with you this evening at candle light for the purpose of having a conference upon the subject of the communication received this day, by you from the <name type="person">Cherokee</name> Chiefs </p>
                                          <closer>With Sentiments of esteem  respect We are your <abbr expan="obedient Servants" type="contraction ">obt. Serts.</abbr>
                                             <signed>
                                                <name type="person">Duncan G. Campbell</name>
                                             </signed>
                                             <signed>
                                                <name type="person">James Meriwether</name>
                                             </signed>
                                             <lb/>
                                                <address>
                                                   <addrLine>To <abbr expan="Messieurs" type="contraction">Messrs</abbr>
                                                   </addrLine>
                                                   <addrLine>
                                                      <name type="person">Wellborn</name>  
                                                      <name type="person">Blair</name>
                                                   </addrLine>
                                                   <addrLine>
                                                      <abbr expan="Georgia Commissioners" type="suspension">
                                                         <name type="place">Ga</name> Comrs</abbr>
                                                   </addrLine>
                                                </address>
                                             
                                          </closer>
                                       </div1>
                                    </body>
                                 </text>
                              </q>
                              <pb n="[13]"/>
                                 <p>The following communication was this day made to the Council of the <name type="place person">Cherokee Nation</name> 
                                 </p>
                                 <q>
                                    <text>
                                       <body>
                                          <div1 type="legal council minutes letter">
                                             <opener>
                                                <dateline>
                                                   <address>
                                                      <addrLine>
                                                         <name type="place">Newtown</name>
                                                      </addrLine>
                                                   </address> 
                                                   <date value="1823-10-16">16th <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr> 1823</date>
                                                </dateline>
                                                <salute>To the Grand Council of the <name type="place person">Cherokee Nation</name>
                                                   <lb/>Friends  Brothers,
                                                </salute>
                                             </opener>
                                             <p>We are happy that a short time has been consumed in the correspondence between  you and the State Commissioners.  This has afforded us an opportunity of becoming partially acquainted with several members of this council.  For the whole body we entertain a high respect, and we trust that with some of you, we have contracted individual friendships.  In saying this we do no violence to our own feelings, neither do we lower the elevated character of the <name type="place">United States</name>.  People who have never seen you, know but little of your progress in the arts of civilized life, and of the regular and becoming, manner in which your affairs are conducted</p>
                                             <p>
                                                <del type="overstrike">
                                                   <unclear/>
                                                </del> Your improvement reflects the greatest credit upon yourselves, and upon the <gap reason="missing page(s)">
                                                   <pb n="[14]"/>ministers, or commissioners, has always been considered one of the highest contempts which can pass between nations, and has often led to the most serious consequences."  Brothers, We have <orig reg="denied">denyed</orig> all these charges which you have <orig reg="alleged">alledged</orig> to our dispositions as emanating from the general Resolution; because the Resolution expresses the most friendly disposition, to keep <hi>bright</hi> the <hi>chain</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Friendship</hi> which <hi>links</hi> the <hi>
                                                         <name type="place person">Cherokee Nation</name>
                                                      </hi>  the <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>
                                                         <name type="place">U. States</name>
                                                      </hi>.  We are ignorant of any difficulties or breach having taken place between us and our Father the President.   Have you appeared before general Council of this Nation at Our <hi>Great Council fire</hi> at <name type="place">New Town</name>, as Commissioners of the <name type="place">U. States</name>?  And have you been rejected and treated with contempt?  No Brothers; such circumstance has not taken place therefore we are entirely <del type="overstrike">
                                                         <unclear/>
                                                      </del> innocent of the denunciations, which you have heaped upon us.
                                                </gap>
                                             </p>
                                             <p>Brothers, we have no desire that the <name type="place">U. States</name> Should incur any expense of procuring supplies for the nation, on the Subject of your mission.  Should you think  proper to come forward to Our next general Council at <name type="place">New Town</name>, the Nation will furnish their own supplies, and as for yourselves, you could obtain as good <orig reg="accommodations">accomodations</orig> thus as the Nation affords.   Brothers, we deem it proper to inform you that our next general Council will be convened <date value="0000-09-01">the first day of September next</date> being, the<pb n="[15]"/>
                                                   <hi>earliest period</hi> which will admit of convenience for the <hi>General Convention</hi> of this <hi>Nation</hi>. 
                                             </p>
                                             <closer>
                                                <salute>We take you by the hand in behalf of the Nation   ourselves as Friends  Brothers.</salute>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">John Ross</name>
                                                </signed>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">Richard Taylor</name>
                                                </signed>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">George Lowrey</name>
                                                </signed>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">Big Cabbin</name> X</signed>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">Sleeping Rabbit</name> X</signed>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">The Hair</name> X</signed>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">Thomas Foreman</name>
                                                </signed>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">
                                                      <unclear>Three</unclear> Killer</name> X</signed>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">T. <unclear>Squie</unclear>
                                                   </name> X</signed>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">
                                                      <unclear>Chiulamee</unclear>
                                                   </name> X</signed>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">Oowanakee</name> X</signed>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">Tarrapin Head</name> X</signed>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">
                                                      <unclear>Chunoyekee</unclear>
                                                   </name> X</signed>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">
                                                      <unclear>Tahkeyah</unclear>
                                                   </name> X</signed>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">Ahalyalee</name> X</signed>
                                                <signed>
                                                   <name type="person">Ticketowee</name> X</signed>
                                                <lb/>
                                                   <lb/>Head Chiefs<signed>
                                                         <name type="person">Path Killer</name>
                                                      </signed> X<signed>
                                                         <name type="person">Charles R Hicks</name>
                                                      </signed>
                                                      <lb/>
                                                         <signed>
                                                            <name type="person">Going Snake</name>
                                                         </signed> X<signed>
                                                            <name type="person">Major Ridge</name> X</signed>
                                                         <signed>
                                                            <name type="person">Chicksawtehee</name> X</signed>
                                                         <signed>
                                                            <name type="person">Luwecullah</name> X</signed>
                                                         <signed>
                                                            <name type="person">The <unclear>Bear</unclear>
                                                            </name>
                                                         </signed>
                                                      
                                                   
                                                
                                             </closer>
                                          </div1>
                                       </body>
                                    </text>
                                 </q>
                              
                           
                        
                     
                  
               
            
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 type="legal council minutes letter">
            <pb n="[16]"/>
               <p>Letter from the <name type="person">Cherokee</name> Council to the <name type="place">U.S.</name> 
                  <abbr expan="Commissioners" type="contraction"> Comrs </abbr> 
                  <unclear>offering</unclear> Reasons for not  meeting at <name type="place">Taloney</name> and at the <unclear>agency</unclear>
               </p>
            
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
