<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="ch061">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Legal] agreement [between] Cherokee [officials and] Jos[eph] McMinn, 1823 May 23, / [signed by] Jno. [i.e., John] Ross ... [et al.]: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch061</idno>
            <idno>oclc: 44853516</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Legal] agreement [between] Cherokee [officials and] Jos[eph] McMinn, 1823 May 23, / [signed by] Jno. [i.e., John] Ross ... [et al.]</title>
               <date value="1823-05-23">May 23, 1823</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary">Copy of a legal agreement dated May 23, 1823 between John Ross, Richard Taylor, Alexander McCoy, and Nathan Hicks, Cherokee officials acting on behalf of the Nation's treasurer, Charles R. Hicks, and  Joseph McMinn, Cherokee Agent (and former Governor of Tennessee), concerning the 1823 Cherokee annuity payment.</note>
               <note type="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="Box">3</note>
               <note type="Folder">4</note>
               <note type="Document">ch061</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Legal status, laws, etc.</item>
                  <item>Indian agents</item>
                  <item>Southern States</item>
               </list> 
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="legal financial claim">
            <pb n="[1]"/>
               <p>Know all men by these Presents that we <name type="person">John Ross</name> 
                  <name type="person">Richard Taylor</name> 
                  <name type="person">
                     <abbr expan="Alexander">Alexr.</abbr> McCoy</name>  
                  <name type="person">Nathan Hicks</name> acting under a Special power and authority from Mr. <name type="person">Charles  R. Hicks</name> Treasurer of the <name type="place person">Cherokee Nation</name> in receiving and receipting for the annuity Stipend of <date value="1823-00-00">1823</date>- of the <unclear>one</unclear> part  <name type="person">
                     <abbr expan="Joseph">Jos.</abbr> McMinn</name> Agent for the <name type="place person">Cherokee Nation</name> of the other part Witnesseth that Party of the first part being duly instructed in the Settlement with the agent to allow the <orig reg="Balance">Ballance</orig> due on a special order on the former Agent <name type="person">
                     <abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Meigs</name> in favor of <name type="person">William H. Salmans</name> 
                  <abbr expan="attorney" type="suspension">atto.</abbr> for <name type="person">McKay</name>  
                  <name type="person">Gillispie</name> bearing date <date value="1822-07-23">July 23rd. 1822</date>, the whole amount One thousand one Hundred  seventy dollars on which  <unclear>credit</unclear> of Two Sums to be placed on Said draft one of Two Hundred  Seventy dollars  another for One Hundred dollars amounting in all three Hundred  Seventy dollars Which would consequently leave a <orig reg="balance">ballance</orig> due on Said draft of Eight Hundred dollars - but as no <unclear>credit</unclear> being placed on Said draft for the One Hundred dollars- the Agent of the Second part not being disposed to allow the credit demanded by the party <add place="supralinear">of </add> first part without entering into the following<pb n="[2]"/>Understanding under which the parties have therefore hereby Settled Viz   - The credits of three Hundred and Seventy dollars is allowed - but in the event of a future Settlement between <name type="person">Charles R. Hicks</name>  
                     <name type="person">
                        <unclear>Wm.</unclear> H. Salmans</name> it Should be clearly and authentically established that the Nation is not entitled to the credit of the One Hundred dollars thus in that case the undersigned party of the first part agree in behalf of the Treasurers of the Nation that the <add place="supralinear">aforesaid</add> sum of One Hundred dollars Should be returned to the Agent the party of the Second part or otherwise Should it appear that the credits admitted are just, then this Settlement Shall be deemed definite  Conclusive  this agreement <add place="supralinear">shall</add> become null and void.  It is agreed by the undersigners that the adjustment should made <del type="overstrike">closed </del> as soon as possible not exceeding Twelve Months<lb/>
                        <figure>
                           <figDesc>Handwritten seals appear next to most of the names in the signature list below.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                     
                  
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>as witness our hands  seals this <date value="1823-05-23">23rd. May 1823</date>
                  </salute> duplicate signed<signed>
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="John">Jno.</abbr> Ross</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">Richd Taylor</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">A McCoy</name>
                  </signed>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">Nathan <unclear>Hicks</unclear>
                     </name>
                  </signed>
                  <pb n="[3]"/>
                     <signed>
                        <name type="person">
                           <abbr expan="Joseph">Jos</abbr> McMinn</name>
                     </signed>
                     <lb/>Witness<signed>
                           <name type="person">
                              <abbr expan="James">Jas.</abbr> G. Williams</name>
                        </signed>
                     
                  
               </closer>
            
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 type="legal financial claim">
            <pb n="[4]"/>
               <p>Copy<lb/>Agreement <name type="person">John Ross</name>, <name type="person">Ric.d Taylor</name>, <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Alexander">Alxr.</abbr> McCoy</name>, <name type="person">Nathan Hicks</name> and <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Joseph">Jos</abbr> McMinn</name>
                     <lb/>Subject<lb/>The payment of $100 Suspended at the instance of the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> - who are <orig reg="support">suport</orig> the objection or Pay the Sum of one hundred <abbr expan="Dollars">Dolls.</abbr>
                        
                     
                  
               </p>
            
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
