<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="ch072">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Talk] 1823 Oct. 27, Newtown, to D[uncan] G. Campbell and Ja[me]s Meriwether / Path Killer ... [et al.] : a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Path Killer</author>
            <author>Ridge, Major, ca. 1771-1839</author>
            <author>Ross, John, 1790-1866</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch072</idno>
            <idno>oclc: 44863140</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Talk] 1823 Oct. 27, Newtown, to D[uncan] G. Campbell and Ja[me]s Meriwether / Path Killer ... [et al.]</title>
               <author>Path Killer</author>
               <author>Ridge, Major, ca. 1771-1839</author>
               <author>Ross, John, 1790-1866</author>
               <date value="1823-10-27">October 27, 1823</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This document is a talk from the General Council of the Cherokee Nation to U.S. treaty commissioners Duncan G. Campbell and James Meriwether, dated October 27, 1823.  The Council rebuts a number of unfounded accusations made by the commissioners in a recent talk they delivered.  The Cherokee Council explains that they have no more land to sell and thus, negotiating a treaty for further land cessions would be useless.  They refer to the Treaty of Holston and numerous other treaties in developing their argument.  The talk is signed by a number of important Cherokee leaders including Pathkiller, Major Ridge, and John Ross.</note>
               <note type="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box">3</note>
               <note type="folder">5</note>
               <note type="document">ch072</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Treaties</item>
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Land tenure</item>
                  <item>Southern States</item>
               </list> 
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[1]"/>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <address>
                        <addrLine>
                           <name type="place">Newtown</name>
                        </addrLine>
                     </address>
                     <date value="1823-10-27">
                        <abbr expan="October">Octr.</abbr> 27th 1823</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>In General Council<lb/> Friends Brothers,
                  </salute>
               </opener>
               <p>You say that your anticipations of success was founded upon, Confidence in any judgement, and that you believed  hoped you would have succeeded in Convincing us that you were right, and would also satisfy us of the nature of our title to the soil which we now occupy.  The doctrine which you have laid for a foundation, can never Convince our judgement that you are Correct, we did not refer to the 7th article of <name type="place">Holston</name> Treaty <date value="1791-00-00">1791</date> as a <hi>foundation</hi> to our <hi>title</hi> to the <hi>soil</hi> upon which we stand.  Our title has emanated from a <hi>supreme</hi> source, which cannot be impaired by the mere circumstance of discovery by foreigners; neither has this title been impaired by Conquest or by treaty  If it was intended that our original title should be forever cast, why did not the the Treaties of peace  declare it in plain terms; and why should<pb n="[2]"/>the <name type="place">United States</name> purchase time after time by Treaties lands which you would wish to Convince us we have no title and when such purchases were made why did they require such a right  title of Conveyance as given in the 4th article of <name type="place">Holston</name> Treaty <date value="1791-00-00">1791</date>, which you have had occasion to refer,  We had noticed the 7th article of <name type="place">Holston</name> Treaty to <orig reg="show">shew</orig> that the <name type="place">United States</name> do acknowledge our right  title and have <hi>guaranteed</hi> to respect the same  This being the Case and the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> possessing the right  title it would have been superfluous  useless for the <name type="place">United States</name> to Convey to the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> a right  title which was already vested in the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> themselves and not in the <name type="place">United States</name>  you say our <hi>possession</hi> is at the <hi>will</hi> of the <name type="place">United States</name>; and that our <hi>rejections</hi> to the several propositions which have been made cannot be expected to pass <hi>away</hi> and produce no  <hi>effect</hi>, and that the <hi>ties</hi> which bind <hi>us</hi> with the <name type="place">United States</name> are <hi>loosening</hi>  the <hi>chain</hi> is becoming weaker  What Brothers do you wish to impair the high<pb n="[3]"/>confidence which we entertain of the magnanimity of your Government, and to <orig reg="harbor">harbour</orig> an opinion that, because the <name type="place">United States</name> are <hi>Great  <orig reg="powerful">powerfull</orig>
                        </hi> and the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> 
                        <hi>small</hi> and <hi>dependant</hi> upon her for protection; that she will trample justice under foot, and compel us to yield what we have peaceably  respectfully refused to let the <name type="place">U States</name> have, for the benefit of the State of <name type="place">Georgia</name> have you not told us that the President have the same <hi>love</hi> towards <hi>us</hi> as his <hi>white</hi> Children; and would not such a treatment of us, as you seem to be apprehensive of be partial wrong,  Brothers we have rejected your propositions because we <del type="overstrike">have</del> love our lands and have none to dispose of,  We rejected the claims of <name type="place">Georgia</name> because we know <add place="supralinear">that</add> the nation owes her nothing under the treaties Cited-  We rejected the proposition of the agent because we think, that it is not expedient to grant it, in as much as we have given him all the <orig reg="privileges">priviledges</orig> granted him by Treaty and are ever disposed to support his authority as an agent so far as our Citizens may be implicated with transgressions  Thus far we have not acted with <hi>ingratitude</hi> towards the <abbr expan="General" type="contraction">Genl.</abbr> Government in rejecting these several propositions; It is a <orig reg="privilege">priviledge</orig> 
                        <pb n="[4]"/>a <hi>right</hi> which belongs to us, to use our pleasure, in complying or rejecting;  Therefore your Charge of ingratitude we conceive is not Consistent  with liberality  Your proposition for a Special Cession of a tract of land, Cannot be <unclear>aceeded</unclear> to  The offer of <hi>money</hi> is not a Consideration which can effect to alter the rejection which have already been made  You have been told in positive terms that <hi>one foot of Land</hi> cannot be sold  You state that you are informed that the Council had on former occasion set much longer than the present session, Your informant is mistaken  Twenty five days is the longest session we have ever had at this place and the present session have now entered the twenty seventh day.  You have no grounds to Complain of a Sudden Close of our negotiation; the subject has been fully discussed  We now consider this a <hi>final close</hi> of our negotiation  beg leave to take you by the right hand, as we meet, in Brotherly Friendship and as such may we ever Continue
                     
                  
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Alexander">A</abbr> McCoy</name>
                  </signed> 
                  <abbr expan="clerk National">clk Nl</abbr> Committee<lb/>
                     <signed>
                        <name type="person">Path Killer</name>
                     </signed> 
                     <abbr expan="Principal" type="contraction">Pl</abbr> chief<signed>
                        <name type="person">Major Ridge</name>
                     </signed>  speaker of <abbr expan="Council" type="contraction">Cl.</abbr>
                     <signed>
                        <name type="person">
                           <abbr expan="John">Jno.</abbr> Ross</name>
                     </signed> 
                     <abbr expan="President">Prest.</abbr> national Committee<address>
                        <addrLine>To <name type="person">
                              <abbr expan="Duncan">D</abbr> G Campbell</name>  
                           <name type="person">
                              <abbr expan="James">Jas.</abbr> Meriwether</name> 
                           <abbr expan="Esquires">Esqrs</abbr> 
                           <name type="place">US</name> Commissioners</addrLine>
                     </address>
                  
               </closer>
            
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
