<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2
  SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="ch077">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Order, 1836 Nov. 3, Headquarters, Fort Cass, [Tennessee] / Brig[adier] Gen[era]l John E. Wool: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Wool, John Ellis, 1784-1869</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch077</idno>
            <idno>oclc: 44864413</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>This work is the property of The  Tennessee  State  Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Order, 1836 Nov. 3, Headquarters, Fort Cass, [Tennessee] / Brig[adier] Gen[era]l John E. Wool</title>
               <author>Wool, John Ellis, 1784-1869</author>
               <date value="1836-11-03">November 3, 1836</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This document is a general order from Brigadier General John E. Wool, at army headquarters at Fort Cass, (Tennessee), dated November 3, 1836.  The order contains directions from the President respecting the implementation of the Treaty of New Echota (signed 1835, ratified 1836), which provided for the removal of the Cherokee Indians to a territory west of the Mississippi River.  Wool indicates that soldiers stationed in the Cherokee Nation are to prohibit any meetings of the Cherokee people for the purpose of opposing the removal treaty.  In addition, it is stated that no delegation from the Cherokee Nation interested in renegotiating the terms of the treaty will be acknowledged.</note>
               <note type="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection"> State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box">3</note>
               <note type="folder">9</note>
               <note type="document">ch077</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee  Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Treaties</item>
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Relocation</item>
                  <item>Southern States</item>
               </list> 
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="military order">
            <pb n="[1]"/>
               <opener>
                  <hi rend="sc">HEAD QUARTERS, ARMY E.T  C.N. <name type="place">FORT CASS</name>
                     <lb/>
                        <date value="1836-11-03">November 3d. 1836</date>


                        <lb/>GENERAL ORDER
                     
                  </hi>
                  <lb/>No. 74
               </opener>
               <p>I am instructed by the President of the <name type="place">United States</name>, through the War Department, to make known to Mr. <name type="person">John Ross</name>, and all others whom it may concern, that it is his determination to have the late Treaty, entered into between the <name type="place">United States</name> and the <name type="person">Cherokee</name> People, and ratified by the Senate, the <date value="1836-05-25">25th May, 1836</date>, <q>religiously fulfilled in all its parts, terms and conditions, within the period prescribed,</q> and that <q>no delegation which may be sent</q> to <name type="place">Washington</name> 
                  <q>with a view to obtain new terms, or a modification of those of the existing treaty, will be received or recognized, nor will any intercourse be had with them, directly or indirectly, orally or in writing;</q> and that the President regards the proceedings of <name type="person">Mr. Ross</name> and his associates in the late Council held at <name type="place">Red Clay</name>, <q>as in direct contravention of the plighted faith of their people, and a repetition of them will be considered as indicative of a design to prevent the execution of the Treaty, even at the hazard of actual hostilities, and they will be promptly repressed.</q>
               </p>
               <p>It is further made known by instructions from the War Department, that <q>if any of our citizens enter the <name type="person">Cherokee</name> country and incite opposition to the execution of the treaty, "they will be proceeded against according to the laws of the State, if any exist on the subject, in which they may enter; and if there should be "no law of the State which can be brought to bear on them, and under which they may be removed,</q> 
                  <q>it is the opinion of the President</q> as expressed through the War Department <q>that they may be removed</q> out of the country, <q>under the 6th article of the treaty,</q> in which the <name type="place">United States</name> guarantee that the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> shall be <q>protected against interruption and intrusion from citizens of the <name type="place">United States</name> who may attempt to settle in the country,</q> unless it is with the express consent <q>of the Committee who are acting under the 12th Article of the Treaty, and by the terms of that Article they alone are authorized to give it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>All officers of the Army, whether commanding Volunteers or Regular Troops, under my command, are required and directed to make known to all persons residing, or who may come within the range of their respective commands, the contents of this order.  And to make diligent search and enquiry in regard to all citizens who may enter the <name type="person">Cherokee</name> country, and incite opposition or interfere with the due execution of the treaty, and report their names and places of residence without delay, to General Head Quarters, in order that they may be proceeded against, according to the laws of the country, and the instructions of the President of the <name type="place">United States</name>.  They are also required and directed to prevent all meetings and to break up all Councils coming to their knowledge, assembled in the <name type="person">Cherokee</name> country, for the purpose of opposing the treaty, or discussing its non-execution."</p>
               <lb/>
                  <signed>
                     <name type="person">John E. Wool</name> 
                     <abbr expan="Brigadier General Commanding" type="suspension"> Brig. Genl Comdg.</abbr>
                  </signed>
               
            
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
