<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0053">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Promissory Note between Tennessee Cherokees and Spencer Jarnagan] 1836 Dec. 7, Athens [Tennessee] : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0053</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Promissory Note between Tennessee Cherokees and Spencer Jarnagan] 1836 Dec. 7, Athens [Tennessee]</title>
               <date when="1836-12-07">December 7, 1836</date>
               <extent>2 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a legal agreement between the Cherokee Indians in Tennessee and Spencer Jarnagan. Jarnagan, an attorney, represented members of the Cherokee Nation in numerous lawsuits.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0053</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Legal documents</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Government relations</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0053a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Athens</name>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Decr.</abbr>
                           <expan>December</expan>
                        </choice> 7, 1836</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>The treaties made between the United States and the <name>Cherokee</name> tribe of Indians in the years 1817 and 1819 and the legislation of the State of <name>Tennessee</name> consequent thereupon, produced in a number of the courts of said State, many and very important law suits, between the nations of that tribe &amp; Citizens of Tennessee, touching the validity of sending reservations of land taken in virtue of those treaties- Litigation in relation to those subjects commenced as far back as 1814- and no suits in our Courts involved questions more important or interesting whether viewed in relations to the value of the property involved or the magnitude and differently of the subjects discussed- As such importance was the matter esteemed by the State of Tennessee herself, that she selected her ablest Counsel to respresent her interests in that behalf.-  The undersigned are cognizant of the fact, that throughout the whole of this litigation, <name>Spencer Jarnagen</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Esqr.</abbr>
                  <expan>Esquire</expan>
               </choice> appeared as <choice>
                  <orig>Council</orig>
                  <reg>Counsel</reg>
               </choice> for the Cherokees <add>
                  <unclear>generally</unclear>
               </add> and that he bestowed upon the causes a faithful &amp; vigilant attention- and that he has also within the period aforesaid attended to other important causes for several of the Cherokees, with like vigilance &amp; attention. <pb n="2" facs="pa0053b.small.jpg"/> Amongst the latter class of cases may be named that of the State vs. <name>Springton</name> &amp; <name>Foreman</name> for the Murder of <name>John Walker</name>-</p>
            <p>The foregoing litigation in our Courts has ranged from the year 1821- up to this time and <unclear>we</unclear> take pleasure in voluntarily making the foregoing statement, and of further adding that two hundred and fifty dollars per annum, would not exceed a very reasonable compensation for Mr. Jarnagin's services-</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Tho.</abbr>
                        <expan>Thomas</expan>
                     </choice> J. Campbell</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>Charles F Keith</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>James F. Bradford</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>Nat Smith</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>Spencer <unclear>Beavers</unclear>
                  </name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Saml</abbr>
                        <expan>Samuel</expan>
                     </choice> Workman</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>John W. <unclear>McBreazeute</unclear>
                  </name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>
                     <unclear>A.</unclear>M. Coffey</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
