<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl674">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Invitation to Whig convention] 1840 Jul. 4, Nashville, Tennessee [to] I.L. Tellinghurt, Washington City / L.D. Morgan, et al : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Morgan, L.D., et al</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl674</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Invitation to Whig convention] 1840 Jul. 4, Nashville, Tennessee [to] I.L. Tellinghurt, Washington City / L.D. Morgan, et al </title>
               <author> Morgan, L.D., et al</author>
               <date when="1840-07-04"> 
			 July 4, 1840</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is an invitation to  I.L. Tellinghurt, from a group known as the  "union of the Whigs for the sake of the Union," to a convention to be held in Nashville, Tennessee, on August 17, 1840, for the promotion of retrenchment and reform in the southern, and western states of the United States.      </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor James K. Polk Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">9</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl674</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor (1839-1841 : Polk)</term>
               <term>Polk, James K. (James Knox), 1795-1849</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Morgan, L. D.</name>
               </term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Shelby, J.</name>
               </term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr93017180"
                        role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Cannon, Newton, 1781-1841</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl674a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Nashville,</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>July 4, 1840</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The friends of "Retrenchment and Reform" in the South and West, propose to hold a general Convention, in this City, on the <date>seventeenth of August</date> next.  </p>
            <p>This "union of the Whigs for the sake of the Union," is to adopt such measures as may seem most likely to rescue from impending danger, and still perpetuate, in all their original integrity, the invaluable blessings of our free institutions.  Dearly purchased by the blood and toil of our forefathers, they must go down unimpaired, to a grateful posterity, if we be true to our responsibilities.</p>
            <p>That our political system would be exposed to corruption, especially from Executive usurpations, was foreseen and guarded against by the framers of the Constitution.  But the experience of fifty years has fully shown that  no checks can be made effectually, except by the unremitting vigilance of the People.  The posture of our affairs, induced by the mal-administration of the General Government, calls loudly upon us for concerted action.  In large <choice>
                  <orig>assemblayes</orig>
                  <reg>assemblies</reg>
               </choice> of the people, the information necessary to their enlightened and harmonious movement, is most readily and conveniently diffused.  While they, together, inquire into, and expose the unnumbered delinquencies of the present administration, they will have the most favorable opportunity of expressing their opinions fully, as to the best mode of redressing their grievances.  Their numbers, their intelligences, their virtue, will ensure success to the friends of "Reform" if they can only be brought to act in concert.</p>
            <p>Wherever such Conventions have been held, in various parts of the Union, they have greatly promoted our cause.  The Whigs of the South and West have caught the enthusiasm so rapidly spreading over the country; and will, no doubt, come up to the approaching Convention in great strength.  Animated by the most cheering prospect, we invite you to come, and swell, and share the triumph of patriots and reformers.</p>
            <closer>
               <add>We are, Sir, Very Respectfully, Your <choice>
                     <abbr>Ob't Serv'ts</abbr>
                     <expan>Obedient Servants</expan>
                  </choice>. <name>L.D. Morgan</name>, <name>N. Cannon</name>, <name>J. Shelby</name>, </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl674b.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Invitation to <name>Nashville</name>
                  <unclear>for aug 17 July 4 20 <choice>
                        <abbr>ans</abbr>
                        <expan>answered</expan>
                     </choice> aug 7</unclear>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Hon</abbr>
                           <expan>Honorable</expan>
                        </choice> I.L. Tellinghurt Washington City</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
