<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc003">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1847 Feb. 15, E[ast] T[ennessee] University [to] Mr.
			 John D. McAdoo, Clinton, Anderson Co[unty], Tenn[essee] / R. M. Moore: a
			 machine-readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Moore, R. M</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Mays</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno>sc003</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 49916198</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1847 Feb. 15, E[ast] T[ennessee] University [to] Mr.
				John D. McAdoo, Clinton, Anderson Co[unty], Tenn[essee] / R. M. Moore</title>
               <author>Moore, R. M.</author>
               <date when="1847-02-15">February 15, 1847</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This document is a letter, dated February 15,
				1847, written from R. M. Moore at East Tennessee University (former name of the
				University of Tennessee) to John D. McAdoo in Anderson County. In the letter,
				Moore related the ill state of his health at the time. He also wrote briefly of
				recent university news. A new student had enrolled, and Moore had befriended
				the student in hopes that he would soon join his society. Also, a student by
				the name of Parshall had left the school and returned home. Moore further
				expressed disdain for the poor performance of his hall's debate team. </note>
               <note type="Collection">R.M. Moore</note>
               <note type="Box">n/a</note>
               <note type="Folder"> MS-35</note>
               <note type="Document">sc003</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee, East</term>
               <term>Tennessee History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Moore, R. M</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc003a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>E. T.</abbr>
                        <expan>East Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
				  University,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1847-02-15">February 15, 1847.</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear John.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>With pain and difficulty do I make the effort of offering a
			 friendly, but limited communication. I am sorely afflicted with a severe pain
			 in my head and an aching of my back and limbs, which make me nervous and
			 unsteady, and therefore I am in a bad situation to write. My shoulder aches and
			 my hand is so unsteady, that it appears that I <choice>
                  <orig>can
			 not</orig>
                  <reg>cannot</reg>
               </choice> write without blotting, and I regret to send a letter to a friend,
			 which looks, as though a blacksmith had written it with a hand spike.</p>
            <p>But you must make allowances for this one, owing to the state of my
			 health. I am unable to study any of consequence, for the anguish of my head is
			 so severe, that it seems that I <choice>
                  <orig>can not</orig>
                  <reg>cannot</reg>
               </choice> bear to
			 steady at <choice>
                  <orig>any thing</orig>
                  <reg>anything</reg>
               </choice>, much less to retain. I have
			 not been in a <choice>
                  <orig>recitition</orig>
                  <reg>recitation</reg>
               </choice>
               <add place="supralinear">room</add>
               <choice>
                  <orig>to-day</orig>
                  <reg>today</reg>
               </choice>, and if I do not
			 get better I think that I shall not recite anymore, but endeavor to get home.
			 My mind is so confused that I am troubled to grasp <choice>
                  <orig>any
			 thing</orig>
                  <reg>anything</reg>
               </choice> to reveal to you which may interest you, at all, and I am hard
			 enough pressed in my best moments to produce subjects of importance and
			 interest.</p>
            <p>I consider that we have, but little if <choice>
                  <orig>any
			 thing</orig>
                  <reg>anything</reg>
               </choice> here to communicate, which deserves a high appreciation. We have a
			 new student, who arrived here recently from 
			 <name type="place">Mississippi</name> and we have got him into our
			 building, though he has not joined our society; yet I think that he will for I
			 think that we have obtained the right side of him. I have taken considerable
			 pains with him by treating him friendly and familiarly, and he seems to be very
			 much pleased with me so far, and also he seems to pleased
			 <add place="supralinear">with</add> some of the other members. I am not like
			 the 
			 <abbr>Ph.'s</abbr> when I wish to get a student in our society, for I
			 <choice>
                  <orig>beleve</orig>
                  <reg>believe</reg>
               </choice> that they begin about the first thing to talk
			 about their society; but I wish to gain a student's good will first.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="sc003b.small.jpg"/>
            <p>The members of our hall conduct themselves very badly in debate. On
			 Saturday night last they were very disorderly, and <add place="supralinear">after</add> the close of debate, the resolution, which was
			 <choice>
                  <orig>past</orig>
                  <reg>passed</reg>
               </choice> on Saturday <add place="supralinear">night</add>
			 previous to invite the Faculty into our hall, was brought up and voted down by
			 a large majority. </p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Parshall</name> has quit college and gone home,
			 though I imagine that his departure will <add place="supralinear">not</add>
			 produce much sorrow with the students.  
			 <name type="person">Charles</name> and long 
			 <name type="person">Kirk</name> I believe are well, and the health of
			 the students generally is good; also their demeanor is considerably better than
			 was it some time since. I had just got so that I could study to some advantage
			 and was advancing much better in my studies; than I have done I believe all of
			 the first part of the session; but I fear that this misery in my head will
			 nearly, if not entirely break up my studying during this term.</p>
            <p>I am informed that 
			 <name type="person">Miss. Haverly</name> is to be married to 
			 <name type="person">McKee</name>, one of the editors of the
			 Tribune.</p>
            <p>I have nothing more at present to offer to you; but to ask you to
			 excuse my badly composed and badly written epistle.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am your true friend,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">R. M. Moore</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>J.</abbr>
                        <expan>John</expan>
                     </choice> D. McAdoo</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="sc003c.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mr. John D. McAdoo</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Clinton</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Anderson 
				<choice>
                        <abbr>Co.</abbr>
                        <expan>County</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr/>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
