<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um057">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1849 Aug. 16, Tallahassee, [Florida] [to] Mattie [Rice] / John H. Rice : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Rice, John H.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um057</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50296371</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1849 Aug. 16, Tallahassee, [Florida] [to] Mattie [Rice] / John H. Rice</title>
               <author>Rice, John H.</author>
               <date when="1849-08-16">August 16, 1849</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a summary written by John H. Rice to his sister, Mattie, on August 16, 1849. In the letter, John writes about the events going on in and around where he lives in Tallahassee, Florida. He writes about his preaching, the cholera that is making many people sick, his approaching marriage, and the Indian Wars taking place in Florida at the time.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Porter-Rice Family Letters MS 154 (Letters 1846-1849)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um057</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Florida</term>
               <term>Seminole Indians -- Wars</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Rice, John H.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um057a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tallahassee</name>
                     <date when="1849-08-16">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Aug</abbr>
                           <expan>August</expan>
                        </choice> 16th 1849</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear <name type="person">Mattie</name>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have several letters from home on have all of them unanswered as yet, but I believe that yours is the oldest so I must write to you first. I am very glad that you wrote to me and I thought your letter a very good one. You must write oftener and not insist upon my answering every letter, for you know that there are so many of you that I would not have a fair chance if I was obliged to write letter for letter with each one of yours. Besides writing to me would be a very good exercise for you. You could <choice>
                  <orig>practise</orig>
                  <reg>practice</reg>
               </choice>  on me so that when you had to write to other people you would not be ashamed or <choice>
                  <orig>affraid</orig>
                  <reg>afraid</reg>
               </choice> to do so. I hope that you are trying to improve in every thing. Do you <choice>
                  <orig>practise</orig>
                  <reg>practice</reg>
               </choice> your music much now? And do you study any Or is your head full of frivolity and follies? You are old enough now dear Mattie to feel the importance of preparing to act well your part in life and above all you are old enough to prepare for a happy &amp; glorious heaven in the world to come. You ought to think a great deal about these things. I do wish that I could come on and see you all. I should enjoy a visit home very much. Do you help your sisters to keep house? Every thing goes on with me pretty much in the old styles. I have had a few chills this summer and I would not be surprised if I should have a few more. Last Friday I went to preach at a country church about sixteen miles from here; it is called <name type="place">
                  <unclear>Jamonico</unclear>
               </name> from a Lake of that name upon which it is situated. The lakes here are not pretty like the lakes at the North, they are full of grass and weeds and present rather the appearance of grass swamps  that of Lakes. I went up on Friday morning and preached that day Saturday &amp; Sunday and returned home Sunday evening <pb n="2" facs="um057b.small.jpg"/> The church there is a very small one the people who compose it are principally from <name type="place">North Carolina</name> and are plain good hospitable people. <name type="person">Mr Neil</name> preached to them twice a month when he was here, While I was there Saturday evening I was suddenly taken very sick and if the cholera had been any where about here I should have thought that I had that disease, I was perfectly well a few moments before I was taken, When all at once I began to throw up and kept on at it until two o'clock in the morning it was three in the afternoon when I began. I had eaten nothing that disagreed with me for I felt a little sick before dinner and only ate a little rice. I was very ill and had to prescribe for myself as there was no doctor near. The Gentleman with whom I was staying wished to send to Tallahassee for a Doctor at midnight but I would not let him. I took Camphor &amp; Laudanum a little Soda and two grains of <choice>
                  <orig>Calomele</orig>
                  <reg>Calomel</reg>
               </choice>, and applied mustard plasters most extensively. This was the first dose of Calomel I have taken for years for you must know that I have become a great enemy to the common use of Calomel. About three o'clock in the morning I fell asleep and when I awoke in the morning I felt that I was cured, though I was very much exhausted I remained in bed until half past ten and then got up and went  over to the church and preached a pretty long sermon and administered the sacrament, and after that drove home was not that doing pretty well for a sick man, I have felt badly ever since though I can not call myself sick. I was greatly shocked the other day to hear from <name type="person">Lizzie Neil</name> that she had the Cholera and I have been very uneasy about her until yesterday when I received a letter from her saying that she was well again. I suppose that she has left <name type="place">New Jersey</name>
               <pb n="3" facs="um057c.small.jpg"/> by this time and is either in <name type="place">Petersburg</name> or on the way there I suppose that she will stay there a month or six weeks at <name type="person">Mrs Ritchies</name> and then come on here. her Father is with her and soon after that I suppose that we shall be married Sister <name type="person">Mary</name> wishes we let her tell the <name type="person">Venable's</name>. I <choice>
                  <abbr>dont</abbr>
                  <expan>do not</expan>
               </choice> care any thing about it, but I do no see any good reason for doing so I do not think that <name type="person">Mr Neil</name> told it in <name type="place">Princeton</name> as she supposes. it may have got out through some of her friends there or it may be a mere guess. You know that the Princeton people are famous for finding out such things and many of her letters to me were mailed at the Princeton post office. that would be enough for them to go upon. I reckon that <name type="person">Sue</name> will think that I got once her kicking very easily. If any of you should go down to Petersburg while Lizzie Neil is there I hope that you will call and see her at Mrs Ritchie's I think that you all will like her very much. My Friend <name type="person">John Gamble</name> is alive yet but he is getting worse though he goes about now a little that is he rides out to his fathers in the country I have not seen him for several days as he has been out there A few Sundays ago I went down to <name type="place">Newport</name> to preach there are two Sulphur springs there which are resorted to by the people of this part of <name type="place">Florida</name> for health! the town is on the <name type="place">St. Macks river</name> and is one of the principal shipping ports for this part of Florida. St. Marks which is the port of Tallahassee is six mile below Newport on the same river I got caught in tremendous rains both going and coming though I did not get wet as I had my cloak and an umbrella with the exception of these two trips I have remained here at <pb n="4" facs="um057d.small.jpg"/> home where nothing has happened worth relating. I suppose that you have seen in the papers that the Florida Indians have begun a war again. You need not be at all <choice>
                  <orig>affraid</orig>
                  <reg>afraid</reg>
               </choice> of their coming any where in our <choice>
                  <orig>neighbourhood</orig>
                  <reg>neighborhood</reg>
               </choice> they are at least three hundred miles from here and we can get the news from them by the way of the north almost as soon as direct by land. We have sent two companies of volunteers from this place to protect the inhabitants on the frontier I am <choice>
                  <orig>affraid</orig>
                  <reg>afraid</reg>
               </choice> that these Indians will give a great deal of trouble. A very nice lady a member of my church moved down into that country a few months ago with her husband &amp; family. but owing to the difficulty of getting supplies food <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> they came back again. and had hardly got back when they heard of the Indians committing murders close by their place. They congratulated themselves very much that they had got off in time. It seems as if Providence thwarted their plans for the very purpose of getting them away from the Indians. I hear a great many stories here of the last Indian War but none of them as interesting as those you can read in the books about the old Indian wars in the west <name type="place">Kentucky</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> though there is something in hearing the stories told by the persons who were actors in the scenes that they describe. I received a letter from Sister Mary last Saturday night I have also had one from <name type="person">Kate</name> and one from <name type="person">Arch</name>. I believe that more than two weeks have elapsed since I wrote to Pa. My church here remains in about the same state A good many of my congregation are absent at the North &amp; else where Write soon to your brother</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Jno</abbr>
                        <expan>John</expan>
                     </choice> H Rice</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
