<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mc062">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1839 Dec. 28, Knoxville, Tennessee [to] Charles F. Welcker, Laurel Banks, Roane County / James M. Welcker : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Welcker, James Monroe</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">mc062</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1839 Dec. 28, Knoxville, Tennessee [to] Charles F. Welcker, Laurel Banks, Roane County / James M. Welcker</title>
               <author>Welcker, James Monroe</author>
               <date when="1839-12-28">December 28, 1839</date>
               <extent>3 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated December 28, 1839 from James Monroe Welcker in Knoxville, Tennessee to his brother Charles Frederick Welcker in Roane County, Tennessee.  James writes briefly about Christmas in Knoxville and his disappointment at not seeing their brother Lewis.  He also talks quite extensively about livestock.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Welcker Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-12, b3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1839</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mc062</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Livestock</term>
               <term>Tennessee, East</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Welcker, James Monroe</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mc062a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Knoxville Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Dec.</abbr>
                           <expan>December</expan>
                        </choice> 28th 1839</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Brother Charles.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>There is very little news here, that is worth writing to any one._ But as Franklin has just arrived, so that Ham can leave for home in the morning I will write a few lines at all events.</p>
            <p>Christmas holy-days are about over here; and I believe nothing has been done here, by way of celebration.  The times here, in fact, are unusually dull and lifeless._ I expected very sanguinely to see brother Lewis this evening in company with Franklin_ had I known that he intended to defer coming up <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> the 8th or 10th of January; as badly prepared as I am for <choice>
                  <orig>loasing</orig>
                  <reg>losing</reg>
               </choice> time I should have gone home some time since.  Inform him that severals up here have been expecting him some time and when he comes to be prepared to stay a day or so._ Say to mother, for me, that her Christmas gift came to hand; and cannot but be prized very highly by me,_ as <choice>
                  <orig>comeing</orig>
                  <reg>coming</reg>
               </choice> from home <unclear>&amp;</unclear> and more especially from any mother_ I think the cake will not fail to fatten me. </p>
            <p>I have heard of no one wanting to hire Ham yet.  As to the price of clover seed you have or will hear more from Frederick than I can inform you_ provided always that there is no great secret about it; and farther if it should not give a clue to his plans and <pb n="2" facs="mc062b.small.jpg"/> future operations._ The pork offered to this market this winter has been nearly or quite double in quantity to that of any previous year.</p>
            <p>Have you any shelters <del type="overstrike">of</del> for the Durham stock; if not they will fare badly to night?  Are they in a thrifty condition?  There is now and has been during a week or two past a lot of the Durham stock in town. They were brought here by <name>Mr. Daugherty</name>  from <name>Kentucky</name>. _ If I do not speak <choice>
                  <orig>publickly</orig>
                  <reg>publicly</reg>
               </choice>, I would say there is very little of the genuine stock in his lot of some 20 or 25._ For some he asks 3 and 4 hundred dollars; but they are greatly inferior to any one of yours.  Some he has sold for 2 and 3 hundred dollars already I do not believe, in fact, I know, I would not give your four for the whole lot._ On yesterday I saw <name>Mr. Heiskel</name>'s Bull for which he gave one thousand dollars._ His is a very fine animal._ But in my opinion he is not superior in any respect to Hanibal_ he is larger it is true; but Hanibal if treated as he should be will be as large or large and I think he <choice>
                  <orig>excells</orig>
                  <reg>excels</reg>
               </choice> Heiskel's in one or two very important parts.  You should have him curried regularly and if you would have the hair on his head and neck kept <choice>
                  <orig>strait</orig>
                  <reg>straight</reg>
               </choice> and smooth it would make a wonderful difference in his countenance. Lewis will infer from this that I have caught the Durham fever.</p>
            <p>Give my respects to all.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>James <choice>
                        <abbr>M.</abbr>
                        <expan>Monroe</expan>
                     </choice> Welcker</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="mc062c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Charles <choice>
                           <abbr>F</abbr>
                           <expan>Frederick</expan>
                        </choice> Welcker</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Esq.</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Laurel Banks</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Roane County</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
