<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch036">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter], 1816 May 4, Washington to W[illia]m H. Crawford, Secretary of War / Rev[erend] Cyrus Kingsbury : a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Kingsbury, Cyrus, 1786-1870</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch036</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44805981</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter], 1816 May 4, Washington to W[illia]m H. Crawford, Secretary of War / Rev[erend] Cyrus Kingsbury</title>
               <author>Kingsbury, Cyrus, 1786-1870</author>
               <date when="1816-05-04">May 4, 1816</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">Copy of a letter dated May 4, 1816 from Reverend Cyrus Kingsbury, American Board missionary, to Secretary of War William H. Crawford applying for government assistance in establishing schools for the Indians. Kingsbury explains the society's reasons for wanting to create the schools and asks that the government provide supplies and equipment for them.</note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">29</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch036</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Indians of North America--Social conditions</term>
               <term>Missions</term>
               <term>Indians of North America--Education</term>
               <term>United States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n90715876"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Kingsbury, Cyrus, 1786-1870</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch036a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>A.<lb/>Note from <name type="person">Rev. Cyrus Kingsbury</name> to the <choice>
                  <abbr>Hon.</abbr>
                  <expan>Honorable</expan>
               </choice>
               <name type="person">Wm. H. Crawford</name>, Secretary of War dated
               </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Washington</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <date when="1816-05-04">May 4 1816</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Perhaps I have already intruded too much upon your time.  The probability that I shall not see you before the sum appropriated to the instruction of the Indians is specified is my apology for troubling you with this communication.</p>
            <p>I have no doubt of the disposition of the <choice>
                  <abbr>Secy.</abbr>
                  <expan>Secretary</expan>
               </choice> of War, or of the President to <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice> my object, so far as their acquaintance with it will enable them to confide in the wisdom of the design,  in the skill  fidelity with which it will be executed.  I only regret that I have not been able to state more fully the motives which induced  the very respectable society, which I have <choice>
                  <orig>honour</orig>
                  <reg>honor</reg>
               </choice> to serve, to direct their attention to the instruction of Indians,  which have influenced my own mind to engage in the service.  I designed to have made the statement when I called on the President, but no convenient opportunity offered.</p>
            <p>The settlement of this country by our forefathers, has in various ways proved <choice>
                  <orig>disasterous</orig>
                  <reg>disastrous</reg>
               </choice> to the natives, <choice>
                  <orig>nowithstanding</orig>
                  <reg>notwithstanding</reg>
               </choice> the laudable exertions, both by the government  individuals to counteract such a result.  Very different have been the consequences to ourselves.<pb n="2" facs="ch036b.small.jpg"/>considering therefore the relation in which we stand to these people, it has appeared no less an act of justice, than a dictate of humanity  a duty enjoined by the the gospel, to extend <add place="supralinear">to</add> them as far as is practicable the distinguished advantages which we enjoy.  This duty is incumbent on individuals  on societies, as well as on the government.  And it was supposed that the exertions which government are making to accomplish this object, could not be better aided, than by instructing the rising generation.  It is no less the dictate of sound reason, than the result of past experience, that exertions of this kind are the most effectual means to secure  the confidence of the Indians,  to give security to our frontier settlements.
               </p>
            <p>These are some of the motives which have led to the present undertaking,  to an application to government.  It was supposed that when the views of the Board of Foreign Missions should be understood, the object would be approved,  so far patronized by the Executive, as the existing provisions of Congress,  the present state of the undertaking would authorize.  I do not ask for any appropriation for myself, or for any persons who may be employed in the schools, but merely for the erection of suitable buildings,  for providing those implements of husbandry  of the mechanic arts, which may render the establishment respectable  useful.  Nor is it wished that any money should be appropriated otherwise, than through the government agent residing in the tribe.  With these brief  hasty remarks I cheerfully submit the subject to your decision.  </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>With sentiments of sincere respect  esteem, your <choice>
                     <abbr>obt very huml. servt.</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient &amp; very humble servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute> Signed<signed>
                  <name type="person">Cyrus Kingsbury</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
