<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0019">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1806 March 24, Chickamaga [to] Return J. Meigs, Southwest Point / David Ross : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Ross, David</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0019</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1806 March 24, Chickamaga [to] Return J. Meigs, Southwest Point / David Ross</title>
               <author>Ross, David</author>
               <date when="1806-03-24">March 24, 1806</date>
               <extent> 3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated March 24, 1806 to Return J. Meigs from Daniel Ross of the Cherokee Nation. Ross has two requests; one is for smallpox vaccines and the other is to replace the current school teacher whom Ross refers to as "reprehensible." </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0019</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians</term>
               <term>Small pox</term>
               <term>Teachers</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Ross, David</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0019a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel</expan>
                        </choice>Return J Meigs</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Southw.</abbr>
                        <expan>Southwest</expan>
                     </choice> point</addrLine>
               </address>
               <name>J.Wm. Coody</name>
               <add>Daniel Ross's letter<date>24 March 1806</date>
               </add>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                     <expan>Mister</expan>
                  </choice> Ross's letter<date>24 March 1806</date>
               </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="pa0019b.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Chickamaga</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>March 24th 1806</date>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Having understood <name>Mr Clark</name> have got the smallpox in his family, induces <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Mrs</abbr>
                     <expan>Misses</expan>
                  </choice> McDonald</name> to visit her grandson <name>John</name>
               <choice>
                  <orig>altho</orig>
                  <reg>although</reg>
               </choice> we have no doubt of his being well taken care of, under the disease by the family he is in_ We should have employed <name>Doctor McNiel</name> in this neighbourhood when he was down, but as some of the Chiefs did not appear willing to introduce the usual mode of <choice>
                  <orig>enoculation</orig>
                  <reg>inoculation</reg>
               </choice> , I did not think proper to make a <choice>
                  <orig>begining</orig>
                  <reg>beginning</reg>
               </choice> without their approbation, The Doctor's charges also appeared so unreasonable to all they <choice>
                  <orig>prefered</orig>
                  <reg>preferred</reg>
               </choice> taking their chances, till the kinepox could be brought into use, it being the kind the <orig>Pathkiller</orig> spoke for</p>
            <p>It is understood with much satisfaction that you use your best endeavors to procure it, &amp; that by this time you are in possession of it, and <choice>
                  <abbr>tho</abbr>
                  <expan>though</expan>
               </choice> Doctor McNeil does not appear to think so favourably of it as I do, I must still think the Nation will acknowledge with a <choice>
                  <orig>greatful</orig>
                  <reg>grateful</reg>
               </choice> heart that you are the saviour of many of them by its introduction through your means &amp; in its purity. If Sir you are able to obtain <add>the</add>
               <choice>
                  <orig>vacine</orig>
                  <reg>vaccine</reg>
               </choice> before <name>Mrs McDonalds</name> &amp; <name>Joe Coody</name> leaves the Point, be so good as to send me on some of the infection, with what directions you may have in your power to give, &amp; I will <add>see</add> to its circulation</p>
            <p>The letter put into your charge some time ago addressed to <name>Mr Blackburn</name>, was from the<name>Pathkiller</name> &amp; <name>John Lowrey</name>, requesting the favour of another teacher to the school established here in the room of <unclear>Mr Dixon</unclear> who has rendered himself, by his improper conduct very <pb n="3" facs="pa0019c.small.jpg"/>
               <sic>very</sic> reprehensible, but I find before that letter could be forwarded Mr Blackburn must have left home on his present tour, This school is capable of <choice>
                  <orig>flurishing</orig>
                  <reg>flourishing</reg>
               </choice> under any steady or reasonable man, Mr Blackburn cannot be worsted in his choice, &amp; if he is willing to try us again with another tutor, I will again use my endeavours to forward the institution but it is not to be expected it will ever prosper under a madman or an imposter. Indeed I suspect with reason that to procure <unclear>a fit</unclear> Indian to accompany him to <name>
                  <unclear>Ireland</unclear>
               </name> had more influence on Mr Dixon's coming to the <name>Cherokees</name>, than to teach the rising race in spelling &amp; reading, as soon as he thought proper to <choice>
                  <orig>breake</orig>
                  <reg>break</reg>
               </choice> off from me he attached himself to the rabble of <sic>of</sic> the place, &amp; <name>Dempsey Fields</name> became his bosom friend as well as some others of the same stamp &amp; by the vouchers of such, he endeavours to justify his inconsistency, not one reputable name in his whole catalogue excepting Lowrey who was  drawn in by imposition, &amp; is now <choice>
                  <orig>sory</orig>
                  <reg>sorry</reg>
               </choice> for lending his name, I only make this remark to you Sir merely lest Dixon should have the folly to be loud in his complaints,</p>
            <closer>With sentiments of respect I am Sir your very <choice>
                  <abbr>Obt. Servt.</abbr>
                  <expan>Obedient Servant</expan>
               </choice>
               <signed>
                  <name>Daniel Ross</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel</expan>
                        </choice> Return J. Meigs</name>}</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
