<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc126">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Legal document] 1805 Mar. 10,  Washington District Court, Green County, Tennessee, Sparling Bowman vs George Alexander et. al. : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc126</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Legal document] 1805 Mar. 10,  Washington District Court, Green County, Tennessee, Sparling Bowman vs George Alexander et. al </title>
               <date when="1805-03-10"> 
			 March 10, 1805</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a summary of a legal complaint brought by the attorney of Sparling Bowman against three defendents  in the matter of a disputed tract of land and a water obstruction  near the Nolochuckey river in Green County .</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fink &amp; Dulaney Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">19</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc126 </note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Legal issue summary</term>
               <term>Land.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc126a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Washington District Court</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>March Term 1805</date>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <name>Sparling Bowman</name> by his attorney complains of <name>George Alexander</name>
               <name>William Alexander</name>
               <unclear>Run  </unclear> and <name>James Pearce</name> late of the County of <name>Green</name> in the District aforesaid, in custody of the Sheriff in a Plea of Trespass on the case; For that whereas the said Plaintiff on the <date>first day of May in year one thousand eight hundred and three</date> and for a long time before and ever since and yet is law fully seized and possessed of a certain tract or parcel of land containing three hundred acres situate lying and being in the said County of Green in the South Side of <name>Nolochuckey river</name> on a creek called <name>Camp creek</name> in said District of <name>Washington</name> and a plantation on said part of Land, and one dwelling house thereon with two Springs of water areas the same within said tract of land from which said Sparling and his family for a long time before and <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> the obstruction hereafter mentioned, took water for the use of him and his said <add>Sparling</add> , family; and one still house on said part of Land with one Still of large capacity, towit, of the Capacity of ninety four Gallons and a large number of vessels in and about said still house which the said Sparling for a long time before and untill the obstruction hereon after mentioned had used and accrued  in distilling Spirits, and also a loom house on said tract of land with a loom in the same and other Utensils used by said Sparling in weaving for a long time before and untill said obstruction hereon after mentioned; the water of which Creek called Camp Creek had before the said first day of May in__ the year aforesaid run &amp; ought to run and still continued, untill the obstruction  hereinafter mentioned to run in the ancient usu <pb n="2" facs="sc126b.small.jpg"/> al course or channel there through said part of Land, near said two springs, the said Still house and said Loom houses without any obstruction or Impediment whatever or in any manner injuring, drawing or order flowing the said part of land, Said Springs, Still House or loom house or any part of them; Nevertheless the said George Alexander, William Alexander and James Pearce not ignorant of the premises, but designing and <choice>
                  <orig>malisiously</orig>
                  <reg>maliciously</reg>
               </choice> intending any unjustly to <choice>
                  <orig>aggreive</orig>
                  <reg>aggrieve</reg>
               </choice> and injure him, said Sparling, and to molest trust and damnify him in the use <choice>
                  <orig>posession</orig>
                  <reg>possession</reg>
               </choice> and occupation of his said tract or parcel of land Springs. Still house with the said Still vessels <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>and et cetera</expan>
               </choice> in and about the same, and loom house with said loom &amp;c in the same, and to deprive him of the greatest part of the Profits thereof, on the said first Day of May in the year aforesaid, and at <choice>
                  <orig>divers</orig>
                  <reg>diverse</reg>
               </choice> other Days and times between that day and the day of <date>January one thousand eight hundred and five</date>, let down and <unclear>shrubs</unclear>  and kept and continued that certain gates or flood gates lately erected upon the said creek called Camp creek, below the said part or parcel of land, and also continued and kept up a certain forge dam or Dam for a bloomery late by erected across said creek in the District aforesaid, below the said tract or parcel of Land, by reason and means of which the water of the said creek at <orig>divers</orig> times within  the time above mentioned was <choice>
                  <orig>stoped</orig>
                  <reg>stopped</reg>
               </choice> run back and overflowed a large part of said tract or parcel of Land, towit, about three acres near to said creek, and adjoining said still house and Loom house and said two Springs of said Sparlings, and covered said spring, filled said still House and Loom House with water and Mud and prevented said Sparling from attending or cultivating one field containing about eleven acres, being part of said tract or parcel of Land of which the said Sparling <pb n="3" facs="sc126c.small.jpg"/> was and yet is seized and possessed by which the said Sparling has been greatly <choice>
                  <orig>dammaged</orig>
                  <reg>damaged</reg>
               </choice> in the possession and occupation of his said that or parcel of lands and during all the time aforesaid hath lost the use, Profit and advantage of said two springs, said Still house and Loom house, said three acres of Land so overflowed and covered with the water of said creek, and said field containing eleven acres, and has been altogether prevented from carrying on the business of Distributing spirits, in said, Still house and from weaving, in his said loom house; to the Damage of said Sparling One Thousand Dollars and  thereupon he brings Suit, and there are Pledges to prosecute</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>Whiteside</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sc126d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Sparling Bowman <lb/>
                  <unclear>us &amp; Nar</unclear>
                  <lb/> George Alexander <lb/> William Alexander <lb/> James Pearce</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
