<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl672">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Extradition request] 1841 Jun. 10, Nashville, Tennessee [to] Governor of Alabama / James K. Polk : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Polk, James K.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl672</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Extradition request] 1841 Jun. 10, Nashville, Tennessee [to] Governor of Alabama / James K. Polk</title>
               <author>  Polk, James K.</author>
               <date when="1841-06-10"> 
			 June 10, 1841</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is an extradition request, dated June 10, 1841, from the governor of Tennessee, James K. Polk, to the governor of Alabama, Benjamin Fitzpatrick.  Polk asks the governor to assure the apprehension and delivery of Hiram Baker to the proper agents in Tennessee, so that he may stand trial.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor James K. Polk Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">8</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl672</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor (1839-1841 : Polk)</term>
               <term>Polk, James K. (James Knox), 1795-1849</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80145740"
                        role="Creator http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/cre">Polk, James K. (James Knox), 1795-1849</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl672a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>State of Tennessee; Executive Department</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>To his Excellency, The <choice>
                     <orig>Govenor</orig>
                     <reg>Governor</reg>
                  </choice> of the State of <name>Alabama</name>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Whereas it has been made known to me by the oath of <name>John M. Bass</name>, President of the union bank of <name>Tennessee</name>, duly made in from of affidavit, and is now on file in the Executive Office of Tennessee, an authenticated copy of which is hereto annexed.  That <name>Hiram Baker</name> stand charged with having committed a felony, on the said Union Bank, which is within our County of <name>Davidson</name>, and is now believed to be running at large in the State of <name>Alabama</name>.  Now I<name> James K. Polk</name>, Governor of the state of Tennessee aforesaid, do by virtue of the authority in me, vested by act of Congress, approved <date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Feby</abbr>
                     <expan>February</expan>
                  </choice>. 12th 1793</date>, entitled "An act respecting fugitives from justice," demand of your Excellency, that the said Hiram Baker, if to be found in the State of Alabama, be apprehended and delivered to <name>Edward B. Beagley</name> and <name>Henry A Morgan</name>, or either of the, when I have appointed agents on the part of the State of Tennessee, to receive the said Hiram Baker and to convey him to the County of Davidson in the State of Tennessee, to be delivered to the Sheriff or jailor of said county, that he may be tried for the offense of which he stands charged__</p>
            <closer>
               <add>In testimony whereof I have hereunto set my hand &amp; caused the Great Seal of the State to be affixed at Nashville this <date>10th day of June 1841</date>.</add>
               <signed>
                  <name>James K. Polk</name>
               </signed>
               <add>By the Govenor <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Jno</abbr>
                        <expan>John</expan>
                     </choice> Young</name> Secretary of State</add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl672b.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Copy Received JSY Demand on the governor of Alabama, for the apprehension of Hiram Baker a fugitive from justice.  The Demand was accompanied by the affidavit of John M. Bass__ duly authenticated by the secretary of state; <unclear>as due </unclear> with a letter of authority__ to the agents__ <unclear>oppents</unclear> to receive__ the felon &amp; carry him to the state of Tennessee.__ Done at <name>Fayettville</name>
                  <date>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Decm</abbr>
                        <expan>December</expan>
                     </choice> 12th 1841</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
