<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm062">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Photograph of a scale cabin reconstruction at Red Clay State
			 Park, Bradley County, Tennessee, taken circa 1980s] / [by Gerald F. Schroedl] :
			 a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Schroedl, Gerald F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Mays</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno>mm062</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 48016807</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work in the property of the Frank H. McClung Museum,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. All other use is prohibited without the
				express written permission of the copyright holder.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Photograph of a scale cabin reconstruction at Red Clay State
				Park, Bradley County, Tennessee, taken circa 1980s] / [by Gerald F. Schroedl] :
				a machine-readable transcription</title>
               <author>Schroedl, Gerald F.</author>
               <date when="1980">1980s</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This photograph is of a scale cabin
				reconstruction at the Red Clay site at Red Clay State Park in Bradley County,
				Tennessee. Federal Period Cherokee did not use machine rounded logs or saddle
				notch in the construction of their log cabins like what the photograph here
				shows. The Federal Period Cherokee would have cut their own logs and would have
				used wither dovetail, half-dovetail, or 'V' notching for their cabins. By 1832,
				the state of Georgia had refused the Cherokee the right to hold council
				meetings unless the meeting dealt with treaties that gave away their lands. The
				Cherokee decided to move their capital from New Echota, Georgia across the
				state line to Red Clay, Tennessee because the state of Tennessee did not
				prohibit the Cherokees from meeting together. Thus, Red Clay became the seat of
				the Cherokee government in 1832 and lasted until the removal of the Cherokees
				to the west in 1838. Red Clay was composed of 11 general councils and the
				meetings were attended by up to 5000 people. It was at Red Clay that the
				Cherokee learned that they had lost all of their land and would be removed to
				the west. Red Clay consists of the sacred Blue Hole Spring, a reconstructed
				council house, and several reconstructed homestead buildings. Red Clay is also
				the home to the Eternal Flame, lit on April 6, 1984. The Cherokees took hot
				coals from their council fire at Red Clay on the Trail of Tears. The flame was
				later taken to Cherokee, North Carolina in the 1950s but was returned to Red
				Clay in 1984. This was the first symbolic step unifying the Eastern Cherokees
				with the Cherokee Nation in Oklahoma since their removal in 1838. Today Red
				Clay State Historical Park is not only a historical site, but is also an
				interpretive site on the Trail of Tears.</note>
               <note type="collection">Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note>mm062document</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Photographs</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</term>
               <term>Red Clay Site (Tenn.)</term>
               <term>Log cabins</term>
               <term>Historic sites</term>
               <term>Bradley County (Tenn.)</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n78090514"
                        role="Photographer http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/pht">Schroedl, Gerald F.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mm062.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>This is a photographic image of a scale cabin
				  reconstruction at 
				  <name type="place">Red Clay State Historical Park </name>in 
				  <name type="place">Bradley County, Tennessee</name>. Photograph
				  taken by 
				  <name type="person">Gerald F. Schroedl</name>, circa 1980s. This
				  information was provided by the 
				  <name type="person">Frank H. McClung </name>Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
