<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl419">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1839 Apr. 4, Carthage, Tennessee [to] Felix Grundy, Washington [D.C.] / A[dam] Fergusson: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Fergusson, A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl419</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1839 Apr. 4, Carthage, Tennessee [to] Felix Grundy, Washington [D.C.] / A[dam] Fergusson</title>
               <author>Fergusson, A.</author>
               <date when="1839-04-04">April 4, 1839</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Adam Fergusson to the Honorable Felix Grundy, dated April 4, 1839. Fergusson has several questions regarding pension law that he wants Grundy to answer. He also discusses the local political climate.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">IV-G-1, B6</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl419</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Pensions</term>
               <term>Working life</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Fergusson, Adam</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl419a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Carthage</name>
                     <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>4th april 1839</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I <choice>
                  <orig>aply</orig>
                  <reg>apply</reg>
               </choice> to you as an old friend and <choice>
                  <orig>acquantance</orig>
                  <reg>acquaintance</reg>
               </choice> for your opinion in relation to Pensioners and Pension claims. A question has been raised by Some as I am informed whether an attorney acting for a Pensioner can charge his reasonable <choice>
                  <orig>expences</orig>
                  <reg>expenses</reg>
               </choice> in travelling to <name>Nashville</name> and back or to be more explicit whether he can charge one dollar per day for himself and horse in travelling to draw a Pensioners claim. The oath is very binding <choice>
                  <orig>Suficently</orig>
                  <reg>Sufficiently</reg>
               </choice> So to prevent his being the least interested; but whether after paying to the Pensioner the whole of his money and then the Pensioner of his own free will pays to his attorney his expences while going  for it creates Such an interest in the Pension as is contemplated in the oath he takes previously is the question I wish to know. If it shall be decided that an attorney cannot <choice>
                  <orig>recieve</orig>
                  <reg>receive</reg>
               </choice> no compensation whatever; Then will the aged and decrepid Pensioner whether male or female but more especially the female be more liable to be swindled out of the money which Government in its unbounded charity designed for their <choice>
                  <orig>Suport</orig>
                  <reg>Support</reg>
               </choice> . for then no person who values his character or reputation will act for them knowing the danger he incurs while the man of no character or feeling and who is not <choice>
                  <orig>responsble</orig>
                  <reg>responsible</reg>
               </choice> will be the only person the Pension can employ <pb n="2" facs="sl419b.small.jpg"/> another <choice>
                  <orig>queston</orig>
                  <reg>question</reg>
               </choice> is whether in establishing a claim to a Pension under any of the late existing laws an attorney or agent who collects the proof records and other documents can charge a regular and Stated compensation. You will See that the establishing a widows claim in this county is attended with much difficulty the record of marriage and other <choice>
                  <orig>testamony</orig>
                  <reg>testimony</reg>
               </choice> being altogether <choice>
                  <sic>in in</sic>
                  <corr>in</corr>
               </choice> the eastern or atlantic States their marriage having taken place when these western States were not inhabited. I Should have been Satisfied with the Plain reading of the various laws that <del type="overstrike">is</del>  the attorney in fact who takes the oath must not be interested in any way whatever but the Pension must wholly inure to the benefit of the Pensioner. But we are likely to have a great Political excitement in our State &amp; every thing that can be Seized upon to make capitol out of to inflame and instead the People will be resorted to. On tomorrow <choice>
                  <abbr>Col</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Polk and the <choice>
                  <orig>varios</orig>
                  <reg>various</reg>
               </choice> other candidates will <choice>
                  <orig>adress</orig>
                  <reg>address</reg>
               </choice> the people it is a fearful crisis both parties are making ready for the <choice>
                  <orig>sumers</orig>
                  <reg>summer's</reg>
               </choice>  campaign and the whigs as they are called <add>who</add> are now the majority <add>in this <unclear>districts</unclear>
               </add> are <choice>
                  <orig>aprehensive</orig>
                  <reg>apprehensive</reg>
               </choice> of consequences . I am but an individual it is true but I <del type="overstrike">have as</del> claim as much right to the freedom of my own opinion as any other citizen whatever being a democrat from my youth under the Jeffersonian and Jackson School I should be <choice>
                  <orig>extremley</orig>
                  <reg>extremely</reg>
               </choice> Sorry to inure the displeasure of any party for mere <pb n="3" facs="sl419c.small.jpg"/> opinions Sake but that time I think is fast approaching in our beloved Tennessee. <add>when any one who <choice>
                     <orig>suports</orig>
                     <reg>supports</reg>
                  </choice> the present administration will be singled out as of <unclear>writing</unclear>
               </add> You will do me an everlasting kindness by writing to me by return of mail or as Soon as convenient and let me know <del type="overstrike">whether</del> your opinion as respects the foregoing questions of law I want this opinion for my own particular guidance <add>to impart to my <choice>
                     <orig>freinds</orig>
                     <reg>friends</reg>
                  </choice>
               </add> as I have and now am employed in establishing Several widows Pensions which will take a great <choice>
                  <orig>expence</orig>
                  <reg>expense</reg>
               </choice> as well as close  <choice>
                  <orig>aplication</orig>
                  <reg>application</reg>
               </choice> and industry in travelling and hunting up the necessary proof and I trust I should be the last man in Tennessee that would wrong one of these <choice>
                  <orig>relecks</orig>
                  <reg>relics</reg>
               </choice> of the Revolution out of a single cent my object having been to charge them only what would indemnify me for the Services performed and money expended. I have written a letter about a week Since to <name>James S Edwards</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                  <expan>Esquire</expan>
               </choice> commissioner of Pensions in which I requested of him the above information and also to obtain your opinion if he thought proper</p>
            <p>
               <del type="overstrike">I shall wait fer</del>
               <add>expect</add> your letter and in the mean time accept the assurances of my great esteem and respect</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>A.</abbr>
                        <expan>Adam</expan>
                     </choice> Fergusson</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Hon</abbr>
                        <expan>Honorable</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name>Felix Grundy</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>attorney General</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Washington</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
