<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch069">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter], 1823 Oct. 24, New Town, Cherokee Nation / Path Killer ... [et al.]: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Path Killer</author>
            <author>Ridge, Major</author>
            <author>Ross, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch069</idno>
            <idno>oclc: 44862174</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter], 1823 Oct. 24, New Town, Cherokee Nation / Path Killer ... [et al.]</title>
               <author>Path Killer</author>
               <author>Ridge, Major</author>
               <author>Ross, John</author>
               <date when="1823-10-24">October 24, 1823</date>
               <extent>5p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">(Copy ?) of a letter dated October 24, 1823 from the Cherokee Council to (U.S. Commissioners Duncan G. Campbell and James Meriwether ?) concerning future cessions of land. The Cherokee government refuses to sell anymore land to the United States and offers several arguments for their position.</note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch069</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Land tenure</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="https://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n82214557"
                        role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Ross, John, 1790-1866</name>
               </term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85180705"
                        role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Ridge, Major, approximately 1771-1839</name>
               </term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Path Killer</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch069a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">New Town</name>, <name>Cherokee Nation</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <date when="1823-10-24">Oct. 24th, 1823</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>In General Council<lb/>Friends  Brothers
                  </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your communication of the 21st Instant have been deliberated by the General Council and it seems that you anticipate a hope that your application for a cession might yet be granted.  We assure you in the strongest terms that our rejection is founded upon a mature and deliberate determination which cannot be changed.  The title of the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> to the lands in their possession is indisputable, and the <name type="place">United States</name> by the treaty of <name type="place">Hopewell</name> in <date when="1791">1791</date>, in the 7th article fully declares it to be so by solemnly <choice>
                  <orig>guarantying</orig>
                  <reg>guaranteeing</reg>
               </choice> it to them.  Brothers, We are fully sensible that we are <hi>dependant</hi> upon the government of the <name type="place">United States</name> for <hi>protection</hi> and have ever manifested a disposition to conduct ourselves in such a manner as comport with our duty in that respect  And we are surprised, and at a loss to know what has given grounds to harbor a contrary opinion of our disposition in that respect.  There must be<pb n="2" facs="ch069b.small.jpg"/>a source from whence a misrepresentation of our disposition has been communicated to our father the President.  The remark that we made <q>that <add place="supralinear">the <name type="person">Cherokees</name>
                  </add>
                  <del type="overstrike">we</del> once possessed an extensive country and they made cession after cession to our father the President to gratify the wishes of our neighboring brethren <choice>
                     <orig>untill</orig>
                     <reg>until</reg>
                  </choice> our limits had become circumscribed</q> was not intended to mean that we would wish to repossess what we had surrendered (as would seem from your eloquent remarks on that point) but to show  that if we continued to yield to our Fathers application in behalf of our neighboring Brethren as we had heretofore done, that the whole of our lands would be gone.  It is not our wish to <q>demolish Temples raised to <unclear/> and dedicated to God, so that Beasts might have a wider range or Game a broader play,</q> nor to <q>lay waste a city that a Wigwam might rise upon its ruins.</q>  But it is our desire that monuments of Science may raised by our hands on the dust of our Progenitors, from which, the Beasts of the field have receded, and the Wigwam tottering into ruin.
               </p>
            <p>The Bow and the Quiver are laid aside and the pursuits of the chase are forgotten.  The axe, the Hoe, the Plow, and the Shuttle, are introduced<pb n="3" facs="ch069c.small.jpg"/>and progressing like a consuming fire; and it is hoped that a mist will not arise to dampen its progress.  You suggest an idea, that if this Nation would preserve a compact form of a Territorial Government of the <name type="place">United States</name> "not within the limits of the States no obstacle would remain to the organization, but" while they are they are within the limits of the States, the State Sovereignty must prevail, and they must become merged in the white population, and take the Standing of individual citizens.  And you further remark, that in case of a cession of a part, that all those who do not chose to become citizens would be indemnified for their loss, and those that chose to become members of the States can be secured in a  residence and let into all the privileges of ordinary citizens."  Brothers, the suggestion of the organization of a territorial government, is a subject of too great weight for the Nation to take up in their present situation, therefore the suggestion cannot meet our acceptation  as respects being secured with indemnification and residence and privileges of citizenship in the States.  We beg leave to ask you to look to the Treaty of <date when="1819">1819</date>.  What was the provisions made for the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> in the 2nd Article of that treaty?  And what has<pb n="4" facs="ch069d.small.jpg"/>been the course pursued by the States of <name type="place">Tennessee</name> and <name type="place">Georgia</name>, and some of their citizens, relative to the sacred obligations contained in that article?  We find that opposition, fraud, and every species of injustice were raised against the interests of the poor inexperienced <name type="person">Cherokees</name> by them; and before the aid and <choice>
                  <orig>assisstance</orig>
                  <reg>assistance</reg>
               </choice> of the magnanimous hand of the General government could be extended to their relief an entire ruin, and loss of property have been sustained by many of them and many of them who are entitled to compensation for improvements under that treaty, have never received one cent, a very small portion of the improvements left have been valued and paid for.  Brothers, we cannot curtail the present limits which <hi>has</hi> been <hi>reserved</hi> to this nation in the Treaty of <date when="1819">1819</date>.  The prosperity and future happiness of our posterity, cannot be lost sight of, when their destiny is placed in our hands; and should we act as an honest father and preserve their interest and their right, they will rejoice and be happy in commemorating our names, when we are no more.  Under these circumstances, our brethren of <name type="place">Georgia</name> cannot, or ought not, to desire us to destroy ourselves, so that they may <choice>
                  <orig>aggrandise</orig>
                  <reg>aggrandize</reg>
               </choice> themselves, and raise<pb n="5" facs="ch069e.small.jpg"/>Temples upon our ruins.  Their State is respectable in wealth and in population as well as in liberal sentiments of honorable men, and the extent of its bounds not small but considerably larger than many of the other states in the Union.  Brothers, we beg leave to present this communication as a positive and unchangeable refusal to dispose of <hi>one foot</hi> more of <hi>lands</hi>, so that no further application or anticipations of success may be encouraged on your part, and that a final close of the correspondence on this subject should herewith take place, as the council will very soon, rise, having already continued four days over the time allowed by the authorities of the nation for its Setting.
                     
                  
               </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>With calmness and cordiality We subscribe ourselves as Friends  Brothers</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Path Killer</name>
               </signed> Head Chief <unclear>his</unclear>
               <signed>X</signed> mark<signed>
                  <name type="person">Major Ridge</name>
               </signed>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Sper.</abbr>
                  <expan>Speaker</expan>
               </choice> of <choice>
                  <abbr>Cl.</abbr>
                  <expan>Council</expan>
               </choice>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">John Ross</name>
               </signed>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Prest. Nl. Ctee.</abbr>
                  <expan>President National Committee</expan>
               </choice>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>A.</abbr>
                        <expan>Alexander</expan>
                     </choice> McCoy</name>
               </signed>, <choice>
                  <abbr>Clk Nl</abbr>
                  <expan>Clerk National</expan>
               </choice> Committee<signed>
                  <name type="person">Elijah Hicks</name>
               </signed>, <choice>
                  <abbr>Clk Nl.</abbr>
                  <expan>Clerk National</expan>
               </choice> Council</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
