<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl014"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Certificate] 1829 Jan. 8 [Certificate of the Anniversary of the Battle of New Orleans] : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl014</idno><idno>OCLC: 50009181</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Certificate] 1829 Jan. 8 [Certificate of the Anniversary of the Battle of New Orleans]</title><date value="1829-01-08">January 8, 1829</date><extent>2p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a certificate, dated January 8, 1829, commemorating the Anniversary of the Battle of New Orleans. The Battle of New Orleans was fought between the United States and Great Britain on January 19, 1815.</note><note type="collection">Sir Emil Hurja Collection</note><note type="box">8</note><note type="folder">2</note><note type="document">sl014</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>New Orleans, Battle of, New Orleans, La., 1815</item><item>Anniversaries</item><item>Louisiana</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="certificate"><pb n="[1]"/><head>ANNIVERSARY. <hi rend="sc">the</hi> BATTLE <hi rend="sc">of</hi> <name type="place">NEW ORLEANS</name>.</head><p><figure><figDesc>portrait, perhaps of Goverrin Tayler</figDesc></figure></p><p>TRIUMPH OF REPUBLICAN PRINCIPLES.</p><p><name type="place">Tammany Hall</name>.</p><p><date value="1829-01-08">January 8th 1829</date></p><p><table><head><hi rend="sc">Managers</hi></head><row><cell><name type="person">Alexander M. Muir</name>,</cell><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">Elisha Tibbits</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Oliver M. Lownds</name>,</cell><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">Philip Thomas</name>,</cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Dennis <unclear>H.</unclear> Doyle</name></cell><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person"><abbr expan="Jonathan">Jona.</abbr> J. Coddington</name>.</cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">John Lorimer Graham</name>.</cell><cell> </cell></row></table><add place="left of figure, sideways"><hi rend="written text"><name type="person"><unclear>Goverrin</unclear> Tayler</name></hi></add><add place="right of figure, sideways"><hi rend="written text"><abbr expan="Oliver">O</abbr>M Lownds</hi></add></p><pb n="[2]"/> <p><address><addrLine><emph><name type="person">John <unclear>Sounier Haliaw</unclear></name></emph></addrLine></address></p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
