<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl052"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1813 March 22 [to] Colonel Sevier / John Sevier : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Sevier, John</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl052</idno><idno>OCLC: 50030541</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1813 March 22 [to] Colonel Sevier / John Sevier</title><author>Sevier, John</author><date value="1813-03-22">March 22, 1813</date><extent>2p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated March 22, 1813 to Colonel Sevier, written by his father, former Governor of Tennessee, John Sevier. Sevier discusses various topics in the letter, including the War of 1812, a lawsuit against Polk, and the condition of his son's mare.</note><note type="collection">Tennessee Historical Society</note><note type="box">Correspondence by Author, 1809 b2</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">sl052</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>United States -- History -- War of 1812</item><item>Polk, James K. (James Knox), 1795-1849</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Staunton</name></addrLine></address><date>22 March 1813</date><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>Your letter of the 9th instant with <name type="person">Mr Pheas</name> two <orig reg="enclosed">inclosed</orig> I have received&mdash; I arrived here on Saturday after traveling in the stage from <name type="place">Fredericksburgh</name> two days and nights without rest or sleep, and frequently had to walk in mud and water to the knees&mdash; I never<orig reg="experienced">exparienced</orig> more <orig reg="fatigue">feateague</orig> in the whole course of my life, and am so sore and bruised all over That it is with difficulty I can get up when down&mdash; I shall not be able to leave this place for a week&mdash; Your <orig reg="Mare">Mair</orig> is much better but her legs is yet some swelled and am afraid when rode will be more so. I am to have a saddle made by the last of the week and will endeavor to <orig reg="set">sit</orig> out so soon as that is done, and will ride slow until I arrive home <orig reg="once">onst</orig> more, which I want much to do, otherways I should not <del type="overstrike">do</del> <add place="supralinear">attempt</add> until after the next session, which is to meet the <date value="0000-05-24">24th May</date> and expected will sit until first of August. I cant remain at home more than 15 or 20 days should I be reelected, the <orig reg="fatigue">feateague</orig> will be great but shall undertake it if I find the <orig reg="mare">mair</orig> can travel&mdash; You may write me at this place least I may not get out&mdash; I cant be at the election at any rate, and must leave this event with my friends, should there be any opposition&mdash; The <name type="person">British</name> are making up the <orig reg="different ">differant</orig> rivers from <name type="place">Norfolk</name>, and it is difficult to say what they intend&mdash; Men are collecting in every quarter of <name type="place">Virginia </name>, and marching down&mdash; The Russian Emperor is offering his mediation, and the Minister is very desirous of bringing about an accommodation between the <name type="place"><abbr expan="United">U</abbr> States</name>  and the British Nation&mdash; I have no news from <name type="person">Harrisons</name> army nor from<name type="place"> Sackets harbor</name>. I wish things there may go <orig reg="well">will</orig>. <pb n="[2]"/> I will be glad you will have an eye to the affairs of the plantation, I have heard nothing from home for a long time&mdash; The suit with <name type="person">Polk </name>did not come on, they pretended that the transcript was lost, but it was only a  <unclear>Finan</unclear> in Polks lawyer in order to keep the suit off and from paying the costs, <abbr expan="though">tho</abbr> I did not wish it tried in the absence of <name type="person">Judge Todd</name>&mdash;</p><p>The important suit Between <name type="person">Patton &amp; Irvin</name>, and the occupants on <name type="place">Duck river</name> have been decided, and the decision of the Circuit Court at <name type="place">Nashville</name> confirmed&mdash; The Occupants alleged and offered to prove, that the warrants on which Patton &amp; Irvins Grant was founded on, had been previously reponed into Grants at least three or four time, but it would not do, it was the lock out of the state, and not for innocent persons to suffer in consequence of the mismanagement of  the state&mdash; I am as confident of my gaining my suit as <abbr expan="though">tho</abbr> it was already done&mdash; I hope are this that <name type="person">Kitty</name> and the children are with you&mdash; I received her letter with one <orig reg="enclosed">inclosed</orig> to you, which I immediately enclosed again and forwarded to this place if you should be here if not to proceed to <name type="place">Knoxville</name> <abbr expan="Tennessee">( T.)</abbr></p><closer><salute>Your affectionate Father</salute><signed><name type="person">John Sevier</name></signed><address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Sevier</name></addrLine></address><date value="1813-03-22">22 March 1813</date></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
