<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl059"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1823, Cabarrus County, North Carolina [to] James Trimble / Charles Harris : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Harris, Charles</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl059</idno><idno>OCLC: 50078344</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1823, Cabarrus County, North Carolina [to] James Trimble / Charles Harris</title><author>Harris, Charles</author><date value="1823-00-00">1823</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written by Charles Harris to James Trimble in 1823. In the letter, Harris discusses with Trimble a lawsuit that he is involved in over land he owns in Tennessee.</note><note type="collection">Coffee Perkins Papers</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">14</note><note type="document">sl059</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Land tenure</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><unclear>Favoni</unclear> <name type="place">Cabarrus County</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">North Carolina</name></addrLine></address><salute><name type="person">Mr Trimble</name></salute></opener><p>I received &caret; <add place="supralinear">a letter from you</add> containing a formula with a plan of <orig reg="instructions">instrutions</orig> relative to a <orig reg="mischievous">mischievious</orig> lawsuit of a Land affair that my name is affixed to in your State &mdash; I know so little of the origin &amp; progress of the lawsuit that I have no <emph>data</emph> to go upon in my mind to decide whether I should approve or disapprove of the conduct &amp; management of the affair &mdash; The thing appeared to me in the origin that there were nothing but self evident truth, to act with &amp; upon &mdash; But like an erratic figure in a <unclear>sum</unclear> of <orig reg="Arithmetic">Arithmatic</orig> no matter however <del type="overstrike">ho</del> where it may be placed but I suppose the newer the <orig reg="beginning">begining</orig> the greater will be the divergence from <pb n="[2]"/> truth in the result &mdash;</p><p><name type="person">Thomas Harris</name> has <unclear>refered</unclear> to <del type="overstrike">sign</del> join with me in the probate you have sent on the solid <orig reg="presumption">presumtion</orig> that he never knew any thing relative to the &caret; <add place="supralinear">affair</add> <orig reg="until">untill</orig> I acquainted him by a letter from <name type="person">Mr Campbell</name> that his name was joined with mine in this <unclear>waful </unclear> Lawsuit he immediately gave me a <unclear>reliage</unclear> and quit claim &mdash; I was no how aware this would ever be farther necessary than merely to promote our mutual satisfaction &mdash; I herewith  <unclear>inclose</unclear> his <unclear>retiafe</unclear> &mdash; with all the requisite authorities that I could find were necessary &mdash;</p><p><name type="person">Jane Alexander</name> is <unclear>so religiously</unclear> <orig reg="melancholy">melancholly</orig> that nothing can be done with her in the affairs of the sublunory would her business appears to be taken at <unclear>last ostensibly</unclear> with the concerns of the undiscovered <pb n="[3]"/> county &mdash; For Matter of merely being against whatever might be surmised &mdash; I got a release from her and all her grown children at or bout the same time Thomas Harris executed his &mdash;</p><p>I hereby enclose a letter from <name type="person">Johnson</name> &mdash; &amp; <name type="person">Calhoun</name> the younger from which I am told by my friend <name type="person">Julius Alexander</name> you may draw some precious confessions</p><closer><salute>I am Sir Yours Sincerely</salute><signed><emph><name type="person"><abbr expan="Charles">Chas</abbr> Harris</name></emph></signed> <pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine><name type="person">James Trimble</name> <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine></address><add place="below address, upside down"><name type="person">Doctor <abbr expan="Charles">Ch</abbr> Harris</name> <lb/> <date value="1823-00-00">1823</date> <lb/> <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr> by <name type="person">Moses S <lb/> Harris</name> &mdash;</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
