<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl069"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1834 May 19, Wilson C[oun]ty, Tenn[essee] [to] Mrs. Martha J. Reams / A. H. Reams : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Reams, A. H.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl069</idno><idno>OCLC: 50079246</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1834 May 19, Wilson C[oun]ty, Tenn[essee] [to] Mrs. Martha J. Reams / A. H. Reams</title><author>Reams, A. H.</author><date value="1834-05-19">May 19, 1834</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written by A. H. Reams to Martha J. Reams on May 19, 1834. In the letter, A. H. Reams describes to Martha how productive his business in Wilson County, Tennessee is, and instructs her to collect  money from people who are indebted to him.</note><note type="collection">Reams Collection Correspondence</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">9</note><note type="document">sl069</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Debt service</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><orig reg="Commerce">Commerse</orig><name type="place"> Wilson <abbr expan="County Tennessee">Cty Tenn.</abbr></name> <date value="1834-05-19">May 19th 1834</date></addrLine><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs Martha J. Reams</name></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Companion,</salute></opener><p>these lines will inform You that I am well, and am getting over my fatigue. I need not say any thing about my arrival as the <unclear>siperre</unclear> returned. But I will mention some little things. <name type="person">Hannible Hersey</name> Paid me <date value="000-05-15">May 15th</date> $2.00 or in full please tell Father to receipt it in full. to my great astonishment when I went to make arrangements with my Landlord for corn &amp; fodder he only asked me $1 and 50 <abbr expan="cents">cts</abbr> per Barrel, and $1.00 per hundred for better Fodder than I left. <name type="person">Mr Newly <abbr expan="Esquire">Esq.</abbr></name> has pure <orig reg="pristine">prestine</orig> Water, and another spring mixed with the lime. I had a call the 17th &mdash; <name type="person"><abbr expan="Brother">Br</abbr> Seay</name>, Wife, &amp; Daughter passed my shop door a few minutes <orig reg="ago">agoe</orig>, and they all solicited, as did sister cook on yesterday that I should come and bring you to see them Martha. so far as my prospects are <orig reg="concerned">conserned</orig>, I can not say but little <sic>I I</sic> Just Say this <pb n="[2]"/> much <abbr expan="I am">I'm</abbr> not discouraged. If you come in the way Father and me was talking about which I am in hopes you will be able to <orig reg="do">dwo</orig> there will be no chance to bring any Chairs I <abbr expan="do not">dont</abbr> <orig reg="reckon">racon</orig> upon the event it should be <orig reg="convenient">conveneint</orig> to slip one ore two in the carriage duo so as I <orig reg="would">wood</orig> feel more <orig reg="independent">independant</orig> in the shop if I had some though that is a small matter and I can get them here, and <orig reg="do">dwo</orig> no want you come in and them <orig reg="corresponds">coresponds</orig>. Tell the Friend who may bring you that the best Rout after he leaves <name type="place">Alexandria</name> will be to come or go around by <del type="overstrike">w</del> Water's Mill and <orig reg="thence">thense</orig> down said creek (Round lick) to <name type="place">Saulsbury</name> the best Rout which is not more than 2, or 3 miles farther than through the hills and five times as good a rout. You must kiss <name type="person">Herschel</name> my son for me as I was so pressed the morning I left that I forgot it for which I feel very sorry. If I <orig reg="do">dwo</orig> not get my shoos from <name type="person">Henry Youngbloods</name> Alexandria before you come on please bring them. <pb n="[3]"/></p><p>I forgot to leave you any money the morning I left tell Father, that I want him to let you have what you want, and also tell him that I am depending on him to change my Journal to Commerce Wilson <abbr expan="County Tennessee">Cty. Tenn.</abbr> and out of monies collected to pay <name type="person">John T. S. Fall</name> &mdash; College Street &mdash; <name type="person">Ben Franklin</name> office, and as he has my bill from <name type="person">Evin</name> $35.08 with a <orig reg="receipt">recipt</orig> $32. he is well prepared to tell the gentleman how the matter stands, and settle that also if convenient and if not it <abbr expan="do not">dont</abbr> matter for Evin received 40 or 50 dollars from me and I expect would not be looser if he waited several years for the money &mdash; if <name type="person">William Gilly</name> <name type="person">George Grizzle</name> nor any of the <orig reg="Balance">Ballance</orig> will pay in send me word how the matter is driving. For I must pay Fall before long. If you see <name type="person">Ezekial Watson</name> as you come through Alexandria <unclear>dun</unclear> him for $12.50 and if he <orig reg="pays">pais</orig> you give him a clear Receipt. <pb n="[4]"/> Give my Love to Father, &amp; Mother, and all the Children. tell the Servants that I still remember them. tell <name type="person">Matilda</name> that I have not <orig reg="forgotten">forgoten</orig> his but still expect some day to present his with some thing for waiting on you, I want to hear from <unclear><name type="person">Is Tubb</name></unclear> as a Physician &mdash; and <name type="person"><abbr expan="Brother">Br</abbr> C T Jones</name> Wife as Patient for whom <abbr expan="I have">Ive</abbr> suffered some <orig reg="uneasiness">onesiness</orig> not being able to assertain how his case has or will <orig reg="terminate">terminat</orig>, remember me especially to <name type="person"><abbr expan="Brother William">Br Wm</abbr> Foster</name>, Grandadies Mother &amp; all enquiring Friends</p><p>I must close with the warmest feelings of my heart to you and our little Boy Burger</p><closer><signed><name type="person"><emph>A. H. Reams</emph></name></signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
