<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl072"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1838 Nov. 5, Batchelors [Bachelors] Hall, Tennessee [to] D[octo]r James L. Alexander / N. B. Hamilton : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Hamilton, N. B.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl072</idno><idno>OCLC: 50132938</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1838 Nov. 5, Batchelors [Bachelors] Hall, Tennessee [to] D[octo]r James L. Alexander / N. B. Hamilton</title><author>Hamilton, N. B.</author><date value="1838-11-05">November 5, 1838</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written by N. B. Hamilton to  Doctor James L. Alexander on November 5, 1838. In the letter, Hamilton discusses several social events that have occurred in Murfreesboro, Tennessee, including a Ladies' Fair and participating in the activities at a local singing school. Hamilton also mentions that a volunteer company has gone to the Cherokee Nation, but he does not know why they have gone there. He concludes the letter by stating that the corn crop will be good in his area that year, but little fruit will be available for sale.</note><note type="collection">Alexander Papers Correspondence</note><note type="box">VI-G-2</note><note type="folder">2</note><note type="document">sl072</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee -- Description and travel</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><orig reg="Bachelors">Batchelors</orig>-Hall &mdash; <name type="place">Tennessee</name> <date value="1834-05-11">May 11th 1834</date></addrLine></address><salute>My Dear Friend</salute></opener><p>I have once more concluded to <orig reg="break">brake</orig> silence, I hope you will not think <orig reg="hard">heard</orig> of me for not writing to you sooner, as I will try and a make up the loss time in my letter, I shall give you the news in general &mdash; The Ladies fair took place in <name type="place">Murfreesboro</name> on the first day of this month, I did not attend as the times are <orig reg="hard">heard</orig> and <orig reg="money">mony</orig> scarce, I thought it best for me to keep out of all such scrapes, if I wished to save my &mdash; credit. &mdash; I have been <orig reg="told">toled</orig> since, <orig reg="they">thay</orig> figured largely &mdash; <orig reg="There">Thare</orig> were upwards of three hundred persons <orig reg="there">thare</orig>, lots and <orig reg="gobs">gobbs</orig> of girls. some very <orig reg="pretty">prety</orig> ones as you may well guess, And some as ugly as the devil, <orig reg="Admittance">Admitance</orig> 25 <add place="supralinear"><abbr expan="cents">cts</abbr></add> to the fair, to the supper $1.00, which you know when put <orig reg="together">to gether</orig> make $ one twenty five. I am told <orig reg="they">thay</orig> sold six hundred dollars worth that day &amp; night, &mdash; the most <orig reg="extravagant">extravegant</orig> prices you ever heard of &mdash;</p><p>We had a <orig reg="volunteer">volenteer</orig> company to leave our town last <orig reg="week">weeak</orig> for the <orig reg="Cherokee">Cheerakee</orig> nation, what for I cant <orig reg="imagine">immagin</orig>, for <orig reg="they">thay</orig> will have nothing to do, and its very probable <orig reg="they">thay</orig> will be discharged in a few days after <orig reg="they">thay</orig> get <orig reg="there">thare</orig>, the <orig reg="Indians">Indeans</orig> say that the whites have them in <orig reg="their">there</orig> power, and <orig reg="they">thay</orig> dont intend to raise a tomahawk against them but, <orig reg="they">thay</orig> will loose the <orig reg="last">lass</orig> drop of blood <pb n="[2]"/> before <orig reg="they">thay</orig> will leave their native country <orig reg="where">whare</orig> <orig reg="they">thay</orig> were borne, cradled, and grew up to man hood. the <orig reg="fact">facked</orig> of  the business <add place="supralinear">is</add> <orig reg="they">thay</orig> have been treated like <del type="overstrike">ace</del> a <unclear>parsel of avesias</unclear> poor souls its a pity but <orig reg="they">thay</orig> were all dead. for <orig reg="they">thay</orig> will be butchered, cut to <orig reg="pieces">peaces</orig>, and  harassed to death as long as there is a drop of Indian blood in <orig reg="existence">existance</orig>, you will excuse me for <orig reg="dwelling">dweling</orig> on this subject so long.</p><p>There is a singing school in this <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood</orig> &mdash; I expect to attend frequently. I dont expect to as much at singing my self, I shall <orig reg="merely">mearly</orig> go as a looker on, to take a <orig reg="peak">peap</orig> at the Girls every now and then, there is one young Lady who will attend that would carry me <orig reg="there">thare</orig>, if there were no more to go, to tell the <orig reg="fact">fack</orig> about the business she is the only girl in this <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood</orig> that is fit to keep fashionable <orig reg="society">sosiety</orig>. and she is nothing to bray of, if she fool, with me much, I, a-court her a little just to see how she will take it, our teacher is a <name type="person">Mr <orig reg="Johnson">Johson</orig></name> <orig reg="formally">formely</orig> of <unclear>sumner</unclear>, its very probable you may know something about the man, he acknowledges acquaintance with me, but I <orig reg="know">no</orig> nothing about the fellow I <orig reg="received">recieved</orig> a letter from <name type="person">Jon</name> to day, he informed me that <name type="person">Bill Lock</name>, would be married on the next day to his dearly beloved <name type="person">Miss Rickman</name>, he will cut a dash with a wife dont you think so Doctor &mdash; <pb n="[3]"/></p><p>Jon named in his letter that Mother&amp; <name type="person">Aunt Polly</name> would not go down to <name type="place">Franklin</name> <orig reg="until">untill</orig> the last of the summer, and <orig reg="they">thay</orig> did not want myself and <name type="person">Ben</name> to go down <orig reg="until">untill</orig> <orig reg="they">thay</orig> went tell her that we will not go down <orig reg="until">utill</orig> she will go &mdash; myself &amp; the <abbr expan="Major">Maj</abbr> will pay you a visit about the last of this month or the first of next if nothing should happen &mdash; Jon wished to know whether I had received a letter from the Judge, tell him I have not as yet. &mdash;</p><p>Crops are generally good <unclear>over corn</unclear>  come up well <sic>that, that</sic> was planted late, those who planted early had to plough up and replant over, <gap reason="document torn"/> look, badly, it came up well, but it has <gap reason="document torn"/> had several frosts on it, and the could <unclear>deas</unclear> <gap reason="hole in document"/> it look very yellow &mdash; there will be but little fruit over <orig reg="here">hear</orig> this year. &mdash; I will now bring my letter to a close, Give my love to Mother &mdash; <name type="person">Pat</name> &amp; Jon. &mdash; to the <abbr expan="Doctor">Dr</abbr> &mdash; &amp; <name type="person">Cousin Mary</name> &mdash; my <orig reg="respects">repects</orig> to <name type="person">R. Blithe</name>. <name type="person">Bob Anderson</name>, and <orig reg="accept">except</orig> the love and best wishes of a sincere friend &mdash;</p><closer><salute>Yours truly &mdash;</salute><signed><name type="person"><emph>N B. Hamilton</emph></name></signed><address><addrLine>To <abbr expan="James">J</abbr> L Alexander</addrLine></address><add place="below address"><abbr expan="Post Script">P. S.</abbr> you will write to me when you <orig reg="receive">recieve</orig> this and give me all the <orig reg="news">newse</orig> in the country <lb/> <emph>N. B. <abbr expan="Hamilton">Ham.</abbr></emph></add> <pb n="[4]"/> <add place="above address"><figure><figDesc>post mark for May 16</figDesc></figure> 10</add><address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Doctor">Dr.</abbr> James L. Alexander</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><orig reg="Hartsville">Hartsvill</orig></name></addrLine><addrLine>&lcub; <emph>Tennessee</emph></addrLine></address> <add place="left of address"><emph>Mail</emph></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
