<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl074"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1838 Nov. 22, Dixons Spring, TN [to] J[ames] L. Alexander, Lexington, KY /     Unknown : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Unknown</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl074</idno><idno>OCLC: 50133413</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1838 Nov. 22, Dixons Spring, J[ames] L. Alexander, Lexington, KY /     Unknown</title><author>Unknown</author><date value="1838-11-22">November 22, 1838</date><extent> 3p</extent><note type="summary"> This is a letter dated November 22 1838, whose author is unclear, addressed to James L. Alexander.  The author discusses  what has been going on in his or her life while Anderson has been in school.</note><note type="collection">Alexander Papers Correspondence</note><note type="box">VI-G-2</note><note type="folder">2</note><note type="document">sl074</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Dixons Springs</name> <date value="1838-11-22"><abbr expan="November">Nov</abbr> 22st 1838</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear <name type="person">James</name></salute></opener><p>I <abbr expan="Received">Rcd</abbr> your Letter of the <date value="0000-11-08">8th <abbr expan="November">Nov</abbr></date> I am glad to hear you are pleased with your <orig reg="Boarding">Bourding</orig> and the prospects of the school &mdash; there is no particular change since you Left &mdash; <name type="person"><unclear>Philpo</unclear></name> &amp;<name type="person"> Cosby </name>  am going to Leave here shortly for <name type="place">Texas</name>&mdash; They find they cannot do any thing at this place&mdash; we have not <abbr expan="Received">Rcd&mdash;</abbr> our goods yet we <del type="overstrike">have</del> heard from <add place="supralinear">them</add> at <name type="place">Pittsburgh</name> <date value="0000-10-23">23th of  <abbr expan="October">Oct</abbr></date> we expect them in a few days &mdash; one of us will go on in the spring and buy a large stock   If you want any thing brought on you must Let me know &mdash; we will go on in <abbr expan="February">Feb&mdash;</abbr> I have just Returned from <name type="place">Dekalb County</name>  I saw <name type="person">Dick Blythe</name> at <name type="place">Alexandria</name> &mdash; he Tells me he is doing very well &mdash; <name type="person">Archy</name>has backed out from commerce &mdash; the society was not as much refined as he would wish &mdash; I heard in alexandria he had only one patient he visited him six times and charged him 80 <abbr expan="Dollars">Dols</abbr>&mdash; I have Picked out a <unclear>palace</unclear> for you and <add place="supralinear">Tan</add> If do not go to <name type="place">Mississippi</name> one in <name type="place">Lancaster</name> the other in<name type="place"> Liberty</name>&mdash; it has been very sickly in lancaster this summer I was Told a doctor could have made a  small fortune at that place this <orig reg="summer">sumer</orig> <pb n="[2]"/> Tell <name type="person">Tan</name> I saw <name type="person">Nep</name> since he left she inquired <add place="supralinear">very   </add> particular about him &mdash; I expect to see <add place="supralinear">her</add> in a few days he must write me let know what to say to her for him &mdash; Dick Blyth sends his respects to you and Tan you must write frequently, Tell Tan he must To me Let me know <add place="supralinear">how</add> he likes<name type="place"> Lexington</name>  &mdash; give my Respects to old <name type="person">Ben</name> &amp; <name type="person">Miss wells</name> &mdash; </p><closer><salute>yours <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;&amp;c</abbr></salute><signed><unclear>RP</unclear></signed><pb n="[3]"/><address><addrLine><name type="place">Dixons Spring <abbr expan="Tennessee"> Tn</abbr></name>Pay 18&frac34;</addrLine><addrLine><abbr expan="November">Nov</abbr> 22</addrLine><addrLine><name type="person">Mr <abbr expan="James"> J.</abbr> L. Alexander</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Lexington</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Kentucky">Ky</abbr></name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
