<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl098"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1838 Sep. 4, Oke [i.e., Oak] Grove [to] James Paine / J[ohn] W. Williams : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Williams, J. W.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl098</idno><idno>OCLC: 50488339</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1838 Sep. 4, Oke [i.e., Oak] Grove [to] James Paine / J[ohn] W. Williams</title><author>Williams, J. W.</author><date value="1838-09-04">September 4, 1838</date><extent> 4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written by J. W. Williams to James Paine on September 4, 1838. In the letter, Williams tells Paine that he has won a Senate seat and that there is a small Whig majority in the Senate for the first time. He also mentions a drought that has destroyed most of the corn crop he farms, as well as the tobacco plants. He concludes the letter by asking Paine to either manage or sell some of the land he owns to make up for the money he will lose from the destruction of his crops.</note><note type="collection">Abernathy Papers</note><note type="box">II-H-3</note><note type="folder">14</note><note type="document">sl098</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</item><item>Crops, Effect of drought on</item><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place"><orig reg="Oak">Oke</orig> Grove</name> <date value="1838-09-04">September 4 1838</date></addrLine></address><salute>My Dear friend</salute></opener><p>It has been Some time Since I have had <orig reg="the pleasure">thay plashure</orig> of hearing from you and your <orig reg="family">famealy</orig> I hope you are all doing Well and Enjoying good health</p><p>I have <orig reg="Just">Jest</orig> got through with a long and Warm <orig reg="Campaign">Campain</orig> With my friend <name type="person">John Barnett</name> for a Seat in the next <orig reg="Legislature">Leagislator</orig> in the house of Senate I was <orig reg="Only">Onlay</orig> Able to beat him 13 Votes <orig reg="he">hea</orig> has been <orig reg="Sheriff">Shearif</orig> 14 Years and <unclear>belionearing</unclear> <orig reg="the whole">thay hold</orig>  time <orig reg="for promotion The Whig">fer per motion Thay Whigh</orig> has a Small <orig reg="Majority">Majorty</orig> in the next le <orig reg="legislature">leagislator</orig> for the first time. <orig reg="We">Wea</orig> are all <orig reg="much alarmed">mutch allarmed</orig> in this <orig reg="country">Cuntreay</orig> With <orig reg="our Crops the drought">hour Cropts thay drouth</orig> has continued So long that <orig reg="We">Wea</orig> think <orig reg="We">Wea</orig> can not make Bread Among us <orig reg="Much More">Mutch Moore</orig> to fatten <orig reg="our">hour</orig> meat <orig reg="the">thay</orig> fodder is burnt up to the <orig reg="Tassel">Tasel</orig> Among one half of our Corn and We have Just Commenced <orig reg="pulling hour">puling hour</orig> <unclear>fods</unclear> that is left We have had no rain to do <orig reg="Any">Anny</orig> good Since I <orig reg="laid">lad</orig> my Corn by and that is a <orig reg="General">Geannearal</orig> thing So far as I am Able to hear from <orig reg="the">thay</orig> is Some <unclear>batte</unclear> old Corn to Sell at <orig reg="one dollar per">ome doller p~</orig> Bushel and <orig reg="they">thay</orig> Wont Sell but a Turn to no one <orig reg="person">peason</orig> at a time and <orig reg="We">Wea</orig> Shall Make No <orig reg="Tobacco">Tobaco</orig> for it is Yet Standing in the patch doing Nothing <pb n="[2]"/> So I cant <orig reg="See">Sea</orig> How <orig reg="we">wea</orig> are to get a long <orig reg="the">theay</orig> next year I have been trying and all in Vain to get a power of <orig reg="attorney">atturneay</orig> for you to Sell or manage <orig reg="the">theay</orig> lands in your <orig>Stat</orig> in Some Way I have now Come to the <orig reg="Conclusion">Conclution</orig> that to make a Wind of it would <orig reg="be">bea</orig> best to get and order of Court and Sell <orig reg="the">theay</orig> lands to to <orig reg="the">theay</orig> highest bidder and I want your advice on that Subject and inform me what way you think would be best to manage them you and my Self Could <orig reg="buy the">by thay</orig> land rather than let them go <orig reg="too">two</orig> low <orig reg="We">Wea</orig> then Would be Able to manage them as <orig reg="We">Wea</orig> might think best you will <orig reg="please">plase</orig> let me <orig reg="know">no</orig> how <orig reg="they">theay</orig> now stand and what is best to do with them I could Send you a <orig reg="tenant">tennant</orig> and have them settled if <orig reg="they">theay</orig> are not, <name type="person">William Jeffrey</name> and his <orig reg="family">famy</orig> is all in good health but <orig reg="poor">poore</orig> <name type="person">Mrs Jeffrey</name> is all Way Talking about and <orig reg="family She">famealy Shea</orig> wish is to move to Your Section of <orig reg="Country">Cuntreay</orig> but Mr Jeffry Will not hear of it <orig reg="they">theay</orig> both look old <name type="person"><abbr expan="Doctor">Doc</abbr> Williamson</name> and <name type="person">Minerva</name> when I last heard from them Was Well <orig reg="they">theay</orig> have only 2 <orig reg="Children">Childron</orig> A boy and A <orig reg="little">liatle</orig> Girl last Two</p><p>I have no <orig n="right">wright</orig> to Complain of health I am <orig reg="yet alone">yeat a lone</orig> and I think it <orig reg="doubtful">doutful</orig> if I Should <orig reg="be">bea</orig> Able to Change it I have met with a great <pb n="[3]"/> Negro <orig reg="family">famealy</orig> this Spring I have often <orig reg="thought">theought</orig> my lot was a bad one but I do <orig reg="know">no</orig> It Could be worse one and I am Content Give my respects to all the <orig reg="family">famealy</orig> and all inquiring friends and accept of them your self</p><closer><salute>I am Y.C.</salute><signed><name type="person">J. W. Williams</name></signed> <pb n="[4]"/> <address><addrLine>Brown's Store <name type="place"><abbr expan="North Carolina">N. C.</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1838-09-07">7th <abbr expan="September">Sept</abbr></date> &rcub;</addrLine></address><add place="above address">25</add><address><addrLine><name type="person">James Paine</name> <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Giles County</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><orig reg="Pulaski">Pulaskie</orig></name></addrLine></address><add place="below address">from <abbr expan="John">Jno.</abbr> W. Williams <lb/> about Selling land</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
