<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl094"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>    [Letter] 1835 Dec. 29, Greenville College, E[ast] Ten[nessee] [to] Thomas Abernathy, Elkton Giles County, West Tennessee / M. S. Temple  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Temple, M. S.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl094</idno><idno>OCLC: 50179135</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>        [Letter] 1835 Dec. 29, Greenville College, E[ast] Ten[nessee] [to] Thomas Abernathy, Elkton Giles County, West Tennessee</title><author>Temple, M. S.</author><date value="1835-12-29">December 29, 1835</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary"> This is a letter dated December 29, 1835 from M.S. Temple to Thomas E. Abernathy.  Temple writes that his mother has gotten married unexpectedly.  He writes about how much the local people want the railroads to come through East TN.  He also tells  Abernathy not to sell the land that he is managing for the Temple family in Giles County yet.</note><note type="collection">Abernathy Papers</note><note type="box">II-H-3</note><note type="folder">F 13</note><note type="document">sl094</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine> &rcub;<name type="place">Greenville,, College,,</name>  <name type="place"><abbr expan="East Tennessee">E,, Ten</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1835-12-29">29th,, <abbr expan="December"> Dec,,r</abbr>,, 1835</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener> <p>  Owing to my not <orig reg="getting">geting</orig> <add place="supralinear">home</add> as soon as I <orig reg="anticipated">antisipated</orig> when I left your <orig reg="house">hous</orig> I have not had an opportunity of writing you a full and <orig reg="satisfactory">satisfactorily</orig>  letter until the <orig reg="present">preasent</orig> moment <orig reg="when">Whin</orig> I got home to Contrary to my expectations I found that my Mother was <orig reg="married">maried</orig> She <orig reg="married">maried</orig> a man by the name of<name type="person">      H,, A,, Farnsworth</name>  he was a widower but has no<del type="erasure">t</del> children <unclear>said hi</unclear> first wife was a widow with <unclear>3</unclear> sons I think he was as good to his step children as almost any man and I hope by the assistance of him who views all creation with an eye of circumspection that we may <add place="supralinear">be</add> <orig reg="enabled">en abled</orig> to go on and perform the task assigned us with <orig reg="cheerfulness">cherefullness</orig>. As to the selling of the Land you have in your care  I am instructed to say that if can not be disposed of at this time as I thought it could probably be when I was at your house I know it would be better for to sell the Land. but under existing circumstances <del type="overstrike">but</del> some of the heirs think it would be <orig reg="advisable">adviseable</orig> to defer the sale&mdash;. you will therefore in your judgement rent it out to the best advantage and make the  most out of the Timber you can, as you have heretofore done &mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;</p><p>I some days ago went to the woods and got you and <name type="person"><unclear>Mr Manessee</unclear></name> some rattle Root which I have now drying and will send it on by <del type="overstrike">at</del> the <orig reg="first">firs</orig> opportunity which from the &mdash; <orig reg="present">preasent</orig> appearance of the weather will not be long  we have in <name type="place"><abbr expan="East Tennessee">E T </abbr></name>at this time <orig reg="almost">allmost</orig> uniform good health a  blessing much to be desired and <del type="overstrike">and</del> I hope will still be continued. The people here are <orig reg="almost">allmost</orig> a going crazy with regard to the  subject of Rail Roads which if <orig reg="carried">caried</orig> into <orig reg="operation">opperation</orig> <pb n="[2]"/> I have no doubt but it will be of great public utility the <name type="place">Charleston</name>and <name type="place"><orig reg="Cincinnati">Cincinatie</orig></name>Rail Road and also the <name type="place">Nashville</name> and <name type="place">Petersburg</name> Rail Roads   are to pass through in this part of    <abbr expan="East Tennessee">E T</abbr> and intersect some where near this if the public does go forward and complete the above contemplated Roads we will <orig reg="almost">allmost</orig> be thrown as it <orig reg="were">wore</orig> in the <orig reg="center">centre</orig> of Market I have nothing <orig reg="more">moore</orig> of importance to write you at <orig reg="present">preasant</orig><name reg="please"> pleas</name> give my respects to your family and also to<name type="person"> Mr. Moors</name> and his family and all enquiring friends and be <orig reg="assured">asured</orig> I am with sentiments of true regard</p><closer><salute>yours Respectfully</salute><signed><emph><name type="person">M,, S,, Temple</name></emph></signed><address><addrLine>To,, <name type="person"> Thos,, Abernathy <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr </abbr></name>&rcub;</addrLine></address> <add><abbr expan="Nota Bene">N B</abbr> If any of the young Ladies should want to know how I am coming on Tell them to <orig reg="address">adres</orig> a few Lines to me and I will be quite apt to Respond to them in full&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;&mdash;</add><pb n="[3]"/><address><addrLine><name type="place">Greenville College<unclear> L</unclear></name>  </addrLine><addrLine><date value="1836-01-01">January 1st 1836</date> &rcub;</addrLine></address><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mr,, Thos,, E,, Abernathy</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Elkton</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Giles County</name> </addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">West Tennessee</name></addrLine></address><add place="lower left corner">Mail &rcub;</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
