<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl107"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title> [Letter] August 17, Cornplanter, [PA] [to]  Mr. William B. Bell, near Charlotte, Tenne[ssee] / J[ane] Bell   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Bell, Jane</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl107</idno><idno>OCLC: 50489516</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title> [Letter] August 17, Cornplanter, [PA] [to]  Mr. William B. Bell, near Charlotte, Tenne[ssee] / J[ane] Bell</title><author>Bell, Jane</author><date value="1840-08-17">August 17, 1840</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Jane Bell to her brother William dated August 17, probably 1840.  Jane offers the good news that, contrary to previous worries, she is still alive and well.  She also writes that millwrights have been in town and that they will be leaving soon. She regrets that she has not seen all their work as apparently it is as entertaining as a stage  show. She writes that she is expecting visits from many family members and that it would be nice if someone from TN came also. She wants William to write her weekly. </note><note type="collection">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">1</note><note type="document">sl107</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Millwrights</item><item>Pennsylvania</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Cornplanter </name><date><abbr expan="August">Augst</abbr> 17th</date></addrLine></address><salute>My dear <name type="person"><abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr></name></salute></opener><p>You will <add place="supralinear">be</add> pleased to hear  that the  <date value="0000-08-12">12th</date> is past, and I am alive and well. I had no fear on the subject, nor any  presentiment, and therefore do not feel as grateful as I should do for my lengthened days. We are all as well as when you were here &mdash; The millwrights leave us tomorrow and I have not had time to see all the machinery in motion, though I heard <name type="person">Mrs. Young</name> say last week, that  persons often went <gap reason="document damaged"/> distance to see a show, that was not as well worth seeing as the machinery in the mill. She also says you look a wholesome youth, for the people here do not think you are of age <pb n="[2]"/>  On Friday last, <name type="person">Wylie</name> went to <name type="place">Franklin</name>, and did not have a letter from you, to any of the family. I was so certain of receiving one, that I was not prepared for such a disappoint<add place="supralinear">ment</add> consequently I had an attack of <unclear>degestion</unclear>,  from which a good hearty cry relieved me. You should never let me suffer any anxiety respecting you or our sisters, for when you are silent, my active imagination construct it into sickness or death. I sometimes wish I did not think so much about you all, and again I would not for any consideration   relinquish the pleasure which <sic corr="the">the the</sic> remembrance of you all create. We are expecting a sister of <name type="person"><abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr> Marsh</name>  <gap reason="document damaged" desc="here next"/> month on a visit and in <date value="0000-10-03">October 3</date> of the <name type="people">Bell</name> family from <name type="place">Pittsburgh</name> so that we shall have  kinsfolk in abundance and if we had a <name type="place">Tennessee</name> Bell,  I for one would be content.</p><pb n="[3]"/><p><name type="person"><abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> G. Bell</name> was here last week. <name type="place">Horses creek</name> furnace is in blast &mdash; We have a carpenter at work who will most likely be at work on <unclear>our  non</unclear> fence this week. The geraniums are just living, I look at them often in a day they being in my way to the cellar the  whortle berries are not yet out of season, a fresh supply today. I suppose you will conclude from the length of this epistle I have very little to <gap reason="document damaged"/> but you are much mistaken <gap reason="document damaged"/>  for I am almost tired to death after the labors of the day <name type="person">Margaret</name> having been in the wash house all the day.  You can scarcely imagine the destruction that was made in the cucumbers, onions, potatoes  <gap reason="document damaged" desc="and"/>  beets in the boarding roo<gap reason="document damaged"/> All the young folks are <gap reason="document damaged"/> if they were up they would <gap reason="document damaged"/> say give my love to cousin <abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr>   Give an abundance of affection to the sisterhood for me for me. Write every week whether it rains or not &mdash;  remember that <add place="left margin">Old Mas<gap reason="document damaged"/> is selling <unclear>wishing</unclear> at the opposite side of the table. say <gap reason="document damaged"/> he can but the <unclear>wishing</unclear> which of course you do not doubt</add></p> <pb n="[4]"/> <bibl><address><addrLine>Free &rcub;   <name type="person"><abbr expan="Jane">J</abbr> Bell</name> <unclear><abbr expan="Post Master">P. M.</abbr></unclear></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Cornplanter </name><date value="0000-08-17">17 Aug</date></addrLine><addrLine><name type="person">Mr William B. Bell</name></addrLine><addrLine>Near <name type="place">Charlotte</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenne</abbr></name></addrLine></address></bibl></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
