<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl111"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>   [Letter] 1821 May 24, Wheeling, Virginia [to]  Miss Anne Jane Bell, near Nashville, Tenn[ess]ee / John Bell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Bell, John</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl111</idno><idno>OCLC: 50499536</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>   [Letter] 1821 May 24, Wheeling, Virginia [to]  Miss Anne Jane Bell, near Nashville, Tenn[ess]ee / John Bell</title><author>Bell, John</author><date value="1821-05-24">May 24, 1821</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">The following document is a letter dated May 24, 1821, from Dr. John Bell to his sister Anne Jane Bell in Tennessee.  John writes the letter to inform his family that he will soon be embarking on a journey to Nashville to visit them.  He also discusses the other places and people he has visited and plans to visit.</note><note type="collection">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">5</note><note type="document">sl111</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Travel</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Wheeling, Virginia</name> <date value="1821-05-24">May 24th 1821</date></addrLine></address><salute>My Dear Sister</salute></opener><p>I may perhaps incur your censure for not having written you before this but I wished to be <unclear>enabled</unclear> to say something specific respecting the probability of my <del type="overstrike">now</del> seeing you &mdash; My last was in the beginning of April from <name type="place">Richmond</name> in which I assured you that no exertion should be wanting on my part for me to visit you this summer and it is now with feelings of peculiar pleasure that I inform you there is no existing impediment against my now doing so So fearful was I of disappointment &amp; of nurturing hopes in you which might not be realized that I have delayed until the present time mentioning my departure from <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> for the west.  I am now actually on my way out to <name type="place">Nashville</name>,  having left Philadelphia on the <date value="1821-05-09">9th</date>. <abbr expan="Instant">Inst.</abbr> At <name type="place">Pittsburgh</name> I spent a few days as well for rest as a to redeem a promise long ago made, &mdash; with <name type="person">Mr. &amp; Mrs. Barlow</name> &mdash; the latter is sister of the young lady in <name type="place">Paris</name> of whom you may remember I spoke more than once in terms of admiration &amp; esteem</p> <pb n="[2]"/>  <p>The kindness of  <name type="person">Mrs. <abbr expan="Barlow">B</abbr></name> &amp; her husband made my time pass more agreeably than I could have hoped for in a place so unpleasant as <name type="place">Pittsburgh</name> generally is to strangers</p><p>The route which I take is circuitous but I shall justify myself better in the eyes of others for the unavoidable <orig reg="expenses">expences</orig> of my journey by uniting  instruction with duty &amp; pleasure &mdash; At <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> I had some persons to see &amp; wished to obtain letters of introduction from there, &amp; at this place which is on the <name type="place">Ohio River</name> about 53 miles <abbr expan="Southwest">S.W.</abbr> of <name type="place">Pittsburgh</name> I joined my old friend <name type="person">Frazier</name> who is now settled here in business &amp; at whose house I stay &mdash; He will join me in <name type="place">Cincinnati</name> &amp; thence we prosecute our course together by way of <name type="place">Lexington</name> , <name type="place">Frankfort</name> &amp; <name type="place">Louisville, Kentucky</name> &amp; <emph>perhaps diverge as far as <name type="place">St. Louis</name></emph>. &mdash; I should wish to keep company with <name type="person">Mr. <abbr expan="Frazier">F</abbr></name> &amp; must as much as possible be regulated by his movements, &mdash; hence a month or more may possibly elapse  before I have the inexpressible pleasure of once more seeing you &amp; my dear Father &amp; family. &mdash; I mention this to prevent any uneasiness &amp; also any undue anticipation of the period of my arrival. &mdash;</p><p> My Uncle is exceedingly impatient for my return to <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> &amp; to see me finally settled <pb n="[3]"/> therefore my Dear <name type="person">Anne Jane</name> make up your mind for my visit's being very short  perhaps not more than a fortnight Thankful for the opportunity now offered, let us not repine We are not the only ones whom fate decrees to <orig reg="separate">seperate</orig> when affections would <orig reg="forever">for ever</orig> keep us united.</p><p>I <unclear></unclear> to enter into any details  about My Uncle &amp; <name type="place">Richmond</name> friends reserving <gap reason="document damaged"/> communications &mdash; I saw <name type="person">Eliza Bell</name> twice during the  few days I was in <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> last &amp; am bearer of a long letter from her to you &mdash; I saw when in<name type="place"> Richmond</name><name type="person">Helly Barlow</name> &amp; her brother <name type="person">Richard</name>  who had come down to take her up to <name type="place">Frederick</name> &mdash; As I did not go beyond <name type="place">Richmond</name> I did not see <name type="person">Mrs. Grammer</name> It must not from this be <orig reg="inferred">infered</orig> that I do not still entertain a great regard for her but somehow or another I did not find it convenient to go over to <name type="place">Petersburgh</name> one of my antipathies you know. &mdash;</p><p>With best love to my dear Father, Mother &amp; sisters Believe me &mdash;</p><closer><salute>Your ever affectionate Brother</salute><signed><name type="person">John Bell</name> &mdash;</signed> <pb n="[4]"/> <add place="above address"><figure><figDesc>postmark stamp</figDesc></figure> 25</add> <address><addrLine><name type="person">Miss Anne Jane Bell</name></addrLine><addrLine>Care <name type="person">Mr. Walter Bell</name></addrLine><addrLine>Near <name type="place">Nashville</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tennee.</abbr></name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
