<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl118"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>   [Letter] 1839 Nov. 3, Clover Dale, [TN] [to] Mrs. A[nne] Jane Bell, Cornplanter, PA /   M[argaret] V. Bell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Bell, Margaret</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl118</idno><idno>OCLC: 50504472</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>   [Letter] 1839 Nov. 3, Clover Dale, [TN] [to] Mrs. A[nne] Jane Bell, Cornplanter, PA /   M[argaret] V. Bell</title><author>Bell, Margaret</author><date value="1839-11-03">November 3, 1839</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">The following document is a letter written by Margaret Bell in Clover Dale, TN to her sister Anne Jane Bell in Cornplanter, PA.  Margaret began the letter on November 3, 1839, and she last wrote in it on November 15.  The letter primarily relates  the events happening in Cloverdale and the friends and family that have been visiting.</note><note type="collection">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">10</note><note type="document">sl118</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>Communication in the family</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Clover Dale</name>, Sunday Morning, <date value="1839-11-03"><abbr expan="November">Nov</abbr> 3 1839</date> <add place="supralinear"><unclear><?xm-replace_text {add}?></unclear></add></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Sister</salute></opener><p>It has fallen to my lot this morning to write, as <name type="person">William</name> has a very bad cold which makes <add place="supralinear">him</add> quite sick for some days; he has been very busy for 3 weeks gathering corn, and just finished yesterday evening.  he has not time to write through the week, and <orig reg="today">to day</orig> he feels <orig reg="too">to</orig> sick to do any thing but sit over the fire and drink hot tea and grunt, the corn crop has measured up very well considering the dry summer, though it did not quite realize our expectations, which you know always goes beyond the mark, The weather this fall has been very dry and warm, we have not had   frost enough yet to kill the tomatoes vines, the ground is so very dry and hard that brother cannot sow <unclear>wheat</unclear> <name type="person">Mr and Mrs Burgess</name>  are now on a  <orig reg="visit">visite</orig> to their children in this <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood</orig>.  they are living in <name type="place">Kentucky</name>, as they did not like <name type="place">Miss<add place="supralinear">o</add>uri</name>  <name type="person">Lotty</name>  was married in <name type="place"><unclear>Missouri</unclear></name> , <orig reg="traveling">Travling</orig> agrees with <orig reg="them">thim</orig> very well, <name type="person">Mrs <abbr expan="Burgess">B</abbr></name> is very flashy and looks younger than she did 10 years ago.  they have not called on us yet.  but they intend visiting  <pb n="[2]"/> all their old <orig reg="neighbors">neighbours</orig> before they return home.  <name type="person">William Napier</name>  is married to a lady in <name type="place">giles county</name>, he arrived at his Fathers last week with his wife, she is not very pretty, and is only 15, it is thought they will <add place="supralinear">live</add>  on <name type="place">yellows creek</name>, <name type="person">Mr Reynolds</name> has received 3 or 4 letters from his brother <name type="person">Mark</name>   and family they are all doing very well.  <name type="person">William Reynolds</name> is married, in his letter to his Uncle he said he thought before he was married all he wanted was a wife, but now he wants every thing else.</p><p><date value="1839-11-15"><sic corr="November">October</sic> the 15.</date> You will think it very strange that such a length of time should transpire, between the dates in my letter,  we have had so much company for the last week, that I have no had time to write, <name type="person">Mr and Mrs Hickman</name> and <name type="person">Rebecca</name> are now at the furnace on a visit of 3 or 4 weeks they arrived at the furnace <add place="supralinear">on</add> tuesday <orig reg="and">an</orig> called on us thursday evening, I returned home with them and stayed until sunday evening, <name type="person">Ellen</name> and   <name type="person">Rebecca</name> came home with me <add place="supralinear">and</add> stayed until wednesday <abbr expan="evening">eveng</abbr> as the gentleman were all at the forge. hunting for some days.  We are all very much pleased with <name type="person">Mr Hickman</name>, <name type="person">Ellen</name> is very gay and fashionable <name type="person">Rebecca</name> has grown very much, she is <orig reg="almost">all most</orig> as tall as her sister, she is going to <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> next spring, <name type="person"><unclear>Mrs V</unclear></name> and   <name type="person"><unclear>Mrs.</unclear> Lee</name> were here <unclear>yesterday</unclear> on a visit to <name type="person"><unclear>Mrs.</unclear> H</name>, We are all to meet at <pb n="[3]"/> <name type="person">Dr <unclear>Hudsons</unclear></name> , day after tomorrow, the <orig reg="gentlemen">gentelmen</orig> are all to amuse themselves hunting, Old <name type="person">Mrs Hickman</name> is still alive, she  is a 100 and 4 years old.</p><p>We have had a great deal of rain for a <orig reg="few">fiew</orig> days past, which is the first we have had since July, that was sufficient to <unclear>lay</unclear> the dust,</p><p>We are all well, and every thing is going on as usual, <name type="person"><abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr></name> sends his love to his niece and nephew They all join with me in love to you and family.</p> <closer><salute>Your sincere sister</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr type="Margaret">M</abbr> V Bell</name></signed> <pb n="[4]"/> <address><addrLine><name type="place">Charlotte <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tn</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1839-11-17"><abbr expan="November">Novr</abbr> 17 1839</date></addrLine></address> <add place="right of address">25</add> <address><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs <abbr expan="Ann">A</abbr> Jane Bell</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Cornplanter</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Venango County</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Pennsylvania">Pa</abbr></name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
