<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl117"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1839 May 12, Clover Dale, [TN] [to] Mrs. Ann Jane Bell, Cornplanter, Venango Co., PA / Margaret V. Bell    : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Bell, Margaret V. </author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl117</idno><idno>OCLC: 50504276</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1839 May 12, Clover Dale, [TN] [to] Mrs. Ann Jane Bell, Cornplanter, Venango Co., PA / Margaret V. Bell    </title><author>Bell, Margaret V.</author><date value="1838-05-12">May 12, 1839</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Margaret V. Bell to her sister Ann Jane Bell dated May 12, 1839. Margaret writes that their father is feeling much better and can walk around some. She writes of the farm and crops and flower gardening. Mr. Collier brought the family a large assortment of gifts. She writes that Jane's friend Allen has been elected second colonel.  </note><note type="collection">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">10</note><note type="document">sl117</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Clover Dale</name><date value="1839-05-12">May 12th 1839</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Sister</salute></opener><p>It is with pleasure <emph>I</emph> inform you that Father is much better than he was when <name type="person">Sally</name> wrote to you last, he is weak and feeble yet, though he is able to walk about the house and yard, he is not strong enough yet to walk to the brier field to see the young corn, which is very fine for this season of the year. though vegetation is much earlier than it ever was known to be in <name type="place">Dickson</name>, some of the pe<add place="supralinear">a</add>ches are now as large as a <unclear>g<add place="supralinear">u</add>inneau</unclear> egg, If you will visit us this fall, you will get some fine peaches off Mothers tree, Your friends are all very anxious to see you, The question is often asked us will she even <add place="supralinear">visit</add> you again. we are  anticipating the pleasure of seeing you and brother <name type="person">Sam</name> this fall you must let us know in time, so we can give the house a thorough cleaning and white washing which it has just undergone The garden is very pretty at this time, it is full of red and white roses, and some purple flowers which we <unclear>call</unclear> <gap reason="word left out"/> but I do not know whether they bloom <pb n="[2]"/> at this season of the year or not, the beets and beans will be ready to eat in a week or <gap reason="document damaged"/> The rose bush which we got from <name type="person">Squire Rouss<gap reason="document damaged"/></name> this spring has red roses on it instead of purple. I am not a little di<add place="supralinear">s</add>appointed, <name type="person">Squire Napier</name>has just left here after spending the day, <emph>which is sunday</emph>,  he inquired very particularly for you, and if  you had any family of your own, he offered his services to <orig reg="accompany">acompaney</orig> me to <name type="person">Mr. <emph><unclear>Baughlen</unclear></emph></name> to see his garden which is laid out in English style. <name type="person">Mr. Collier</name> has returned from the city with a <orig reg="splendid">splended</orig> assortment of goods, brother sent us several articles, a <orig reg="blue-black">blublack</orig> for <name type="person">Cary</name> a calico for Mother, and a painted <orig reg="jaconet">jacinet</orig> which I get, and 2 black veils a vest and coat pattern for <name type="person">Will</name>. <name type="person"><unclear>Aun</unclear> Winni Richersons</name> grand son in law <name type="person">Mr. Cane</name> <orig reg="died">dide</orig> very sudden last week, he was found dead in the field where he had been ploughing. <name type="person">Mr. Morris</name> is to preach <name type="person">Mr. Napiers</name> funeral next Sunday Your <name type="place"><orig reg="Pittsburgh">Pittsburg</orig></name> <unclear>atter</unclear> weaves very well, <name type="person">Cary</name> <unclear>brushwove</unclear> a piece of bed ticking which is the best we ever made, <name type="person">Cousin Susan</name> is now on a visit at <name type="person">Mr. Mills</name>, <name type="person">Mrs. Roberts</name> came up with her, she spent a day with us, we like her almost as well as her husband, Your particular friend <name type="person">Allen</name> is elected  second colonel, he must be <pb n="[3]"/> very popular, when <add place="supralinear">a</add> man of his principles, can be elected in this county,  you know he does not treat. <name type="person">Sally</name> and <name type="person">Will</name> is going to <name type="place">Charlotte</name> to day. I <orig reg="have">hav</orig> not time to finish my letter as they are in a hurry, we have two sick <unclear>bushes</unclear> one will <orig reg="either">eather</orig> die or get well in a week, the other is convalescent. we are all well, </p> <closer><salute>Your affectionate sister</salute> <signed><name><abbr expan="Margaret">M.</abbr> V. Bell</name>.</signed> <pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine><name type="place">Charlotte <abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></name> </addrLine><addrLine><date value="1839-05-15">May 15th 1839</date> <add place="right of return address">&rcub;</add> <add place="right of address">25</add></addrLine><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs. Ann  Jane Bell</name>.</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Cornplanter</name>.</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Venango County</name>.</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Pennsylvania">Pa</abbr></name>.</addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
