<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl125"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>   [Letter] 1847 Sep. 12, Clover Dale, [TN] [to] Mrs. Ann Jane Bell, Charlotte, Dickson Co[unty], Tenn[essee] / Sally [Bell] : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Bell, Sally</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl125</idno><idno>OCLC: 50512993</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>   [Letter] 1847 Sep. 12, Clover Dale, [TN] [to] Mrs. Ann Jane Bell, Charlotte, Dickson Co[unty], Tenn[essee] / Sally [Bell] </title><author>Bell, Sally</author><date value="1847-09-12">September 12, 1847</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated September 12, 1847, from Sally Bell to her sister Ann Jane Bell in Dickson County, TN.  Sally discusses their financial situation and expresses thanks for the money both Ann Jane and their brother William has sent to her.  She also reports that another William Bell had intended to become the clerk on a ship.  Finally, she writes that a crowd of people had cheered on a company of Volunteers in town that day.</note><note type="collection">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">11</note><note type="document">sl125</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>Finance, Personal</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Clover Dale</name> <date value="1847-09-12">Sep 12th 1847</date></addrLine></address><salute>My dear Sister</salute></opener><p>I received your letter two days since, I went <orig reg="immediately">immeadantly</orig> to the stores in search of the forting, I could not get any as wide as you wished it, I got it so cheap I thought I would get 2 borders and if it did think the two would last as long as one, I also send you a <orig reg="piece">peice</orig> of <unclear>bobinett</unclear> I had in the house I received the inclosed $10 in your letter, and also a few lines from <name type="person">Will</name> the week before inclosing 10 for which I am very thankful, if Will could spare us a little more we would like it <name type="person">William</name>  had <orig reg="engaged">ingaged</orig> to be <orig reg="clerk">clerck</orig> on a boat at 50 dollars a month but when they got to <name type="place"><orig reg="Cincinnati">Cincinnatta</orig></name> the Captain wife was sick, and he gave up the boat <orig reg="until">untill</orig> the last of this month, he has the <orig reg="promise">promis</orig> of the same situation if he can meet the boat at <name type="place">St Louis</name>, which he is anxious to do,  he was only sick a week after  his return, but last week the chills came back on him, they are slight but considerable fewer afterwards, he has them every other evening and quite well the next day. he <pb n="[2]"/> is to have some pills which I hope will stop them soon, he has been very temperate in his eating and drinking for some month back for fear he would be sick this fall.</p><p>there was a great <orig reg="crowd">croud</orig> in this place <orig reg="today">to day</orig> <unclear>marching</unclear> up a company of volunteers, I have been <orig reg="very">verry</orig> busy sewing for  <abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> he was nearly out of clothes, I did not finish  <orig reg="hemming until">heming untill</orig> late this evening, and as I wish to send this by mornings mail I cannot write any more, till <name type="person">Cary</name> I think I wrote <del type="overstrike">for</del> last, did your <unclear>rose</unclear> moss seed grow if it did not I can send you more, they say it will keep <orig reg="through">threw</orig> the winter if <orig reg="kept">keept</orig> in the house, Will joins me in love to you all write soon,</p> <closer><salute>your affectionate Sister</salute><signed><name type="person">Sally</name></signed><pb n="[3]"/> <address><addrLine><name type="place">Eddyville <abbr expan="Kentucky">Ky</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="0000-09-12"><abbr expan="September">Sept</abbr> 12th</date></addrLine></address><add place="right of address">&rcub;</add><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs. Ann Jane Bell</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Charlotte</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Dickson <abbr expan="County">Co</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name></addrLine></address><add place="left of address">Receipt for $20&mdash;00</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
