<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl136">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[Letter] 1813 Dec. 7, Baxter Grove / Willie Blount : a machine readable
                    transcription of an image</title>
                <author>Blount, Willie</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
                    <name>Debra Roney</name>
                    <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
                    <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
                <address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address>
                <date>2002</date>
                <idno>sl136</idno>
                <idno>OCLC: 50548262</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives,
                        Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching,
                        and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in
                        the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
                        Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
                        741-2764.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl><title>[Letter] 1813 Dec. 7, Baxter Grove / Willie Blount
                        </title><author>Blount, Willie </author><date value="1813-12-07">December 7,
                        1813</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from
                        Governor Willie Blount dated December 7, 1813 to an unknown military
                        commander. He is explaining that he does not know how long the term of
                        service for a local detachment of men is supposed to be. He also regrets the
                        lack of supplies for the soldiers. Much of the letter discusses the
                        movements of Creek, Choctaw, and Chickasaw forces; and of various US
                        military generals and colonels.</note><note type="collection">John Cocke
                        Papers V-J-3</note><note type="box">n/a</note><note type="folder"
                        >F:8</note><note type="document">sl136</note></bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
                <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1
                    spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
                <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
                <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward
                    which a reference or figure points.</p>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                        <item>Military supplies</item>
                        <item>Military planning</item>
                        <item>Cherokee Indians</item>
                        <item>Creek Indians -- Wars</item>
                        <item>Choctaw Indians</item>
                        <item>Southern States</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div1 type="letter">
                <pb n="[1]"/>
                <opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Baxter Grove</name>. <date value="1813-12-07"><abbr expan="December">Dec.</abbr> 7th 1813</date>.</addrLine></address><salute>Dear
                        Sir;</salute></opener>
                <p>I have just <abbr expan="received">rec'd</abbr> yours of the 3rd <abbr
                        expan="Instant">Inst.</abbr> &amp; now acknowledge the receipt of one of a
                    prior date respecting the term of service of the detached Militia, &amp; again
                    inform you that I answered, by <name type="person"><abbr expan="Major"
                            >Majr.</abbr> Scarcy</name> , before I left <name type="place"
                        >Nashville</name> yours respecting the term of service of the volunteers,
                    which I presume you have <abbr expan="received">rec'd</abbr> before this: as
                    also <name type="person"><abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr> Scarcy</name>on the
                    subject of <name type="person">Mr Hickman</name>'s become sutler to your Army,
                    who was to have left <name type="place">Nashville</name> with
                        <unclear>shoes</unclear> ten days ago. &mdash; were I beyond a doubt <abbr
                        expan="satisfied">satisfy'd</abbr> that on the 10th <abbr expan="Instant"
                        >Inst.</abbr> the volunteers term of service was actually to expire, I have
                    not the authority to order their discharge or to supply their places &mdash;
                    These two points rest <orig reg="solely">soley</orig> with the President to do
                    or order to be done; hence I could not take upon myself such responsibility. I
                    have however as before advised, informed him of the wish &amp; expectation of
                    the volunteers; &amp; asked him how their place were to be supplied in the event
                    they were to be <abbr expan="discharged">discharg'd</abbr>: but as yet I have
                    not <abbr expan="received">rec'd</abbr> his answer. I have no other instructions
                    relative to the term of service of the detached militia than the <abbr
                        expan="Secretary">Sec.</abbr> of wars letter more than a year ago, requiring
                    the 2500 to be detached for six months tour of duty. &mdash; his instructions to
                    call them into service for this campaign said nothing about the term <del
                        type="overstrike">of service</del> they were to serve, presuming, I suppose
                    that they were to serve <pb n="[2]"/> six months if necessary, unless sooner
                    discharged by order of the President &mdash; I shall try to be informed by the
                        <abbr expan="Secretary">Sec.</abbr> of war on this subject &amp; communicate
                    his answer to you &mdash; I have sundry times required of the <abbr
                        expan="Secretary">Sec.</abbr> of war that <name type="person"><abbr
                            expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Williams</name>' <abbr expan="Regiment"
                        >Reg't</abbr> should be ordered to <unclear>ask</unclear> against the <name
                        type="people">Creeks</name> &mdash; No answer yet &mdash; <name
                        type="person">Williams</name> is very anxious to be with you; but his <abbr
                        expan="Regiment">Reg't</abbr> are as yet neither armed nor <orig
                        reg="clothed">cloathed</orig> &mdash; he writes me that he would give all he
                    is worth to be with you &mdash; I have no authority or instructions from the war
                    Department to order aid of men expected of <name type="person"><abbr
                            expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> Carroll</name> to raise upon the present
                    emergency&mdash; but have done every thing in my power to do in an <orig
                        reg="unauthorized">unauthorised</orig> way to promote success of the
                    object.</p>
                <p>I have heard of two companies going or being ready to go from <name type="place"
                        >Robertson <abbr expan="County">Cty.</abbr></name>.&mdash; It is gratifying
                    to learn that <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> Cocke</name>
                    will join you on the 12th <abbr expan="Instant">Inst.</abbr> &amp; very much so
                    to learn that <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> White</name>
                    has given so good account of the <name type="person">Hillabee Indian</name>
                    towns &mdash; his men are brave &mdash; &amp; he is a warrior himself &mdash;
                    they will do their duty &mdash; If when you are ready the Enemy will do you the
                    favor to fight you at the Hickory grounds the contest will soon be over &mdash;
                    I don't expect that many of them will get off with whole bones. &mdash; I cannot
                    some how think that any of your Army would be willing to return home before the
                        <name type="person">Creeks</name> are <orig reg="whipped &amp; well whipped"
                        >whipt &amp; well whipt</orig> &mdash; <name type="person"><abbr
                            expan="General">Genl</abbr> Claiborne</name> writes me that his
                    volunteers &amp; detached militia, with <name type="person"><abbr
                            expan="Colonel">Colo</abbr> Russils</name>
                    <abbr expan="Regiment">Regt</abbr> of <abbr expan="United States">US</abbr>
                    infantry are on the Last of the <name type="place">Alabama</name>, some distance
                    in the Creek country for the purpose of cooperating with you &mdash; that he has
                    7 or 800 barrels of <del type="overstrike">flour</del>
                    <pb n="[3]"/> provisions on the way there for you &mdash; that it will be there
                    in a few days &mdash; that <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr>
                        Hourney</name> will do every thing in his power to aid you in forwarding
                    supplies from <name type="place">orleans</name>
                    <name type="person">McKee</name> writes me that 500 barrels of flour had been
                    sent up <del type="overstrike">the</del> to <name type="person">Claiborne</name>
                    camp from <name type="place">Mobile</name> for you, &amp; that he <gap
                        reason="document damaged "/> use all his diligence to have more sent on
                    without <gap reason="document damaged"/> for you from <name type="place"
                        >Mobile</name> &mdash; that the <name type="person">Chocktaws</name> have
                    marched against the <name type="person">Creeks</name> &mdash; that the <name
                        type="person">Chickasaws</name> will shortly do so &mdash; I hope you will
                    be supplied &amp; strong enough soon to do might on a broad <orig reg="seal"
                        >seale</orig> &mdash; You have a fine field for action &amp; I know you will
                    improve it to the best advantage &mdash; I dont hear a word from <name
                        type="person">McGee</name> about supplies, but believe he is busy furnishing
                        <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> Cocke</name>
                    <orig reg="until">untill</orig> he joins you, expecting probably that <name
                        type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Pope Ward</name> &amp; are
                    supplying you under <name type="person">Ward</name>s arrangement &mdash; but it
                    is strange he did not supply you before he heard <name type="person">Ward</name>
                    was coming on &mdash;</p>
                <p>Had you had supplies in due time ten thousand difficulties would have been
                    avoided &amp; more than ten thousand benefits would have resulted to the
                    service. I have never exerted myself more than I have done to get you supplied
                    &mdash; I never felt more zeal about the success of <sic corr="a">a a</sic>
                    campaign than about this &mdash; It is every thing to <name type="place"
                        >Tennessee</name>, &amp; surely every <name type="person">Tennessean</name>
                    thinks so &mdash; I hope the Volunteers would not leave you for the world</p>
                <closer><salute>yours Sincerely</salute><signed><emph><name type="person">Willie
                                Blount</name></emph></signed><add place="lower left corner">A true
                        copy <lb/> Attest <lb/>
                        <name type="person">E. Foster 3</name>
                    </add></closer>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
