<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl156"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1840 Jun. 6, Philade[lphia], [PA] [to] James A. Woods, Nashville, Tenn[essee] / Jane Theora [Woods]   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Woods, Jane Theora</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl156</idno><idno>OCLC: 50564336</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1840 Jun. 6, Philade[lphia], [PA] [to] James A. Woods, Nashville, Tenn[essee] / Jane Theora [Woods]</title><author>Woods, Jane Theora </author><date value="1840-06-06">June 6, 1840</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Jane Woods to her brother James Woods dated June 6, 1840. Jane writes about a  picnic she recently attended. She declares that Philadelphia is incorrectly named  "The City of Brotherly Love". She anticipates her family's visit and asks James to give her love to many people in Nashville.</note><note type="collection">Woods Family</note><note type="box">Foster-Handy</note><note type="document">sl156</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Philadelphia">Philade</abbr></name> <date value="1840-06-06">June 6th / 40</date></addrLine></address><salute>My dear Brother</salute></opener><p>Your kind epistle was received a week since but really have not had time to answer it, I <orig reg="believe">beleave</orig> it was Wednesday week that I received it, and did anticipate replying to it on the following Saturday, but was prevented from doing so, by fulfilling an <orig reg="invitation">invertation</orig> to a <orig reg="picnic">pick-nick</orig> party on the banks of the <name type="place">Wissihiccou</name> a beautiful creek about seven miles from the City. There was two Omnibus's full of girls, we started about eleven o'clock in the morning and arrived at our place of  rendezvous about half-past twelve, it is a very  <emph><orig reg="romantic">romantick</orig> spot</emph> . (if I may use the expression) we rambled about an hour or so, and then made <orig reg="preparations">preperations</orig> to crown our queen <name type="person">Miss Blight</name>, who is a very pretty girl, in the mean time the <emph>eatables</emph> come, just before we crowned the queen, we set the table (if I may so say) on some rough planks, but <emph>I</emph> would not have wished a better place, for the table, the fare was excellent we had <orig reg="viz">vis</orig>, Ham, Rolls, Pickles, Rusk , Oranges, Lemonade, <pb n="[2]"/> Ice Cream, Cake of different kinds, <abbr type="et cetera">&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;</abbr>. the remainder of which I have not time to mention, about four o'clock in the evening we had some company, to come out among who was<name type="person"> Miss Hanks</name> &amp; her intended (as report says) <name type="person">Mr Gardell</name>, on horse-back Miss Hanks was dress off in a very handsome riding-dress, and Leghorn <sic corr="hat">hat hat</sic> with a black blond <abbr type="vail">vale</abbr>, she looked <emph>very</emph> pretty.</p><p><name type="person">Margaret</name>  received a letter from your <name type="person">Uncle James</name> last Tuesday who stated the agreeable fact of Father, Mother, &amp; <name type="person">Bun</name>'s leaving on the <date value="1840-06-01">first of June</date> for the <emph>charming</emph> City of <emph><abbr expan="Philadelphia">Philada</abbr></emph> , the City of  <emph>brotherly-love, I</emph> am <emph>sure</emph> I do not know where they <emph>keep their love, I</emph> have <emph>never</emph> seen it, &caret; <add place="supralinear"><emph>but</emph></add> <emph>perhaps</emph> they are keeping it for <emph>hard times</emph>, I will not say any thing more about them, but thank my <emph>stars</emph> that I have not long to stay with them than I have. but to return to the former part of the sentence, I never was so glad to hear of any thing in all my life, it was hard enough realize Fathers coming on with <name type="person">Uncle Joe</name>, but when I heard that <emph>Mother</emph> &amp; <emph>Bun</emph> were coming I could not say a word, nor can I <emph>yet</emph> realize it, Although Uncle James said that they would leave on the <date value="1840-06-01"><emph>first</emph> of June</date> I <emph>will not</emph> look for them until the <emph>last</emph>, for you know <pb n="[3]"/> how the good <unclear>foly</unclear> of <name type="place">Westwood</name> are about leaving home. You said in your letter that some one of the family wrote every week <gap reason="tear in docunment "/> one, but I think that you must surely miscount, or that there is a mistake <orig reg="somewhere">somewhare</orig> for upon <emph>an average</emph> I  receive about one every <emph>three</emph> weeks, Tell <name type="person">Josephine</name> she has forgotten me, or at least she has <emph>forgotten</emph> to <emph>write to me</emph> . <emph>Answer</emph> this <emph>scrawl soon</emph> for I do not think that  it deserves the title of a letter, The girls send their love to all, <abbr expan="Margaret">Mag</abbr>Woods &amp; <name type="person">Martha T. </name>send their love <sic corr="to">to to</sic> <emph>you</emph> particularly, </p><closer><salute>and accept the love of an ever affectionate sister</salute><signed><name type="person">Jane Theora</name>.</signed><add place="post script">P. S. Give my love to <name type="person">Aunt Mary</name> &amp; <name type="person">Uncle Bob</name> with all of their children. <unclear><name type="person">Mammy</name></unclear> and all of hers, <name type="person">Maria</name> and all of hers particularly <name type="person">Cealy</name>, <name type="person">Aunt Avarey</name> &amp; all of hers, <name type="person">Aunt Cilla</name> &amp; <name type="person">Uncle <unclear>Puiger</unclear></name> , <name type="person">Aunt <unclear>Sary</unclear></name> &amp; <name type="person">Mr. <emph>Harding</emph></name> her beau, <name type="person">Patsy</name>, <name type="person">Preston</name>, <name type="person">Fred</name>, <name type="person">Isaac</name>, <name type="person">Uncle Lain</name>, <name type="person">Uncle Will</name>, <name type="person">Uncle Davy</name> &amp; <name type="person">Aunt Rachel</name> the next time You see them, and tell them that I live with the <orig reg="hope">hop</orig> of seeing them &caret; <add>all</add> in a year from now. Jane</add><pb n="[4]"/> <emph>single</emph><add rend="different hand, ink">25</add><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mr. James A. Woods</name></addrLine><addrLine>Care <name type="person"><abbr expan="Robert">Robt</abbr> Woods <abbr expan="Esquire">Esq</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
