<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl154"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1845 Feb.16, Westwood, [TN] [to] Joseph Woods, Columbia, Tennessee / Julia [Woods?]    : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Woods, Julia</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl154</idno><idno>OCLC: 50564127</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1845 Feb.16, Westwood, [TN] [to] Joseph Woods, Columbia, Tennessee / Julia [Woods?]</title><author>Woods, Julia </author><date value="1845-02-16">February 16, 1845</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter to Joseph Woods in Columbia, TN from his sister Julia, dated Feb. 16, 1845. She reports the sinking of a steamboat named Pathfinder, a neighbor girl nearly burning to death, and other happenings in her town of Westwood. She also mentions some friends who will be accompanying the President to inauguration.</note><note type="collection">Woods Family</note><note type="box">Foster- Handy</note><note type="document">sl154</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Life change events</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Westwood</name> <date value="1845-02-16">February 16th 1845</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Brother</salute></opener><p>As ma dislikes to write she desired me to answer your letter which I do with a great deal of pleasure There is little or <gap reason="hole in document " desc="no"/> news here <gap reason="document damaged"/> I believe I never saw N<gap reason="hole in document "/>stitute of news before All the news <unclear>stunn</unclear><gap reason="hole in document"/> is marriages which will not interest you unless <name type="person">Mr <del type="overstrike">Lat</del> <add place="supralinear"><del type="overstrike">Lapl</del></add> <unclear>Lapslies</unclear></name> will though that is not certain yet But he looks as nice as a new pin At <name type="person">Mrs Johns</name>. <name type="person">M. Hills</name> party he looked as spry and was bowing about and cutting cake for the <emph>young</emph> ladies all night Last night we heard of the burning of the steam  boat (named after your <orig reg="favorite">favourite</orig> novel) The Pathfinder It ran up the <del type="ovrstrike">path</del> <name type="place"><add place="supralinear">Yazoo</add> river</name> and I believe there were not many aboard except the officers of the boat who  nearly all saved by swimming ashore I forgot to mention before that <name type="person">Adeline Maria</name>s youngest child got burnt nearly to death about three weeks ago while playing down to aunt <name type="person">Jennie</name>s house with the rest of the children who were so frightened when she caught that  they did not have presence of mind enough to put her out until we ran to the wood pile and told <name type="person">Bill</name> who was cutting wood and he <orig reg="jumped">jumpped</orig> over the fence and tore her clothes off but she was then sadly burnt The doctors she is a great deal better now but that will be sometime before she can walk a year at least <pb n="[2]"/> <name type="person">Louden</name> was bit very bad the other day  by a dog when walking along behind him which you know is famous for Ma says she believes <del type="overstrike">s</del> he would be like<name type="person"> Lot</name>s wife Turn <gap reason="hole in document" desc="into a "/> pillar of salt rather than quit looking be<gap reason="hole in document" desc="hind him"/> <name type="person">Mr Armistead</name> has apprenticed <name type="person">Hunt</name> to a shoe <gap reason="hole in document"/> <orig reg="opposite">oposite</orig> the ware house to learn the trade <gap reason="hole in document"/> he has made a pair of shoes for <name type="person">Roberte</name> <name type="person">Mr Branch</name> has gone to <name type="place">Washington</name> with the President and will not return until after the <orig reg="inauguration">enauguration</orig> Ma and Sis <name type="person">Josephine</name> sends <orig reg="their">thier</orig> love to you and <name type="person">Daulphine</name> says <add rend="different hand">my love to <del type="overstrike">oncle</del> <add place="supralinear">uncle</add> <name type="person">Jo</name></add> &caret; <add place="supralinear">written with her own hand</add> And little <name type="person">Eliza</name> says <add place="different hand">mine too</add> This is rather a long letter for me so I will close I hope you will return as longer as this at any rate to</p><closer><salute>Yours Sister</salute><signed><name type="person">Julia</name></signed><add place="post script">P. S. Excuse all mistakes for it is by candle light I write and <name type="person">Daught</name> plagues me so There is one of her knocks now by that <abbr expan="Julia">J</abbr></add> <pb n="[3]"/> <address><addrLine>Master <name type="person"> Joseph Woods</name></addrLine><addrLine>Care of <name type="person">Bishop Otey</name>,</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Columbia</name>,</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
