<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl155"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1843, May 18, Philadelphia, [PA] [to] Col. James A. Woods, Westwood, Ten[nessee] / E. L. Handy   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Handy, E. L.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl155</idno><idno>OCLC: 50564295</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1843, May 18, Philadelphia, [PA] [to] Col. James A. Woods, Westwoood, Ten[nessee] / E. L. Handy</title><author>Handy, E. L. </author><date value="1843-05-15">May, 18, 1843</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated May 18, 1843, from E. L. Handy in Philadelphia to Colonel James Woods in Westwood, TN.  Handy updates his friend on news from Philadelphia and of other friends.  The letter also discusses the crops and produce that were currently in season.</note><note type="collection">Woods Family</note><note type="box">Foster- Handy</note><note type="document">sl155</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Lettes</item><item>Crops</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><add place="top of page">I am extremely happy to add that since my last letter my brother has improved very much and is decidedly better.</add><address><addrLine><name type="place">Philadelphia</name> <date value="1843-05-18">May 18 / 43</date></addrLine></address><salute>My Dear <name type="person">James</name></salute></opener><p> I have not since my arrival have had the pleasure of hearing a word from any of  <gap reason="hole in document "/> directly or <gap reason="hole in document" desc="indirectly"/> I wrote to <name type="person">Robina</name>   from <name type="place">Louisville</name> and hope soon to have a letter from her, but if she should fail to  write me I cannot but think that <name type="person"><unclear>Tout</unclear></name> will let me hear from her. I do very much want to hear how the dear child is getting along&mdash; <orig reg="whether">whither</orig> she rides Gen Thumb and how he behaves &mdash; Say to Tout that she must certainly write me &amp; tell me about every thing that is going on&mdash; I often think of you all James and sometimes imagine you all seated around the breakfast or supper table discussing the peculiar qualities of the hoe cake Egg bread or hot biscuit  &mdash; and enjoying the delicious grass butter &amp; rich milk &mdash; how I would like to be at least within a days travel of you and occasionally come down upon you in surprise &mdash; tell your Mother that I have tried <pb n="[2]"/> very hard since I got home to have corn bread made and baked such as she has but it wont do. We cant <unclear>come</unclear> it in our quaker city &amp; I am compelled at last to fall back on the old fashioned baked bread. of which I &caret; <add place="supralinear">am</add> almost tired out &mdash; I suppose you are now busily <gap reason="document damaged"/> with your <gap reason="hole in document"/> <orig reg="arrangements">arangements</orig> your corn must be up &amp; replanted before this but I feel more interested in your <emph><orig reg="potato">potatoe</orig></emph> crop than any other. have you yet found out the difference between early and late potatoes? and have you planted as large a crop as you did last year? have you had the same old hat  fitted up  and do you intend wearing your summer coats of the same old cut? I had expected to return to  <abbr expan="Nashville">N</abbr> before coming home or I should have procured the <orig reg="pattern">patern</orig> of your Coat &mdash; I hope you will retain the <orig reg="pattern">patern</orig> till I see you again. I had a letter from our friend <name type="person">Gale</name> since I got home. you will remember that I <abbr expan="received">rcd</abbr> a letter from him whilst at <name type="place">Westwood</name> addressed to me at <name type="place"><abbr expan="Philadelphia">Philad.</abbr></name> and from there forwarded to Nashville. in that letter you doubtless recollect he <orig reg="spoke">spooke</orig> in such exalted terms of the ladies of <abbr expan="Philadelphia">Philad.</abbr> as to leave but little doubt that he <orig reg="thought">thot</orig> them far ahead of any he had <pb n="[3]"/> ever seen &mdash; My last letter was addressed to me at Nashville and forwarded from there to <abbr expan="Philadelphia">Philad.</abbr> in this letter he pours it out upon the Nashville ladies as thick as he did in the former one upon those of our City. unfortunately for our friend his letters all reach me in a different <gap reason="hole in document"/> place from that <gap reason="document damaged"/> which they are intended &mdash; nevertheless Gale is a real clever fellow &mdash; and not the less clever because he thinks a great deal of <name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Col </abbr> Woods</name> &mdash; I suppose by this time you have strawberries at Westwood. We have had none yet in our city. We had green peas in Market this morning for the first time &mdash; Speaking of peas reminds me of a good joke that occurred with a friend of mine a day or two since &mdash; he went to market to buy a quarter of lamb. the butcher perceiving his ignorance about meat sold him goat meat for lamb. &amp; he did not find out the difference till a day after the family had dined on it. he was very mad its true when he did find out the mistake &mdash; but that made no sort of difference as the goat had been eaten.</p><p><pb n="[4]"/> Remember me in love to your Mother &amp; <abbr expan="your ">yr</abbr> <emph>Wife</emph> <name type="person">Bun</name> &amp; <name type="person">Mr. A.</name> <name type="person">Mr. &amp; Mrs Branch</name> <name type="person">Rob</name>. <name type="person">J.</name> and <name type="person">Kip</name> my dear little <name type="person">Tout</name> for me. also remember me to <name type="person">Aunt Woods</name> &amp; family. <name type="person">Aunt Betsey</name> &amp; family <name type="person">Aunt Hannah</name> &amp;  <name type="person">Aunt <unclear>Prece</unclear></name> &amp; family                     &mdash; and to <name type="person">Mr. Tabeis</name> family.<name type="person"> Mr. &amp; Mrs. Jo Norell</name> and to <name type="person">Mr. Lean</name> and to Every one that you think I have left out of the list <add place="middle of page, rotated"><address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> James A. Woods</name>.</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Westwood</name> near</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten.</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine>single</addrLine></address><add cert="different hand, ink">Responded to <date value="1843-05-30">May 30th. 43</date></add></add> Do James let me hear from you soon write me a long letter</p><closer><salute>yours <abbr expan="affectionately">aff</abbr></salute><signed><name type="person">E. L. Handy</name>.</signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
