<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl168"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Speech] 1814 Jan. 11, Fort Hampton, [to Chief] Cutteoty [i.e., Cotetoy] and others  of the  Cherokee Nation / Joseph Brown   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Brown, Joseph</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl168</idno><idno>OCLC: 51159015</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Speech] 1814 Jan. 11, Fort Hampton, [to Chief] Cutteoty [i.e., Cotetoy] and others  of the  Cherokee Nation / Joseph Brown   </title><author>Brown, Joseph </author><date value="1814-01-11">January 11, 1814</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a transcription of a speech given by Joseph Brown to Chief Cotetoy and other Cherokee on Jan. 11, 1814. Brown has taken eight Cherokee from Cotetoy because they are descended from an African slave woman that Cotetoy stole from Brown's father.  Brown says that he forgives Cotetoy for killing members of his family, and that he wants them to live in peace and friendship. </note><note type="collection">Joseph Brown Papers</note><note type="box">THS-JB</note><note type="folder">83-86</note><note type="document">sl168</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Cherokee Indians -- Claims against</item><item>Slavery</item><item>Southern States</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="speech"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Fort Hampton</name>  <date value="1814-01-11">January 11th 1814</date></addrLine></address><salute>Friends &amp; Brothers</salute></opener><p>I Would <unclear>agree to inform</unclear> you that I think it is a Duty to <unclear>Re take</unclear><orig reg="possession"> possesion</orig> of these Negroes for <orig reg="various">varies</orig> reasons in the first place because <orig reg="they">the</orig> are my property and it would be <unclear>wrong</unclear> to make government pay for them because <orig reg="they">the</orig>  were taken when <orig reg="peace">peas</orig> <orig reg="professed">profesed</orig> by said Nation &amp; again when my self  &amp; Brother &amp; sisters were <unclear>banned</unclear> by treaty a number of us were not of age &amp; one Brother that was  taken a prisoner when I was, was still in bondage in the <name type="people">Creek Nation</name> &amp; not more than sixteen years of age &amp; all my white Brothers <unclear><orig reg="Does">Dose</orig></unclear> know that there is no law can be made that will take the property of an Infant, but always  <del type="overstrike">the</del> when the Infant comes of age when ever he finds his property he can prove it and take the same by a Due Course of law and in as much as there is no law <orig reg="here">hear</orig> the laws of Justice says that I should take them, in as much as said <name type="person"><orig reg="Cotetoy">Cutteoty</orig></name> acknowledges these eight Negroes to be the <orig reg="Descendents">Desendents</orig> of the Woman that he took from my father in the year <date value="1788-00-00">1788</date> it is right that I should take them And my friend <orig reg="Cotetoy">Cutteoty</orig> I hope you will not think hard of me for taking <orig reg="possession">posesion</orig> of the Negroes because <pb n="[2]"/> you Do know that it is right for all men to have those right &amp; as it is well known to you that I Do not Do as you have Done I only take my Own property, you took my property, &amp; <orig reg="Worse">Wors</orig> than all that you took the life of my father &amp; two Brothers &amp; five other young men in a time when peace was profesed by your own Nation, I Do Not Do this, I <orig reg="only">onley</orig> take my property,  Because I Do know my <orig reg="people">peopel</orig> are gone &amp; <orig reg="any">aney</orig> thing that I Can Do Will not bring them back I am therefore Willing to forgive you <orig reg="only">onley</orig> because it is Certain both you and me are <orig reg="accountable">accountabel</orig> for our Conduct to the <orig reg="great">grate</orig> Father and in as Much as the <orig reg="Great">Grate</orig> Father put it into your mind When you had <unclear>me striped</unclear> , to take my life, that if you Did that the man <del type="overstrike">that the man</del> that <unclear>took me</unclear> would kill the <orig reg="negroe woman">Negroewoman</orig> that you had taken &amp; sent up by water, Now <orig reg="since">sin</orig> you see the good you have Done in sparing me you Now have man that is <orig reg="able">abul</orig> to  help you Much in the Destruction of your Enemies I think that when these Negroes are <pb n="[3]"/> gone you will feel Much Better you will then know that I have got a small part of my Wright but yet it is all you have, &amp; you have had them more than a sufficiency to pay you for your <orig reg="trouble">troubel</orig> <unclear>in</unclear> raising them &mdash; And <unclear><abbr expan="although">altho</abbr></unclear> you have been the <orig reg="cause">caus</orig> of me loosing my &caret;<add place="supralinear">property</add> and living in <del type="overstrike">property</del> poverty <orig reg="almost">allmost</orig> all my life I Am Now Willing to forgive you all that you have ever <orig reg="Done">Doen</orig> as to the Destruction of my family <del type="overstrike"><?xm-replace_text {del}?></del> <unclear></unclear> <gap reason="holes in document"/> hand in friendship. &amp; <unclear>never a gain raise</unclear> a flag for friendship When you aim at war this is a scandal to any Nation I wish you Not to think hard of my talk but let us try to live in friendship I am yours <unclear>&amp;c</unclear></p><closer><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Joseph">J</abbr> S,, Brown</name></signed> <add place="post script">We Do Certify that the above is the <unclear>true lance</unclear> of a talk Delivered by <name type="person">Joseph Brown</name> to <orig reg="Cotetoy">Cutteoty</orig> &amp; others of the <name type="people"><orig reg="Cherokee">Cherroke</orig> nation</name> at fort Hampton <date value="1814-01-11">11th January 1814</date></add><signed><name type="person">Saml McGee</name> <name type="person">Adam R Alexander</name> <lb/> <name type="person">Joseph B Porter</name> <name type="person">Joseph Coe</name></signed><pb n="[4]"/> Cutteoty Surren &caret; <add place="supralinear">der</add> <lb/> of Indian Negroes <lb/> <date value="1814-01-11">11th of January 1814</date></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
