<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl170"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Legal Quits of Claim and Registration Certification] 1814 -1816 [for] James Hamilton   of Davidson County, Tennessee and William Anderson of Lexington County Ky : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl170</idno><idno>OCLC: 51159456</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Legal Quits of Claim and Registration Certification] 1814 -1816 [for] James Hamilton   of Davidson County, Tennessee and William Anderson of Lexington County Ky</title><date value="1814-12-15">Dec. 15, 1814</date><date value="1816-05-00">May, 1816</date><date value="1814-12-15">Dec. 15, 1814</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">These are three different documents. The first one is dated Dec. 15, 1814, and is written by James Hamilton. It is a quit of claim of the Cherokee/African slaves that his brother in law, Joseph Brown took back from the Cherokee Chief Cotetoy. The slaves were descendents of a slave named Sue that was owned by Hamilton's father in law (Joseph Brown's father), James Brown, and stolen by Cotetoy. The second paper is the registration certification for said quit, written by Joseph Porter in May 1816.   The third paper is dated Dec. 15, 1814. It is a quit of claim to two slaves, Jinney and Suey, and offspring,  by William Anderson. He also states that Joseph Brown has payed him $150 for the portion of James Brown's estate that Anderson inherited. </note><note type="collection">Joseph Brown Papers</note><note type="box">THS-JB</note><note type="folder">83-86</note><note type="document">sl170</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Legal documents</item><item>Cherokee Indians</item><item>Slavery</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>Kentucky</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="legal documents"><pb n="[1]"/><p>Know all Men by these <orig reg="presents">preasents</orig> that I <name type="person">James Hamilton</name> of the <name type="place">State of Tennessee</name> and <name type="place">County of Davidson</name> have and by these <orig reg="present">preasents</orig> quit Claim to Certain Negroes (<abbr expan="Videlicit">Viz</abbr>) <name type="person">Jinney</name><name type="person">Suey</name><name type="person">Jainney</name> <name type="person">Newchous</name> <name type="person">Tannenole</name> <name type="person">Senelaca</name> <name type="person">Dorusendey</name> &amp; Omiah Certain Negroes <unclear>Recovered</unclear> by <name type="person">Joseph Brown</name> from the <name type="people">Cherokee</name> <orig reg="Indians">Indiens</orig> a part of  the property taken by said Cherokee Indiens from My father in law <name type="person">James Brown</name> Deceased  and as I <orig reg="Never">Neaver</orig> have <abbr expan="Received">Recev.d</abbr> <orig reg="any">aney</orig> part of Said Estate since the Death of said Deceased and Will Not be accountable for aney Demand against said Estate I therefore quit all Claim to aney part of the <unclear>said</unclear> Negroes <del type="overstrike">and Do <orig reg="Warrant">Warrent</orig> and Defend the same from my <orig reg="Heir or assignee">Haire or assigne</orig> to the other Ligation of Said Estate</del> as to me or my <orig reg="Heirs">Haire</orig> Witness my hand &amp; seal <date value="1814-12-15">15th December 1814</date> <unclear>Test</unclear></p><signed><name type="person">George W Chartton</name> James Hamilton <add place="right of signature"><figure><figDesc>seal</figDesc></figure></add><name type="person">Milberry Hamilton</name> <name type="person">Samuel Tarner</name><add place="under signatures" cert="different hand, ink">Acknowledged by James Hamilton <date value="1815-07-09">July 9th 1815</date> <name type="person">Joseph B. Porter</name> <unclear>I was</unclear></add></signed></div1><div1 type="legal document"><pb n="[2]"/><head>quit Claim of  Indian Negroes to Joseph Brown <add cert="different hand, ink" place="under the header"><orig reg="interred">Entired</orig></add></head><pb n="[3]"/><head>State of <name type="place">Tennessee</name> <name type="place">Maury County</name> <date value="1816-05-00">May Term 1816</date></head><p>when <orig reg="the">th</orig> within quit claim deed was Exhibited into open Court and the Execution thereof duly proven by the oath of Milberry Hamilton &amp; <unclear>Subscrybing</unclear> witness thereto and <unclear>ordered</unclear> to be <orig reg="certified">certifiyed</orig> for <orig reg="registration">rigistration</orig></p><signed>Joseph B. Porter</signed></div1><div1 type="legal document"><pb n="[4]"/><p>Know all Men by these preasents that I <name type="person">William Anderson</name> of the state of <name type="place"><orig reg="Kentucky">Kaintucky</orig></name>&amp; <name type="place">County Lexington</name> Do as an <orig reg="Heir">Hair</orig> of the Estate of James Brown Deceased quit all Claim to two Negro <orig reg="Women">Wemen</orig> &amp; their family (Viz Jinney &amp; Suey &amp; their offspring unto Joseph Brown and the other ligatures of said Estate as the said Joseph Brown has this Day payed me one Hundred &amp; fifty Dollars it being my proportional part of said Estate the Receipt Whereof  is <orig reg="hereby">hearby</orig> acknowledged Witness My hand and seal <date value="1814-12-15">15th December 1814</date></p><signed>James Hamilton <abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> Anderson <add><figure><figDesc>seal</figDesc></figure></add> Milberry Hamilton</signed><gap reason="bottom of page torn off"/></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
