<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl177"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1844 Jul. 10, Bolivar [to]     Col[onel] Jos[eph] Brown,  Maury [County], Ten[essee] /  D[avid] F. Brown : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Brown, David F.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl177</idno><idno>OCLC: 51173191</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1844 Jul. 10, Bolivar [to]     Col[onel] Jos[eph] Brown,   Maury [County], Ten[essee] /  D[avid] F. Brown</title><author>Brown, David F. </author><date value="1844-07-10">July 10, 1844</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">The following document is a letter dated July 10, 1844, from David F. Brown to his father Col. Joseph Brown in Maury County, Tennessee.  David talks of his travels across Missouri and Arkansas and the business of his brother Joseph and others.</note><note type="collection">Joseph Brown Papers</note><note type="box">THS-JB</note><note type="folder"> 148-165</note><note type="document">sl177</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>Communication in the family</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Bolivar</name> <date value="1844-07-10">July 10th 1844</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Father</salute></opener><p>I suppose you are aware that we <orig reg="arrived">arived</orig> here some two or three weeks Since for I believe <unclear>Maj Bell ?</unclear> we he wrote you we were on the road.  We are all well we had a tedious trip in <unclear>courage</unclear> of the waters being so very high &mdash; we came by land as far as <name type="place">little Rock</name> where we were compelled to take a steam boat for <name type="place">Memphis</name> It is our calculation to visit you the first of next month if we all keep well.  We have <orig reg="written">writen</orig> to our brother in <name type="place"><orig reg="Mississippi">Missippi</orig></name> to meet us here &amp; go up to <name type="place">Maury</name> with us if it suits them <unclear>commence</unclear> James wrote us that he had to go up this <orig reg="summer">sumer</orig> but did not know whether it would suit to take the family <pb n="[2]"/> They were all well at James &amp; Jakes eight or ten days since <name type="person">Mrs <unclear>McCreads</unclear></name>  health Continues very bad &amp; Jane dont wish to be away from her long as we expect to <orig reg="Start">Stat</orig> back in October It is likely we will leave our three daughters some where in <name type="place">tennessee</name> to go to school if we can make satisfactory arrangements to do so Our youngest son Lycurgus is a sprightly boy running about &amp; talking We saw <name type="person">Mr Hale</name> at the hot Springs in <name type="place">Arkansas</name> who informed us that you had sold out your place to <name type="person">Mr Love</name> &amp; <unclear><abbr expan="Company">C</abbr></unclear> Joseph is living at <name type="place">Galviston</name>  I have not seen him for upwards of two years, though we heard from them by <name type="person">Mr Stuart</name>  his brother in law as we came on they are all well he is trading in lumber shipping it from <name type="place"><abbr type="New">N</abbr> Orleans</name> to Galviston.  The <name type="place">Texas</name> question is doing wonders for the Democrats here &mdash; more when we meet</p><closer><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="David">D.</abbr> F. Brown</name></signed> <pb n="[3]"/> <address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel Joseph">Col Jos.</abbr> Brown</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Cave Springs</name> <unclear><abbr expan="Post Office">PO</abbr></unclear></addrLine><addrLine>Maury</addrLine><addrLine><abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten.</abbr></addrLine></address><add place="left of address">Care of <name type="person">M. Lowe</name> &rcub;</add> <add place="bottom, left" rend="different hand, ink">David F. Brown <lb/> letter <lb/> 1844</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
