<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl176"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1843 Feb. 22, Bastrop [TX] [to] Col. Joseph Brown, Maury County, Tennessee / David F. Brown   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Brown, David F.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl176</idno><idno>OCLC: 51165706</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1843 Feb. 22, Bastrop [TX] [to] Col. Joseph Brown, Maury County, Tennessee / David F. Brown</title><author>Brown, David F. </author><date value="1843-02-22">February 22, 1843</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from David F. Brown to his father Joseph Brown dated Febrary 22, 1843.  David updates his father about his family, his brother Joseph, and the death of a woman named Julia Ann.  David mentions skirmishes between Mexican and US soldiers as far into Texas as San Antonio. Twelve US soldiers were taken prisoner, but the people have hope they will be released because there is a revolution against Santa Anna going on in Mexico. He also mentions that Jane (unsure if he is referring to his aunt, wife, or sister in law by brother Joseph) wishes to visit Joseph in order to improve her health.</note><note type="collection">Joseph Brown Papers</note><note type="box">THS-JB</note><note type="folder">148-165</note><note type="document">sl176</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>United States -- Army -- Military life</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Bastrop</name><date value="1843-02-22"><abbr expan="February">Feb</abbr> 22nd 1843</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Father</salute></opener><p>I <orig reg="barely">bearly</orig> have time to say to you that we are all in our usual health &amp; are getting on as well as could be expected considering the distracted state of our county the scarcity of many <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;c</abbr> Our family suffered considerably with sickness last fall as well as brother Joseph I suppose Joseph wrote you all the circumstances of this sickness &amp; the death of <name type="person">Julia Ann</name> last summer she died of  fever imprudently going into the sun when hot &amp; imprudence whilst sick Joseph came here late in the spring &amp; rented some land of  <unclear>mee</unclear> he also cleared some land which he was to have as long as he wanted it but he planted too late &amp; made a bad crop, he became <orig reg="dissatisfied">disatisfied</orig> &amp;  moved to <name type="place">houston</name> last fall I got  letter from him some time since &amp; he <orig reg="informed">informd</orig> me he thought he would be able to make some property there for many is out of the question I am <orig reg="fearful">fearfull</orig> he will never have patience &amp; stability enough to do any thing any where, he let me have stockholder he still has old <unclear>packoletta</unclear> but he has been a <unclear>chore</unclear> <orig reg="expense">expence</orig> to him ever since he has been here, he has been in bad health &amp; out of  flight for a season you sent me <orig reg="money">mony</orig> to second your deed but neglected to send the papers <pb n="[2]"/> Old <name type="person">Capt Farney</name> has been living at my house for the last 12 months working at his trade he is in fine health &amp; well pleased with the country The <name type="person">Mexicans</name>weakened our frontier very much last year They made two or three <orig reg="invasions">nvasions</orig> as far as <name type="place">st Antonio</name> &amp; carried off a good many prisoners Our government sent out 6 or 7 hundred troops  into their country to retaliate but the mexican troops all fled before then, they took two or three towns &amp; started back, but 300 of the troops concluded they must go back &amp; have a fight they attacked &amp; took the town  of <name type="place"><unclear>Meor</unclear></name>  but were soon attacked by a large force of the Mexicans &amp; after fighting 24 hours &amp; killing some four or five hundred &amp; <orig reg="losing">loosing</orig> 12 men they were compelled to surrender as prisoners of war, they were started on to the <name type="place"><orig reg="city ">citty</orig> of Mexico</name> in chains but we are in hopes they will be released as we learn there is a considerable revolution now going on in Mexico between <name type="person"><orig reg="Santa Anna, Antonio Lopez">St Anna</orig></name> the dictator &amp; congress The congress party profess liberal principles &amp; will no doubt be <orig reg="favorable">favourable</orig>  to <name type="place">Texas</name> &amp; <name type="place"><orig reg="Yucatan">Youcatan</orig></name> <name type="person">Elijah Porter</name>  <name type="person"><abbr expan="John">Jno</abbr> T Porter</name> oldest Son is among the prisoners We now have <unclear>comissioner</unclear> among the <unclear>indians</unclear> for the purpose of forming a treaty &amp; exchanging prisoners  <pb n="[3]"/> I am now just going to plant corn I shall have 20 acres of cotton 40 of corn &amp; 8 or 10 of small grain &amp; potatoes I have rented 60 acres to the <name type="person">Frazer</name> boys the old lady has not yet left <name type="place">NewOrleans</name> We have had a most extraordinary <orig reg="freshet">freshett</orig> in this country &amp; has damaged the country very much in the  way of damaging stock sweeping off fences &amp;c It swept <orig reg="off">of</orig> the fence of one of my fields 23 acres <unclear>res</unclear> on to my corn crop &amp; spoiled 150 bushels of corn &amp; about 300 <orig reg="bushels">bushells</orig> of  potatoes I got a letter from Jno T Porter a week or <orig reg="two">tow</orig> since they are hard run &amp; very  much distressed about Eliz <gap reason="document damaged"/> <name type="person">Mr Ceylon Frazer</name>  is now  waiting &amp; I must close Jane Says she <gap reason="hole in document"/> back this <orig reg="summer">sumer</orig> she wants to spend some time with you as she always has better health there than any where else; but I think it <orig reg="doubtful">doubtfull</orig> whether we can arrange it so or to send her on account of the scarcity of money Jane expects to be confined in a few weeks</p><closer><salute><abbr expan="Respectfully">Resp</abbr> yours <abbr expan="and etcetera">&amp;c</abbr></salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="David Franklin">D.  F</abbr>   Brown</name></signed><pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine><name type="place">Lafayette <gap reason="hole in document"/> O. <abbr expan="Louisiana">La</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1843-03-15">March 15 1843</date></addrLine></address><add place="upper right corner">free</add><address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> <abbr expan="Joseph">Jos</abbr> Brown </name><add place="supralinear">P.M</add></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Cave spring</name> <abbr expan="Post office">P. Off</abbr></addrLine><addrLine>&rcub;<name type="place">Maury County</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine></address><add place="up left side of page">D <unclear>H</unclear> Brown <lb/> letter 1842</add> <add place="down right side of page"><name type="person">W. H. Lyon</name><lb/> <unclear>Demopolis</unclear> <lb/> <name type="person">Sarah Davidson</name></add><add place="along bottom of page"><figure><figDesc>misc math problems</figDesc></figure></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
