<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl183"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1841 Jan. 30 [to] Joseph Brown, Maury County Tenn[essee] / Joseph Porter Brown   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Brown, Joseph Porter</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl183</idno><idno>OCLC: 51173614</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1841 Jan. 30 [to] Joseph Brown, Maury County Tenn[essee] / Joseph Porter Brown</title><author>Brown, Joseph Porter </author><date value="1841-0130">January 30, 1841</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated January 30, 1841 to Joseph Brown from his son Joseph Porter Brown regarding a trip he plans to take to visit his father.</note><note type="collection">Joseph Brown Papers THS-JB</note><note type="box">n/a</note><note type="folder">202-205</note><note type="document">sl183</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Randolph</name><date value="1841-01-30"><abbr expan="January">Jany</abbr> 30th 1841</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Father</salute></opener><p>Your letter some time since <orig reg="arrived">arived</orig> at hand in a few days after It was written I should have written before this but I have intended starting up ever since I arived Never <orig reg="more">mor</orig> than a <orig reg="weak">weak</orig> a head but know it has become my duty to stay <orig reg="until 3rd">untill 3d</orig> Monday. In february I find my <orig reg="mother-in-law">motherinlaw</orig> involved in matters  <unclear>her</unclear> for <unclear>her</unclear> son <name type="person">E P. Stewart</name>  he is at present <orig reg="gone">gon</orig> to <name type="place">New Orleans</name> to try and make money enough to pay what debts she is bound for on his account. I am still trying to extricate her from some other <orig reg="business">buisness</orig> she is involved in I have some money to raise here on my own account about $175. after which I will be up and see you to remain some few weaks I want to bring my family up only one child, our oldest we lost in <name type="place">Texas</name>, we called this one for sister Jane. <name type="person">Jane Gillespie Brown</name>, she <orig reg="favors">favours</orig> the Browns very much. <name type="person">Mrs. Frazier</name> has <orig reg="been">bin</orig> very sick in fact we did not expect her to live for two weeks She is now <pb n="[2]"/> the mend slowly. I am quite anxious to get off I heard from brother <name type="person">John</name> a few days ago he was then in New Orleans had found some vacant land in the<name type="place"> Attuckapas Country</name>  that he is entering, I suppose he will move there, you may look for us about the last of February. we are only tolerable with bad colds &mdash;</p><closer><salute>Yours affectionately</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Joseph">J.</abbr> Porter Brown</name></signed><pb n="[3]"/><address><addrLine><abbr expan="Reverend">Rev.</abbr><name type="person">Joseph Brown</name> P.M.<name type="place">Cave Spring</name><abbr expan="Post Office">P.O.</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Maury County</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn.</abbr></name></addrLine></address><add place="above address">Postmark</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
