<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl190"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1842 Dec. 26, Louisvill[e] [KY] [to]    Geo[rge] W[ashington] House, Nashville, Tenn[essee] / John A Burk : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Burk, John A </author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl190</idno><idno>OCLC: 51196208</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1842 Dec. 26, Louisvill[e] [KY] [to]    Geo[rge] W[ashington] House, Nashville, Tenn[essee] / John A Burk</title><author>Burk, John A </author><date value="1842-12-26">December 26, 1842</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from John A. Burk to George W. House, dated December 26, 1842.  He discusses patient care.</note><note type="collection">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note><note type="box">2</note><note type="folder">2</note><note type="document">sl190</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Medical care</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place"><orig reg="Louisville">Louisvill</orig></name> <date value="1842-12-26"><abbr expan="December">Dec</abbr> 26th 1842</date></addrLine></address><salute>Sir</salute></opener><p>I <abbr expan="Recieved">Rec</abbr> your letter this morning <orig reg="which made">wich maid</orig>  me <orig reg="laugh">laff</orig> to think what fools <orig reg="there are">their ar</orig> tell the <name type="person"><abbr expan="Doctor">Doc</abbr> Robson</name> he must eat 2 before he becomes a <orig reg="christian">christan</orig> and then he must keep it up <orig reg="four">fore</orig> night and then he must take <unclear>som bun tea</unclear> to work it off and then he will be a Doctor of the first order all this is nothing  but tell the Doctor if was to crack a <unclear>samson</unclear> and then find out what it was he  all <orig reg="probability">provibility</orig> he would not live twenty <orig reg="four">fore</orig> hours for <orig reg="excitement">exsiment</orig> would kill him <orig reg="sure">shour</orig> <orig reg="therefore">their fore</orig> you must not tell the Doctor but give him my best complement and tell him we must leave him in the dark at least at  the Present keep them all in the dark I will send you plenty of pills and <orig reg="do">doe</orig> the thing that is <orig reg="right">rite</orig> with you treat all my <orig reg="patients">pashents</orig> well and you shall <orig reg="make">mak</orig> plenty dont you give 1 of the samson at the <unclear>risk</unclear>of your life to any body and dont <orig reg="show">sho</orig> them to <orig reg="anyone">any wone</orig> I <orig reg="wrote">rote</orig> you last week and that will keep you tell I send let me hear from you take good <orig reg="care">kier</orig> that   they dont <orig reg="steal">steel</orig> som of your pills you shall hear from me <orig reg="soon">soune</orig> send word how many samson you have <pb n="[2]"/> on hand they will keep us from want in this life and your sweet son also but of you doe show them to any <orig reg="body">boddy</orig> I never will forgive you in life I will treat &caret; <add place="supralinear">you</add> like a Gentleman if I <orig reg="show">sho</orig> them to any boddy in this <orig reg="world">wourld</orig> it shall be you and that is <orig reg="enough">a nuff</orig> for you to <orig reg="know">no</orig>&mdash; dont send to william for what he owes I will see him in the spring &mdash; my daughter is in a low state of <orig reg="health">helth</orig> and that will keep me <orig reg="here">hear</orig> this winter &mdash; give my best Respects to<name type="person"> Mr Ferguson</name> and all the <orig reg="family">famley</orig> also to <name type="person">Mr Bedford</name> tell him I think I have got home in time to save my <orig reg="child">chaild</orig> and that is more then all the world to me god <orig reg="bless">bles</orig> my friends and also my enemies but I no of none and if you hear them <orig reg="speak ill">spake ill</orig> of me draw back and with them and <orig reg="be sure">beshoure</orig> you keep them down and let them rise no more I am at work for you no news</p><closer><signed><name type="person">John A Burk</name></signed><pb n="[3]"/><address><addrLine><abbr expan="John">Jn</abbr> A Burk</addrLine><addrLine>Lousvill <abbr expan="December">Decmr</abbr> /42 </addrLine></address><pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="George Washington">Geo. W.</abbr> House</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name></addrLine></address><add cert="different hand, ink" place="bottom of page">Recd Thursday Morning <date value="1842-12-29">Dec 29/42</date> <lb/> <abbr expan="answered">answd</abbr> '' '' '' '' '' &mdash;</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
