<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl227"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1850 June 7, Pulaski [to] Mary House / George House    : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>House, George W.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl227</idno><idno>OCLC: 51217706</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1850 June 7, Pulaski [to] Mary House / George House</title><author>House, George W.</author><date value="1850-06-07">June 7, 1850</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated June 7, 1850 from George W. House to his wife Mary. George tells his wife the cities he will be travelling through and which ones to write him at.</note><note type="collection">Orr Collection-IV-J-2</note><note type="box">3</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">sl227</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Tennessee -- Description and travel</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Pulaski</name><date value="1850-06-07">June 7, 1850</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Mary</salute></opener><p>I am at last here, after quite a <orig reg="fatiguing">fatigueing</orig> trip through the hills of this county but am in good health&mdash; Yet have not been <orig reg="successful">successfull</orig> in finding several of the agents at home&mdash; I am also afraid that "Tom" is a little foundered his feet are very tender to say the least of it&mdash; I shall however continue my journey onward if only in a slow way&mdash; I wrote to you from <name type="place">Columbia</name> which letter you have no doubt received I am beginning to realize the old and <abbr expan="often">oft</abbr> repeated sentiment&mdash; that there is no place like home with wife child &amp; friends&mdash;  I am however underway and shall by the aid of a divine presence continue my journey. I have not met with anything of a character sufficiently novel or interesting to write to you about&mdash;  My thoughts are upon you and my business which I shall endeavor to accomplish&mdash;   I have not been able to sell yet owing to the demand for everything being dull&mdash;  I shall make an extra effort in <name type="place"><abbr expan="Alabama">Alaba</abbr></name> I shall write to you again from <name type="place">athens</name> but when <pb n="[2]"/> I shall reach that place cant say&mdash; Remember me to all &caret; <add place="supralinear">the household</add> and always in your prayers&mdash; My love to Mother and to Sallie Lou <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;c</abbr> I write in haste and will be better able to give you a long letter from <name type="place">Athens <abbr expan="Alabama">Alaba</abbr></name> You must write to me at <name type="place">Florence Alabama</name> to the care of <name type="person">N B Barten</name> druggist&mdash; when I reach <name type="place">Tuscumben</name> or <name type="place">Courtland</name> I can tell you where to write again&mdash; Tell Tomy I shall expect to hear a good account from him&mdash; I saw <name type="person">Mr Plummer</name> all well, but a one of his children&mdash; With my love and prayers I am</p><closer><salute>Your own</salute><signed>George</signed><add place="under signature">I send Mc 20&cent; to day</add> <pb n="[3]"/><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs Mary House</name></addrLine><addrLine>Care of <name type="person"><abbr expan="George">Geo </abbr> W  House</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name></addrLine><addrLine><abbr expan="Tennessee"><name type="place">Tenn.</name></abbr></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
