<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl278"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>   [Letter] 1835 Oct. 21, Nashville, T[ennessee] [to] A. J. Donelson, Washington City / S. H. Laughlin : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Laughlin, S. H.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl278</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1835 Oct. 21, Nashville, T[ennessee] [to] A. J. Donelson, Washington City / S. H. Laughlin</title><author>Laughlin, S. H.</author><date value="1835-10-21">October 21, 1835</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated Oct. 21, 1835, from S. H. Laughlin to Major Andrew J. Donelson. Laughlin is writing about the political situation, especially as it pertains to President Jackson. He mentions some promising Democrats. Laughlin promises to keep Donelson updated on the news that he will not find in the newspapers. He mentions a dinner being given in honor of Colonel Polk in Mooresville. Laughlin writes that he and some others are supporting Polk for Speaker of the House, over a man named Bell.</note><note type="collection">A. J. Donelson Papers</note><note type="box"> I-D-3</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">sl278</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</item><item>Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><add place="left of address">(Private)</add><address><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville</name>, <abbr expan="Tennessee">T.</abbr> <date value="1835-10-21"><abbr expan="October">Oct.</abbr> 21, 1835</date>.</addrLine></address><salute>Dear Sir,</salute></opener><p>Your several communications of the 28th and 30th <abbr expan="ultimo">ult</abbr> and of the 1st. <abbr expan="instant">inst.</abbr> together with your letter for publication, have all been duly received, and shall be confidentially attended to as desired. Your communication for the Union has been given to the public as you will have seen. The further course I shall take in relation to the matter of the franks, and the new remarks of the Banner, you will see next week.</p><p>The papers will inform you of the progress our new General Assembly is making in the business of President making. What they will do with <name type="person">Ridley</name>'s resolutions, now lying on the table of the House, specifically approving severally of the leading measures of the administration, and of the conduct of the President separately in relation to each, yet remains to be seen. These resolutions are framed with a special view of having a distinct vote taken in relation to each important measure. It will be a sore pill to some hypocrites and some apostates to be forced to vote in that way, but they will be compelled to do it or disgrace themselves by giving the  go by, in some way, to the whole in a mass. &mdash; In debate, we have decidedly the advantage of talents. <name type="person">Nicholson</name>, <name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> Polk</name>'s convert from the last remains of Whiteism, is a great accession to us. <name type="person">Guild</name> is a man of good sense a bold generous fellow &mdash; but who, by the by something manifests more <pb n="[2]"/> courage than discretion. In Ridley, <name type="person">Humphreys</name> ( a son of the Judge and member from <name type="person">Fayette</name>) and <name type="person">Turney</name> we have men equal to the ablest of the enemy. Some of their best men, don't go the whole &mdash; <name type="person">Carnthers</name> for instance. In the Senate, <name type="person">Craighead</name> &mdash; and &caret; <add place="supralinear">I</add> rather hoped for than expected it &mdash; is taking good ground. But even up to this time, it is very much undecided how a good many respectable members will finally stand on the great questions which now agitate the state growing out of the Presidential controversy. Matters on hand, as they arise, which you would not learn from the papers, I will communicate in such hasty letters as I can find time to write at least once or twice a week.</p><p>Tomorrow, the people of <name type="place">Maury</name> are to give Col. Polk a dinner at <name type="place">Mooresville</name>. <name type="person">Mr Grundy</name> started out as a guest on yesterday, and is to make a speech. I have besought &caret; <add place="supralinear">him</add> as with tears to cry aloud and spare not. The time has actually arrived here now, when, as Mr. <abbr expan="Grundy">G.</abbr> said of the sword in his war circular of 1812, "cursed is he that keepeth back himself from the fight, or holdeth back his means." That we will win the day next year I feel no reasonable fears, but &caret; <add place="supralinear">it</add> will be by a hand fought battle.</p><p><name type="person">Bell</name> admitted in a conversation with <unclear><name type="person">Falls</name></unclear> of the Mississppian, a few weeks since, that unless they can unite all branches of the opposition in the support of <name type="person">Judge White</name> next winter, their case will be gone and hopeless. The ackowledgement was not made confidentially, and I urged Falls to use <pb n="[3]"/> it in Mississippi when he got home. What he may be able to make out of it, or what course he may take in relation to it, I do not know.</p><p>There will be a strong necessity, in order to aid us here, of running Col. Polk for speaker, if it can be done with the <gap reason="hole in document"/> wishes of our party. In correspondence which I have had with <name type="person"><abbr expan="Governor">Gov.</abbr> Reynolds</name> and <name type="person">Col. May</name> of <name type="place">Illinois</name>, I find that the delegation of that state have the matter much at heart. This correspondence  was sought by Gov. <abbr expan="Reynolds">R.</abbr> with a view of consulting our friends here. He informed me that he had written to <name type="person">Mr. Blair</name> on the subject. I wrote also to Mr. Blair but have received no answer. I am entirely sure that <name type="person">Shields</name>, <name type="person">Huntsman</name> and <name type="person">Dunlap</name> of our delegation will all go with <name type="person">Johnson</name> in supporting Polk against Bell. In Illinois, at least <del type="overstrike">one paper</del> two papers &mdash; the Springfield Republican and St. Clair Gazette &mdash; have avowed their preference for Col. P. as has been &caret; <add place="supralinear">also</add> done by the Democrat, if not others in <name type="place">Alabama</name>. The Albany <unclear>Osgers</unclear> , I think, gives an intimation in its remarks on Col. Polks speech of June last. This, however,   is a weighty matter which can only be adjusted after our friends get to <name type="place">Washington</name>. It is a matter, however, of great importance here, for we now feel certain that if Bell finds he can't beat Polk himself, he is determined to try to have it done by another, and he would like to have that other to be one of our friends. When <del type="overstrike">such men as</del> old <name type="person">Peteray</name> here, who knows Bells' plans as far he would divulge them to such a man, as &caret; <add place="supralinear">is</add> told by our friends that Polk can <gap reason="document torn"/> ell, he always takes a pinch of snuff, and <gap reason="overstrike"/> ntly asks, if <pb n="[4]"/> Polk can beat <name type="person">Mason</name>. That he intends <del type="overstrike">it</del> &caret; <add place="supralinear">the remark</add> as an answer, and not as asking a question, is certain.</p><p>Please present my kindest respects to the President, and to <name type="person">Col. Earl</name>and for yourself,</p><closer><salute>Accept assurances of my highest respect and esteem</salute><signed><name type="person">S. H. Laughlin</name>.</signed><dateline>Oct 21st 1835</dateline> <add place="left of signature"><address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Major Andrew">Maj. A.</abbr> J. Donelson.</name></addrLine></address></add><add place="center of page"><abbr expan="Post Script">PS.</abbr> In my rambling letters, written at snatches of time during the sitting of the Assembly, when I have to report and copy documents and twenty other extra things for our papers, as well as for other friends, you must excuse the most hasty <orig reg="scribbling">scribling</orig> <abbr expan="Laughlin">L</abbr></add> <add place="bottom of page, rotated"><address><addrLine>Maj. A. J. Donelson,</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Washington City</name></addrLine></address></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
