<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl276"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1844 May 15, Loudon County, Virginia [to] Andrew J. Donelson, Tennessee / John A. Carter   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Carter, John A.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl276</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1844 May 15, Loudon County, Virginia [to] Andrew J. Donelson, Tennessee / John A. Carter</title><author>Carter, John A.</author><date value="1844-05-15">May 15, 1844</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from John A. Carter to Andrew J. Donelson, dated May 15, 1844. Carter thanks Donelson for helping Betty and her child to Virginia. Carter asks Donelson if he is willing to buy a slave named Polly. In an addition to the letter that Donelson writes two years later, he states that he did buy Polly.</note><note type="collection">A. J. Donelson Papers</note><note type="box"> I-D-3</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">sl276</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Slavery</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Loudon County </name><abbr expan="Virginia">Va</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1844-05-15">May 15th 1844</date></addrLine></address><salute>My Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>I am pleased to tell you that Betty &amp; her child arrived at my farm in due time safe, &amp; you will be pleased to accept my thanks for your care of them &amp; the aid you gave me in getting them to <name type="place">Virginia</name>; I have just <orig reg="met">meet</orig> with mr <name type="person">George Glasscock</name> formerly of Virginia now of <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tence</abbr> and who tells me he lives in some 40 or 50 miles of you, &amp; the object of my now writing is to <orig reg="inform">enform</orig> you that I have <orig reg="authorized">authorised</orig> Mr Glasscock to make some satisfactory arrangement in regard to the remaining negro woman (Polly) I think you mentioned that she had <unclear>married</unclear> one of your men, if so I hope you will find it agreeable to purchase her but of course can not expect  <pb n="[2]"/> you to do so unless agreeable to you, if you wish to purchase polley Mr Glasscock will arrange with you the price &amp; I think you also mentioned that there were one or more children; <unclear>hoping</unclear> that you will be relieved from any further trouble with this negro &amp; returning you my thanks for your kindness I remain</p><closer><salute>Very Truly  <abbr expan="Your Servant">Yr Snt</abbr></salute><signed><name type="person">John A. Carter</name> <lb/> Executor of <name type="person">H. R. Dulany</name></signed><add place="left of signature"><address><addrLine><abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Donelson &rcub;</addrLine></address></add><add place="bottom of page" cert="different hand, ink">Informed Mr. Carter on the <date value="1846-04-23">23rd April 1846</date> &mdash; that I could buy the woman at a fair price &mdash; if he were authorised to sell. That I did not wish her to remain at my plantation on the present terms &mdash; that I would pay no <unclear>hire</unclear> for her &mdash; her <unclear>saving</unclear> had not more than paid present <unclear>advances</unclear> &mdash; that I wished him to come and see me &mdash; <lb/> <abbr expan="Andrew">A</abbr> J Donelson <lb/> at <name type="place">Washington</name>23rd April <lb/> 1846 &mdash;</add> <pb n="[3]"/><address><addrLine>Col <name type="person">Andrew J Donelson</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine><addrLine>Attention</addrLine><addrLine>Mr Glasscock</addrLine></address><add place="upside down at bottom of page">May 15th. 1844 <lb/> Mr Dulany &mdash; ad &mdash;<lb/> to be attended to when <lb/> I went Washington &mdash; April 1846 &mdash;</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
