<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl280"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>1829 Feb. 28, Nashville [TN] [to] Andrew J. Donelson, Washington City, D[istrict of] Columbia / J. G. Martin   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Martin, J. G.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl280</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1829 Feb. 28, Nashville [TN] [to] Andrew J. Donelson, Washington City, D[istrict of] Columbia / J. G. Martin</title><author>Martin, J. G.</author><date value="1829-02-28">February 28, 1829</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from J. G. Martin to Andrew J. Donelson, dated February 28, 1829. Martin writes about helping Mr Steel with a cotton shipment. He sends the love of Mrs. Martin to Donelson and family. He also writes that he wants news of the President's Inaugural speech.</note><note type="collection">A. J. Donelson Papers</note><note type="box"> I-D-3</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">sl280</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Cotton</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><date value="1829-02-28"><abbr expan="February">Febry</abbr> 28th 1829</date></addrLine><addrLine><abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> <name type="person">Andrew J Donelson</name> &mdash;</addrLine></address><salute><abbr expan="Dear">D</abbr> Sir</salute></opener><p>The Republican of <unclear>Lesteroay</unclear> announced the arrival of the <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> at the City on the 11th <abbr expan="instant">inst</abbr> this being my first knowledge that you had reached your destination, I can now say to you that the <unclear>Genl's Cotton 42 Bales ? 22: 234 asper ? &amp; I and your 10 Bales ? 5.028 </unclear> was shipped on Board <abbr expan="Steam Boat">StmBt</abbr> Cumberland <name type="person">Capt <unclear>Seoi</unclear> Sawless</name> <date value="1829-01-29"><abbr expan="January">Jany</abbr> 29th</date> in good order at the request of <name type="person">Mr Steel</name> I attended to its delivery Bills <unclear>Soony</unclear> &amp; they are yet in my possession but will &caret; <add place="supralinear">be</add> <unclear>handed</unclear> over to Mr Steel when convenient &mdash;</p><p>I have been once or twice, to the hospitable now deserted Hermitage' Steel Keeps all things in fine order &caret; <add place="supralinear">but</add> alas! There is a blank? never again to be filled &mdash;</p><p>Mr Steel told me last sunday that he had but little trouble with the Genl <unclear>hands</unclear> yet some with yours and that the fellow Charles should not <unclear><?xm-replace_text {unclear}?></unclear> on the plan if he could sell him &amp; buy another he says that he feels <add place="supralinear">certain</add> of his running away in Springdale stated to me things went on <orig reg="very">verry</orig> much to his satisfaction no question he is a stirring business man; Your fences; <unclear><?xm-replace_text {unclear}?></unclear> &amp; show that &mdash; <pb n="[2]"/></p><p>My family and our friends I believe are &mdash; generally will without any thing particularly new or interesting &mdash; <name type="person">Mrs Martin</name> presents her <unclear>love to your</unclear> wife; and Cousin Mary with Respects to yourself the Genl; and wishes <del type="overstrike">to</del> you to say to her sister &amp; to Mary that she would be glad to hear from one or both of them &mdash; &amp; that their absence is a greatly regretted by her in one respect yet she is <unclear>intirely</unclear> happy at and Pleasures they may enjoy</p><p>Present me Respectfully to the <unclear>ladies &amp; to</unclear> the Genl</p><closer><salute>with Esteem <unclear><?xm-replace_text {unclear}?></unclear> your most <abbr expan="obedient servant">ob st</abbr></salute><signed><name type="person">J. G. Martin</name></signed><add place="after signature"><abbr expan="Post Script">PS</abbr> any information that you may want in my power to communicate from <unclear>third parts</unclear> shall be cheerfully attended to I shall be glad to hear from you often as my family now!!  with myself have almost the seclusion of cloistered nuns</add><salute>Respectfully</salute><signed>JGM</signed><pb n="[3]"/> Let me see if you Heard  the <abbr expan="President">Pres</abbr> Elects. Inaugural as soon as it comes out and oblige one that is some what out of the way of Mails &mdash; &amp; Yet loves to hear what is going on. <pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine>Capt. Andrew J Donelson</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Washington City</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="District">D</abbr> Columbia</name></addrLine></address><add place="left of address">mail &rcub;</add><add place="down right margin" cert="different hand, ink">Feby 28. Nashville <lb/> <abbr expan="Major">Maj</abbr> Martin &mdash; <lb/> Private</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
