<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl306"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter]  June 2, Washington [City, D. C.] [to] A Fergusson, Carthage, Tenn[essee] / W. B. Campbell   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>W. B. Campbell</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl306</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title> June 2, Washington [City, D. C.] [to] A Fergusson, Carthage, Tenn[essee] / W. B. Campbell</title><author>W. B. Campbell</author><date value="1837-06-02">June 2, 1837</date><extent>2p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter to A. Fergusson from W. B. Campbell, dated June 2, possibly in 1837. Campbell writes that the pension claim of Mrs. Cobb has been suspended for lack of evidence. He writes about an incident that took place in the House. Representative John Bell (TN) hit Representative Hopkins Turney (TN)   for calling him a liar during a speech.</note><note type="collection">Fergusson Papers</note><note type="box">IV-G-1 b2</note><note type="folder">10</note><note type="document">sl306</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Washington</name> June 2 18<unclear>37</unclear></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Sir,</salute></opener><p><name type="person">Mr Edwards</name> informs me that <name type="person">Mrs. Cobb</name>s, claim for a pension is suspended on account of the want of satisfactory proof of the service of  her husband, and of her marriage before the termination of his service. It is now so late in the session that no action of any importance can be had in congress upon the petition of Mrs Cobb, and I have concluded to delay its presentation until the session,_ It is a <unclear>very</unclear> difficult matter to get these claims through &amp; if the proof which Mr. Edwards requires could be possibly obtained, it would be far better <pb n="[2]"/> than to place her claim before congress. many claims of this kind have been before congress for many years &amp; have not yet been acted upon_</p><p>I have no news only that our <name type="person">John Bell</name>, struck <name type="person">Turney</name> of our State yesterday, in the House of <unclear>Representatives</unclear>_ Bell was speaking &amp; Turney, rose up near him &amp; stated that he <abbr expan="Bell">B</abbr> stated a false hood, &amp; B in quick time hit him a blow or two,__ they were separated, &amp; all soon became quiet &amp; B proceeded with his speech. we will adjourn about the 1st July</p><closer><salute>Very Respectfully your <abbr expan="Obedient Servant">Obt Srt</abbr></salute><signed><name type="person">W B Campbell</name></signed><address><addrLine><name type="person">A Fergusson</name> <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Carthage</name></addrLine><addrLine><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr> </addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
