<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl315"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1849 Jun. 27, Gallatin, Tennessee [to] [Adam] Fergusson / Jas. T. Crary   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Crary, Jas. T.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl315</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1849 Jun. 27, Gallatin, Tennessee [to] [Adam] Fergusson / Jas. T. Crary</title><author>Crary, Jas. T.</author><date value="1849-06-27">June 27, 1849</date><extent>2p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from J. T. Crary to Adam Fergusson, dated June 27, 1849. Crary writes about politics in Tennessee. He mentions General Trousdale. He writes that cholera has hit Gallatin very hard. He writes that he wanted to visit Carthage but could not leave his school. He  wants Fergusson to write him with a summary of the speeches that he missed.</note><note type="collection">Fergusson Papers IV-G-1</note><note type="box">3</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">sl315</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Cholera</item><item>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name>Gallatin</name> <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr> <date value="1849-06-27">June 27th 1849</date></addrLine><addrLine>Mr Fergusson,</addrLine></address><salute>Dear Sir:</salute></opener><p><name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Gen</abbr> Trousdale</name> leaves here this morning, (accompanied by <name type="person">Mr. Smith</name>,) for <name type="place">Sparta</name>, I am very sorry that I have not an opportunity to hear the old soldier, but on account of Cholera  we had no speaking here, <name type="person">Gen. Brown</name> is unwell &amp; will not fulfill all the appointments, so Gen. <abbr expan="Trousdale">T.</abbr> will take the field by himself for the present,</p><p>I get most cheering accounts from all parts of the state, The old General's worth is duly appreciated, by true patriotic citizens of <name type="place">Tennessee</name> &amp; he will produce a greater panic in the Whig ranks than that of Cholera, &amp; we can see from the tone of their journals, that they are ala[rmed] <gap reason="document torn"/> considerably, If the Democracy of the State <gap reason="document torn"/> will rouse themselves from <gap reason="document torn"/> unite, themselves, &amp; then <gap reason="document torn"/> am confident of victory, <gap reason="document torn"/></p><p><abbr expan="messieurs">Messrs</abbr> <unclear><name type="person">Gains</name>&amp; <name type="person">Cullam</name></unclear> , I <gap reason="document torn"/> <unclear>triage</unclear> to day, Write to <gap reason="document torn"/> the <unclear>contents</unclear> to the people, that is if <gap reason="document torn"/> for Democracy <name type="person">Mr. Boyers</name> is at home <gap reason="document torn"/> &amp; will do his duty as <unclear>editor</unclear> of the Legion <gap reason="document torn"/></p><pb n="[2]"/><p>The Cholera has made horrible <orig reg="havoc">havok</orig> in town, We have had some 19 or 20 deaths written the past 2 weeks, mostly among negroes, The bankeeper, (Mr <unclear>Esses</unclear> ,) of the Map House, died Monday evening, There are two or three cases now in town,  <name type="person">Mr. Martin</name>, post master, is now sick in my office but not yet dangerous, <name type="person">Mr. Dale</name>, the <orig reg="peddler">pedler</orig>, who was going to take Charles trunk, <abbr expan="and etcetera">&amp;c</abbr> , to him, is sick, &amp; has been ever since my return from <name type="place">Smith</name>, I have been trying to make other arrangements, to send them, but I think the chance is bad, but however, I will send it as soon as possible,</p><p>I would of been highly pleased to of been at <name type="place">Carthage</name> to day, but I have a very large school &amp; cannot neglect it. <name type="person">Mr. Bigley</name> has left, &amp; <name type="person">Mr. Dougless</name> is his successor, As I could not hear the candidates myself, I wish you to write either to me, or T. Boyers, &amp; give an account of the speaking &amp; probable success,</p><p>Give my compliments &amp; esteem to your interesting family, &amp; believe me</p><closer><gap reason="document torn"/><salute>Friend <gap reason="document torn"/> humble servant,</salute><signed><name type="person">Jas T. Crary</name></signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
