<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl316"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter]   1843 Jun. 20, Pension Office [to] A[dam] Fergusson, Carthage, Tennessee / G[eorge] W[illia]m Crump : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Crump, George William</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sl316</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>   1843 Jun. 20, Pension Office [to] A[dam] Fergusson, Carthage, Tennessee / G[eorge] W[illia]m Crump</title><author>Crump, George William</author><date value="1843-06-20">June 20, 1843</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated June 20, 1843, from George William Crump to Adam Fergusson, attorney and pension agent for Tennessee.  Crump writes on the matter of the pension claim of Elizabeth Kelly and her husband William Kelly, who was a member of the revolutionary militiamen.</note><note type="collection">Fergusson Papers</note><note type="box"> IV-G-1 b3</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">sl316</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>War pensions</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine>Pension Office,</addrLine><addrLine><date value="1843-06-20">June 20th 1843</date>.</addrLine></address><salute>Sir,</salute></opener><p>The papers in the case of <name type="person">Elizabeth Kelly</name> claiming a pension under the act of <date value="1838-07-07">7th July 1838</date>, have been examined and placed upon file.  The Declaration should be made before a court of Record, in open Court, except in case of actual bodily inability to attend, when a Judge or Justice of a Court of Record may act out of Court, he certifying the fact of inability.  When the Claim of the husband <name type="person">William Kelly</name> was admitted there were no rolls to which <orig reg="recognize">reconise</orig> could be had to test the services.  There are at present Rolls in the possession of the <orig reg="Comptroller">Comptoller</orig> General of <name type="place">South Carolina</name>, and the certificate of the officer should be produced showing the services performed.  William Kelly in his declaration claims for six months service in the militia of South Carolina  against the Indians, in <date value="1775-00-00">1775</date> , as a Volunteer under <name type="person">Lieutenant John Dairs</name>, <name type="person">Captain James Stein</name>, <name type="person">Colonel John Thomas</name> and <name type="person">General Williamson</name>.  In <date value="1776-00-00">1776</date> as a <orig reg="drafted">draughted</orig> Militiaman under Captain James Stein and <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> John Thomas; one month and ten days in <date value="1779-00-00">1779</date> as a draughted Militiaman under Captain James Stein, <name type="person">Lieutenant Colonel William  Waford</name> three months and twenty days.  In <date value="1781-00-00">1781</date> as a draughted man in <name type="place">north Carolina</name> under <name type="person">Captain Jacob Vinsant</name> and Colonel Po<gap reason="document faded"/> <pb n="[2]"/> months.  If we may judge from the time of the last Service named by the deceased husband, the claim comes properly under the act of 7 July 1838.</p><closer><salute>I am very respectfully, <lb/> Your <abbr expan="obedient">ob</abbr> Servant,</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="George William">G Wm</abbr> Crump</name></signed><add place="bottom left corner"><address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Adam">A</abbr> Fergusson</name>, <abbr expan="Esquire">Esq.</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Carthage</name>,</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine></address></add><pb n="[3]"/> <add place="top of page" cert="different ink"><figure><figDesc>miscellaneous calculations</figDesc></figure></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
