<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl363"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Legal] 1837 Sep. 1, Henry County, Tennessee [to] T. C. Monroe / Joseph Ridgway   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Ridgway, Joseph</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sl363</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1837 Sep. 1, Henry County, Tennessee [to] T. C. Monroe / Joseph Ridgway</title><author>Ridgway, Joseph</author><date value="1837-09-01">September 1, 1837</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a bill of sale dated September 1, 1837. It is between T. C. Monroe and Joseph Ridgway.  Monroe will gain some slaves and land for covering a debt of Ridgway's. Along with the agreement are statements from the County Clerk and the Registrar for Henry County, dated September 9, 1837.</note><note type="collection">Dunlap Papers</note><note type="box"> I-B-4</note><note type="folder">1</note><note type="document">sl363</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Henry County (Tenn.)</item><item>Real property</item><item>Slave trade</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Bill of sale"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><add cert="different hand, ink"><address><addrLine>State of <name>Tennessee</name></addrLine><addrLine><name>Henry County</name>&rcub;</addrLine></address></add></opener><p>I have this day sold and do hereby <orig reg="convey">convay</orig> to <name>T. C. Monroe</name> his <orig reg="heirs">hirrs</orig> and assigns for ever for <add cert="different hank, ink">one ____</add> dollars to me paid two men and one woman slave named <name>Gabriel Humphrey</name> &amp; Sarah I warrant the title to said slaves to the said T. C. Monroe his hirrs and assigns against the lawful claim of all persons and I also warrant them to be sound healthy sensible and slaves for life. also one <unclear>tract</unclear> of land containing fifty acres a part of a three hundred and sixty two acre tract entered in the name of <name>John Swor</name></p><p>The condition of the above obligation is such that the said T. C. Monroe is security for <unclear>now</unclear> that is to say to a note to one <name>John <add>M</add> Clark</name> in the sum of <add cert="different hank, ink">fifteen hundred dollars</add> under seal and date of <add cert="different hand, ink"><date>2 day of June 1837</date></add> due on the <date>2 day of <abbr expan="October">Oct</abbr> 1837</date> where of I am desirous to <unclear>secun</unclear> and make certain the payment of the same.</p><p>Now if I should pay the said debt at the time afore said then this obligation to be void but if I should not then the said T. C. Monroe as <orig reg="trustee">trusttee</orig> after going <unclear>of</unclear> days notice in writing at the court house door of Henry County and the election,, <add><unclear>ground</unclear></add> of the district. <abbr expan="Number">No</abbr>11 and three other public places in the neighborhood  may expose the said negroes and land to public sale and sell to the highest  bidder for cash and appropriate the proceeds first to the payment of the <orig reg="necessary">nessary</orig> <orig reg="expenses">expencis</orig> and cost secondly to the satisfaction of said debt of the <add cert="different hand, ink">sum of fifteen hundred dollars</add> <pb n="[2]"/> and thirdly to pay the <orig reg="balance">ballance</orig> if any there be to me</p><p><add cert="different ink">This <date>1st day of September A. D. 1837</date> In the presence of <name><abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> Ridgway</name>  <lb/><name>W. D. Poe</name> <lb/> <date>8th <abbr expan="September">Sept</abbr></date></add></p><closer><signed><add cert="different ink"><name>Joseph Ridgway</name><figure><figDesc>seal</figDesc></figure></add></signed></closer></div1><div1 type="legal "><opener><address><addrLine>State of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Henry County &rcub;</addrLine></address></opener><p>Personally appeared before me <name>Thomas K Porter</name> Clerk of the county court for said county William Ridgway &amp; W. D Poe witness to the foregoing deed of trust who being first sworn <unclear>upon</unclear> &amp; say they are personally acquainted with Joseph Ridgway the bargainor and that he acknowledged the execution of the same in their presence on the day it bears date &amp; for the purposes there in mentioned</p><p>Witness my hand at office the <date>9th of <abbr expan="September">Sept</abbr> 1837</date></p><closer><signed><abbr expan="Thomas">Tho</abbr> K Porter <abbr expan="clerk">clk</abbr></signed></closer></div1><div1 type="legal"><opener><address><addrLine>State of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Henry County &rcub;</addrLine></address></opener><p>Registry office September the 9th 1837  then the within bill of Sale from Joseph Ridgeway  <sic corr="to">to to</sic> T C Monroe and the certificate of probate were duly registered in my office in book <unclear>&amp;</unclear> and page</p><closer><signed><name>James  <unclear>Leper</unclear></name> <abbr expan="Registrar">Regtr</abbr></signed><lb/> of Henry County <pb n="[3]"/><address><addrLine>Joseph Ridgway</addrLine><addrLine>Bill of Sale <unclear>Tn</unclear></addrLine><addrLine>T. C. Monroe</addrLine></address><add>fees paid</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
