<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl439"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>   [Letter] 1818 Apr. 16, Knoxville, Tennessee [to] John Overton, Nashville, Tennessee / Jos[eph] McMinn : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>McMinn, Joseph</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sl439</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>   [Letter] 1818 Apr. 16, Knoxville, Tennessee [to] John Overton, Nashville, Tennessee / Jos[eph] McMinn</title><author>McMinn, Joseph</author><date value="1818-04-16">April 16, 1818</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated April 16, 1818 from  Governor Joseph McMinn in Knoxville, Tennessee to Judge John Overton in Nashville, Tennessee.  In the letter, McMinn states that he is preparing to set out for the Cherokee agency on request of the president to supervise the  removal of the Cherokee Indians to West of the Mississippi river.</note><note type="collection">Overton Papers</note><note type="box">Correspondence</note><note type="folder">12</note><note type="document">sl439</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee -- History</item><item>Letters</item><item>Cherokee Indians -- Relocation</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener> <address><addrLine><name>Knoxville</name></addrLine></address> <date>16 April 1818</date> <salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>It now very late in the night <orig reg="though">tho</orig> will briefly observe, what judge white mentioned to me this morning that your friend about <name>Nashville</name> <abbr expan="expressed">expresd</abbr>, a wish that you should serve as a commissioner in <orig reg="running">Runing</orig> the line between this state &amp; <name>georgia</name>__</p><p>I intended from the first <del>the</del> to take the commissioner from the East and the mathematician from the west <abbr expan="mister">mr</abbr> Fisk was selected for the cotton, and <abbr expan="colonel">colo</abbr> williams for the former appointment__  It so happened that both declined I then addressed <abbr expan="general">genl</abbr> coffee, and <pb n="[2]"/> <abbr expan="general">genl</abbr> lCocke__ The former <abbr expan="general">genl</abbr> coffee declined__ and <abbr expan="general">genl</abbr> Cocke accepted who stand, as commissioner, major gaines of <name>Franklin</name> county has been solicited as mathematician, who has not answered as yet <abbr expan="though">tho</abbr> from what I have heard I think it probable he will serve </p><p>Thus judge you see how I am circumstanced, and I leave you to determine__ I let out in the morning god willing for the <name>cherokee</name> agency where I shall be stationary for a few weeks, in compliance with a request from the president, who has asked me to superintend the removal the <name>cherokees</name> west of the <name>mississippi</name>  <pb n="[3]"/>  where its expected they will all reside in a short time__ I have fitted out lg Boats all loated with <name>cherokee</name> and their property__  many more are preparing to go on the rise of graf__</p> <closer>god Bless you <signed>Jos. McMinn</signed> <add>P.S I formed my plan of selecting these officers from a belief that the mathematician could be obtained better from the west than the east <name>J McMinn</name> Judge Overton</add>   <pb n="[4]"/> <add><name>Knoxville <abbr expan="Tennessee">T</abbr></name> <date>17 <abbr expan="April">Apl</abbr> 1818</date> <address><addrLine>Honorable John Overton Nashville</addrLine></address> 18 1/2</add>  <add><name>Jos. McMinn</name> <date><abbr expan="April">Apl</abbr> 16th 1818</date></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
