<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl472"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1796 Apr. 25, Tellico Blockhouse [Tennessee, to] David Henley, Knoxville [Tennessee] / John McKee: a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>McKee, John</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sl472</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1796 Apr. 25, Tellico Blockhouse [Tennessee, to] David Henley, Knoxville [Tennessee] / John McKee </title><author>McKee, John</author><date value="1796-04-25">April 25, 1796</date><extent>2p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from John McKee to David Henley, dated April 25, 1796. McKee, who is in charge of Indian relations, is concerned  that the   government will stop giving out whiskey and other amenities to the Chiefs that come to visit. He believes that they will suspect other policies towards them will change also, and become unfriendly.</note><note type="collection">David Henley Collection</note><note type="box">n/a</note><note type="folder">24</note><note type="document">sl472</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee</item><item>Henley, David, 1749-1832.</item><item>Blount, William, 1749-1800</item><item>Indians of North America -- Government policy</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name>Tellico Blockhouse</name><date>April 25th 1796</date></addrLine></address><salute>Sir</salute></opener><p>In my letter to you of the 18th Instant forwarded by <name>Mr Byers</name> I quoted a paragraph of a letter from <name>Governor Blount</name> who as Governor of the <abbr expan="South">S</abbr> Western Territory was Superintendant of Indians affairs for the Southern District respecting necessary expenditures in the Indian department to which I have yet <orig reg="received">recieved</orig> no answer</p><p>Heretofore when any principal chiefs or other Indians on public business came to this place I was authorized to supply them with provisions whiskey and such articles of <orig reg="clothing">cloathing</orig> at their services <orig reg="entitled">intitled</orig> them to, and should such supplies be now with held I fear it would excite in them a suspicion that the late change of Government in this country is connected with a Change of the disposition of the <name>United States</name> towards their nation, which might be attended with the worst consequences.__ Permit me, Sir, again to solicit your attention to this subject and to request the favor of a line by the first opportunity.</p><closer><salute>I am, Sir, with respect <lb/> your Obedient Servant</salute><signed><name>John McKee</name></signed><address><addrLine><abbr expan="Colonel David">Col D</abbr> Henley</addrLine><addrLine>Agent <abbr expan="Department">Dept</abbr> War</addrLine></address><pb n="[2]"/><address><addrLine><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo</abbr> <name>David Henley</name></addrLine><addrLine>Agent Department of War</addrLine><addrLine><name>Knoxville</name></addrLine></address><add><name>Mr Dinmoor</name></add><add>Tellico <lb/> April 25 1796 <lb/> Col John McKee</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
