<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl489"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1823 Apr. 15, Cairo, Tennessee [to] John Overton, Nashville, Tennessee / James Winchester   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Winchester, James</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name> </respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sl489</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1823 Apr. 15, Cairo, Tennessee [to] John Overton, Nashville, Tennessee / James Winchester</title><author>Winchester, James</author><date value="1823-04-15">April 15, 1823</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated April 15, 1823 from James Winchester in Cairo, Tennessee to John Overton in Nashville, Tennessee.  It is a brief, one-sided letter, and its subject matter is not completely clear.   Winchester mentions opposition to  Memphis in an unknown matter, and developing strategy for court.</note><note type="collection">James Winchester Papers</note><note type="box">2</note><note type="folder">3</note><note type="document">sl489</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee -- History</item><item>Letters</item><item>Court administration</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine>Cairo</addrLine></address> <date>15th April 1823</date> <salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>I have had the satisfaction to receive your <orig reg="favor">favour</orig> of the 4th instant on the subject of the interests of <name>Memphis</name>, <abbr expan="though">tho</abbr> only by last mail, I have great confidence in your <orig reg="vigilance">vigilince</orig> and skill to counter act the plans and intrigues of the opposition to that place and shall accordingly <unclear>requites</unclear> in all you do on that subject, for those whom I represent as well as for myself, I would have hastened to your house in order to have had a personal interview But my partner <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Cage has gone to <name>Huntsville</name>, and my son is frequently absent on business of the <name>C.S. Bunt <abbr expan="Company">Co</abbr></name> I am therefore necessarily confined to this place at present moreover I have considered that no plan of defence could be advantageously formed at this distance from the place of return, You must be <orig reg="governed">governd</orig> by circumstances in the spot that is in the vicinity of the premises, I have no doubt but you will find a numerous combination for removing the place of holding courts, but that number will be very much reduced when the opposition comes to fix on the spot at which they will remove to, have I think you <pb n="[2]"/> you will find room to maneuver, It will I expect be much easier to convince many when the court ought not to be held, than <orig reg="when">whene</orig> they ought to be held, But I need not advise nor even in time a course for you to pursue who are much better qualified for the duties to be <orig reg="performed">performd</orig> than I am</p><closer>Respectfully and Sincerely Your Obedient <abbr expan="Servant">Svnt</abbr> <signed><abbr expan="James">J</abbr> Winchester</signed> <add>Judge Overton</add> <pb n="[3]"/><address><addrLine> Cairo <abbr expan="Tennessee">T</abbr></addrLine></address> <date>April 15</date>  <address><addrLine>Judge John Overton Nashville</addrLine></address> <add><abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> <name><abbr expan="James">Ja</abbr> Winchester</name> <date><abbr expan="April">Apl</abbr> 15th 1823</date></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
