<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl554"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1806 Aug 17, Knoxville [Tennessee, to] James Winchester,  Sumner County [Tennessee] / Sampson Williams et. al.   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Williams, S[ampson]</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sl554</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1806 Aug 17, Knoxville [Tennessee, to] James Winchester,  Sumner County [Tennessee] / Sampson Williams et. al.</title><author>Williams, S[ampson]</author><date value="1806-08-17">August 17, 1806</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Sampson Williams and John Wynne to General James Winchester, dated August 17, 1806. Williams and Wynne inform Winchester of some Bills that propose to divide Tennessee into administrative districts. They describe the details such as locations and  reactions to the idea. They  mention that some people want to call a constitutional convention. Winchester is asked if he plans on running for Congress. If so, they assure him of support.</note><note type="collection">James Winchester Papers</note><note type="box">3</note><note type="folder">11</note><note type="document">sl554</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee</item><item>Winchester, James, 1752-1826</item><item>Politics</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name>Knoxville</name> <date>August 17th 1806</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>As we Know you are anxious to hear the probable result of the deliberations of the collected wisdom of <name>Tennessee</name> we shall here endeavour to give you the out lines of the most important matters which have yet come before us in the course of the Session__ at the commencement of the Session a committee was appointed to take into consideration our landed business that committee has been busily engaged ever Since in Sketching out a land system and will be able to report tomorrow by Bills which contemplates dividing the State into Six Districts in the following manner the Military reservation to make one, South of the Military <orig reg="reservation">reservasion</orig> and west of a <orig reg="meridian">meredian</orig> line from the south east corner of the military reservasion to form an other, and East of that line to the dividing waters on the top of <name>Cumberland Mountain</name> to make an other_ one south of <name>French Broad</name>, and two others of these two Districts and to appoint a Surveyor General in each District_ and two registers of the Land office, one in East and one in west Tennessee and a Board of <pb n="[2]"/> commissioners to examine into all existing claims all of whose duties are well defined and proper restrictions laid on them for a breach of duty except the board of commissioners <orig reg="whose">whoes</orig> <orig reg="powers">prowers</orig> are unlimited and their decisions final- but to this measure there is considerable <orig reg="opposition">oposition</orig> _ Some are anxious for going on to perfect titles <orig reg="immediately">immediatly</orig> without the investigation of frauds and what the final result may be is uncertain, but we rather think the plan first sketched out most likely to <orig reg="Succeed">Suceed</orig> _ and all west <del type="overstrike">Tennessee</del> <add>of <name>big Pigeon</name></add> and South of French Broad to be Surveyed and an accurate <orig reg="plan">plann</orig> thereof <gap/> returned to each Surveyor General __ before enties are made__ the people South of French Broad <abbr expan="etcetera">&amp;c</abbr> to have their land at one Dollar <abbr expan="per">pr</abbr> acre payable <orig reg="annually">anually</orig> in ten equal <orig reg="installments">instalments</orig> with interest__</p><p>The <orig reg="College">Colledge</orig> in west Tennessee to be Established at <name>Nashville</name> but not determined <add>where</add> in this end of the State__ where would you wish the <orig reg="academy">accadamy</orig> Established in your County-</p><p>the call of a convention is again <orig reg="agitated">adgitated</orig> but not yet decided upon- but the most violent Exertions are <orig reg="resorted">rsorted</orig> to to convince <pb n="[3]"/> the members of the propriety of such <orig reg="measure">mesure</orig> , but <name>Wilkerson</name> in the <orig reg="Senate">Sinate</orig> and <name>Lillard</name> in the representatives have so far acted consistently and if they remain so, we shall be able to baffle all their Efforts-</p><p>we shall also take the liberty to ask you <orig reg="whether">wheather</orig> you are, or intend being a candidate for Congress, we have both before we left home held up your name, and we <add>think you</add> will get nearly a unanimous vote in our respective Counties-- but we discover <orig reg="electioneering">electionering</orig> here and we should <add>be glad</add> to Say we were <orig reg="authorized">authorised</orig> from you, to say <add>you</add> were a candidate as we both conceive ourselves doubly bound to Support your Election Should you be a candidate- it is here Stated you will not be a candidate</p><p>Accept the assurances of our Esteem and well wishes for your health and happiness</p><closer><signed>S,, Williams</signed><signed><name>John  K Wynne</name></signed><add><abbr expan="Post Script">PS</abbr> when anything transpires that we think interesting to you or any of our fellow citizens you shall be advised thereof <name><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo</abbr> Douglas</name> agrees with us and desires to be remembered</add><signed><abbr expan="Sampsom Williams">SW</abbr></signed><signed><abbr expan="John K. Wynne">J KW</abbr></signed><pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine>Sampson Williams</addrLine><addrLine><add>&amp;</add> John K. Wynne</addrLine><addrLine>17th <abbr expan="August">Augt</abbr></addrLine></address><add>Free</add><address><addrLine><abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> James Winchester</addrLine><addrLine><unclear>PM</unclear></addrLine><addrLine><name>Sumner County</name></addrLine><addrLine><name>Cragfont</name></addrLine></address><add>Exertions are rsorted...</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
