<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl586"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1808 Apr. 22, Chickasaw Nation [to] James Winchester, Sumner County, Tennessee / Thomas Wright   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Wright, Thomas</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sl586</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>1808 Apr. 22, Chickasaw Nation [to] James Winchester, Sumner County, Tennessee / Thomas Wright</title><author>Wright, Thomas</author><date value="1808-04-22">April 22, 1808</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter from Thomas Wright to General James Winchester, dated April 22, 1808. Wright is the U. S. agent to the Chickasaw Nation. Wright is writing on behalf of a Chickasaw who is inquiring about the fate of his brother. The man is rumored to  have been killed in the area of Sumner County, therefore Wright hopes that Winchester has heard of it.</note><note type="collection">James Winchester Papers</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">11</note><note type="document">sl586</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee</item><item>Chickasaw Indians</item><item>Winchester, James, 1752-1826</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name>Chickasaw Nation</name></addrLine><addrLine><date>april 22d 1808</date></addrLine></address><salute>Sir</salute></opener><p>a Native of this Nation came to me this morning requesting me to write to you for information respecting his Brother who he was informed was killed (perhaps shot) in your <orig reg="Neighborhood">Neighbourhood</orig> some time during the last fall or winter. he appears <orig reg="anxious">anctious</orig> to know the truth of the report. The Chickasaw that is missing has been absent for two or three years in which time he has been to <name>Washington City</name> &amp; perhaps to <name>Baltimore</name> and <name>Philadelphia</name>; last year had returned home ward as far as <name>Duck river</name>, there exchanged some property he had obtained by some means for whiskey and returned back-shortly after which it is reported he was killed in, or in the vicinity of the Neigh <pb n="[2]"/> bourhood in which you reside. should any such circumstance have happened, it probably would have come to your knowledge, and in order to establish the confidence of the Nation of Indians among whom I reside, in the Government of the <name><abbr expan="United">U.</abbr> States</name>; I am willing to give them every <orig reg="explanatory">explanitory</orig> satisfaction in my power; where a doubt could subsist of their confidence being misplaced. I am the more particular as some of the neighbouring Indians (the <name>Creek</name>s in particular) appear to be so ignorant of their own welfare, as to commit depredations on our frontier settlements.</p><p>will you be so obliging as too inform me by letter whether any such circumstance (as the above named) has happened within your neighborhood, and if in the <orig reg="affirmative">afirmative</orig> please name the circumstances.</p><closer><salute>I am respectfully <lb/> sir your <abbr expan="Obedient Servant">Ob Servt</abbr></salute><signed><name>Thomas Wright</name> <lb/> U. <abbr expan="States Agent">S. Agt</abbr> to the Chickasaws</signed><address><addrLine><name><abbr expan="General">Gen</abbr> __ Winchester</name></addrLine></address><pb n="[3]"/> <add>Answered <lb/> 22d may 1808</add> <add>Free</add> <add>Th. Wright P.M.</add><address><addrLine>Gen__ Winchester</addrLine><addrLine><name>Sumner County</name></addrLine><addrLine><abbr expan="West">W.</abbr> <name>Tennessee</name></addrLine></address><add>Mail</add><address><addrLine>Thomas Wright</addrLine><addrLine><name>chickasaw Bluffs</name></addrLine><addrLine>22d <abbr expan="April">Apl</abbr> 1808</addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
