<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl590"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Stay of Execution ] 1846 Jun. 10 [for] Clarissa, a slave / Aaron Brown   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Brown, Aaron</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Hardin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sl590</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Stay of Execution ] 1846 Jun. 10 [for] Clarissa, a slave / Aaron Brown</title><author>Brown, Aaron</author><date value="1846-06-10">June 10, 1846</date><extent>2p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a 23 day stay of execution from Tennessee Governor Aaron Venable Brown for a slave named Clarissa, who was convicted of infanticide by the Circuit court for Franklin County.  The governor ordered the stay in order to review the case.</note><note type="collection">Governor Aaron V. Brown Papers</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">1</note><note type="document">sl590</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Tennessee -- History</item><item>Slavery</item><item>Letters</item><item>Brown, Aaron V. (Aaron Venable), 1795-1859</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Stay of Execution"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine>State of Tennessee</addrLine></address></opener><p><name>Aaron V. Brown</name> Governor of the Same To all who shall see these presents; Greeting <lb/> Whereas it has been represented to me that at a late Term of the Circuit Court for <name>Franklin County</name>, a certain negro woman slave named Clarissa was convicted of Infanticide or murder, and was Thereupon adjudged by the court to be hanged on the 12th <abbr expan="Instant">Inst</abbr>. and whereas it has also been represented to me that the said Clarissa is a fit object of Executive Clemency </p><p>Now therefore and that the subject may be the more fully inquired of, and examined by me.  I do by virtue of the Power &amp; authority in me rested, hereby require and direct that the execution of said judgment on the said slave be delayed and postponed until <date>Friday The Third day of July</date> next and that on the said <date>3rd day of July 1846</date> the sentence and judgment of the Court aforesaid be had and executed</p><p>Given under my hand this <date>10th day of June 1846</date> &amp; carried the great seal of the state to be <unclear>moved</unclear> <gap reason="cut out"/> <abbr expan="governor">gov</abbr> of <name>Tennessee</name> <pb n="[2]"/> <add>Clarissa <abbr expan="Respecting">Respect</abbr></add></p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
