<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl673">
  <teiHeader>
	 <fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
		  <title>[Letter] 1840 Feb. 25, Murfreesboro, Tennessee [to] Levi Woodbury / M. Spence : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
		  <author> Spence, M.</author>
		  <respStmt>
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
			 <name>Debra Roney</name>
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name>
		  </respStmt>
		</titleStmt>
		<publicationStmt>
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
		  <address>
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
		  </address>
		  <date>2003
		  </date>
		  <idno type="SPCID">sl673</idno>
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
		  <availability>
			 <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
		  </availability>
		</publicationStmt>
		<sourceDesc>
		  <bibl>
			 <title> [Letter] 1840 Feb. 25, Murfreesboro, Tennessee [to] Levi Woodbury / M. Spence</title>
			 <author>  Spence, M.</author>
			 <date value="1840-02-25"> 
			 February 25, 1840</date>
			 <extent>3p</extent>
			 <note type="summary">This document is a letter dated February 25, 1840 from M. Spence on behalf of the Nashville Murfreesboro &amp; Shelbyville Turnpike Company, to Levi Woodbury.  The purpose of the letter is to assure payment of interest due on the state bond; Spence cites scarcity of specie for the delay.</note>
			 <note type="collection">Governor James K. Polk Papers</note>
			 <note type="box">1</note>
			 <note type="folder">9</note>
			 <note type="document"> sl673</note>
		  </bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	 </fileDesc>
	 <encodingDesc>
		<projectDesc>
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
		</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="4">
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
		</editorialDecl>
		<refsDecl>
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
		</refsDecl>
		<classDecl>
		  <taxonomy>
			 <bibl>
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
			 </bibl>
		  </taxonomy>
		</classDecl>
	 </encodingDesc>
	 <profileDesc>
		<textClass>
		  <keywords>
			 <list>
				<item>Tennessee -- History</item><item>Tennessee. Governor (1839-1841 : Polk)</item><item>Polk, James K. (James Knox), 1795-1849</item>
			 </list>
		  </keywords>
		</textClass>
	 </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
	 <body>
		<div1 type="Letter"><pb n="1"/>
		  <opener><address><addrLine>Murfreesboro Tennessee</addrLine></address><date><abbr expan="February">Feby</abbr> 25th 1840</date><add><abbr expan="Honorable">Hon</abbr> <name>Levi Woodburry</name> <abbr expan="Secretary of the Treasury">Secty Trea</abbr></add><salute>Sir</salute></opener><p>The cashier of the union bank of <name>Tennessee</name> called on me as treasurer of the <name>Nashville Murfreesboro &amp; Shelbyville Turnpike Company</name> for the semi annual  payment of Interest due on the State Bond which fell due last month  and I am sorry to inform you that the payment as yet has not been made which is in consequence of the great scarcity of specie here, and in Nashville. the Company, having nothing but the Common Currency on hand but so soon as the demand was made myself and other members of the Company.  made every effort to procure the amount in specie but we could not obtain it at any rate as almost every dollar has been <orig reg="bought">boughte</orig> up and carried off by a salt Company and others but I have no doubt but the amount can be obtained in a few days if so you may be assured the <abbr expan="amount">amt</abbr> will be paid over immediately and my object in writing to you was to inform you that the delay in payment was not caused by any neglect <pb n="[2]"/> or <unclear>inattention</unclear>   on the part of the Company but alone for the unexpected scarcity of the proper sort of funds to make the payment <unclear>in,</unclear> but I again assure you that every exertion will be used in paying the amount which I have no doubt will be in a few days</p>
		<closer><add>with respect I am your <abbr>obt sert</abbr></add><signed><name>M Spence</name></signed> <add>Treasurer <abbr expan="Nashville Murfreesboro &amp; Shelbyville  ">N.M &amp; S</abbr> Turnpike <abbr expan="Company">Co</abbr>.</add><pb n="[3]"/> <add><address><addrLine>Hon Levi Woodburry <abbr expan="secretary">scty</abbr> Treasurey N States Washington City</addrLine></address>T. No 103 <unclear>March 6</unclear></add></closer></div1>
	 </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
