<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl694">
  <teiHeader>
	 <fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
		  <title>[Petition] Stuart County Kentucky, re: Walkers line [to] Sam Houston  / Citizens of Stuart County : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
		  <author> Citizens of Stuart County</author>
		  <respStmt>
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
			 <name>Debra Roney</name>
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name>
		  </respStmt>
		</titleStmt>
		<publicationStmt>
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
		  <address>
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
		  </address>
		  <date>2003
		  </date>
		  <idno type="SPCID">sl694</idno>
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
		  <availability>
			 <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
		  </availability>
		</publicationStmt>
		<sourceDesc>
		  <bibl>
			 <title> [Petition] Stuart County Kentucky, re: Walkers line [to] Sam Houston  / Citizens of Stuart County </title>
			 <author> Citizens of Stuart County</author>
			 <date value="1828-00-00"> 
			 ca. 1828</date>
			 <extent>2p</extent>
			 <note type="summary">This document is a petition to governor Sam Houston of Tennessee regarding the settling of the state boundary line separating Stuart and Trigg counties on the Tennessee/Kentucky border.</note>
			 <note type="collection">Governor Sam Houston Papers</note>
			 <note type="box">1</note>
			 <note type="folder">3</note>
			 <note type="document"> sl694</note>
		  </bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	 </fileDesc>
	 <encodingDesc>
		<projectDesc>
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
		</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="4">
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
		</editorialDecl>
		<refsDecl>
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
		</refsDecl>
		<classDecl>
		  <taxonomy>
			 <bibl>
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
			 </bibl>
		  </taxonomy>
		</classDecl>
	 </encodingDesc>
	 <profileDesc>
		<textClass>
		  <keywords>
			 <list>
				<item>Tennessee -- History</item><item>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</item><item>Houston, Sam, 1793-1863.</item>
			 </list>
		  </keywords>
		</textClass>
	 </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
	 <body>
		<div1 type="Petition"><pb n="1"/>
		  <opener><add>To his Excellency <name>Samuel Houston</name> Governor of <name>Tennessee</name></add></opener><p>The undersigned beg leave to call your attention to the subject of settling the state boundary line in that part that separates <name>stuart</name>, &amp; <name>Trigg</name> counties as the Legislature of <name>Kentucky</name> hath passed a resolution on that subject, and as you will be called on by the Execution of that state to cooperate with him in that business, we with due deference would suggest the following remarks, That owing to a line found having the appearance of Walker's marks.  Extending from two miles East of <name>Cumberland</name> to the <name>Tennessee River</name> about two miles north and unconnected with the line run by Walker.  as directed by the Government of <name>virginia</name> from the Southeast corner of the State of Kentucky which refuted line hath been a source of much perplexity  <orig reg="growing">growin</orig> out of the excessive  power by the officers of both states over a few <unclear>inhabitants</unclear> <gap reason="document is faded"/> over which each claim jurisdiction that the Territory is small Say 18 or 20 square miles which we presume of too little magnitude to be regarded as an object with either state or Counties &amp; <orig reg="adjoining">ajoining</orig> and we suppose the Legislature of Kentucky noted the subject with a special  view to the relief of us that is <orig reg="acquired">aquired</orig> and as we are unable to perceive how surveyors that may be appointed by the chief <unclear>majestry</unclear>  of the two states__ with the article of <unclear>Stipulation</unclear> of the <date>11th of February 1820</date> entered into by the <pb n="[2]"/> commissioners appointed by both States before them can connect those lines without doing  violence to other parts of the compact we would further remark that whether those marks north of walkers general line were made by walker and little to the purpose walker  work out to be a strait line extending to the Tennessee River this would give uniformity to the boundary between the two states and tranquility to the people immediately interested, with this view of the Subject we would respectfully submit, the following (viz) that in your correspondence with the Executive of <name>Kentucky</name> you permit him by his surveyor or surveyors to remark and settle walkers line from  the South east corner of Trigg County to the Tennessee River, and where no marks can be found that he shall be governed by the course of  Said line.  We believe this would be in strict conformity with the expectation &amp; praise worthy spirit in which the stipulation was made</p><p>We tender these remarks with feelings &amp; <unclear>views</unclear>  congenial with that vital self governing principle that so <unclear>eminently</unclear> adorns our system of government</p><p><table><row><cell>Names</cell><cell>Names</cell></row><row><cell><name>1 Sam <add>his mark</add> L Sells</name></cell><cell><name>Herman J Downs</name></cell></row><row><cell><name>John J Acree</name></cell><cell><name><abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> C Jones</name></cell></row><row><cell><name>Joshua Sheelan</name></cell><cell><name>Elisha M Hain</name></cell></row><row><cell><name>Robert Hamletten</name></cell><cell><name>Thomas B Powell</name></cell></row><row><cell><name>Charles hamlleton</name></cell><cell><name>David Charhill</name></cell></row><row><cell><name>James Charhill</name></cell><cell><name>Thos. S. Elliott</name></cell></row><row><cell><name>Enous outland</name></cell><cell><name>Nathan Skinner</name></cell></row><row><cell><name>Jordan Champain</name></cell><cell> </cell></row></table></p><p><pb n="3"/> <name>Robin W. Wells</name><name>John Skinner</name><name>Ebenezer L Brown</name><name>Lewis H Jernigan</name><name>Jesse Brown</name><name>James Mcdelee</name><name>Christopher Brandon</name><name>Joseph Shaw</name><name>Allen Elliott</name><name>Isaac McKinney</name><name>Jonathan Eliott</name><name>lewis Pryor</name><name>David Morris</name><name>David Grants</name><name>Cornelius Manning</name><name>Abraham Franklin</name><name>Samael Kennady</name><name>Jonathan Eloatt Juner</name><name>Samuel Canadway Senor</name><name>Henry King</name><name>Lewis Eliott</name><name>Daniel Skinner</name><name>Henry Dunkin</name><pb n="4"/> <address><addrLine>Canton <abbr expan="Kentucky">Ky</abbr>&lcub; Paid<date>14 March</date> His Excellency<name> Samuel <orig reg="Houston">Huston</orig></name></addrLine><addrLine>Nashville <abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></addrLine></address><add>Walkers Line <lb/> Stuart County</add></p>
		</div1>
	 </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
