<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl705">
  <teiHeader>
	 <fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
		  <title>[Letter] 1805 Jul. 29, Blount County [to] John Sevier, Nashville, Tennessee / Colonel Jas Scott : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
		  <author>Scott, Jas</author>
		  <respStmt>
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
			 <name>Debra Roney</name>
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name>
		  </respStmt>
		</titleStmt>
		<publicationStmt>
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
		  <address>
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
		  </address>
		  <date>2003
		  </date>
		  <idno type="SPCID">sl705</idno>
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
		  <availability>
			 <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
		  </availability>
		</publicationStmt>
		<sourceDesc>
		  <bibl>
			 <title>[Letter] 1805 Jul. 29, Blount County [to] John Sevier, Nashville, Tennessee / Colonel Jas Scott </title>
			 <author> Scott, Jas</author>
			 <date value="1805-07-29"> 
			 July 29, 1805</date>
			 <extent>3p</extent>
			 <note type="summary">This document is a letter dated July 29, 1805 from Colonel Scott to governor John Sevier of Nashville, Tennessee.  The purpose of the letter is to ask assistance in a matter relating to an alleged complaint of stolen and damaged property sustained by a resident of Blount county by several Cherokee Indians.</note>
			 <note type="collection">Governor John Sevier Papers</note>
			 <note type="box">1</note>
			 <note type="folder">8</note>
			 <note type="document"> sl705</note>
		  </bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	 </fileDesc>
	 <encodingDesc>
		<projectDesc>
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
		</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="4">
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
		</editorialDecl>
		<refsDecl>
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
		</refsDecl>
		<classDecl>
		  <taxonomy>
			 <bibl>
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
			 </bibl>
		  </taxonomy>
		</classDecl>
	 </encodingDesc>
	 <profileDesc>
		<textClass>
		  <keywords>
			 <list>
				<item>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</item><item>Cherokee Indians -- Claims against</item><item>Tennessee -- History</item><item>Sevier, John, 1745-1815</item>
			 </list>
		  </keywords>
		</textClass>
	 </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
	 <body>
		<div1 type="Letter"><pb n="1"/>
		  <opener><address><addrLine>Blount County</addrLine></address>  <date>July 29 1805</date> <salute>sir</salute></opener><p>On the 25 <abbr expan="Instant">Inst</abbr>, Mr William McNabb Inhabitant of six Mile came to My House with a complaint of  Injuries He had sustained by some of His <orig reg="Neighbors">Neighbours</orig> the Cherokees <orig reg="they">the</orig>  came to His House in A pleasant friendship and Asked for Bread Which he gave them and on their Return Home the Went through his Cornfield and Cut up part of His Corn he <orig reg="supposes">suposes</orig> About <del type="overstrike">Across his</del>    three or four rows    Across his field which was forty <unclear>acres</unclear>   the Also cut up the greater part of His vines and their produce__</p><p>He is very <orig reg="suspicious">suspeicious</orig> by their Conduct the Intend something more Hostile to himself or family he Wishes <orig reg="Inquiry">Inquirey</orig> made to know the Cause <pb n="[2]"/> of such conduct as He never gave them no Cause of offence neither Were they Intoxicated With Spirits and Cannot Possibly have any <unclear>Cloak</unclear> for their Conduct__ I <add>hope</add> your Excellency Will Endeavour to procure Information What the Cause of such treatment Was and have <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> McNabb Made the <orig reg="situation">stituation</orig> for the Loss he has sustained as he has taken the Legal status Which the Law Directs__ here the offence Appears very trifling but I find the officers of the general <orig reg="government">goverment</orig>  Very <orig reg="Tentative">Tenative</orig> of the Rights and <orig reg="privileges">priviliges</orig>  of the Cherokees and I hope We Will be <orig reg="Equally">Eaquely</orig>          supported in our Rights</p>
		<closer><add>I have the <orig reg="Honor">Honour</orig> to be your Excellency's Most <abbr expan="Obedient Servant">Obed servt</abbr></add>  <signed><name>Jas Scott</name></signed> <pb n="[3]"/>  <add><address><addrLine>His Excellency John Sevier <lb/> Knoxville</addrLine></address> <lb/> <abbr expan="Colonel">Colo</abbr> Scott Letters <lb/>  <abbr expan="Answered">Ansd</abbr>. <date>12th August 1805</date></add></closer></div1>
	 </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
