<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sl759">
  <teiHeader>
	 <fileDesc>
		<titleStmt>
		  <title>[Affidavit] 1818 Jan. 18, Knox County, Tennessee [to] Robert Lindsay / Jesse Terry  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
		  <author>Terry, Jesse</author>
		  <respStmt>
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
			 <name>Debra Roney</name>
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name>
		  </respStmt>
		</titleStmt>
		<publicationStmt>
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
		  <address>
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
		  </address>
		  <date>2003
		  </date>
		  <idno type="SPCID">sl759</idno>
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
		  <availability>
			 <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
		  </availability>
		</publicationStmt>
		<sourceDesc>
		  <bibl>
			 <title> [Affidavit] 1818 Jan. 18, Knox County, Tennessee [to] Robert Lindsay / Jesse Terry</title>
			 <author>Terry, Jesse</author>
			 <date value="1818-01-18">January 18, 1818</date>
			 <extent>4p</extent>
			 <note type="summary">This document is an affidavit dated January 18, 1818, it is the result of the deposition of Jesse Terry, of Roane County, Tennessee  by a justice of Knox County, Robert Lindsay.  The subject of the affidavit is a "free girl of color" named Peggy Scott who was believed to be stolen from her parents in Roane County and taken to Georgia.</note>
			 <note type="collection">Governor Joseph McMinn Papers</note>
			 <note type="box">1</note>
			 <note type="folder">4</note>
			 <note type="document"> sl759</note>
		  </bibl>
		</sourceDesc>
	 </fileDesc>
	 <encodingDesc>
		<projectDesc>
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
		</projectDesc>
		<editorialDecl n="4">
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
		</editorialDecl>
		<refsDecl>
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
		</refsDecl>
		<classDecl>
		  <taxonomy>
			 <bibl>
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
			 </bibl>
		  </taxonomy>
		</classDecl>
	 </encodingDesc>
	 <profileDesc>
		<textClass>
		  <keywords>
			 <list>
				<item>Tennessee -- History</item><item>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</item><item>McMinn, Joseph, 1758-1824</item>
			 </list>
		  </keywords>
		</textClass>
	 </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
	 <body>
		<div1 type="Affidavit"><pb n="1"/>
		  <opener><address><addrLine>State of Tennessee <lb/>   Knox County</addrLine></address></opener><p>This day <name>Jesse Terry</name> of <name>Roane county</name> appeared before me <name><abbr expan="Robert">Robt</abbr> Lindsay</name> __ a justice of said County of <name>Knox</name> and being duly sworn <orig reg="deposed">deposeth</orig> and saith  That he has seen in the <orig reg="possession">posession</orig> of a certain <name>William Starne</name> in <name>Clark County</name> <name>Georgia</name> a girl of <orig reg="color">colour</orig> which is the reputed daughter  of a certain <name>Daniel Scott</name> of <name>Roane County</name> <name>Tennessee</name> who is a free man of colour  Said girl Peggy has lived with said Daniel Scott and been always heretofore reputed free__ that Deponent has seen in the posession of said <unclear>Starne</unclear>  a Bill of sale for said girl Peggy dated the <date>22 <abbr expan="November">Nov</abbr>. 1817</date> Signed by a certain <name>Edward Kindred</name>and <name>Mary Holt</name> of <name>Morgan County</name> that he knows the Signature of <name>Edward Kindred</name> to be genuine and that of Edward Kindred of said Morgan County__ that Deponent believes said girl Peggy Scott was stolen from her parents in Roane County and carried to georgia and held as aforesaid by said Edward Kindred <pb n="[2]"/> and Mary Holt otherwise called <name>Mary Ann Neal</name></p><p>and that said Edward and Mary have since as Deponent is informed and believes, absconded from their former residence and fled from justice</p>
		<closer><add>Sworn to and <unclear>Subscribed</unclear>  the <date>18th day of <abbr expan="January">Jary</abbr> 1818</date>   <abbr expan="Robert">Robt</abbr> Lindsay as Justice of peace Knox County</add><signed><name>Jesse Terry</name></signed> <pb n="[3]"/>   <add>About 5 <abbr expan="feet">ft</abbr> 11 inches__ 30 years of age__ fair Hair blue__ fair complexion__ <lb/> M A Neill__ about common size__ 3-__ <abbr expan="years">yrs</abbr> age__ black Hair, black eyes</add> <pb n="[4]"/>     <add>Jesse Terry relative to the case of <abbr expan="Edward">E</abbr> Kindred &amp; Mary Holt also Mary Ann Neal <lb/> 1818 Negro Stealing</add></closer></div1>
	 </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
