<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0045">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles of Agreement [1803 Oct. 20] between the United States and the Cherokee Nation : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0045</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Articles of Agreement [1803 Oct. 20] between the United States and the Cherokee Nation</title>
               <date when="1803-10-20">October 20, 1803</date>
               <extent> 3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a legal agreement dated October 20, 1803, between the Cherokee Nation and the United States to build a turnpike through Tennessee to Georgia.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0045</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Legal documents</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Government relations</term>
               <term>Turnpikes</term>
               <term>Georgia</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0045a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>Articles of Agreement between the <del>Cherokee Nation</del>
               <add>
                  <name>United States</name>
               </add> and the <name>Cherokee Nation</name> for opening <del type="overstrike">&amp; establishing</del> a road through the said nation from the State of <name>Tennessee</name> to the State of <name>Georgia</name>
            </head>
            <p>Article 1st- We the <add>Headmen &amp;</add> warriors of the Cherokee nation- agree <del type="overstrike">to open a Communication</del> that the United States may open <del type="overstrike">a road</del>
               <add>communication</add> from the State of Tennessee to the State of Georgia. Solely at their expense.</p>
            <p>Article 2nd.  The Cherokee nation reserve to themselves the advantages of the <del type="overstrike">Ferries</del>
               <add>
                  <unclear>Ferries</unclear> &amp; Stand</add> on the said road, &amp; agree that one Ferry shall be kept at <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>so.</abbr>
                     <expan>south</expan>
                  </choice> west point</name>, one at <name>Tellico</name> &amp; one at the <name>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Chatahouchee</orig>
                     <reg>Chatahoochie</reg>
                  </choice> River</name>   &amp; that <del type="overstrike">(unclear)</del> the said Ferries to wit at Tellico &amp; at the place where the said road shall Cross the Chatahoochie River shall be rented by the Agent for the Cherokees to Citizens of the United States (to the highest bidder) for the benefit of the Cherokee nation for the term <del type="overstrike">not exceed</del> of five years &amp; that at the expiration of the <del type="overstrike">(unclear)</del> the said Ferries shall revert to the said Cherokee nation, when the Leases shall be renewed or kept by the Cherokees</p>
            <p>Article 3- The Cherokee nation shall establish Houses <add>of <unclear>inferlamorent</unclear>
               </add> on the said road at three place; exclusive of those that <del type="overstrike">will</del>
               <add>shall</add> be established at the Ferries.</p>
            <p>Article 4 It is hereby stipulated that after the said road shall be opened by the U. States- The Cherokee nation shall form themselves into Turnpike Company with <unclear>their counties</unclear>
               <add>for <unclear>keeping the</unclear>
               </add> &amp; in order to preserve <gap/>
               <pb n="2" facs="pa0045b.small.jpg"/> on the said road, it is the request of the Cherokee nation that the United States will plan a military force, not less than a Subalterns Command at or near the point where the said road shall <unclear>extend</unclear> the Georgia line to wit <add>
                  <unclear>a line</unclear>
               </add>
               <name>Jackson County</name> in the <del type="overstrike">said</del> State of Georgia <add>as aforesaid</add>- on the Cherokee lands, of which a sufficient quantity shall be appropriated for wood &amp; for the garrison &amp; the United States shall make such regulations as may be found necessary to prevent persons <add>travelling said road from</add> evading the payment of ferriage Or toll; &amp; shall fix the rates of ferriage &amp; toll according to Custom in such cases</p>
            <p>Article 5. No Cattle shall be driven through said road from the Southern States</p>
            <p>Article 6 <del type="overstrike">In order to prevent <del type="overstrike">trading</del>
                  <add>persons <unclear>passing from</unclear>
                  </add> without license person taking Horses thro, the said road shall give the description of them when they reserve passports</del>
            </p>
            <p>Article 6 In order to prevent <del type="overstrike">persons treading on the said road from </del>
               <add>
                  <del type="overstrike">who might</del>
               </add> the stealing of Horses, or <add>the</add> purchasing them without license, or other impositions relating to the live stocks of the Cherokees; a description of Horses &amp; <del type="overstrike">taken thro the said</del> &amp; livestocks <del type="overstrike">road</del> shall be <add>
                  <del type="overstrike">shall be</del>
               </add>
               <unclear>inserted</unclear> in the passports of those persons taking them thro. the <del type="overstrike">Indian Country</del> on the said road.    the Cherokees Shall <del type="overstrike"> not</del> be <add>only</add> answerable <del type="overstrike">only</del> for <del type="overstrike">Estrays</del>
               <add>Horses</add>
               <unclear>attently</unclear> from <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear>taken</unclear>
               </del> Stolen by their people &amp; not for Estrays.</p>
            <p>Article 7. The <unclear>presence</unclear> in renting the Ferries shall be given to persons having <unclear>connection with</unclear> Cherokee nation other things being equal</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="pa0045c.small.jpg"/>
            <p>Article 7.  All Officers Civil &amp; military &amp; <unclear>military</unclear> men of the United States when on <unclear>public service</unclear>
               <del type="overstrike">public express public Express &amp;</del> mail Carrier &amp; mail states shall be exempted from any Command for ferriage on toll on any part said road also all Cherokee with their Horses <unclear>Cattle &amp;c</unclear>
               <del type="overstrike">shall be</del> and all white men resident in the Cherokee nation shall be exempted from paying toll or ferriage on the said road- </p>
            <p>Article 8.  Commissioners Shall be appointed by the United States to <unclear>explore</unclear>, survey, &amp; mark the trees where the said road shall be opened, &amp; the Cherokees shall appoint four of their principal Chiefs to assist the Commissions as aforesaid in <del type="overstrike">exploring</del> the <del type="overstrike">execution of the <unclear>same</unclear>
               </del> in exploring the ground for the said road of which they shall have <unclear>timely notice</unclear> from the <add>Cherokee</add> Agent.  </p>
            <p>Article 9.  Duplicates of this agreement shall be made, one sent to the <choice>
                  <abbr>Secry</abbr>
                  <expan>Secretary</expan>
               </choice> of War, one lodged with the agent for the Cherokee nation &amp; one Delivered to the principal Cherokee Chief</p>
            <p>
               <add>Minutes of the Chiefs &amp; So.west point <date>20th Octo. 1803</date> relative to <unclear>granting</unclear> the road-</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
