<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc147">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Bill of Sale] 1814 May 30,  Benjamin Powell to William B. Lenoir : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Powell, Benjamin</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc147</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Bill of Sale] 1814 May 30, Benjamin Powell to William B. Lenoir</title>
               <author>  Powell, Benjamin</author>
               <date when="1814-05-30"> 
			 May 30, 1814</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a bill of sale by Benjamin Powell  for three slaves  in the amount of four-hundred dollars to  William Lenoir.  Lenoir  was a Revolutionary War
general and famous North Carolina politician of Fort Defiance, in  Caldwell County.  He later moved to Roane county, Tennessee.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Lenoir Family Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">22</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc147 </note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Lenoir family</term>
               <term>Slave trade</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Associated name http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/asn">Powell, Benjamin</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc147a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>Know all men by these presents that I <name>Benjamin Powell</name> of <name>Burke County</name> and State of <name>North Carolina</name> for and in consideration of the sum of four hundred dollars to me in hand paid by <name>William B. Lenoir</name> of <name>Roane County</name> and State of <name>Tennessee</name> (the receipt whereof is hereby acknowledged) have bargained and sold and by these presents do bargain and sell and convey unto the said William B. Lenoir all my right title interest and claim, and also all right title interest and claim that <name>Peter Cardwell</name> hath or ever had in consequence of his intermarriage with <name>Elizabeth Harris</name> to the following named negroes to wit, Wilson, Isom &amp; Joshua which negroes are now in <choice>
                  <orig>posession</orig>
                  <reg>possession</reg>
               </choice> of the said William B Lenoir, and are the children of a negro woman named Betty who was lent to <name>Fathe Harris</name>
               <add>by her grandfather John Hobbs</add>  during her natural life and after her death she and her increase was to be equally divided among all her children And I do hereby warrant and defend the said negroes Wilson Isom and Joshua to the said William B. Lenoir his heirs and assigns free and clear from any incumbrance and claim that I have acquired to said negroes in consequence of my intermarriage with <name>Nancy Harris</name> daughter of said Fath Harris and also from all incumbrances and claims of <name>Peter Cardwell</name> and from all and every of our heirs or assigns.</p>
            <p>In witness whereof the said <name>Benjamin Powell</name> hath hereunto set his hand and seal this <date>30th day of May <choice>
                     <abbr>A.D.</abbr>
                     <expan>anno Domini</expan>
                  </choice> 1814</date>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>Benjamin Powell</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Tho</abbr>
                        <expan>Thomas</expan>
                     </choice>. Lenoir</name>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                        <expan>William</expan>
                     </choice> Lenoir</name>
               </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sc147b.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Benja</abbr>
                     <expan>Benjamin</expan>
                  </choice>. Powell <lb/> to <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                     <expan>William</expan>
                  </choice> B. Lenoir <lb/>  Bill of sale</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
