<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl078">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1845 Apr., Dixons Spring, [Tennessee] [to] Miss Sarah Donoho / Ja[me]s L. Alexander : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Alexander, James L.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl078</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50137003</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1845 Apr., Dixons Spring, [Tennessee] [to] Miss Sarah Donoho / Ja[me]s L. Alexander</title>
               <author>Alexander, James L.</author>
               <date when="1845-04">April 1845</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by James L. Alexander to Miss Sarah Donoho in April 1845. In the letter, Alexander expresses his love and  respect for Miss Donoho and hopes that she feels the same way about him.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Alexander Papers Outgoing</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">VI-G-2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl078</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Love -- letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Alexander, James L.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl078a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Dixons Spring</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1845-04">April — 1845</date>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Miss Sarah Donoho</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>It is with feelings of the most profound respect that I take the liberty of Thus addressing You. The only apology I have to offer for the intrusion, is the motive, which prompts me to the presumption. I beg leave to congratulate myself on taking this opportunity which I have <choice>
                  <orig>desined</orig>
                  <reg>designed</reg>
               </choice> for some time of declaring my attachment for You, <unclear>asked</unclear> of soliciting an interest in my <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice>.</p>
            <p>I know Your own heart is too sincere to suspect treachery in another, or suffer Your ear to be caught by the <unclear>synen</unclear> voice of flattery. I therefore hope as I have engaged in the subject, you will permit me to tell You, with all the <choice>
                  <orig>candour</orig>
                  <reg>candor</reg>
               </choice> and frankness I am capable of assuming. that I love You with all the fervency with which woman is capable of being, ⁁ <add place="supralinear">loved</add> and If You are not otherwise engaged may I presume to solicit  a place in Your friendship and Love. — If my love is reciprocated by Yourself it shall be my study and exertion to merit Your affection, and if I can obtain that felicity which You are formed to bestow I shall be happy indeed. My heart beats high in expectation of its fancied joys. My <choice>
                  <orig>immagination</orig>
                  <reg>imagination</reg>
               </choice> paints in alluring <choice>
                  <orig>colours</orig>
                  <reg>colors</reg>
               </choice>, the charms of Your <pb n="2" facs="sl078b.small.jpg"/> Youth and beauty  regulated by virtue and innocence, and associated with all that is mild pure and benevolent. Of these I wish to partake. —</p>
            <p>
               <del type="overstrike">Your attention to this sute</del> I have said enough to awaken Your attention to this subject. I hope you will not be offended by my freedom. If it appears of little or no consequence to Yourself. You will at least ascribe the mention of it to motives of sincere regard in Your friend and loner; and if it should meet with Your approbation. I hope to conduct myself with the like <choice>
                  <orig>honour</orig>
                  <reg>honor</reg>
               </choice> and integrity that I have the satisfaction of knowing I never Yet violated. —</p>
            <p>It may be that this is rather a sudden affair to You, and that You cannot answer without consideration. Take what time You may think proper. Our short acquaintance renders it impossible<unclear> for me to decide</unclear> what the operations of Your mind may be. I am compelled now to quit the subject and leave You to the exercise of Your own free will, which I hope will coincide with my present wishes. In Your breast I will repose my cause. —</p>
            <p>In conclusion I now offer You my heart and hand. What more Can I say: What more can I offer. I have neither Rank Wealth or <choice>
                  <orig>Splendour</orig>
                  <reg>Splendor</reg>
               </choice> to bestow; but will promise to devote myself to Your happiness, and endeavour to prove a friend worthy of being  rewarded by Your love and Your <choice>
                  <orig>sosiety</orig>
                  <reg>society</reg>
               </choice>. — <pb n="3" facs="sl078c.small.jpg"/>
               <name type="person">Mr N B Hamilton</name> my particular and confidential friend will deliver You this letter. If its contents should meet with Yours approbation and I am so fortunate as to be considered deserving Your choice, or worthy to be selected as Your Companion in the <choice>
                  <orig>necissitudes</orig>
                  <reg>necessitudes</reg>
               </choice> of life. You will make it known by keeping it. But if after a satisfactory consideration of ⁁ <add place="supralinear">the</add> matter. You arrive at a different conclusion, You will please return it through the same person by whom it is handed to you.</p>
            <p>With sentiments of the highest regard and purest love I have the <choice>
                  <orig>honour</orig>
                  <reg>honor</reg>
               </choice> to subscribe myself  Most respectfully your friend and servant —</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <emph>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Jas</abbr>
                           <expan>James</expan>
                        </choice> L. Alexander</emph>
                  </name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Miss Sarah Donoho</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address">(Private and Confidential)</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl078d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Miss Sarah Donoho</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
