<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um006"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1838 Feb. 18 [to] Mr. John D. Coffee, Nashville, Ten[nessee] / A[ndrew] J[ackson] Coffee : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Coffee, Andrew Jackson</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um006</idno><idno>OCLC: 50193575</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1838 Feb. 18 [to] Mr. John D. Coffee, Nashville, Ten[nessee] / A[ndrew] J[ackson] Coffee</title><author>Coffee, Andrew Jackson</author><date value="1838-02-18">February 18, 1838</date><extent>2p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written from Andrew Jackson Coffee to his brother, John D. Coffee on February 18, 1838. In the letter, Andrew Coffee tells his brother about his school subjects and of events taking place that he is not present to witness.</note><note type="collection">Andrew Jackson 1804-1844 MS 28</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">1</note><note type="document">um006</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><add place=", left"><figure><figDesc>postmark seal</figDesc></figure></add><add place="above address, right">12 &frac12;</add><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mr. John D. Coffee</name></addrLine><addrLine> &lcub;<name type="place">Nashville</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Ten</abbr></name></addrLine></address><pb n="[2]"/> <address><addrLine><date value="1838-02-16"><abbr expan="February">Feb</abbr> the 16th 1838</date></addrLine></address><salute>My brother</salute></opener><p> I sit down this evening to <orig reg="fulfill">fullfill</orig> the promise of <orig reg="writing">writeing</orig> to you. I am <orig reg="studying">studing</orig> <orig reg="Latin">latin</orig> look <unclear>vire romae</unclear>, Greek <orig reg="grammar">gramar</orig> <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;c</abbr> <name type="person">Alese</name> is <orig reg="studying">studing</orig> the <orig reg="Latin grammar">latin gramar</orig>, geography <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;c</abbr>, <orig reg="cousin">co &caret; <add place="supralinear">u</add> sin</orig> <name type="person">Calista</name> was <orig reg="married">maried</orig> on Thursday to <name type="person">Judge Posey</name> . <orig reg="Cornelia"><name type="person">Conelia</name></orig>, <name type="person">Redford</name>, <name type="person">Caroline</name>, <name type="person">Hester</name>, <name type="person">Elizabeth</name>, <name type="person">Coffee</name> were the waiters, <name type="person">Mr. Clarke</name>, <name type="person">Houston</name>, <name type="person">Savage</name> were &caret; <add place="supralinear">the</add> waiters, all the young <orig reg="ladies">laidies</orig> and gentlemen of the <orig reg="town">toun</orig> and country were there would have no doubt had a very merry time of it but for the badness of the weather and the intoxication of few of the <orig reg="young">yong</orig> gentlemen, among others. <name type="person">J. Galaspia</name>, <name type="person">Catherine</name> is going to the infant school and is learning very fast, <name type="person">William</name> and <name type="person">Joshua</name> is well and is growing very fast, <name type="person">Big Phill</name> was working in the island and a limb fell from a tree and come very near killing him but he is getting better, mama got a letter from papa dated the <date value="0000-01-27">27th of Jan</date>, he had not got any of his <orig reg="business">buisness</orig> done and did not know when he would be at home. <name type="person">Mr Lorance</name> is going to commence a <orig reg="manual laborers">manul laberers</orig> school, give my love to all.</p><closer><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Andrew Jackson">A. J.</abbr> Coffee</name></signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
