<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.0 id="um013"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1849 March 27 [to] Alexander D. Coffee / Andrew Jackson Coffee : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Coffee, Andrew Jackson</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um013</idno><idno>OCLC: 50199483</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1849 March 27 [to] Alexander D. Coffee / Andrew Jackson Coffee</title><author>Coffee, Andrew Jackson</author><date value="1849-03-27">March 27, 1849</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated March 27, 1849 to Alexander D. Coffee from his brother Andrew Jackson Coffee. Andrew write his brother about various political appointments about to occur in Alabama, and that he was honored by the late President for his services in the Battle of Buena Vista.</note><note type="collection">Andrew Jackson Coffee Family Papers, MS27</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">15</note><note type="document">um013</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Mexican War, 1846-1848</item><item>Alabama</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Washington D.C.</name></addrLine></address><date value="1849-03-27">March 27th 1849</date><salute><abbr expan="Dear">Dr</abbr> Alex,</salute></opener><p>Your letter of the 4th <abbr expan="instant">inst</abbr> came to hand some days back and I have delayed to write to you until I settled the matter with the "Union" Office, which I have done at <orig reg="last">lust</orig>, by paying $2. and closing the whole matter which I hope will prove satisfactory.</p><p>I will try to procure you the "Patent office" reports, but I fear it will be difficult to procure, I will however do my best.</p><p>Things progress here steadily. notwithstanding the grumbling of some of our Democratic folks, <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> Taylor</name> is disposed to stick to his avowals that "he had no friends to reward and  no enemies to punish" and if in the end he departs from that policy the Cabinet ought to be held responsible for the matter, They <orig reg="have">huve</orig> deceived the <abbr expan="General">Gen'l</abbr> in some things already, <unclear>??"Nous bevrous"??</unclear> <pb n="[2]"/> I expect <name type="person">Judge Lewis</name> of <abbr expan="Alabama">Ala</abbr> will be <orig reg="appointed">appointen</orig> Solicitor of the Treasury in the place of <name type="person">Mr Gillet</name> who will have to walk the chalk. Salary $3,000 per annum, and a son of <name reg="person">Nick Davis</name> will be <orig reg="appointed">appointen</orig> agent for the preservation of the Public timber in <name type="place"><abbr expan="Alabama">Ala</abbr></name>. Salary $2.500. both are clever gentlemen and I do not know of any Whigs who I would rather have hold the offices than themselves, <unclear><name type="person">??Judge Gapple??</name></unclear> of <name type="place">Mobile</name> has been appointed District Judge in place of <name type="person">Crawford</name> <abbr expan="Deceased">Dec'd</abbr> and <name type="person">Pittman</name> has been appointed Postmaster at <name type="place">Huntsville</name> in place of  <name type="person">Mr Ninnally</name> who has gone to <name type="place">California</name>, If I hear of any more <abbr expan="Alabama">Ala</abbr> appointments I will let you know of it. <name type="person">John J. Walker</name> a Brother of<name type="person"> Pope Walkers</name> is here and an applicant for the Collectorship at Mobile I cannot learn what his chances are, I would not <pb n="[3]"/> be <orig reg="surprised">suprised</orig> if he got it however.</p><p>No further news now. I do not know when I will be able to get <orig reg="off">of</orig>. I am looking for orders however every day, and will come by to see you all a moment.</p><p>We all are well and Betty joins me in love to Ann, Ma, the girls <abbr expan="& et cetera & et cetera">&amp;c &amp;c</abbr>, yourself not forgotten.</p><closer><salute>In haste Your Brother</salute><signed><name type="person">Andrew J. Coffee</name></signed><add place="bottom of page">I forgot to mention that the Late President by and with the advice and consent of the Senate conferred on me Brevet of <orig reg="Lieutenent Colonelcy">Lieut Colonlecy</orig> for "gallant and meritorious services rendered in the Battle of <name type="place">Buena Vista</name>" for which honor I am duly grateful.</add><signed><abbr expan="Andrew Jackson Coffee">AJC</abbr></signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
