<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um017"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1850 Oct. 5 [to] Mr. Alex[ander] D. Coffee, Florence, Ala[bama] / Andrew J[ackson] Coffee : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Coffee, Andrew Jackson</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um017</idno><idno>OCLC: 50199974</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1850 Oct. 5 [to] Mr. Alex[ander] D. Coffee, Florence, Ala[bama] / Andrew J[ackson] Coffee</title><author>Coffee, Andrew Jackson</author><date value="1850-10-05">October 5, 1850</date><extent>2p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written from Andrew Jackson Coffee to his brother Alexander D. Coffee, dated October 5, 1850. In the letter, Andrew discusses an amount of money owed him by Robert and William Warren and about some "Bounty Land" coming to the family for his father's service in the Creek War of 1812 and with Britain in 1814 and 1815.</note><note type="collection">Andrew Jackson Coffee Family Papers 1833-1903 MS 27</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">21</note><note type="document">um017</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Creek War, 1813-1814</item><item>Southern States</item><item>United States -- Politics and government -- 1849-1853</item><item>Land tenure</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><add place="above address"><figure><figDesc>post mark seal</figDesc></figure></add><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mr <abbr expan="Alexander">Alex</abbr> D. Coffee</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Florence</name></addrLine><addrLine><abbr expan="Alabama"><name type="place">Ala</name></abbr></addrLine></address><pb n="[2]"/><address><addrLine><name type="place">New Orleans</name> <date value="1850-10-05">October 5th 1850</date></addrLine></address><salute>My dear Alex</salute></opener><p>I again send you a sheet of the "News letter" as it may prove interesting to you. I have not heard from Florence in so long a time that I do not know that any of you are in the land of the living however it is an old adage that "no news is good news". So I will take it for granted that all are well and thriving I have no news to write of much interest. I am happy to state that we are all in excellent health. <name type="person">Bettie</name>, myself the children and the Servants. I suppose you are very busy with your work <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;c</abbr> I hope I may be able to pay you a visit before very long when I will take much pleasure in visiting your <unclear>butter biscuit</unclear> and before a great while I suppose you will be visiting this notable city. If so I shall be most happy to entertain you during your visit and I will try to show you all the sights of the city. I see from a late law of Congress that there will be some "Bounty Land" coming to Ma for Pas Services in the Creek war of 1812 and the British war of 1814 &amp; 1815. As soon as I am certain the terms of the laws <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;c</abbr> I will prepare papers and so forth for the purpose of establishing the claims I will be worth some thing &mdash; Will you be so kind as to call on <name type="person"><abbr expan="John">Jno</abbr> Simpson &amp; <abbr expan="Company">Co</abbr></name> and ascertain what has become of the notes I left in his hands for collection of <name type="person"><abbr expan="Robert">Robt </abbr></name>and <name type="person"><abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> Warren</name> has any money been collected or is there likely to be any. I have not heard a word from them and do not know what their position may be. One note was due <date value="1849-07-01">1 July 1849</date> the other <date value="1850-01-01">1 <abbr expan="January">Jany</abbr> 1850</date> both <abbr expan="amount">amt</abbr> $166.66 making $333.33 &mdash; Give our love to <name type="person">Ann</name>, to Ma, <name type="person">Rachel</name>, <name type="person">Cate</name>, <name type="prson">William</name>, <name type="person">Joshua</name>, and <name type="person">Andrew</name> and our regards to all friends and accept the same for your self</p><closer><salute>Your Brother</salute><signed><name type="person">Andrew <abbr expan="Jackson">J.</abbr> Coffee</name></signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
