<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um043"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1836 Jul. 30, Macon, Noxubee Cty., Miss[issippi] [to] E.H. Porter, Raleigh, Tennessee / LeRoy B. Gaston : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Gaston, LeRoy B.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um043</idno><idno>OCLC: 50281343</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1836 Jul. 30, Macon, Noxubee Cty., Miss[issippi] [to] E.H. Porter, Raleigh, Tennessee / LeRoy B. Gaston </title><author>Gaston, Leroy B.</author><date value="1836-07-30">July 30, 1836</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated July 30, 1836 to E. H. Porter of Tennessee from LeRoy Gaston regarding various business ventures in Mississippi and Georgia.</note><note type="collection">Porter-Rice Family Letters, MS 154, 1830-1839</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">2</note><note type="document">um043</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Business enterprises</item><item>Southern states</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><add place="above address">25</add><address><addrLine><name type="place">Macon <abbr expan="Mississippi">Miss</abbr></name><date>August 8</date> <name type="person">Mr. <abbr expan="Ethel Henry">E. H.</abbr> Porter</name> <name type="place">Raleigh</name> <name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine></address><pb n="[2]"/><address><addrLine><name type="place">Macon Noxubee <abbr expan="City Missisippi">Cty Missis</abbr></name><date value="1836-07-30">30th July 1836</date></addrLine></address><salute>My Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>Circumstances standing a <emph>little </emph> in the way have prevented my writing to you at as an early a date as I contemplated; but I will now take time to inform you that I arrived safely at my Brothers in <name type="place">Kemper County</name> on the 7th <abbr expan="instant">inst.</abbr> On my way down, and since my arrival I have made upon the subject of our conversation before I left <name type="place">Raleigh</name>. My opinion, from the best information <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr> is that you will do well by occupying the stand at <name type="place">Aberdeen</name> at as early a date as you possibly can. It is the most eligible point= and commands a more extensive fertile section of country than any other I have heard spoken of, unless it be <name type="place">Gainsville </name>some distance below. The latter place had the advantages of being more central and accessible. They are both cut-off in a measure, from a winter intercourse with the <orig reg="interior">interiour</orig> <add place="supralinear">by the prairies,</add> a season of the the year too the most important for the advantage of your business. It would be a spur and spring to the business which I think would never subside, and would add incalculably to its profits, were you to occupy one of those stands this fall. I would earnestly advise, if possible, to forego some of your already conceived plans, and strain a point to do so. The farming interest of the country is just now in the stage of incipiency, and presents the fairest opportunity that it ever will for you to lay fast hold of it. I would suggest that you send <name type="person">Mr Charr</name> if you have no one to spare from your own shop to put in one of those places. I would <pb n="[3]"/> I believe prefer Gainsville from one consideration. A railroad from that place will in all probability be constructed across the prairies sometime in the course of next year; And it is destined to become a place of some importance.&mdash;</p><p>I have myself gone into business with my brother in merchandizing. I bought out his former partners interest, at cost and six <abbr expan="per cent">pr. ct.</abbr> upon 12 <abbr expan="months">mos.</abbr> time. And I am here now on a purchase of Articles that we need to replenish the stock, which we are now obliged to do in consequence of this former partner's having failed to go to <name type="place">Mobile </name>according to promise. We get goods from overstocked merchants in this place at <name type="place">New York</name> cost  and twenty <abbr expan="per cent">pr ct</abbr> with 6 &amp; 12 <abbr expan="months">mos</abbr> time. Our stand is a moderately good one; but we intend dividing and occupying another and a better stand as it is represented to be. </p><p> As I am in haste I must be brief. Give the above information to any friend or <emph>interested</emph> person who may inquire after me. I think at this time that it may be possible for me to be in <name type="place">Raleigh</name> about the first of <abbr expan="November">Novr.</abbr> next, as I have some idea of going to New York and making that in my <orig reg="route">rout</orig>. Tell <name type="person">Mr. Reinhardt</name> that when I get leisure enough I will write to him and give him a history in full of matters &amp; things in general. Keep what things you have of mine yet on hand that were contained in the box. They are movable, and worth more to me now I have a prospect of being settled than I can probably get for them. I should be very glad to hear from you and any farther information in my power to communicate upon notice will be cheerfully given.</p><closer><salute>With much <abbr expan="respect">respt.</abbr> and esteem for all of you i.e. yourself &amp; <name type="person">Mrs. Porter</name> I am </salute><signed><name type="person">LeRoy B. Gaston</name></signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
