<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um068"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1841 Feb. 1, Columbia, Tennessee [to]   Col[onel] Robert J. Chester / M[ary] J[ane] Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Chester, Mary Jane</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um068</idno><idno>OCLC: 50315038</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1841 Feb. 1, Columbia, Tennessee [to]   Col[onel] Robert J. Chester / M[ary] J[ane] Chester</title><author>Chester, Mary Jane</author><date value="1841-02-01">February 1, 1841</date><extent>3p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written by Mary Jane Chester to her father, Colonel Robert J. Chester, on February 1, 1841. In the letter, Mary thanks her father for sending her money, expresses delight that her examination is over, and agrees to comply with his wishes that she not write so many letters home.</note><note type="collection">Chester Family Papers MS 25 (February 1841)</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">7</note><note type="document">um068</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Boarding school students</item><item>Tennessee -- History</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Columbia Tennessee</name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1841-02-01"><abbr expan="February">Feby</abbr> 1st 1841</date></addrLine></address><salute>My dear Papa</salute></opener><p>Your kind letter of the 24th <abbr expan="Ultimo">Ult.</abbr> arrived here yesterday. It was very kind in your sending me that money. I gave it to <name type="person">Mr. Smith</name>, he seemed very much pleased and said that it  was a very liberal subscription. I told him that $1 &frac12; was for the Paper.</p><p>The examination is just over. It continued three days there <del type="overstrike">there</del> were not many people the first day &caret; <add place="supralinear">on account of the weather</add> but the &caret; <add place="supralinear">third</add> day the house was crowded. I missed but one question the whole time, and I do not think that I should have missed that one had I not been so much frightened. <name type="person">Mr Walkers</name> family came every day. <name type="person">Cousin Sam</name> said that he intended to write to you immediately after it was over. So I expect that you will receive his letter before you do mine. The <name type="person"><abbr expan="Reverend">Rev</abbr> Mr Wheat</name> of <name type="place">Nashville</name> was here: and read out the Composition.</p><p>Father you requested me in your last letter not to write so many letters. I will discontinue all my letters to every person with the exception of our family. I was very much distressed when I read that part of your letter. I did not think that I had ever written any thing that I would not be willing for any person <pb n="[2]"/> to read. I am very glad that you have told not to write. I will do any thing that I think would please you and Mama I know the reason that you did not speak of it when you were here. You did not like to speak of any thing that you thought would give me pain.</p><p>I do not think that I can graduate this Summer. I wish that you would write to Mr. Smith about it. <orig reg="Oh">O</orig>! I should like to graduate so much. I study as hard as it is possible for any one to study. Next session I will try and get the Premium in <orig reg="diligence">dilligence</orig>, but I should like for that to remain a secret. I have not time to write a longer letter.</p><p>Give my love to <name type="person">Aunt <abbr expan="Patsey">P.</abbr></name> &amp; <name type="person">Aunt <abbr expan="Narcissa">N</abbr></name>, and all my relations kiss my Sister and brothers and Mama.</p><closer><salute>I remain your ever affectionate Daughter</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Mary Jane">M. J.</abbr> Chester</name></signed><address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel Robert">Col Robt</abbr> J Chester</name></addrLine></address><add place="below address"><abbr expan="Post Script">P. S.</abbr> I forgot to tell you that I wrote to Grand Mother the other. do you see any impropriety it <sic>it</sic>.</add> <pb n="[3]"/> <add place="above address"><figure><figDesc>mathematical figures</figDesc></figure> <date value="1841-02-03">3rd <abbr expan="February">Feby</abbr> 1841</date> <figure><figDesc>post mark for February 3</figDesc></figure> 18</add><address><addrLine><abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Robert J Chester</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Jackson</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
