<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="um065"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>   [Letter] 1840 Dec. 27, Jackson, Tennessee [to] Miss Mary Jane Chester, Columbia, Tennessee / Elizabeth Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Chester, Elizabeth</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um065</idno><idno>OCLC: 50312881</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>   [Letter] 1840 Dec. 27, Jackson, Tennessee [to] Miss Mary Jane Chester, Columbia, Tennessee / Elizabeth Chester</title><author>Chester, Elizabeth</author><date value="1840-12-27">December 27, 1840</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">The following document is a letter, dated December 27, 1840, from Elizabeth Chester to her daughter Mary Jane Chester.  Elizabeth writes to her daughter who is being schooled at the Female Institute in Columbia, TN, and updates her on the happenings back home in Jackson.  She talks of all the people who will be recently married and mentions her husband, Colonel Robert Chester's recent trip to visit Mary Jane.  Also included is a short letter written to Mary Jane from her younger sister Martha.</note><note type="collection">Chester Family Papers MS-25 (12/1840)</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">5</note><note type="document">um065</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Boarding school students</item><item>Tennessee -- History</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Jackson</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Tennessee</name> <date value="1840-12-27"><abbr expan="December">Dec.</abbr> 27 <add rend="different hand, ink" place="supralinear">[1840]</add></date></addrLine></address><salute>My Dear Daughter</salute></opener><p>Last week brought me a letter from you I Delayed answering it <orig reg="until">untill</orig> now because I know that your Pa Pa had   been to see you and would give you all the news of the Family and town, I am extremely anxious for his return so that I can learn your true situation if you look in good health I hope you told him all your wants and troubles if you have any you wish to know what we are all doing we went to church this morning had a sermon by <name type="person"><abbr expan="Doctor">Dr</abbr> Campbell</name> and a masonic <orig reg="Parade">Parrade</orig> in Celebration of St. John the Evangelist had quite a full house the three Brides were there <name type="person">Mrs Compton</name> <name type="person">Mrs Scurlock</name> and <name type="person">Mrs Rodgers</name> , nothing but weddings tell <name type="person">Jane</name> that her old <emph>Beau</emph> <name type="person">Mr Calvin Henderson</name> and <name type="person">Miss Eliza Patterson</name> are to be married what say you to that and your old Beau <name type="person">Mr Tatton</name> to <name type="person">Miss Hunt</name> last though not least <name type="person">Mr Mass</name> and <name type="person">Sarah Ann Meachum</name> <name type="person">Miss Mary Turly</name> arrived at home on yesterday Several of the Young Gentlemen are on Tiptoe expectation for her appearance I think she will be the <orig reg="Belle">Bell</orig> <pb n="[2]"/> this Winter, I am <orig reg="afraid">affraid</orig> my dear Mary Jane that I ought not to write so much nonsense I fear it may distract your mind from you studies, how spent you your Christmas? I hope some one was kind enough to ask your Company on that day and that you were gay and happy, have you seen nothing of <name type="person">Mrs Mary Polk</name> you have not mentioned her in any of your letters, Christmas day we all dined at Sister <name type="person">Butlers</name> our number was small your Pa not returned <emph>you</emph> not <gap reason="document damaged"/> <name type="place">Mississippi</name> has been there for two months <name type="person">Mr Rawlings</name>  not at home <name type="person">Mr Patton</name> and Family in <name type="place">Florida</name> Uncle S<gap reason="document cut off" desc="Sam"/> <del type="overstrike">and</del> and Family in <name type="place">Shelby</name>  <name type="person">Mrs William Patton Barr</name>  &amp; <name type="person"><abbr expan="Doctor">Dr</abbr> Jameson</name> were there, the Children are all around me making the house ring with laughter and  <orig reg="merriment">merrime</orig> oh! how I wish you were here <del type="overstrike">of</del> to make one of these happy number, I shall not know peace <orig reg="until">untill</orig> you return I have a thousand fears and anxieties about you, we must <orig reg="exercise">excercise</orig> patience and trust in providence for the result, your <name type="person">Aunt Narcissa</name> is again well I hope she will not have any more, Chills you must take as much <orig reg="exercise">excercise</orig> as you can I think it conduces to health I &caret; <add place="supralinear">think</add> you had better learn <orig reg="ornamental">ornimental</orig> needle work but you can <orig reg="exercise">excercise</orig> your own wishes on that subject I hope you Played on the Piano for your Father I have nothing more to add but all off our love and Prayers for your happiness <orig reg="safety">safty</orig></p> <closer><salute>affectionately your Mother</salute><signed><name type="person">Elizabeth Chester</name></signed>    </closer></div1><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[3]"/><opener><salute>My Dear Sister</salute></opener><p>Christmas Gift how I do want to see you I thank you for your Beautiful letter I wonder if I shall ever write so good I am going to write you a long letter this week I have vacation now how I wish you were at home now</p> <closer><salute>I remain your affectionate Sister </salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Martha Butler">M B</abbr>  Chester</name></signed><add place="below" rend="different hand"><abbr expan="Post Script">PS</abbr> My Dear Mary Jane in your letter to the Ge<gap reason="document damaged" desc="rls"/> be guarded in what you write particularly about <name type="person">Miss Lyon</name> you know they will <orig reg="show">shew</orig> your letters</add><salute>very affectionately your mother</salute> <signed>Elizabeth Chester</signed> <pb n="[4]"/>  <add place="above address" rend="different hand, ink">Mrs <abbr expan="Elizabeth">E</abbr> Chester Answered</add> <address><addrLine><name type="person">Miss Mary Jane Chester</name> </addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Columbia</name></addrLine><addrLine><emph>Tennessee</emph></addrLine></address> <add>My Dear Mother <lb/> <date value="1840-12-27">27 <abbr expan="December">Decr</abbr> 1840</date></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
