<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 n="um091"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1844 Jun. 25, Jackson, Tenn[essee] [to]    Col[onel] Robert J. Chester, Jonesboro, East Tennessee / M[ary] J[ane] Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Chester, Mary Jane</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name><name>Jim Cole</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>um091</idno><idno>OCLC: 50323681</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1844 Jun. 25, Jackson, Tenn[essee] [to]    Col[onel] Robert J. Chester, Jonesboro, East Tennessee / M[ary] J[ane] Chester</title><author>Chester, Mary Jane</author><date value="1844-06-25">June 25, 1844</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter, dated June 25, 1844, from Mary Jane Chester in Jackson, TN, to her father Colonel Robert J. Chester.  Colonel Chester was visiting his family in Jonesboro, and Mary Jane writes this letter to update her father on the news of Jackson and the condition of all the children.  Among the items she discusses are the formation of a voluntary military company to send to Texas during the Mexican-American War and the upcoming plans of Jackson's Democratic Party.</note><note type="collection">Chester Family Papers MS-25 (1844-1873)</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">12</note><note type="document">um091</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Mexican War, 1846-1848</item><item>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</item><item>Tennessee -- History</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Jackson <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn,</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1844-06-25">June 25th 1844</date> &mdash;</addrLine></address><salute>Dear Papa,</salute></opener><p>This is Tuesday, the day that I promised to write, but I fear that I shall not be able to make any letter <emph>very</emph> interesting to you.</p><p>The Children are all well at present, and have been so with the exception of <name type="person">Sam</name>, he had two or three Chills. we broke them upon him by the aid of Quinine and <emph>his drain</emph>, he is entirely recovered now, and speaks very often about you, when any one troubles him, he threatens to <emph>tell his papa</emph>. <name type="person">King</name>, as usual cries at night and will sleep with me.  The other boys are very busy preparing for their Examination.  I think will acquit themselves <orig reg="very">verry</orig> well, I believe it takes place on next Monday.  I wish very much that you could here at that time.</p><p>Nothing of interest has <orig reg="occurred">occured</orig> except that the <emph><name type="place">Texas</name> men</emph> &mdash; They have found a Texas Volunteer Company.  Cousin the <orig reg="Captain">Captin</orig>.  Your Son <name type="person">John</name> forms one of the number, his Uncle Sam and Cousin <name type="person">Will</name> insisted very much upon it. <pb n="[2]"/> It is generally understood that their object is to benefit neither the democrat of Whig party but I have my suspicions on the subject.  There is to be a "<emph>grand Ball</emph>"  on the fourth of July, given to this Military Company.  Uncle Sam is one of the subscribers, indeed I expect it will be quite a <emph>grand affair</emph>, that is, if they can get good Music &mdash; <name type="person">Aunt McLillan</name> , passed through the other day on her way to the <name type="place">Gibson Wells</name>, she remained with us only, for breakfast but said she would return in about a week &mdash; There has been a <emph>well</emph>, near <name type="place"><orig reg="Campbell's">Cambell's</orig> bridge</name>, similar to those at Gibson, Those persons who have <orig reg="analyzed">analized</orig> the water, think them about the same &mdash; <abbr expan="Do not">Dont</abbr> you think <emph>Jackson's improving</emph>? Cousin <name type="person">Jane</name> is to give a <emph>small</emph> Tea Party tomorrow evening.  I can assure you I feel quite delighted at the idea, for this place is rather dull &mdash;.  Our Trip to <name type="place">Nashville</name> is entirely given out, I feel rather rejoiced that otherwise, for it would not be pleasant travelling in such warm weather.  Uncle Will has heard very distressing news about his plantation, that almost the whole of it, is overflowed, Cousin is undecided whether he will go down or not &mdash; <name type="person">Mr. Hinds</name> expects to leave of thursday.  I believe Cousin Jane's Party is given to him.</p><p>I suppose ere this, you have arrived at Jonesboro &mdash; if so, give our best love to Grand Mama, <name type="person">Aunt Kate</name> &amp; all of our Relations.  I can imagine your joy at being, again at your old Home.</p><p>We received the two letters you wrote. Our Friend <name type="person">Bill <pb n="[3]"/> Jones</name> has called to see us two or three times.  the <emph>large stage</emph> House that he took away with him did not suit.  he was <emph>too poor</emph> &mdash; his Father has not yet called.</p><p>The Democrats still appear to be in fine spirits about the election  they speak of giving a large brand dance down at the "big  Spring" on the 18th of July &mdash; I think that is one of Uncle Will's propositions.  I believe I have told you of everything that has taken place since you left.  We are all anxious to hear from you, Write to us often.  The Children send their love to you.   <name type="person">Aunt Butter's</name>  family are all well &mdash; they send their love to you &mdash;</p><closer><salute>Your affectionate Daughter</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Mary Jane">M J.</abbr> Chester</name></signed><add place="bottom"><abbr expan="Post Script">P. S.</abbr><name type="person">Martha's</name> Music school has not yet commenced <gap reason="ink blot"/></add> <pb n="[4]"/> <add place="left of address"><figure><figDesc>postmark for Jun. 26</figDesc></figure> 25</add> <address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> Robert J. Chester</name> ,</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Jonesboro</name>,</addrLine><addrLine><emph><name type="place">East Tennessee</name></emph></addrLine></address><add place="left of address">Mail &rcub;</add> <add place="below address" rend="different hand, ink">My Dear Mary Jane <lb/> <date value="1844-06-25">25 June 1844</date></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
