<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0001">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Answers to enquiries relating to the Cherokees, 1817 Aug., Cherokee Agency / Colonel Return J. Meigs: A machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Meigs, Return Jonathan, 1740-1823</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Knoxville Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>pa0001</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44886930</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Tennessee Special Collections Library.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Answers to enquiries relating to the Cherokees, 1817 Aug., Cherokee Agency / Colonel Return J. Meigs</title>
               <author>Meigs, Return Jonathan, 1740-1823</author>
               <date when="1817-08">August 1817</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a set of questions and answers relative to the social and physical condition of the Cherokee Indians.  Notation on the document indicates that it was written in August 1817 by Colonel Return J. Meigs and directed to a Mr. Trott.</note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">Special Collections Library, The University of Tennessee Knoxville</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true"> Penelope Johnson Allen</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">91</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0001</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for the University of Georgia Libraries Electronic Text Center</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Health and hygiene</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Social conditions</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n92008354"
                        role="Author http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/aut">Meigs, Return Jonathan, 1740-1823</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0001a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>
               <add place="top">Notes to <name type="person">Mr. Trott</name> from <name type="person">Col. R. J. Meigs</name> - <name type="place">Cherokee Agency</name>, <date when="1817-08-03">3 August 1817</date>
               </add> Answers to enquiries relating to the <name type="person">Cherokees</name>.</head>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  What is the number of the <name type="person">Cherokees</name>?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  The whole number of the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> is by estimation 13,000.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  In what part of the <name type="place">United States</name> are they situated?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  Principally within the Chartered limits of <name type="place">Georgia</name>
               <name type="place">Tennessee</name> but recently imigrations have been made to <name type="place">Arkansas river</name>.  The number of these emigrants is estimated at about 3000.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  What is the state of the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> with respect to property?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  They have great numbers of Domestic <choice>
                  <orig>annimals</orig>
                  <reg>animals</reg>
               </choice>, a considerable number of Negro slaves, a number of good plantations, a number of Grist mills, some sawmills,  they manufacture <choice>
                  <orig>Salt Petre</orig>
                  <reg>Saltpeter</reg>
               </choice>  Gun powder by the aid of white men.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  What is their State as <add place="supralinear">to</add> acquired information?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  A considerable number <add place="supralinear">have</add> the knowledge of letters  figures.</p>
            <p>
               <del type="overstrike">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                     <expan>Question</expan>
                  </choice>:</del> but schools are greatly needed for the poor children.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  What is their present state  future prospect with respect to education?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  There is at present two public schools, some private schools, and a prospect of more public or free schools by respectable societies from <name type="place">Massachusets</name>
               <name type="place">Kentucky</name>.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  What number of children at proper age for instruction?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  Not less than 1200 or 1500 between six and fourteen years of age, at a moderate calculation, but they are scattered over a great tract of Country.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  What is the state of the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> with respect to religious knowledge?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  They have as a people no acquired knowledge of religion.  Their Green corn dance, so called, is undoubtedly of religious origin, it is only an annual meeting  may be justly termed a Feast of the first fruits.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  Do the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> believe in the being of a God?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  Yes universally.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="pa0001b.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  What conceptions have they of his attributes?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  That <add place="supralinear">his</add> power,  his goodness are infinite, that he approves or disapproves of our conduct here.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  Do they believe in a future state of existence?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  Yes  that <add place="supralinear">it</add> will be terrestial enjoyment.   For want of instruction they cannot elevate their minds above materiality  they have no apprehensions of future unhappiness.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  What are their most prominent traits of character?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  Hospitality and kindness (and without ostentation) to the whole human race except in instances where they concieve that they are grossly injured.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  How do gross injuries affect them?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  They think it not only right; but necessary  very honorable to retaliate  take ample revenge.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  Is their resentment implacable, unforgiving and inexorable?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  No.  On receiving satisfaction they make peace and <choice>
                  <orig>reieve</orig>
                  <reg>receive</reg>
               </choice> the Children of their enemy into their bosoms, accept them by the force of <choice>
                  <orig>immagination</orig>
                  <reg>imagination</reg>
               </choice> as their own, to fill the place of those killed by the same enemy.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  Do they then love their enemies?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  No, not as enemies; it is not a sentiment of nature, and revelation has not reached <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear/>
               </del>
               <add place="supralinear">their minds</add> or hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  Are they willing to receive instruction?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  Yes, but lessons must be short.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  What is the greatest obstacle to <add place="supralinear">their</add> improvement?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>: <add place="supralinear">a dislike of all</add> Restraint, <unclear>close</unclear> application is abhorrent to their minds.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  Can that obstacle be removed?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  Yes.  By waiting, by patience <add place="supralinear"/> ingenuity <add place="supralinear">in</add>
               <del type="overstrike">of</del> the teachers.  <hi>line <add place="supralinear">must be</add> upon line</hi>. <add place="supralinear">
                  <del type="overstrike">line upon line</del>
               </add>
               <hi>here a little</hi>, and <hi>there a little</hi>.  They<pb n="3" facs="pa0001c.small.jpg"/>they cannot be hurried, <del type="overstrike">if they are hurried</del> it will disconcert them, and all will be lost.  care must be taken not make the lessons tedious they cannot at present bear long, close application if that is attempted all will be lost.
                  </p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  What are the principal pursuits <del type="overstrike">of the</del>
               <name type="person">Cherokees</name> for subsistence?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  Hunting is the favorite pursuit where there is game.  where it is scarce, the men are Herdsmen  cultivators.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  What are the pursuits of the females?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  Raising Cotton, Indigo, spinning, dyeing yard  weaving  taking care of family household affairs.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  In what estimation are the women held by the males?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  Since the introduction of domestic manufactures the females are held in higher estimation by the men.  They are emerging from a partial kind of slavery with their proper place in society.  They are more esteemed by the males,  as esteem  love are concomitant between the sexes, love is becoming a sentimental passion never known in a perfect savage state.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  Have the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> strong prejudices against whites?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  No they hold all good men in high esteem - respect.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  Are there <add place="supralinear">any</add> intermarriages between the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> and the whites?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  Yes.  A great number  they are increasing; nearly half the <name>Cherokee nation</name> are the offspring of such int<add place="supralinear">er</add> marriages.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  Is there any apparent improvement in such offspring, <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear/>An</del> either in body or mind?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Ansr.</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice> In size only. nothing in symetry of form or in mental powers. The form of the aborigine is the most perfect, <choice>
                  <orig>there</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice> Head-shoulders, Chest hands  feet, are with few exception the most perfect.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  Is there any apparent difference <add place="supralinear">in the</add> temper and disposition or in the intellectual faculties between the aborigines  the offspring of <unclear>their</unclear> intermarriages?</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="pa0001d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  There is a marked difference <add place="supralinear">
                  <del type="overstrike">in</del>
               </add>
               <del type="overstrike">their manner  deportment between them.</del> the offspring <add place="supralinear">of their intermarriages</add> are more volatile, have more levity, more cunning, less thought, less solidity, less dignity of deportment.  There is no ostentation, no <del type="overstrike">affection</del>
               <add place="supralinear">self <del type="overstrike">
                     <unclear/>
                  </del> consequences</add> in the male and no affectation or coquetry in the female of the aborgine -nature has been bountiful both to the exterior  to the mind and soul of the aborigines.  They are undoubtedly susceptible of the finest improvement  in <del type="overstrike">all the</del> moral qualities decidedly have the advantage <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear/>
               </del>.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                  <expan>Question</expan>
               </choice>:  Have the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> any knowledge of the <del type="overstrike">Heavenly Bodies</del> Constellations of the Zodiac? or names for any of the <choice>
                  <orig>starrs</orig>
                  <reg>stars</reg>
               </choice>?</p>
            <p>
               <del type="overstrike">Answer</del> Answer.  They have.  The Ursa Major they call the <unclear>Auneelqonah</unclear>
               <add place="supralinear">the Great Bear</add>  have observed its movement round the Pole.  The Pleiades.  they call the little Boys.  The evening <choice>
                  <orig>starr</orig>
                  <reg>star</reg>
               </choice> they <add place="supralinear">call</add> the Torch from its superior Brightness.</p>
            <p>
               <del type="overstrike">How</del>
               <add place="supralinear">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Qu</abbr>
                     <expan>Question</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>:  How do they reckon time?</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>An</abbr>
                  <expan>Answer</expan>
               </choice>:  For the year they count the moons; but making only 12 by throwing away the <unclear/> Days <choice>
                  <orig>The</orig>
                  <reg>They</reg>
               </choice> calculate <del type="overstrike">a time of year by winter</del> their own age by winters.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
