<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl362">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1837 Jun. 24, Nashville [to] Rev[eren]d Finis Ewing, Lexington, Missouri / Ja[me]s Smith: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Smith, James</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl362</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1837 Jun. 24, Nashville [to] Rev[eren]d Finis Ewing, Lexington, Missouri / Ja[me]s Smith</title>
               <author>Smith, James</author>
               <date when="1837-06-24">June 24, 1837</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated June 24, 1837 from James Smith to Reverend Finis Ewing of the Cumberland Presbyterian Church.  Smith is the printer of the church's newspaper, and he informs Ewing that the publication will soon cease as a result of Smith not having been paid for his printing services.  He writes that he has little hope that the Presbytery can continue to afford the paper.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Finis Ewing Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">I-A-4</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">17</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl362</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Religious thought -- 19th century</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Smith, James</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl362a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name>
                     <date>24 June 1837</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Br</abbr>
                     <expan>Brother</expan>
                  </choice> Ewing</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I duly received your very brief note enclosing $5.00.  I wrote you two or three times last winter and no reply.  once from <name>Leighton Alabama</name>
            </p>
            <p>You have learned by this time the action of the Assembly in relation to the College and paper.  The first I believe will do well The other I have reason to fear will not be continued.  The terms of the continuation you have seen. I do most anxiously desire to see <name>Cumberland</name> Presbyterian  in possession of a good paper but am nearly hopeless on the subject. as I hardly expect the brethren to return their pledges and it has come to such a pass with me now that, without being put in possession of what is owing to me however willing I cannot go on.  Judge yourself of my condition from the fact that my printing office alone cost about Twelve thousand Dollars the Cumberland Presbyterian Debts amount to about to $13,000 I have on hands books and due for <unclear>now</unclear> sold about $6,000 <pb n="2" facs="sl362b.small.jpg"/> all of which is unavailable, the banks have <choice>
                  <orig>stoped</orig>
                  <reg>stopped</reg>
               </choice> business, and every man to whom I owe crying give, give, give added to this I have been printing the Union (government paper) and a methodist paper, for which the Editors owe me nearly a thousand Dollars &amp; I cannot get it  From this parts and the circumstance that when I commenced business my whole capital was only about $1,500.  I leave you to judge what my <unclear>perplexities</unclear> must be.  Did the Church by a rigorous exertion collect and pay me one half what is owing me by her members I could  come out triumphantly, but on this subject there is little hope and being convinced that the longer I go on as I have done the  <unclear>worse</unclear> it will be I shall have to stop.  I think I can sell out my printing office so as to pay what I owe and then the world is before  me though it is a hard matter to take for the benefit of brethren for years and then be ruined by them and have to begin anew with a large and very <pb n="3" facs="sl362c.small.jpg"/>
               <choice>
                  <orig>hepless</orig>
                  <reg>helpless</reg>
               </choice> family.  But I thank God I have some fortitude and if for my sins I have to be trampled in the dust I hope I shall have grace to bear it.</p>
            <p>On the other hand if the brethren will exert themselves I will go on that is if they collect enough to make me so to do.</p>
            <p>I had made out all my accounts for western Missouri clergymen to send them to you to have them distributed among the brethren but hate to  trouble you and therefore decline for the present.  The truth is I dont know what to do O that God would direct me</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>yours in best ends</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Jas</abbr>
                        <expan>James</expan>
                     </choice> Smith</name>
               </signed>
               <add>you know <name>Raines</name> published a <choice>
                     <abbr>C P</abbr>
                     <expan>Cumberland Presbyterian</expan>
                  </choice> paper at <name>Pittsburgh</name>, it is dead and he has disgraced himself &amp; his church <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>JS</abbr>
                     <expan>James Smith</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl362d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Revd</abbr>
                           <expan>Reverend</expan>
                        </choice> Finis Ewing</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Lexington</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Missouri</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Rev</abbr>
                     <expan>Reverend</expan>
                  </choice> Jas Smith <lb/>
                  <date>June 24 1837</date>
               </add>
               <add>Delayed in consequence of having been mislaid</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
