<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl006">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1813 Dec. 19 [to] William B. Lewis Esq[uire] Nashville, Tennessee / Andrew Jackson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Jackson, Andrew</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl006</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50007766</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1813 Dec. 19 [to] William B. Lewis Esq[uire] Nashville, Tennessee / Andrew Jackson</title>
               <author>Jackson, Andrew</author>
               <date when="1813-12-19">December 19, 1813</date>
               <extent> 4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated December 19th 1813 to William B. Lewis from Andrew Jackson. Jackson complains about losing the Tennessee Volunteers to sickness and desertion. He requests that the Lewis convince the Governor of Tennessee to issue an order to keep the Tennessee Militia involved in the Creek War. See also document sl005 for an early printed transcription of this letter.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Sir Emil Hurja Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">15</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl006</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Creek War, 1813-1814</term>
               <term>Military offenses</term>
               <term>Military assistance</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79088888"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl006a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Head quarters <name type="place">Fort Strother</name>
                     <date when="1813-12-19">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Decbr</abbr>
                           <expan>December</expan>
                        </choice> 19th 1813</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Dr </abbr>
                     <expan>Dear</expan>
                  </choice>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The Blankets has not reached this place as yet whenever they come up, I will send you the order to cover the number sent on, and the quarter masters <choice>
                  <abbr>recpt</abbr>
                  <expan>receipt</expan>
               </choice> for the same— I fear before they reach me I shall have no men to buy or wear them and my camp will be deserted without any means taken by the Governor fill their vacancy, by draft I have wrote by several expresses, in due time to have reached him and his answer have been to hand before the 10th instant, had is answers been such as I am now told it is the <name type="place">Tennessee</name> Volunteers Infantry would have been still here doing there duty as good soldiers or receiving examplarory punishment for disobedience</p>
            <p>The East Tennessee Troop it appears was only brought into the field for three months, and not one under the requisition of the <choice>
                  <orig>secrotary</orig>
                  <reg>secretary</reg>
               </choice> of war all named marching home but one <choice>
                  <abbr>Regt.</abbr>
                  <expan>Regiment</expan>
               </choice> whose time will be up the 14th proximo, and behold the militia from my Division has caught the disease, and home they must be on the 4th <choice>
                  <abbr>Inst.</abbr>
                  <expan>Instant</expan>
               </choice> month— I have said to them— that they are in for the campaign or under the act of congress but I shall be governed by the <choice>
                  <orig>oppinion</orig>
                  <reg>opinion</reg>
               </choice> of the governor— <choice>
                  <orig>Thiss</orig>
                  <reg>This</reg>
               </choice> a campaign so necessary for the safety and protection of the frontiers, so far as Tennessee has to take apart <pb n="2" facs="sl006b.small.jpg"/>in it is likely to be shamefully abandoned, and the reputation of the state eternally disgraced, and no <del type="overstrike">act</del>fervent act as far as I can learn to prevent it, what is the Governor about, is his feelings ready to submit to such a <choice>
                  <orig>disgracefull</orig>
                  <reg>disgraceful</reg>
               </choice> scene, after our boasted patrotism, and fervent wishes to be permitted to carry war and destruction into the hands of the creek nation, and after the fortunate entrance made into it, contrary to the underhand endeavors to prevent me from <choice>
                  <orig>opperating</orig>
                  <reg>operating</reg>
               </choice> from the want of supplies, which I expected from <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl </abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice>Cocke</name>
               <emph>and his command</emph> to <emph>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                        <expan>General</expan>
                     </choice> White</name>
               </emph> (which I <emph>enclose to the governor and will explain all</emph> and every matter and thing as it respects the cooperation and supplies promised by <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Cocke</name>, all which is noted and in due time will be attended to— for the Lords sake arouse the governor from his <choice>
                  <orig>lethergy</orig>
                  <reg>lethargy</reg>
               </choice>— bring to his view the Disgraceful principle, on which the credit of the State stands and he will exert himself— at the militia under the requisition of the President, as adopted under the late law of the state be drafted for six months, and sent on to fill up the disgraceful retrograde of the Volunteers, or let him peremptory, order the Volunteers to return if he believes he has not the power to discharge them and let him issue a general order, directing all deserters to be appre <pb n="3" facs="sl006c.small.jpg"/>hended, and transferred to the regular army, there to serve the <choice>
                  <orig>ballance </orig>
                  <reg>balance</reg>
               </choice>of their time, let him do this and explain at what time <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Roberts</name> Brigade Service ends, and should it end on the 4th proximo say to him unless at that period our cooperation or aid from Tennessee as promised &amp; expected by the President of  the <name type="place">United States</name>, and by <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Pinkney</name> the commander in chief, is to end and our state <choice>
                  <orig>eternaly</orig>
                  <reg>eternally</reg>
               </choice> disgraced, that he must exert himself fulfill his powers and order a requisition to be up against the day, that those in service expires, this is the conduct of the surgeons— and although <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Floyds</name> Brigade time of service has expired having served 6 months, &amp; till the express informs me, that the governor <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>of</unclear> Georgia has the relief is at hand and <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>will</unclear> reach him before the first requisition is discharged— this is proper and right— and I hope the governor will exert himself, and save our state from everlasting disgrace— I have ordered <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl </abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice>Cocke</name> back to fill up the requisition of the <add place="supralinear">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>secrotory</orig>
                     <reg>secretary</reg>
                  </choice> of war made <choice>
                     <abbr>thro</abbr>
                     <expan>through</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add> governor of the state had this been done at first regardless of the <choice>
                  <orig>disgracefull</orig>
                  <reg>disgraceful</reg>
               </choice> retrograde of the T. V. S. Infantry I should been moving on and soon put and end to the Creek War— My respects to your lady<name type="person"> Mrs. Lewis</name> and all the family &amp; receive my thanks for the cheese &amp; Butter <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> &amp; believe me respectfully <choice>
                  <abbr>yrs &amp; c &amp; c &amp;c </abbr>
                  <expan>yours and et cetera and et cetera and et cetera</expan>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <emph>Andrew Jackson</emph>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb n="4" facs="sl006d.small.jpg"/>
            <closer>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">William B. Lewis <choice>
                           <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                           <expan>Esquire</expan>
                        </choice>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr> Asst.</abbr>
                           <expan>Assistant</expan>
                        </choice> D. L. M. <choice>
                           <abbr>Genl.</abbr>
                           <expan>General</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                     <name type="place">Nashville Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="Bottom of page">Letter from<choice>
                     <abbr> Genl. </abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Jackson dated Fort Strother <date when="1813-12-19">19th Dec. 1813</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
