<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl355">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1825 Sep. 12, St. Louis, M[issouri] [to] Finis Ewing, Boonville, Cooper County, M[issouri] / Salmon Giddings   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Giddings, Salmon</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl355</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1825 Sep. 12, St. Louis, M[issouri] [to] Finis Ewing, Boonville, Cooper County, M[issouri] / Salmon Giddings</title>
               <author>Giddings, Salmon</author>
               <date when="1825-09-12">September 12, 1825</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Salmon Giddings to Finis Ewing, dated September 12, 1825. Giddings announces that the  Presbyterian General Assembly has declared the Cumberland Presbyterians to be an independent body of Christians. He believes that Ewing will enjoy this news. William C. Carr is mentioned in regards to a local election. Giddings gives Carr some compliments, and believes that Ewing's brother knows him.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Finis Ewing Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">I-A-4</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">10</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl355</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Missouri</term>
               <term>Cumberland Presbyterian Church History</term>
               <term>Religious Life</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n89639889"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Giddings, Salmon, 1782-1828</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl355a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>St. Louis</name>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Sept.</abbr>
                           <expan>September</expan>
                        </choice> 12. 1825</date> ___</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have the satisfaction of communicating to you a piece of Information highly gratifying to me &amp; I presume no less so to you. At the Past Meeting of the <choice>
                  <abbr>Gen.</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice>- Assembly of the <choice>
                  <orig>Presbyterean</orig>
                  <reg>Presbyterian</reg>
               </choice> church, The subject of the Decision of the synod in regard to your denomination was brought up by the Delegate from our Presbytery. The object of  our Presbytery was to know in what relation to us we were to consider your body. The decision was that we were to consider The <name>cumberland Presbyterians</name>, as an independent body of Christians a decision honorable in my estimation to the cause of  religion &amp; one that removes difficulties that I have felt in my mind.</p>
            <p>I have nothing highly important in regard to the state of religion here. There is an increased attention to Meetings &amp; some seriousness on the minds of several. five were added to my church at our last communion two weeks since three of whom on the hopeful subjects of renewing grace written a <choice>
                  <orig>fiew</orig>
                  <reg>few</reg>
               </choice> months past.</p>
            <p>Politicks agitate the minds of many in this part  <pb n="2" facs="sl355b.small.jpg"/> of the country. Mr <name>William C. Carr</name> is the only candidate in this part of the state who has yet offered. He is a man of good moral character friendly to religion though not a professor, He is a man of integrity &amp; decent talents &amp; acquirements Is from <name>Kentucky</name> &amp; If I mistake not has lived with your Brother ____</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I remain yours with esteem in the Fellowship of the Gospel of our Common Lord</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Salmon Giddings</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Rev. F.</abbr>
                           <expan>Reverend Finis</expan>
                        </choice> Ewing</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl355c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>St Louis <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>MO</abbr>
                           <expan>Missouri</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>Sept 19</date> }</addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Rev. Finis Ewing</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Cooper County</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Boonville</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
