<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc115">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Deed] 1803 Jan. 22, Davidson County, Woolsey Warrington to Lucy White : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc115</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Deed] 1803 Jan. 22, Davidson County, Woolsey Warrington to Lucy White</title>
               <date when="1803-01-22"> 
			 January 22, 1803</date>
               <extent> 3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a Deed for 50 acres of land in Davidson County, Tennessee dated January 22, 1803. The land was sold to Lucy White, now known as  Granny White, by one Woolsey Warrington.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Granny White Deed</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc115 </note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Legal documents</term>
               <term>Real property</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc115a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>This Indenture made twenty second day of January in the year of our Lord One thousand Eight hundred &amp; three, between <name>Woolsey Warrington</name> of the County of <name>Davidson</name> &amp; State of <name>Tennessee</name> of the one part and <name>Lucy White</name> of <name>Williamson County</name> &amp; State aforesaid of the other part, witnesseth that the said Woolsey Warrington for and in consideration of the sum of three hundred dollars in his hand paid the receipt hereof is hereby acknowledged Hath bargained, sold, conveyed &amp; confirmed unto the said Lucy White her heirs &amp; assigns forever all that Tract or parcel of Land lying &amp; being in the said county of Davidson &amp; including a Head Spring of Browns Creek, Beginning at a Sugar tree on <name>John Hopes</name> South boundary line, thence with said line<choice>
                  <abbr> cont</abbr>
                  <expan>continues</expan>
               </choice>  eighty poles to <unclear>ash Elm</unclear> thence South One Hundred poles to three Sugar <choice>
                  <orig>Saplins</orig>
                  <reg>Saplings</reg>
               </choice> thence  West Eighty poles to a sugar tree thence North to the beginning Containing <pb n="2" facs="sc115b.small.jpg"/> Containing by computation fifty acres be the same more or less, being a tract granted by the State of North Carolina to David Beatty, as appears by a Grant No 381 Dated July 19th 1797_ then conveyed by said Beatty to said Warrington as appears by a Deed of Conveyance Dated February 22nd 1802. Together with all woods, waters  Mines Minerals Hereditaments  &amp; appurtenances to the said land belonging in any will appertaining to Have &amp; to Hold unto the said Lucy White her Heirs &amp; assigns forever, and the said Woolsey Warrington for himself his Heirs Executors &amp; administrators Doth Command &amp; agree to wit the said Lucy White her Heirs &amp; assign that he will warrant &amp; forever defend the above mentioned land &amp; premises from the just claim of all manner of persons whatever , In witness as hereof the Woolsey Warrington has hereunto set his hand &amp; seal the Day &amp; year above <choice>
                  <orig>writen</orig>
                  <reg>written</reg>
               </choice>
               <lb/> Signed Seal &amp; Delivered <lb/> In presence of  Woolsey Warrington <lb/>
               <name>Benjamin White</name>
               <lb/>
               <unclear>
                  <name>W Tutherland</name>
               </unclear>
               <pb n="3" facs="sc115c.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>State of Tennessee <lb/> Davidson County Court July Sessions 1803 Benjamin White one of the Subscribing Witness Proved on Oath the Execution of the Within Deed of Conveyance to be the Act and Deed of the said Woolsey Warrington_<lb/>
               <name>Andrew Ewing C,D,C</name>
            </p>
            <p>State of Tennessee <lb/> Davidson County { Register Office <lb/> The Within Deed of Conveyance &amp; <lb/> Probate are duly Registered in Book F <lb/> page 65, Sept. 24th 1803 <lb/>
               <name>Nathan Ewing <unclear>Reg</unclear>
               </name>
               <lb/> fees paid <lb/> Warrington <lb/> To <lb/> L. White { Deed <lb/> 50 acres <lb/> Registered September <lb/> 24th 1803</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
