<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch017">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1802 Apr. 28, [to] Colo[nel] Henry McKinney, Jackson County, [Tennessee] / Archibald Roane: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Tennessee. Governor (1801-1803 : Roane)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch017</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44763255</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1802 Apr. 28, [to] Colo[nel] Henry McKinney, Jackson County, [Tennessee] / Archibald Roane</title>
               <author>Roane, Archibald, 1759-1819 [Tennessee. Governor (1801-1803 : Roane)]</author>
               <date when="1802-04-28">April 28,1802</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter from Archibald Roane, Governor of Tennessee (1801-1803), to Colonel Henry McKinney, in Jackson County (Tennessee), dated April 28, 1802.  Roane informs McKinney that he has information regarding the recent depredations committed by inhabitants of Jackson County and is fearful of reprisal by the Indians in the area.  He indicates his intention to placate the Indians, but urges McKinney to seek criminal charges against the perpetrators, despite any deals they may have made to avoid justice.  He refers to an enclosure from Mr. B. Blackburn that is no longer attached.  Another letter from Roane relative to this issue also appears in the Southeastern Native American Documents Database as <ref>ch018</ref>.</note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> 1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true"> 22</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch017</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Indians of North America--Violence against</term>
               <term>Indians of North America--Government relations</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n96010062"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Roane, Archibald, 1759-1819</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch017a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <date when="1802-04-28">28th. April 1802</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir, </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I regret the Unwarrantable transactions which I understand have taken place in your County.  You are more exposed to danger in case of an Indian War than any other part of the State, And I am sorry to hear that some of the <del type="overstrike">Citizens</del>
               <add place="supralinear">Inhabitants</add> by their Conduct seem more disposed to bring on a War than the Citizens of any other place. I do not believe there is any danger yet in your quarter, but if the people persist in their present line of Conduct I cannot Answer for the consequences.  The innocent blood that will probably be shed will lie at their door, and they will merit the reproach of every good Citizen.</p>
            <p>If real danger should occur I shall use every means in my power to protect and preserve the lives and property of my fellow Citizens;  But all my efforts to prevent that danger will be rendered Abortive unless the Orderly Citizens take some measures to check that turbulent spirit which seems but too much to prevail in some part of your County.  Why cannot a prosecution be commenced against <name type="person">Richmond</name> and <name type="person">Irwin</name> If they are guilty of a Wanton Act in Violation of the laws and treaties they ought to suffer the penalty, and any <unclear>Barters</unclear> that have been or may be made that they cannot be taken to Justice, will fail.  No man in the state need pretend to be superior to the law, Nor<pb n="2" facs="ch017b.small.jpg"/>shall I be deterred from discharging the duties I owe to the State by such empty boasts.
               </p>
            <p>If on the contrary they believe themselves Justifiable in killing the Indian, they ought for their own sakes to surrender themselves to the Civil Authority of the State and court an enquiry into the nature of the transaction that their innocence might appear to the World.  If such an Enquiry should take place, and they should be found <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear/>
               </del> Justifiable if might have a good effect on the minds of the Indians and would remove the impressions which have been made on my mind by the reports in Circulation.</p>
            <p>I wish to hear from you on this subject and to have a true impartial statement of the case, either supported by Affidavits or in such other form as may be most admissable.</p>
            <p>Without something of this kind any steps I might take to tranquillize the minds of the Indians would be attended with doubt and uncertainty and might in the end prove injurious.</p>
            <p>The Judges will be on the road to <name type="place">Nashville</name> in a few days perhaps this might be a <choice>
                  <orig>favourable</orig>
                  <reg>favorable</reg>
               </choice> opportunity to determine in what manner to proceed in making a Statement of the facts or to procure a warrant if it should be thought proper, and necessary.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="ch017c.small.jpg"/>
            <p>The Letter from Mr. <name type="person">B. Blackburn</name> to which I alluded in mine to <name type="person"> 
                  <reg>H</reg> 
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col.o</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> McKinney</name> stated that the Indian <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear/>
               </del> was killed by <name type="person">Richmond</name> and <name type="person">Irwin</name> That the people were much alarmed and requested support in case of danger.  That <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Majr</abbr>
                     <expan>Major</expan>
                  </choice> Russell</name> was collecting a party to go to the mountains in search of some Indian camps and he was afraid of the consequences.  He stated also that frequent Barters were made that the men could not be brought to justice, and concluded with expressing a hope that they would be convinced to the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Mr. Blackburn</name>s Letter is somehow mislaid.  I am inclined to believe the information respecting <name type="person">Major Russell</name> was inaccurate as I have not heard any thing of it since</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>A.</abbr>
                        <expan>Archibald</expan>
                     </choice> Roane</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <p>No. 1 <lb/>Letter to <name type="person"> 
                  <reg>H</reg> 
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col.o</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> McKinney</name>
               <date when="1802-04-28">28 April 1802</date>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="ch017d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>I had a Letter from <name type="person">Mr. Blackburn</name> on this subject and <add place="supralinear">not</add> having <del type="overstrike">not</del> time at present to write to him particularly.  I have enclosed this to him that he may read it and send it on to you.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute> I am <choice>
                     <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                     <expan>Dear</expan>
                  </choice> Sir with respect Your <choice>
                     <abbr>mo. obdt Servt.</abbr>
                     <expan>most obedient servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Archibald Roane</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel</expan>
                        </choice> Henry McKinney</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson County</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <lb/>(Copy)<lb/>
               <del type="overstrike">The Letter from <name type="person">Mr. B. Blackburn</name>
                  <unclear/>
               </del>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
