<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl577">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1818 Dec. [to] J[ames] Winchester / J[ohn] W. Overton   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Overton, J.W.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl577</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>{Letter] 1818 Dec. [to] J[ames] Winchester / J[ohn] W. Overton</title>
               <author>Overton, J.W.</author>
               <date when="1818-12">December 1818</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to General James Winchester from Judge John Overton, dated December 1818. Overton is writing about the tract of land that would later become Memphis, Tennessee at the hands of  Overton, Winchester, and General Andrew Jackson. In Overton's letter he is explaining who owns how much of the land then known as Chickasaw Bluff, including relatives of Winchester. He also gives suggestions about how to administer the property, and says that they should begin laying off the town as soon as possible.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">James Winchester Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">9</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl577</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Overton, John, 1766-1833</term>
               <term>Real property</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Overton, John, 1766-1833</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl577a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Jackson</name> and myself purchas <gap/> the <name>chickasaw Bluff</name> track about the year 1796__ I have retained my part of it ever since. I never knew and in what manner the Genl disposed of his part__ Latterly I have inquired of  him, and he tells me that he never made <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Saml</abbr>
                     <expan>Samuel</expan>
                  </choice> Donelson</name> a deed as he believes, as Saml Donelson was in debt to him, nor did he ever make any contract to that effect, that he recollects, Hence <gap/> it seems clear that you and the heirs <gap/> your Brother William have only <unclear>one eighth</unclear>
               <gap/> of the interest in the chickasaw Bl <gap/> tract of 5000 acres, that I own one <gap/> of which there is no dispute that you, and the heirs of your brother William half only an eighth of the interest in the chickasaw Bluff tract of 5000 acres_ that I own one half, of which there is no dispute__ that you <pb n="2" facs="sl577b.small.jpg"/>
               <gap/> of William Winchester, <del type="overstrike">and Jackson,</del> each <gap/> eighth part &amp; Jackson a fourth___</p>
            <p>It is very important that something <gap/> ould be done as quick as possible, in relation to the laying off a town at the Bluff, as towns are now the fashion, and other sites above may come in competition with it.</p>
            <p>I would therefore recommend, that you immediately appraise your relations, the heirs of Mr <name>William Winchester</name> of the importance of uniting  our views __ that they will constitute an agent here to act for them, making provision for the death of such agent; so that the purchases of lots may not be injured or subject to injury. They should give a  power of attorney, <choice>
                  <orig>authorising</orig>
                  <reg>authorizing</reg>
               </choice> A.B. to unite <gap/> making deeds for town lots__ that death as to <gap/> of the heirs shall not annul the power; and <gap/> case of the death of the said A.B. then <gap/> shall succeed; and in case of his death, <gap/> D. shall succeed , and have all the powers and authorities of the said A.B. the attorney originally appointed. In this way, no injury will arise to purchasers of lots, by the death of any of those interested in the land__ which so frequently produces <pb n="3" facs="sl577c.small.jpg"/> injury, and discourages purchasing town <gap/> rest of the proprietors <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>viz</abbr>
                     <expan>videlicet</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add> Overton, <choice>
                  <abbr>J</abbr>
                  <expan>James</expan>
               </choice> winchester, <gap/> Jackson, will do the land they, viz: vest similar powers in the same person or persons, to make deeds in case of death._</p>
            <p>I beg that you will communicate these things to the heirs of William Winchester as quick as possible; if they do not think proper to join in laying off the town, we will apply to <del type="overstrike">the</del> court, and get a partition made, setting aside the part to itself; and winchester, Jackson and Overton will proceed to lay off a town on the part laid off, and set  a part to them. This not being the interest of the heirs of <choice>
                  <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                  <expan>William</expan>
               </choice> Winchester, I expect they <unclear>will</unclear>
               <gap/> unite with us, and lend out the necessary p <gap/> to lay off said town, <unclear>constituting</unclear> an agent, <gap/> agents, in case of death, and with a provis <gap/>
               <unclear>garcessly</unclear> , that death in any of the partes conce <gap/> shall not annul said power.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am <choice>
                     <abbr>Resply</abbr>
                     <expan>respectfully</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>yr m ob s</abbr>
                     <expan>your most obedient servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>J</abbr>
                        <expan>John</expan>
                     </choice>W Overton</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Genl Winchester</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl577d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Judge Overton <lb/> Dec 1818.</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
