<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl578">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1823 Apr. 4, Nashville [Tennessee, to] James Winchester, Cairo [Tennessee] / J[ohn] W. Overton   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Overton, J[ohn] W.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl578</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1823 Apr. 4, Nashville [Tennessee, to] James Winchester, Cairo [Tennessee] / J[ohn] W. Overton</title>
               <author>Overton, J.</author>
               <date when="1823-04-04">April 4, 1823</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Judge John Overton to General James Winchester, dated April 4, 1823. The subject is Memphis, which was founded by Overton, Winchester, and General Andrew Jackson. Overton is concerned about the future of Memphis. Apparently, some in the Legislature want to take Memphis' court house away. Overton believes that this would be harmful to its success. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">James Winchester Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">9</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl578</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Memphis history</term>
               <term>Politics</term>
               <term>Overton, John, 1766-1833</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Overton, John, 1766-1833</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl578a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name>_ <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Apl</abbr>
                           <expan>April</expan>
                        </choice> 4th 1823</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Genl</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>From some recent hints given it might have been perceived that I received our prospects respecting <name>Memphis</name>, in a gloomy way and that it might be necessary for me or one of the owners to go immediately to the spot__ on my honor I tell you, unless I go there immediately__ and adopt some bold liberal and decisive measure the place (as to its being of consequence, or value, is gone for ever) I have consequently watched the opposition made to it__ have attended our Legislature every Session on that ground__ and must do so  the whole of next Session (3d Monday in <choice>
                  <abbr>Sept</abbr>
                  <expan>September</expan>
               </choice> ) as the affairs of Memphis__ whether it shall be a decent little Town in our day (say <add>in</add> 25 or 30 years,) or <pb n="2" facs="sl578b.small.jpg"/> or a mere <choice>
                  <orig>harbour</orig>
                  <reg>harbor</reg>
               </choice> for a few drunken Boatmen (beside those now there)__ This is the question to be tried at our next Session__ and those opposed to Memphis_ wishing to take the Court house away (which will be its ruin) are numerous and active__ My health is weak very weak this spring_ best if alive will be active_ and confidently believe my <unclear>Grasp of many</unclear> matters and things is superior to all of them put together _ This may seem arrogant but 40 years experience has given me this confidence__ I have full power to act for Jackson__ and Marcus has for you__ on the ground I shall decide and act, __ as it is not in my character to be indecisive</p>
            <p> I repeat, without immediate &amp; prompt attention, &amp; action  we are to be put down; and we must expect to make <pb n="3" facs="sl578c.small.jpg"/> temporary sacrifices to receive permanent advantages__ To err is but human. I may do so possibly but if I do our interest being in common, and <add>mine</add> double yours  well suffer accordingly__ but I have no fear. I should be glad to see you, as I cannot start from here sooner than monday <gap/> week__ By letter it would be <gap/> possible to detail to you, so as <gap/> you a full <unclear>vilel</unclear> by return of mail drop me a line, if you do not come over</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Reply</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>JW Overton</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>PS</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice>_ Marcus &amp; <name>Carr</name> are securely selling their goods_ with them whether it is a town in their day or not is not so material <del type="overstrike">to them</del> __ <name>Lawrence</name> is in the woods surveying__ It is not from them I learn <unclear>things</unclear>
               </add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl578d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                        <expan>General</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name>James Winchester</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>near</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Cairo</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Judge Overton <lb/> 4th Apl 1823</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
