<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc187">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1838 Apr. 4, Kingston, Tennessee [to]  Thomas McAdams / Mary N. Stephenson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Stephenson, Mary N.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc187</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1838 Apr. 4, Kingston, Tennessee [to]  Thomas McAdams / Mary N. Stephenson </title>
               <author> Stephenson, Mary N. </author>
               <date when="1838-04-04"> 
			 April 4, 1838</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated April 4, 1838 from Mary N. Stephenson to her brother Thomas McAdams.  The purpose of the letter is to update the status of marriages and family, as well as various social events in Kingston, Tennessee.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Mary Stephenson Letter</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-1872</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc187</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Stephenson, Mary N.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc187a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Kingston</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date when="1838-04-04">April 4th 1838</date>
               <salute>Dear Brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I received yours and sisters letter which afforded me much pleasure it being the first that I have received from home since I left</p>
            <p>I am sorry to hear of so much sickness in <name>washington</name> hope that before this they are all better but it appears that it dose not stop them from <choice>
                  <orig>marring</orig>
                  <reg>marrying</reg>
               </choice>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Mitchel past through this last week and informed me of the marriage of Jack and also of the intend one of Rheuben  which I suppose they got through with It afforded me a very great satisfaction to see cousin Sam, he gave me all the news I suppose he spent one night and part of a day in this place.</p>
            <p>It is a pleasure to me to hear of new kin but especially such good ones as miss Kain, the next time you see her <choice>
                  <orig>pleas</orig>
                  <reg>please</reg>
               </choice> tell her that I wish her and all the rest of the named folks all the pleasure of a married life  As for the widower tell the girls that they may take care of his debt ship and not poke him at me tell Brother D that we had a party the thursday after he left it was given to the school, their was some <unclear>4 or 3</unclear> ladys and but 10 gentlemen had a very pleasant party, <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice>. Pell waited on cousin and myself, the managers were WP Smith, PH Keith and <name>Peet McEwin</name> it was given at Mr Morgens <unclear>Presbyty</unclear> is in session at this time in this place there is three or four preachers hear that is boarding <choice>
                  <orig>hear</orig>
                  <reg>here</reg>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <p>I have had to change my seat on account of Mr Montgomery having come up to study <del>in</del> a <choice>
                  <orig>surmond</orig>
                  <reg>surmon</reg>
               </choice> I suppose, and it has <choice>
                  <orig>broaken</orig>
                  <reg>broken</reg>
               </choice> the charm of my thoughts so you may not expect much more <add>turn over</add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sc187b.small.jpg"/> I should like very much to know how Pa <choice>
                  <orig>tounge</orig>
                  <reg>tongue</reg>
               </choice> is <choice>
                  <orig>whethe</orig>
                  <reg>whether</reg>
               </choice> it has got well or not,</p>
            <p>Tell all of my friends that it would afford me a very great pleasure to receive a letter once and a while from them, you must write often as it will not cost me anything, tell Emily that I am waiting with great <choice>
                  <orig>impatence</orig>
                  <reg>impatience</reg>
               </choice> for the forward letter from her,</p>
            <p>There is a <choice>
                  <orig>goodeal</orig>
                  <reg>good deal</reg>
               </choice> of sickness in this place at this time, Jim is down with the same disorder that is prevailing which is the same that was hear when we arrived </p>
            <p>The family join with me in love to you all <choice>
                  <orig>pleas</orig>
                  <reg>please</reg>
               </choice> look over the mistakes in this as it has been <choice>
                  <orig>writen</orig>
                  <reg>written</reg>
               </choice> in haste, as I am expecting the preachers for supper and <choice>
                  <orig>their</orig>
                  <reg>there</reg>
               </choice> is preaching to night will not have time to enjoy it, and it was intended to be when commenced</p>
            <closer>All well Your affectionate Sister <signed>Mary N Stephenson</signed>
               <add>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Tho</abbr>
                        <expan>Thomas</expan>
                     </choice> C Mcadams</name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>PS</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> how is washington</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
