<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm001">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Photograph of pit with remains of dog, Chota, ca. 18th century,
			 taken in 1969] / [by Richard R. Polhemus] : a machine-readable
			 transcription</title>
            <author>Polhemus, Richard R.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Tara Hottenstein</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. 3k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>mm001</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44394278</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Museum, University of
				Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Photograph of pit with remains of dog, Chota, ca. 18th
				century, taken in 1969] / [by Richard R. Polhemus]</title>
               <author>Polhemus, Richard R.</author>
               <date when="1969"> 1969</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary"> This photograph is of an Overhill Cherokee pit
				containing the skeletal remains of a dog. Chota or Echota was an Overhill
				Cherokee village located in what is today Monroe County, Tennessee. In the
				mid-18th century, Chota was recognized by Europeans as well as other Indians
				for its powerful socio-economic influence and was regarded as the capital of
				the Cherokee Nation. Chota, as with all the Overhill Cherokee sites, is now
				inundated by the Tellico Reservoir. Excavations of Overhill Cherokee villages
				were conducted by the University of Tennessee between 1967 and 1983 as part of
				the Tellico Archaeological Project. Excavations continued until 1983, and
				laboratory studies and report preparation continued until 1987. The excavations
				were conducted in anticipation of the flooding of the Lower Little Tennessee
				River Valley, in eastern Tennessee, by the Tellico Dam Reservoir. The
				excavations were conducted under contract with the National Park Service and
				the Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA). Principal Investigator, Alfred K. Guthe.
				Field Director, J. Worth Greene.</note>
               <note type="Collection"> Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note type="document"> mm001</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Domestic animals</term>
               <term>Dogs</term>
               <term>Animal remains (Archaeology)</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Salvage archaeology</term>
               <term>Historic sites</term>
               <term>Photographs</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79025770"
                        role="Photographer http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/pht">Polhemus, Richard R.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mm001.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>This is a photographic image of a large rectangular pit
				  with postholes at either end, used to support a roof or cover, subsequently
				  used to bury a small dog. Chota; mid 18th century, excavations by the
				  University of Tennessee 1969, Photograph by Richard R. Polhemus. This
				  information was provided by the Frank H. McClung Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
