<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm015">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Detail of map indicating the Overhill Cherokee Village of
			 Tomotley] / [John Gerrard William De Brahm] : a machine-readable
			 transcription</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Catherine Michelle Love</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Tara Hottenstein</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. 3k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>mm015</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 45080777</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Museum, University of
				Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Detail of map indicating the Overhill Cherokee Village of
				Tomotley] / [John Gerrard William De Brahm]</title>
               <date/>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This is a photograph of John Gerrard William De
				Brahm's map detail of the area of the Little Tennessee River Valley containing
				the Overhill Cherokee village of Tomotley. De Brahm spent time in Tomotley as
				the guest of Chief Ostenaco in 1756 and contributed to the design and building
				of Fort Loudoun, 1756-1759. In 1773 DeBrahm completed his "Report of the
				General Survey in the Southern District of North America" which includes
				information he gathered about the Cherokees while he lived among them.</note>
               <note type="collection">Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note type="document">mm015</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Maps</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Dwellings</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Little Tennessee River Valley (Ga.-Tenn.)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mm015.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Detail of John Gerrard William De Brahm's map of an area
				  of the Little Tennessee River Valley, showing the Overhill Cherokee Village of
				  Tomotley. De Brahm stayed here as a guest of Chief Ostenaco in 1756. De Brahm
				  was a British military engineer who contributed to the design of Ft. Loudoun,
				  1756-1759. This map is published in DeVorsey, L. Jr. 1971. DeBrahm's Report of
				  the Great Survey in the General Survey in the Southern District of North
				  America, University of South Carolina Press, Columbia, SC. This information was
				  provided by the Frank H. McClung Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
