<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tl025">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> [Letter to] the Chiefs of the Creek Nation / the inhabitants
			 residing on the Shawnee River: a machine-readable transcription of an
			 image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Holly Adams</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno>tl025</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 47826174</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, Tennessee. It may be used freely by individuals for
				research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability
				is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter to] the Chiefs of the Creek Nation / the inhabitants
				residing on the Shawnee River</title>
               <date when="1800">ca. 1800</date>
               <extent>2 p</extent>
               <note type="summary">The following document is an undated letter
				addressed to the chiefs of the Creek Nation, which appears to have been written
				on behalf of the white settlers living along the Shawnee River. In this letter,
				the settlers appear to have been making an offer of peace with the Creeks. The
				letter states that the Chickasaws, who were in good relations with the whites,
				had informed the settlers that the majority of the Creek people wished to be at
				peace with them. However, the letter refers to several instances that were
				looked at as being acts of aggression by the Creeks, including the theft of
				some horses and the loss of white lives. The letter also mentions an instance
				in which the settlers stumbled upon a deserted Indian camp and retained the
				horses and other articles from that camp, securing them until it was known to
				what tribe they belonged. The settlers contend they moved to the West with the
				intention of being at peace with all the tribes there, nor, they state, do they
				wish to encroach upon Indian lands or molest Indian peoples. </note>
               <note type="Collection"> Tennessee Historical Society</note>
               <note type="Box">11</note>
               <note type="Folder">n/a</note>
               <note type="Document">tl025</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Creek Indians--Government relations</term>
               <term>Chickasaw Indians--Government relations</term>
               <term>Creek Indians--Claims against</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tl025a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>Brothers if We may so <choice>
                  <orig>Tirm</orig>
                  <reg>Term</reg>
               </choice> you We have had
			 accounts from our Brothers the 
			 <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Chicasaws</orig>
                     <reg>Chickasaws</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name>
			 that the majority of your Nation are <choice>
                  <orig>desierous</orig>
                  <reg>desirous</reg>
               </choice> to
			 be at <del type="overstrike">peace</del>
               <add place="supralinear">Brotherhood</add> With us</p>
            <p>To the Chiefs of the 
			 <name type="place">Creek Nation</name>, The Inhabitants Residing on
			 the 
			 <name type="place">Shawnee River</name>
               <lb/> Sends
			 <choice>
                  <orig>Greetting</orig>
                  <reg>Greetings</reg>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <p>We Have Been Informed by our Brothers The 
			 <name type="person">Chickasaws</name> that if
			 <add place="supralinear">a</add> Majority of your Nation are Desirous to be at
			 Peace and Brotherhood and <del type="overstrike">of Which</del>
               <unclear>(several words faded)</unclear>
               <name type="place">Shawnee River</name>; And Although we have all along
		  Last fall And this Winter have Been <choice>
                  <orig>Lossing</orig>
                  <reg>Losing</reg>
               </choice> of
		  Horses; And sometimes some of Hunters have Been killed; by some that have been
		  Enemies to us, And have Never Molested Any Indians; <choice>
                  <orig>Untill</orig>
                  <reg>Until</reg>
               </choice> Lately <unclear>y !</unclear> some of our Young Men
		  was Occasionally over any Waters of 
		  <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Tennsee</orig>
                     <reg>Tennessee</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> And
		  happened to Come on Several Camps Deserted by <unclear>unclear symbol</unclear>
		  Indians, Whom we Would fondly have Spoken With, but could not find any, And we
		  then Judging by <choice>
                  <orig>there</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice> Leaving of <choice>
                  <orig>there</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice> Camps that they had perhaps Come in to
		  <unclear>De(?)</unclear> our Settlement <choice>
                  <sic>And And</sic>
                  <corr>And</corr>
               </choice> finding
		  some horses <add place="supralinear"> other Articles</add> we Carried them
		  off with us; But Upon a Council held by our Chiefs, the Horses was Order to be
		  secured, <choice>
                  <orig>Untill</orig>
                  <reg>Until</reg>
               </choice> it Could be known to What Indians they
		  Belonged unto; in Order To be Returned And If they Belong to Any Who are at
		  peace <unclear>with</unclear> us or would be Willing to be At peace With us;
		  Upon Condition that If Any Horses from us should be Carried into the 
		  <name type="place">Creek Nation</name> the Chiefs Would secure them so
		  as that we May have them Again, And We on our Parts shall Always be Ready to do
		  the Same by you, these Terms our Brothers <unclear>unclear symbol</unclear>
               <name type="person">Chickasaws</name> have Agreed to With us And as
		  they are Young the More Among us As Well as Amongst you Who Are not to be
		  <unclear>Revealed</unclear> Any Other ways then by <unclear>Signing</unclear>
		  of Such horses As they Shall Either Carry into You or us 
		  <del type="overstrike">And</del> Delivering of <unclear>Us and (the)</unclear>
		  Again  </p>
            <p>And Whereas We Came <del type="overstrike">here</del>  settled
		  here in hopes of having been at Peace With all <unclear>unclear
		  symbol</unclear> Nations of the Indians As we had Purchased the Lands on this
		  River from <unclear>unclear symbol</unclear>
               <name type="person">Cherokee</name> Indians in a <choice>
                  <orig>Publick</orig>
                  <reg>Public</reg>
               </choice> treaty <unclear>unclear symbols</unclear> At
		  <unclear>Walange</unclear> And As We have Drawn a line Lately very near to us
		  Which <gap agent="damage"/> Not settle over nor Molest
		  <unclear>unclear symbol</unclear> Hunting Ground, in Case
		  <gap agent="damage"/> to these our Terms, Otherwise we Cannot Engage
		  for our Young men <gap agent="damage"/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="2" facs="tl025b.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Coppy</orig>
                  <reg>Copy</reg>
               </choice> of a <choice>
                  <orig>Lettr</orig>
                  <reg>Letter</reg>
               </choice>
			 to <unclear>unclear symbol</unclear>
               <name type="place">Creek Nation</name> of Indians</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
