<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc095">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1830 Apr. 20, Washington City [to] James Park, Knoxville, East Tennessee / Luke Lea : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Lea, Luke</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc095</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1830 Apr. 20, Washington City [to] James Park, Knoxville, East Tennessee / Luke Lea</title>
               <author>Lea, Luke</author>
               <date when="1830-04-20">April 20, 1830</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated April 20, 1830 from Luke Lea to James Park.  Lee primarily addresses personal correspondence with Park; however, much of the letter addresses congressional business</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Park Family</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-538 b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc095</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee, East</term>
               <term>Law and legislation</term>
               <term>Washington (D.C)</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007155840"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Lea, Luke, 1783-1851</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc095a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Washington City</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>April 20th 1830</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>,</opener>
            <p>I had the pleasure a few days since of receiving your <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice> of the 9th instant, and was not a little astonished to hear that you had <choice>
                  <abbr>recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> only two letters from me during the present session, for I have written you more than twice that number.  I regret, exceedingly, the unfortunate misunderstanding which has taken place between the Ramsey's and their connections, and <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice>. Churchwell.  I am unable from your account of the matter to see, why any unpleasant feelings should have been felt on the occasion in the first instance- I apprehend it is as you conjecture, for future <choice>
                  <orig>opperations</orig>
                  <reg>operations</reg>
               </choice>.</p>
            <p>I can give you but little information of a political character, that is new.  The white cause is every day gaining ground, and will continue to do so I hope until he shall reach the presidency.  It is well for you and the nation to know that the present elections in <name>virginia</name> are no <choice>
                  <orig>teste</orig>
                  <reg>test</reg>
               </choice> as to the presidential election- The question now is in <name>Virginia</name> the right of instruction- It is not probable that congress will adjourn before the middle of June, indeed it cannot and do the business of the country, which it is absolutely necessary to be done- <pb n="2" facs="sc095b.small.jpg"/> In a political point of view, I am of opinion that the country is not injured by congress remaining yet a little longer in session, and have the corrupt actings and doings of the governed probed to the bottom-Our cause, I mean the cause of the country, will lose nothing by investigation.-</p>
            <p>I have heard of <name>William Park</name> and the Young Ladies being at <name>Philadelphia</name>- It is expected they will return this way-Judge Whits &amp; lady are in good health and spirits-my respects to <choice>
                  <abbr>Mrs</abbr>
                  <expan>Misses</expan>
               </choice> Park and family- will thank you for a line at any time-</p>
            <closer>I am with great respect your friend &amp; <choice>
                  <orig>obt</orig>
                  <reg>obedient</reg>
               </choice>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Srvt </abbr>
                  <expan>Servant</expan>
               </choice>
               <signed>Luke Lea</signed>
               <add>
                  <name>James Park</name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Esqr.</abbr>
                     <expan>Esquire</expan>
                  </choice>  P.S. The Senate have not yet acted on the Cherokee Treaty-what its decision will be no one can tell as all their proceedings remain yet a secret- L.L.</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sc095c.small.jpg"/> Free, <name>Luke Lea</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>James Park Enqr. Knoxville East Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
