<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl372">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1837 Oct. 15 [to] A[ndrew] J[ackson] Donelson, Nashville, Ten[essee]
                    / Dan[iel] S. Donelson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Donelson, Dan. S.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl372</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives,
                        Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching,
                        and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in
                        the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
                        Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
                        741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1837 Oct. 15 [to] A[ndrew] J[ackson] Donelson, Nashville, Ten[nessee] /
                        Dan[iel] S. Donelson</title>
               <author>Donelson, Dan. S.</author>
               <date when="1837-10-15">October 15, 1837</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated October 15, 1837. It is to Andrew
                        Jackson Donelson from his brother Daniel S. Donelson. Daniel informs Andrew
                        that the cotton crop is looking good. He updates Andrew on the health of
                        various family members. Daniel assures him that Andrew's children are being
                        well cared for. Daniel also mentions a local election.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bettie M. Donelson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">III-E-2-3, b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl372</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1
                    spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward
                    which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee, Middle</term>
               <term>Donelson, Andrew Jackson (1799-1871)</term>
               <term>Family</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Donelson, Daniel S.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl372a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Oct</abbr>
                           <expan>October</expan>
                        </choice> 15th
                        1837</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Andrew</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letter from <name>Louisville</name> of the 10th <choice>
                  <abbr>inst</abbr>
                  <expan>instant</expan>
               </choice> was received by yesterday mail. We were all much pleased to
                    hear that you had reached that place in saf <add>e</add> ty and with less
                    fatigue than was anticipated in consequence of the bad roads. Nothing has
                    transpired here upon your farm out of the usual way since you left, every thing
                    is moving on smoothly __ about twenty thousand pounds of cotton was picked out
                    last week, it is opening finely, and I have no doubt will continue to do so
                    having had a few mornings <add>since</add> a slight frost enough to check its
                    growth without injury to the balls __ you are now <del type="overstrike">certain</del> I think certain of a fine crop of this article and every
                    nerve should be exerted for its speedy housing __ my advice therefore <pb n="2" facs="sl372b.small.jpg"/> to <name>mr Holiday</name> is that he should keep an eye single to
                    the this object as the season is a good way advanced. All are well both white
                    and black with the exception of my youngest child, who has been quite <choice>
                  <orig>sicke</orig>
                  <reg>sick</reg>
               </choice> of chill and fever. the next
                        <unclear>peroniner</unclear> comes on tomorrow morning I am in
                        <add>hopes</add> we will be enabled to stop. In regard to the management and
                    care of your children I hope you will be under no apprehensions as I assure that
                    both margaret and myself will do our utmost in our attentions to them, as much
                    so as though they were our own.</p>
            <p>All relatives are well save the wife of cousin William who is said to be
                    dangerously ill of congestive fever. Nancy and <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Cahal</name> are to be shortly married, he has said to our
                    brethren that <pb n="3" facs="sl372c.small.jpg"/> if she will not consent to their union in her house,
                    they will be united elsewhere __ so the thing goes Knowing the understanding
                    between yourself and <name>D,, Hoggalt</name> about the <unclear>horse</unclear>
                    I had previous to getting your letter given directions that <name> Carter</name>
                    should take take him up last night, it has been accordingly done.</p>
            <p>The senatorial <add>election</add> has been <unclear>postponed</unclear> to the
                    coming weeks &amp; <choice>
                  <orig>heer</orig>
                  <reg>hear</reg>
               </choice> that it will be brought on, and
                    that <name>Foster</name> will be elected, I judge so from reading an article in
                    the last union, from which I infer that <name>Bill</name> and Foster have
                    effected a reconciliation and that <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>F</abbr>
                     <expan>Foster</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add> is
                    the man__ Bill having had at no stage of the game any chance.</p>
            <p>margaret your children and all unite in love to you __ <name>mr mahoney</name>
                    sends his compliments. We will <choice>
                  <orig>looke</orig>
                  <reg>look</reg>
               </choice> with great
                    certainty for you in some 4 or 5 weeks from the time you left. <pb n="4" facs="sl372d.small.jpg"/>
                    Present me kindly to <name>mr van Buren</name> , and say to him that I am a
                    well-wisher to the success of his administration.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>your Brother</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Dan S.
                        Donelson</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Maj A. J.</abbr>
                              <expan>Major Andrew Jackson</expan>
                           </choice> Donelson</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <del type="overstrike">Washington City</del>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Nashville</name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                        <del type="overstrike">D. C.</del>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
               <add>
                  <abbr>Recd</abbr>
                  <date>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>octr</abbr>
                        <expan>october</expan>
                     </choice> 27/37</date>
               </add>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P.S</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> The mail of yesterday brought a letter to
                        you from mr van Buren D</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
