<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mc001">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1832 Apr. 13, Harnageville, G[eorgi]a [to] Charles F Welcker, Kingston, Tennessee / W[illia]m A. Love: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Love, William A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent> ca. </extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>mc001</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50435992</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1832 Apr. 13, Harnageville, G[eorgi]a [to] Charles F Welcker, Kingston, Tennessee / W[illia]m A. Love</title>
               <author>Love, William A.</author>
               <date when="1832-04-13">April 13, 1832</date>
               <extent>4 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a letter written by William A. Love in Harnageville, GA to Charles F. Welcker in Kingston, dated April 13, 1832.    Love writes the letter to his friend to update him on the situation in regards to Cherokee land. Love also writes at length on religious matters.  </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Welcker Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1831-32</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mc001</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Land tenure</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Relocation</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Georgia</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Love, William A.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mc001a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Harnageville <choice>
                           <abbr>Ga</abbr>
                           <expan>Georgia</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1832-04-13">13th April 1832</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Charles</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>When reflecting on the many interesting Events that happened during my residence in <name type="place">Athens</name> those in which You was an actor or participant creates some of the most Lively &amp; <choice>
                  <orig>pleaseing</orig>
                  <reg>pleasing</reg>
               </choice> recollections, and <unclear>an</unclear> my part they have sealed a Friendship which I trust will be as Lasting as my Life, I have often thought of writing You, but the Lack of something to interest or amuse You has invariable induced or rather <choice>
                  <orig>compeled</orig>
                  <reg>compelled</reg>
               </choice> me to postpone it, and Even now You must <add place="supralinear">not</add> suppose I am in a better situation, Indeed I am a citizen of <emph>Harnageville</emph> the Lawful capital of  <emph>
                  <name type="place">Cherokee County <choice>
                        <abbr>Ga</abbr>
                        <expan>Georgia</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>
               </emph>and that I am doing very Little professional business, for at Least one of the strongest reasons in the world <del type="overstrike">is there</del> there is very little to do, I am in hopes however the time is not for distant when I may have better news, The survey of the <name type="place">Cherokee nation</name> has commenced and is now going on, <pb n="2" facs="mc001b.small.jpg"/> a lottery for the disposition of the lands will take place it is expected so soon as the survey is completed, which will be in the course of 3 or 4 months, and will be settled this fall and winter without the interposition of the General Government, The Indians will remain undisturbed in their <emph>actual improvements</emph>, In them they will be protected, Georgia pays &amp; intends to pay no respect to the decision of the Supreme Court in the <name>Missimary</name> case, they are Let in the penitentiary, But Enough of this, I fear it is to be the mother of discord, nay it is that already; of something worse,</p>
            <p>Then let us turn to <add place="supralinear">the consideration of</add> something which is all harmonious and beautiful; something that claims the calmest deliberations of our minds and the warmest affections of our hearts, It is that upon which depends our happiness here and our Eternal happiness or misery hereafter, Surely then it is something that deserves our earliest our highest consideration, It is that which prepares us to meet God in peace; the Religion of Jesus Christ, I ask myself the solemn question  "have I that Religion, I trust I have, Yes I thank God for the hope which he has given <add place="supralinear">me</add> in his son, "the lamb of God which taketh away the sins of the world" that I have tasted of the Heavenly gift, &amp; been made a partaker <del type="overstrike">in</del> of the Holy Ghost &amp; the powers of the world to come, <pb n="3" facs="mc001c.small.jpg"/> May he give me Grace to continue faithful unto the End and at last receive me to praise Him in heaven Shall I propose the same solemn question to Yourself — and shall my soul thrill with heavenly Joy at Your answer in the affirmative, If You cannot answer me thus; let me admonish You to set about the important business. It admits of no delay, "now" is the proper time, May my God help You to improve it, to his honor &amp; glory and the Salvation of Your own immortal Soul, But my Dear Charles I fear like myself in earlier days You will acknowledge its importance, but postpone it until a more "convenient season" What argument shall I use to <add place="supralinear">induce You to</add> discard the black insinuation of the Prince of darkness, Shall I say that Your only regret will be that You did not <choice>
                  <orig>imbrace</orig>
                  <reg>embrace</reg>
               </choice> religion Years ago, that for the sacrifice of trifling pleasures You gain Eternal <choice>
                  <orig>Joye</orig>
                  <reg>Joy</reg>
               </choice>, the substantial, the Supreme good, May God convince of the truth and may You seek and obtain his pardon is my first &amp; fondest wish for You, Let me hear from You soon,</p>
            <p>Give my Compliments to Your Father &amp; Mother, <name type="person">Lewis</name>, <name type="person">Catharine</name>, <name type="person">Frederick</name> and all the family and accept for Yourself the assurance of my kindest warmest solicitude</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm.</abbr>
                        <expan>William</expan>
                     </choice> A. Love</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Charles F. Welcker</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="bottom">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>PS</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> Let me know what Your father is going to do about those negroes at <name type="place">Gainsville</name>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="mc001d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Harnageville <choice>
                        <abbr>Ga</abbr>
                        <expan>Georgia</expan>
                     </choice> }</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1832-04-13">13th April 1832 </date>}</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="top right">12 ½</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mr. Charles F Welcker</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Kingston</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <emph>
                        <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                     </emph>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left">Mail</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
