<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl158">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1818 Mar. 7, Westwood, [TN] [to] Joseph Woods, New Orleans, [LA] / J. W.    : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>J. W.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl158</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50564985</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1818 Mar. 7, Westwood, [TN] [to] Joseph Woods, New Orleans, [LA] / J. W.    </title>
               <author>J. W. </author>
               <date when="1818-03-07">March 7, 1818</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to Joseph Woods  from someone with the initials J. W., dated March 7, 1818. The author of the letter is updating Joseph on the news from Westwood, people's health, and their activities. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Woods Family</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">Foster-West</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl158</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Diseases</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">J. W.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl158a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Westwood</name>
                     <date when="1818-03-07">March 7th 18</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear, W</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I hope <choice>
                  <orig>er</orig>
                  <reg>ere</reg>
               </choice>, this you have received my letter, which will give you more pleasure than you have known since you left your home with all its pleasures I have received your two last letters the first of which contained the <choice>
                  <orig>beautifull</orig>
                  <reg>beautiful</reg>
               </choice> Ring , you sent me, with which I am much pleased; you have not told me in any of your letters, how you are situated, or where you board, neither have you said, one word, about my Brother, <name type="person">Frank</name>; whether he has <choice>
                  <orig>commeced</orig>
                  <reg>commenced</reg>
               </choice> business and what his prospects are, or whether he has entered <choice>
                  <orig>in to</orig>
                  <reg>into</reg>
               </choice> a partnership, We have had so many distressing Occurrences since I wrote you last that I hardly know where to begin, in the first place, <name type="person">Maria Price</name>, when returning from <name type="person">Mr.  Bradford</name>s, fell from her horse and broke her collar bone, I got her to Town the <pb n="2" facs="sl158b.small.jpg"/> same day and had it set, but she has been quite indisposed since, not long after that our dear friend, and good <choice>
                  <orig>physition</orig>
                  <reg>physician</reg>
               </choice>
               <name type="person">Dr. Erving</name>, was taken ⁁ <add place="supralinear">with</add> a bad cold and had one fever, but recovered from it, and by his anxiety to do good to others he exposed himself in such a way, <del type="overstrike">t</del> he relapsed, and is gone — the grief of all, who knew him, cannot be described, his <choice>
                  <orig>beautifull</orig>
                  <reg>beautiful</reg>
               </choice>, <choice>
                  <sic>and and</sic>
                  <corr>and</corr>
               </choice> amiable , wife, is in greater grief  than we can imagine, there has been a great deal of sickness in the town and <choice>
                  <orig>neighbourhood</orig>
                  <reg>neighborhood</reg>
               </choice> this winter, and our family has not, escaped this; thank God our lives are spared; Of late we have had a <choice>
                  <orig>peste</orig>
                  <reg>pest</reg>
               </choice> in the creek that has swept up all our fences  that was in its reach, there never has been any thing like it since we have lived here before <name type="person">Mr. Little</name> is in great distress about it and thinks he has lost an hundred <choice>
                  <orig>pannell</orig>
                  <reg>panel</reg>
               </choice> of fence, he is very attentive good man, too good to the negroes, for he often lets them all go off and <choice>
                  <orig>dose</orig>
                  <reg>does</reg>
               </choice> the work himself, <name type="person">Lewis</name> he cannot do any thing with he is, outlawed if the President had got to <name type="place">Nashville</name> I should <pb n="3" facs="sl158c.small.jpg"/> have changed <unclear/> for one of the other bags with a hope, that he might never come back, I can see no reason why such a <choice>
                  <orig>villian</orig>
                  <reg>villain</reg>
               </choice> should be kept on the place or ever in the country, my garden is coming on but poorly, the heavy rain has almost washed away those, <unclear>cacked bats</unclear> , and other curiosities, that were made <unclear>then</unclear> but they may all go. if I can only live to see you once more, <name type="person">Miss Martha</name> is with me at present her health I think is something better than when you left home; I hope you will make yourself perfectly easy, on my account as I enjoy my usual health since I wrote you last, do not trouble yourself to look for a cordial, stand as I do not care for any without I could have had the one I saw; you complain of dull times but I think you appear to be as busy as ever, do not spend your time in writing long letters to me I am satisfied to know you are well, and do ⁁ <add place="supralinear">not</add> write oftener, than affection, induces you</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">J W</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl158d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mr. Joseph Woods</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">New Orleans</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="under address">
                  <del type="overstrike">
                     <unclear/>
                  </del>
               </add>
               <add place="up left side of page">
                  <name type="person">
                     <unclear>Mrs</unclear> W.</name>
                  <date when="1818-03-07">7 March</date>
                  <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Recd</abbr>
                     <expan>Received</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <date when="1818-04-02">2nd April </date>
                  <lb/> answered <date when="1818-04-03">3rd <choice>
                        <abbr>Apl.</abbr>
                        <expan>April</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
