<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl579">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1823 Apr. 13, Nashville, T[ennessee, to] James Winchester, Cairo, T[ennessee] / John W. Overton   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Overton, John W.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl579</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1823 Apr. 13, Nashville, T[ennessee, to] James Winchester, Cairo, T[ennessee] / John W. Overton</title>
               <author>Overton, John W.</author>
               <date when="1823-04-13">April 13, 1823</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Judge John W. Overton to General James Winchester, dated April 13, 1823. Overton  writes  regarding  Memphis, which he, Winchester, and General Andrew Jackson founded. Overton is writing about the proposition before the Legislature to move the court from Memphis. Overton is afraid that the move will ruin Memphis as a successful city. He also asks Winchester to help him with a lawsuit he is trying.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">James Winchester Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">9</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl579</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Overton, John, 1766-1833</term>
               <term>Memphis history</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Overton, John, 1766-1833</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl579a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Apl</abbr>
                           <expan>April</expan>
                        </choice> 13th 1823</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>on wednesday morning early I start by the steam boat Nashville to <name>Memphis</name>__ AsI  intimated in my last events are developing themselves <unclear>Therein</unclear> clearly that all our property are lost, unless something is done; and nothing will do unless I go myself Every effort is making to take the court from that place, and fix it elsewhere. Believing as I do that every thing as to the growth of the place depends on keeping the court I shall use every reasonable means to preserve it. Should Memphis be put back  in that way, it may never survive so fatal a blow_ in all human probability it never would as some other place, would take the lead, and keep it. Witness Nashville <pb n="2" facs="sl579b.small.jpg"/> and every other town; in whose <choice>
                  <orig>neighbourhood</orig>
                  <reg>neighborhood</reg>
               </choice> as good cites may be found__ It best <unclear>illy</unclear> suits me to go__ as I am in bad health__ Unless I go now, I cannot before next Session of the Legislature. where all would be lost; and all the plans I have hitherto adopted by attending the Legislature, be defeated</p>
            <p>Tell <name>Mr Roberts</name>, he had better get the suit with <name>Ring</name> respecting the land, depending at <name>Lebanon</name>_ continued</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>yr</abbr>
                     <expan>your</expan>
                  </choice> friend</salute>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>J</abbr>
                     <expan>John</expan>
                  </choice> W Overton</signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                        <expan>General</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Jas</abbr>
                        <expan>James</expan>
                     </choice> Winchester</addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl579c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>You can see that it will be impossible for me to be at Lebanon on monday two weeks 28th this month, to try the Suit between <name>Seary</name> heir &amp; <name>Eaton</name>. I beg Genl, that you will go over to Lebanon on Sunday 27th so as to be on the ground on monday when it is called and you or <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Col</abbr>
                        <expan>Colonel</expan>
                     </choice> Smith</name> from <name>Jackson</name> or <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Maj</abbr>
                        <expan>Major</expan>
                     </choice> Walker</name> from <name>Wilson</name> as Eatons agent must make affidavit for the continuance. I have had a complaint in my stomach for this, is the 3d Spring &amp; the Doctors advise me to travel for 3 or four weeks__ It never has been counted on  affidavit. and the <choice>
                     <abbr>ct</abbr>
                     <expan>court</expan>
                  </choice> cannot  refuse I think, on account of my indisposition &amp; no other person understanding the case_  Speak to Lawyer Anderson who will act for me in getting it continued_ I have also written to <unclear>Walker</unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr> JO</abbr>
                     <expan>John Overton</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl579d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Judge <name>John Overton</name>
                  <lb/> 13th April 1823 <lb/> concerning suit <lb/> between the heirs <lb/> of Searey &amp; Eaton</add>
               <add>answerd <lb/>
                  <date>20th apl /1823</date>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Genl <name>James Winchester</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>near</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Cairo</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>T</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Judge</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
