<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl308">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1838 Jan. 30 Washington City [to] Adam Fergusson / W. B. Campbell   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Campbell, W. B.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl308</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1838 Jan. 30 Washington City [to] Adam Fergusson / W. B. Campbell</title>
               <author>Campbell, W. B.</author>
               <date when="1838-01-30">January 30, 1838</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from W. B. Campbell to Adam Fergusson, dated January 30, 1838. Campbell writes that he is sending information requested for by Fergusson. He writes about a possible scandal involving Congressmen J. F. H. Claiborne and Samuel Jameson Gholson in the Mississippi election. He also writes about the Congressional session, pension laws, and the National Bank question.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers </note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">IV-G-1 b2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">10</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl308</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>United States -- Politics and government -- 1815-1861</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007144179"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Campbell, William Bowen, 1807-1867</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl308a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Washington City</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>January 30. 1838</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I here transmit you the information which I have obtained from <name type="place">Richmond</name> in relation to the cases <add place="supralinear">about</add> which you had addressed me,_ I send you the information that you may make any other suggestions about the cases which may have been overlooked or not attended to_</p>
            <p>I have transmitted you a copy of all the laws, &amp; resolutions <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>and etcetera</expan>
               </choice> in relation to the revolutionary soldiers &amp;c_ I could not obtain a copy of a list of pensioners, as the list you said was published by order of the Senate &amp; there is no copy remaining,_ I will try &amp; procure you a list if I can_</p>
            <p>We are engaged in the House of <choice>
                  <abbr>Rep.</abbr>
                  <expan>Representative</expan>
               </choice> on the <name type="place">Mississippi</name> election, and hope to <pb n="2" facs="sl308b.small.jpg"/> have the vote taken upon it <choice>
                  <orig>tommorrow</orig>
                  <reg>tomorrow</reg>
               </choice> I calculated that the party in power will retain <name type="person">Gholson</name> &amp; <name type="person">Claiborne</name>, contrary to the decision of the people of Mississippi at their regular election. This if <unclear>done</unclear> will be one of the most flagrant acts of corruption ever perpetrated by a <choice>
                  <orig>deleberative</orig>
                  <reg>deliberative</reg>
               </choice> assembly. But Party spirit is carried to such an extent, that I <unclear>begin to tremble for</unclear> institutions_ The <unclear>Sub-Treasury</unclear> is again before both branches of congress in a more objectionable form than as introduced at the call session. We are all who are in the opposition to that measure very confident that it will not pass, and are much gratified that our legislature have expressed their opinion against it It is a measure that should be opposed by every exertion. And every expression of opinion by deliberation assemblies, by <unclear>primal</unclear> assemblies of the people &amp; by individuals by letters <unclear>&amp;c</unclear> have their influence in a government <pb n="3" facs="sl308c.small.jpg"/> organized as our is as yet, and it should have great influence, for I am a true believer in the right of the people to instruct, and the duty of the <unclear>agent</unclear> to obey._ The resolution which you mentioned as having been introduced in the Senate has not yet passed that body nor reached our house,_ I should be decidedly in <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice> of altering or amending the law as you have stated so as to embrace the cases you named we will try at this session to have the pension law extended to the soldiers of the Indian wars_ down to 1795 I Know not whether it will succeed_ I hope it may_ I think we can certainly amend the pension law so as to embrace the widows who were married during the Revolution._ Let me hear from you often. I can get any information you may want from Richmond <pb n="4" facs="sl308d.small.jpg"/> &amp; will do so with great pleasure_ Let me know the <unclear>news of </unclear>
               <del type="overstrike"><?xm-replace_text {del}?></del> my own native <unclear>hill</unclear> country_ the sweetest spot on the earth, with all its <unclear>homeliness</unclear>_</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>With great respect your <choice>
                     <abbr>Obt Svt</abbr>
                     <expan>Obedient Servent</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">WB Campbell</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Adam <choice>
                           <orig>Ferguson</orig>
                           <reg>Fergusson</reg>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Eqr</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
