<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl273">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1843 Apr. 23, Shelbyville [to] Samuel Orr, Mount Pleasant, Tenn[essee] / John Orr   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Orr, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl273</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1843 Apr. 23, Shelbyville [to] Samuel Orr, Mount Pleasant, Tenn[essee] / John Orr</title>
               <author>Orr, John</author>
               <date when="1843-04-23">April 23, 1843</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from John Orr to Sam Orr, dated April 23, 1843.             John apologizes for not writing sooner, and that he can not blame it on being occupied with women. He writes that the night before was supposed to be the Second Coming according to Miller's doctrine. John does not believe in Miller. He also mentions that he does not support the temperance movement. He reports no success at getting a job for James, and that he has not heard from an uncle or Jane in some time.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl273</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Religious thought -- 19th century</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Orr, John</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl273a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Shelbyville</name>
                     <date when="1843-04-23">April 23rd 1843</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear Sam</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I forget whether I wrote to you last or you to me. but am inclined to <choice>
                  <orig>beleive</orig>
                  <reg>believe</reg>
               </choice> that the <unclear>sin</unclear> rests with myse ⁁ <add place="supralinear">l</add> f (as I am very much given to the Commission of such) and if so, I claim your forgiveness or the grounds of my ␣</p>
            <p>I am at a loss for a suitable word to fill that space with, I cannot plead want of time in my extenuation for if there is any one thing that I have too much of, it is idle time for if I were a "Ladies Man" the <unclear>"Sex's</unclear> Idol" <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>and etcetera</expan>
               </choice> I might plead attendance upon them as a very good reason for not writing sooner but this I cannot do without stretching the truth neither am I again attempting to court the muse nor, — being an alien — do I ever muddle with politicks or listen to <unclear>stump speeches</unclear> . I am equally uninterested in the temperance reform (which by the by, is about to prove no reform at all, as far as Shelbyville is concerned) and as to <name type="person">Miller</name>s doctrine, I put not the least faith in it — "Speaking of guns" I am writing to you upon the very "Ides of March" this is the day that the <choice>
                  <orig>fullfillment</orig>
                  <reg>fulfillment</reg>
               </choice> of Miller's prophecy was to have taken effect last night when it was lightning and thundering and blowing <pb n="2" facs="sl273b.small.jpg"/> and hailing and raging sulphur <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c &amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>and etcetera and etcetera</expan>
               </choice> I was not a little frightened I can assure you I began to think that the odds were something like ten to one in Millers favor, but to day, the tables are turned, my fears have <unclear>vanished</unclear> hope has dispersed them all, just as this Sabbath morning glorious sun dispersed the darkness and terms of the past night. Pshaw! who could for a moment beleive that this bright earth would be destroyed at a time when every tree, and shrub, and flower begins to put on it's livery of green seeming to rejoice in it's new existence; when every warbler of the grove, from the mocking bird to the turkey buzzard, seems not only willing but uncommonly anxious to split its wind-pipe, merely as any expression of joy as the return of spring: the thing if absolutely ridiculous, you may depend upon it, that if ever this world passes through the fiery ordeal that the prophetic Miller has consigned it to, the consuming blaze will break out somewhere in the frigid zone, about the middle of winter —</p>
            <p>But I have been digressing sadly — it is the failing of all very prolific writers — <name type="person">Byron</name> was subject to it (see Don Juan) I started off in pursuit of a proper english word to fill a blank upon page first — <pb n="3" facs="sl273c.small.jpg"/> and have failed to find one, so you can fill it up to pledge yourself provided you lave out laziness &amp; —</p>
            <p>I have been unable up to the present term to procure a situation for James in the way of business there is little or nothing doing here <unclear>you can form</unclear> a guess at what a low ebb it has arrived at, when I tell you, that the house of J &amp; T <unclear>Leakin Co</unclear> (the most extensive in the place) employing when I first came to <choice>
                  <abbr>Sh</abbr>
                  <expan>Shelbyville</expan>
               </choice> four clerks and a book Keeper have now in their employ only one clerk and even that one is not kept busy — I tried to give <choice>
                  <abbr>Ja</abbr>
                  <expan>James</expan>
               </choice> . a place there and at several other houses and failed</p>
            <p>I had a letter from Uncle W some time since stating his intention to pay S a visit, I have neither seen nor heard from him since I <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>ansd</abbr>
                     <expan>answered</expan>
                  </choice> it,</unclear> what has become of him? I wrote home shortly after I last wrote to you but have not <choice>
                  <abbr>recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> an <choice>
                  <abbr>ans</abbr>
                  <expan>answer</expan>
               </choice> yet if you have had a letter since you wrote me last, let me have all the news — I have not heard from <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Au</abbr>
                     <expan>Aunt</expan>
                  </choice>
               </unclear> Jane in some time although it has been more than a month since I wrote</p>
            <p>I have a note on <name type="person">Henry W Spencer</name> for 28$ due two years ago he used to live in Mt. P. I wish you would make <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>some</unclear>  inquiry about him, and find out if possible whether or not it can be collected and where a constable would be likely to find him</p>
            <p>As this has been written in a hurry you must make allowances for it — give my love to Ja. and Uncle Wm remember me to all my old acquaintances and beleive me <choice>
                  <abbr>D Saml</abbr>
                  <expan>Dear Samuel</expan>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your very affectionate brother</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">John Orr</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl273d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="above address">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>ansd</abbr>
                     <expan>answered</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <date when="1843-06-19">June 19</date>.</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mr <name type="person">Samuel Orr</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Mount Pleasant</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="under address">mail</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
