<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm018">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Photograph of mid-18th century central hearth Cherokee
			 townhouse at Tomotley, taken in 1976] / [by Gerald F. Schroedl] : a
			 machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Schroedl, Gerald F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Catherine Michelle Love</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Tara Hottenstein</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. 3k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>mm018</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 45081581</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Museum, University of
				Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Photograph of mid-18th century central hearth Cherokee
				townhouse at Tomotley, taken in 1976] / [by Gerald F. Schroedl]</title>
               <author>Shroedl, Gerald F.</author>
               <date>1976</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This is a photograph of a central hearth of a
				Cherokee townhouse from the Overhill village of Tomotley dating back to the
				mid-18th century. All political and social events were held in these large
				winter townhouses, which were cone-shaped and appeared to look like a small
				mountain from a distance. Some were large enough to hold 500 people. The seats
				were arranged like an amphitheater with the seats rising one above another,
				leaving an area in the center for a fire. Excavations of Tomotley were
				conducted by the University of Tennessee in 1976 as part of the Tellico
				Archaeological Project in anticipation of the flooding of the Lower Little
				Tennessee River by the Tellico Dam Reservoir. The excavations were conducted
				under contract with the National Park Service and the Tennessee Valley
				Authority (TVA). Principal investigator, Alfred K. Guthe. Field Director,
				Gerald F. Schroedl</note>
               <note type="collection">Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note type="document">mm018</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</term>
               <term>Salvage archaeology</term>
               <term>Historic sites</term>
               <term>Hearths</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n78090514"
                        role="Photographer http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/pht">Schroedl, Gerald F.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mm018.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>UT TVA 40<unclear/>5 Tomotley Feature 393 
				  <date when="1976-08-21">21 August 1976</date>
                     <unclear/> 135 30</head>
                  <figDesc>Central hearth Cherokee townhouse at Tomotley, mid-18th
				  century. Excavations by the University of Tennessee, 1976. Photograph by Gerald
				  F. Schroedl. This information was provided by the Frank H. McClung
				  Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
