<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl359">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1835 Dec. 24, Nashville [Tennessee] [to] Finis Ewing, Lexington, Missouri / Ja[me]s Smith   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Smith, Ja[me]s</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl359</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1835 Dec. 24, Nashville [Tennessee] [to] Finis Ewing, Lexington, Missouri / Ja[me]s Smith</title>
               <author>Smith, Ja[me]s</author>
               <date when="1835-12-24">December 24, 1835</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Rev. James Smith to Rev. Finis Ewing, dated December 24, 1835. Smith is upset with Ewing's misinterpretation of Smith's opinions on methods of proper Baptism. Smith writes that he is unsure whether to take a loan, as interest will be charged, and he does not believe in usury.  He is upset that Missouri allows usury. Smith updates Ewing on the progress of publishing some lectures. Smith teases Ewing for hiring someone to read the lectures to him.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Finis Ewing Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> I-A-4</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">17</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl359</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>Cumberland Presbyterian Church</term>
               <term>Religious Thought - 19th Century</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Smith, James</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl359a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name>, <date>24 December 1835</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Uncle Finis</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Yours of the <date>22nd October</date> came duly to hands enclosing $50.00 for which I thank you <gap/> are so candid in your remarks on my church history <gap/> the <choice>
                  <orig>candour</orig>
                  <reg>candor</reg>
               </choice> almost borders on severity Pray where do I hold out the idea, that immersion is the proper mode of Baptism True I state the fact that in the 1st Century the practise obtained now had you read a little farther on you would have found it stated that they immersed females naked. Can it be <choice>
                  <orig>infered</orig>
                  <reg>inferred</reg>
               </choice> from that statement that I believe such a practise <choice>
                  <orig>consistant</orig>
                  <reg>consistent</reg>
               </choice> with the discipline of the church of Christ  But, in my opinion the last <unclear>inference</unclear> is <add>as</add> fair as the first But as Uncle Fine appears to have read only the 1st Century <add>and</add> with the same object in view that a certain methodist preacher had when he read a page or two about Wesley. <choice>
                  <abbr>viz</abbr>
                  <expan>videlicet</expan>
               </choice> to kick the Scotchman I will not cavil about it but bear my Kicking with all meekness and if I live to publish a second edition I will so surround and satisfy and explain both these statements that no man will believe that I view immersion as the proper mode whether the subject be naked or clothed <pb n="2" facs="sl359b.small.jpg"/> I do not know <choice>
                  <orig>whither</orig>
                  <reg>whether</reg>
               </choice> I will want the $200.00 or not in spring but 10 percent interest is certainly usury and I am Sorry to hear that your state authorities sanction such conduct. You talk of 6 errors in that Lectures come up to 20 and we may strike a bargain usury notwithstanding</p>
            <p>I have not yet get the paper for your work but will publish a prospectus and have the work out by the assembly. But if I wait <gap/> the brethren get a sufficient number of subscribers I will wait until my head is gray. I Know them <choice>
                  <orig>to</orig>
                  <reg>too</reg>
               </choice> well to expect much in that way. So you must excuse me I have set my heart on the publication of the Lectures and if the Lord in his providence does not say no the brethren may say what they please, Ill bring the book out if I have to peddle it off myself.</p>
            <p>What a blessing I have gotten before this for the typographical errors in <choice>
                  <abbr>Br</abbr>
                  <expan>Brother</expan>
               </choice> Ewings last sermon well now it is too bad that my <unclear>brethren</unclear> should have me running all over the country dunning for a little money to meet demands on the office and thereby expose me to the censure of those whose <unclear>productions</unclear> are mangled and murdered in my absence; But in earnest before I left <pb n="3" facs="sl359c.small.jpg"/> I corrected the sermon twice but <unclear>find</unclear> the last were neglected to be inserted</p>
            <p>Shall the Pulpit live or die? I have only 2 or 3 sermons on hand cant begin the 2d <choice>
                  <abbr>vol</abbr>
                  <expan>volume</expan>
               </choice> without a better supply. what will Uncle Fene do? Some of the big brethren within a thousand miles of Cumberland College would write were it not for the <gap/> ssociation!!!! Could Br. Ewing by some means inform such (without <choice>
                  <orig>comitting</orig>
                  <reg>committing</reg>
               </choice> me) that their bigness <choice>
                  <orig>savers</orig>
                  <reg>savors</reg>
               </choice> not of  the spirit of the Gospel. Two sermons from <name>Loury</name> in the last number worth their weight in gold.</p>
            <p>The date of your letter with fifty dollars I mention <unclear>ureny</unclear> I have not the proper letter before me</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>very affectionately <lb/> yours in best bonds</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Jas</abbr>
                        <expan>James</expan>
                     </choice> Smith</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P.S.</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> That is an old adage "A fool and his money are soon parted" Dont however design to hint that you acted unwisely in giving an incompetent brother 25 cents to read my letter and gave away your money for nothing. Maybe he will attempt this for 50 cents and <unclear>
                     <choice>
                        <orig>choak</orig>
                        <reg>choke</reg>
                     </choice>
                  </unclear> at it before he is done My Printers <unclear>Devil</unclear> will undertake it for fourpence, half penny and board himself while he is at it. aye and pay half a cent for every word he <choice>
                     <orig>mises</orig>
                     <reg>misses</reg>
                  </choice> . Ye must be poor readers in Missouri</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl359d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>Nashville. <name>
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>T.</abbr>
                              <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </name>
                        <date>
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Dec</abbr>
                              <expan>December</expan>
                           </choice> 30</date>
                     </figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Rev</abbr>
                        <expan>Reverend</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name>Finis Ewing</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Lexington</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Missouri</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
