<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm019">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Drawing depicting Cherokee townhouse and summer pavilion
			 posthole patterns at mid-18th century Tomotley, created in 1976] / [by Marion
			 Drescher] : a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Drescher, Marion</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Catherine Michelle Love</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Tara Hottenstein</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. 3k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>mm019</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 45081860</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Museum, University of
				Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Drawing depicting Cherokee townhouse and summer pavilion
				posthole patterns at mid-18th century Tomotley, created in 1976] / [by Marion
				Drescher]</title>
               <author>Drescher, Marion</author>
               <date>1976</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This is a drawing of posthole patterns dating
				back to the mid-18th century of a winter townhouse (top) and summer pavilion
				(below) from the Overhill Cherokee town of Tomotley. All political and social
				events were held in these townhouses. The winter townhouse was a large conical
				structure, which contained amphitheater seating around a central hearth. The
				rectangular summer town or council house was an open pavilion suitable for warm
				weather. Excavations of Tomotley were conducted by the University of Tennessee
				in 1976 as part of the Tellico Archaeological Project in anticipation of the
				flooding of the Lower Little Tennessee River by the Tellico Dam Reservoir. The
				excavations were conducted under contract with the National Park Service and
				the Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA). Principal investigator, Alfred K. Guthe.
				Field Director, Gerald F. Schroedl.</note>
               <note type="collection">Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note type="document">mm019</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Drawings</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Dwellings</term>
               <term>Holes</term>
               <term>Salvage archaeology</term>
               <term>Historic sites </term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Artist http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/art">Drescher, Marion</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mm019.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Drawing of posthole pattern of Cherokee townhouse and
				  summer pavilion at Cherokee town of Tomotley, mid-18th century, University of
				  Tennessee excavations, 1976. Drawing by Marion Drescher. This information was
				  provided by the Frank H. McClung Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
