<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0040">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1824 Apr. 19, Washington [to]  Mr. John Ross  / Sam Houston: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Houston, Sam</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0040</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1824 Apr. 19, Washington [to]  Mr. John Ross  / Sam Houston</title>
               <author>Houston, Sam</author>
               <date when="1824-04-19">April 19, 1824</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated April 19, 1824 written by Sam Houston, future governor of Tennessee,  to John Ross, future chief of the Cherokee Nation.  Houston writes in response to some questions posed by Ross in regards to John Spears, an interpreter for the Cherokee who served as a delegate on behalf of the Arkansas tribe of the Cherokee.  There is apparently a controversy involving Lewis Ross over whether or not Spears was entitled to receive a plot of land.  </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0040</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Land tenure</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n82151189"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Houston, Sam, 1793-1863.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0040a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Washington</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>19th <choice>
                           <abbr>Apl.</abbr>
                           <expan>April</expan>
                        </choice> 1824</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>A Copy-</add>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have the pleasure to acknowledge your letter of 8th <choice>
                  <abbr>inst.</abbr>
                  <expan>instant</expan>
               </choice> In reply to the Several questions propounded by you, I will answer that at the time <name>Mr John Spears</name> visited this <del type="overstrike">place</del> place, it was certainly in Character of an <name>Arkansas</name> Delegate. When the inability to Come on of <name>Takatokah</name> who had been associated with <name>Talonteesky</name> as a delegate from Arkansas, was ascertained by <add>the</add> arrival of Talonteesky alone, it was concluded by <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Gov.</abbr>
                     <expan>Governor</expan>
                  </choice> McMinn</name>  to fill the vacancy of Takatokah by the substitution of Mr. Spears  who was considered as a part of the Arkansas Tribe of <name>Cherokees</name>. whether Spears was actually enrolled as an emigrant for Arkansas I do not now recollect_ <pb n="2" facs="pa0040b.small.jpg"/> but I do distinctly recollect that he was appointed, as a delegate from Arkansas._</p>
            <p>Until Spears was employed at the Agency as Interpreter his residence had  been at <name>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Hiawassee</orig>
                     <reg>Highwassee</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> old Town, and that his farm and family remained at that pace were notorious facts.  Once, or oftener to my knowledge he was absent from the Agency to visit his family: and spoke to me of his farm.  the place on which he resided <del type="overstrike">near</del>
               <add>near</add> the agency was the property of <name>Mrs. Cary</name> with whom he lived, but did not as I understood (according) to the laws of the Nation acquire Any right to it. as all property found in possession of the wife at marriage, remains in right of the wife after her marriage._ I cannot speak as to the <pb n="3" facs="pa0040c.small.jpg"/> Compensation which Spears is <choice>
                  <orig>alledged</orig>
                  <reg>alleged</reg>
               </choice> to have received, but I have no doubt it is the fact; but this can be <choice>
                  <orig>assertained</orig>
                  <reg>ascertained</reg>
               </choice> by <choice>
                  <orig>refering</orig>
                  <reg>referring</reg>
               </choice> to documents in the War Department_ there was  a small field (or what is often denominated in the west "a patch") between Mrs Carys and the Hiawassee river; but as to the extent of her improvements, they were very inconsiderable, and her <choice>
                  <orig>Cabbins</orig>
                  <reg>Cabins</reg>
               </choice> appeared very indifferent._ that Spears had any right to a reservation at that place, or at any other place within the Cherokee Nation, more than I now have, I do not believe, and I am well satisfied I have none that <name>Mr Lewis Ross</name> had a just and equitable right I am perfectly satisfied_.</p>
            <p>To the best of my recollection it was understood while I lived in the family of Mr. Ross that he had taken, or did intend to take his <pb n="4" facs="pa0040d.small.jpg"/> his reservation embracing the agency, and also a ferry upon the Highwassee river near to where his farm was situated.  What will be the result of the difficulty, I cannot pretend to say; but of this fact I am well satisfied_ If Mr L. Ross, does not get his reservation, as he proposed taking it under the Treaty of 1817. manifest injustice will be done to him.  If Spears should receive a reservation, at any other place than Hiawassee Old Town, he will receive a <choice>
                  <orig>benifit</orig>
                  <reg>benefit</reg>
               </choice> to which he has no right under the Treaty of 1817.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have the <choice>
                     <abbr>hon</abbr>
                     <expan>honor</expan>
                  </choice> to be <choice>
                     <abbr>yr  Obt. Servt.</abbr>
                     <expan>your most Obedient Servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>Signed <name>Sam Houston</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Mr. John Ross</name>.</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
