<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um058">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1849 Oct. 8 [to Mary Porter] / Ed[ward] E Porter : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Porter, Edward E.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um058</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50296672</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1849 Oct. 8 [to Mary Porter] / Ed[ward] E Porter</title>
               <author>Porter, Edward E.</author>
               <date when="1849-10-08">October 8, 1849</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a letter, dated October 8, 1849, from Edward E. Porter to his sister Mary Porter.  In the letter, Edward discusses his busy schedule at school and his possible career plans.  Edwards also expresses interest in instigating communication with a girlfriend of Mary's and speaks of matters of religion.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Porter-Rice Family Letters MS-154 (letters 1846-1849)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um058</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Porter, Edward E.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um058a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>"In our room" <date when="1849-10-08">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Oct</abbr>
                           <expan>October</expan>
                        </choice> 8th 1849</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Sister</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I know that you have thought strange of me for not writing to you before. But believe me never, — since I can remember — have I been so pushed <emph>for time</emph>, as Since the <choice>
                  <orig>begining</orig>
                  <reg>beginning</reg>
               </choice> of this session.  I have had <emph>six</emph> hard studies — besides  French — And all of the Societys duties to attend to &amp; also those of the sons of Temperance.  I had the <emph>Salutatory</emph> address to deliver before society at her first meeting, and have also had to <emph>lead</emph> in all the <emph>debates</emph> Since it began; and also hold a <emph>troublesome</emph> office in the <choice>
                  <abbr>S</abbr>
                  <expan>Sons</expan>
               </choice> of temperance. Thus you see <emph>Dear Mary</emph> that I have had very little time that I could call my own.  But I <emph>know I am forgiven</emph> I have heard from  <emph>home once</emph> since I <choice>
                  <abbr>recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> at <name type="place">Albany</name>  by <name type="person">
                  <emph>Joseph Boon</emph>
               </name>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>hands pointing to "Joseph Boon"</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <unclear>Jes</unclear>
               <emph>Joseph am arrive</emph>.  They were all well at home when <del type="overstrike">I wrote</del> he left.  But the strangest thing yet remains to be told.  Father sent <name type="person">Ben</name> &amp; myself each a <emph>Watch</emph> (not a dog) a <emph>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>runing</orig>
                     <reg>running</reg>
                  </choice> watch</emph>, <emph>one that keeps times</emph>!!, <emph>A Silver Watch</emph>!!! I thought he was <emph>crazy</emph> when he Said he <emph>thought</emph> of doing it; But now I <emph>know</emph> he is.  What had better be done with him? I wish he would get crazy and send me some <emph>money</emph>, as I have not seen 10 <choice>
                  <abbr>cts</abbr>
                  <expan>cents</expan>
               </choice> since, yesterday was two weeks ago! — — — — — — — — —</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="um058b.small.jpg"/>
            <p>Mary! Oh if you only knew how <emph>happy</emph> your letter made me when I read it, you would have some idea of a Brothers love.  Can you imagine any happier scene, than to see <choice>
                  <orig>two</orig>
                  <reg>to</reg>
               </choice> whom God hath united by the ties which bind a Brothers &amp; Sister — placing mutual confidence in each other, and seeming to live, only that <emph>each</emph> may be a help &amp; comfort to the other? Let us both unite and form such a <emph>Scene</emph> as <emph>this</emph> I have represented.  At the present time I am earnestly considering what Profession I will choose, to which I will devote the remainder of my life.  At one time the Law with its honors &amp; profits recurs  to my mind as being the most Suitable; Again the Ministry With its responsibilities, &amp; reward <emph>hereafter</emph> forces itself upon my mind; And while weighing the "why &amp; the why fore" on both sides, another thought comes home with triple force: the thought that I should be a missionary.  There is a field here opens itself, which is extensive &amp; Grand almost beyond comprehension.  Survey it on every side! Consider that within its boundaries, six hundred millions of souls are embraced, All of whom if we must believe the scriptures, will be <emph>irrecoverably</emph> lost, if they do not embrace Christ as he is freely offered to him in the gospel. Methinks I hear the Macedonian "Cry come over and help us."  But who will go?  Every one shrinks from the labors &amp; dangers attending on being a missionary; And can point out some neighbors or friend, whose duty it is <emph>undoubtedly</emph> to go.  Thus each <choice>
                  <orig>trys</orig>
                  <reg>tries</reg>
               </choice> to throw off the responsibility, upon another; And all doing this, no one will be found to go.  But shall <emph>I</emph> go?  Say. <figure>
                  <figDesc>fingers pointing to "Say"</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="um058c.small.jpg"/>
            <p>From your description of <name type="person">Fannie Ferguson</name>, I must confess that I am — not in love — but <emph>her ardent admirer</emph>; And in truth if I was not <choice>
                  <orig>shure</orig>
                  <reg>sure</reg>
               </choice> of a <emph>rebuke</emph> I would address a small <emph>note to her </emph> However tell her that whoever <emph>my sister</emph> loves, is also loved by <emph>"My Sister's" brother</emph>. And if <emph>you</emph> think <emph>she</emph> would not be mortally offended, I will make the proposition of a <emph>regular correspondence</emph>, in my next.  Tell me do you think <emph>we could do it</emph>! Would it not be romantic. two persons who have never seen each other keeping up a regular correspondence!!! But I think it will all turn out <emph>romance</emph>, And not be much <emph>reality about</emph> it! But <name type="person">
                  <emph>Miss Mary Graham</emph>
               </name> must not consider herself slighted  At <emph>all</emph>; for I have no doubt Ben will lay a plot for her.  In conclusion of this subject Remember me to <emph>both</emph> of them; And as you are all thrown together, <choice>
                  <orig>persuing</orig>
                  <reg>pursuing</reg>
               </choice> the same studies: be kind and affectionate to one another; And you should try to find out one anothers <emph>good qualities</emph>; not <emph>faults</emph>. And above all Mary, be <choice>
                  <orig>respectfull</orig>
                  <reg>respectful</reg>
               </choice> to  <emph>your teachers</emph>; And although you may not like them now, but consider them <choice>
                  <orig>tyranical</orig>
                  <reg>tyrannical</reg>
               </choice> — <emph>a little</emph> —; yet remember you are now <emph>moulding</emph> your mind, for usefulness hereafter; not only in this world, but in the world to come. I have no doubt, but that, in after years, we will look back to the present time, with feelings of thankfulness to those, who are now conducting us through the crooked labyrinths of science; and will also experience feelings of regret that we have wasted so many precious hours, And let slip so many opportunities of improvement.  But above all my dear <emph>sister</emph>  let me intreat you to strictly perform your spiritual duties.  Oh is it not  blessed thing to be a <emph>christian</emph>! To think that we ⁁ <add place="supralinear">have</add> not only provided for ourselves comfort &amp; peace of conscience during our short stay upon this earth; <pb n="4" facs="um058d.small.jpg"/> but have also made provisions for passing an <emph>eternity</emph> of bliss, with God, and angels, &amp; friends to whom we bid farewell years ago.  Consider well the duties obligatory <choice>
                  <orig>opon</orig>
                  <reg>upon</reg>
               </choice> you as a <emph>christian</emph>, and follower of Christ.  Those around you will watch to see how religion <emph>becomes</emph> you; And will judge the cause by you.  And it is not a soul-refreshing thought that all of our family have professed their faith in Christ; and have assurance of a better world hereafter.  Then let not one chain of the <emph>link</emph> be broken.  Let us not neglect our daily prayer; And pray especially that God would give us faith &amp; grace sufficient, and strength to resist all temptation.  Are Fanny &amp; Mary <choice>
                  <abbr>G</abbr>
                  <expan>Graham</expan>
               </choice> professors of Religion?</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Ben</name>  &amp; <name type="person">Davis</name> are in my room studying a lesson, and make such a fuss I must close this letter.   </p>
            <p>Our new President has not yet come to hand, and I <choice>
                  <abbr>dont</abbr>
                  <expan>do not</expan>
               </choice> know when he will come.  I had to get excused from recitation today, in order to write to you; so you know how hard pushed I am. You can find out from Fannie <choice>
                  <abbr>F</abbr>
                  <expan>Ferguson</expan>
               </choice> if she would be pleased with my suggestion; and if she will, put on the <emph>top of your next letter</emph> the following sign <lb/> Yes <figure>
                  <figDesc>fingers pointing to "Yes"</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <emph>and if not</emph> put No<figure>
                  <figDesc>fingers pointing to "No"</figDesc>
               </figure> And on this way <name type="person">Mrs Anderson</name>  will not understand what you mean, Of Course you will not show this letter to <emph>any</emph> one.  If Fannie has the least hesitation about it let me know, and of course I will drop the subject.  You will not tell her all I said, but simply that I would like to do it.  I will try and write to you regularly, But if you do not <choice>
                  <orig>recieve</orig>
                  <reg>receive</reg>
               </choice> a letter regularly attribute it, to my <emph>inability</emph> &amp; not to <emph>negligence</emph>.  Write immediately, And Believe me I Remain Your</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Affectionate Brother</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Ed</abbr>
                        <expan>Edward</expan>
                     </choice> E Porter</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
