<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl700">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Order] 1805 Jun. 29, Nashville, Tennessee [respite] for Samuel Forrester / John Sevier : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Sevier, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl700</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Order] 1805 Jun. 29, Nashville, Tennessee [respite] for Samuel Forrester / John Sevier </title>
               <author>  Sevier, John</author>
               <date when="1805-06-29"> 
			 June 29, 1805</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is an Executive Order dated June 29, 1805 from Governor John Sevier of Tennessee.  The order is a respite and prolongation of punishment for Samuel Forester for the murder of a female slave.  In the order, Sevier dictates the specific time Forrester is to be escorted to  the  gallows by the Sheriff of   Davidson County, Tennessee.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor John Sevier Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl700</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Sevier, John, 1745-1815</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr89016779"
                        role="Creator http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/cre">Sevier, John, 1745-1815</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl700a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <add>
                  <name>John Sevier</name> Governor in and over the State of <name>Tennessee</name>
                  <lb/> To all to whom these presents shall come</add>
            </opener>
            <p>Whereas at a Court began and held for the District of Mero at <name>Nashville</name> before the Honorable <name>David Campbell</name>, <name>Hugh S White</name> and <name>John Overton</name> esquires Judges of our Superior Courts of law and equity on the Second monday of May in the year of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and five, and of the Independence of the <name>United States</name> the twenty ninth, <name>Samuel Forester</name> was arraigned tried and found guilty of murdering a certain female negro Slave named Mille, the property of a certain Garrett Fitzgerald, for which murder the said Samuel Forrester was Sentenced to be punished with death, and the Sentence to be put into execution by the Sheriff of Davidson County on the fifteenth day of June the present month.</p>
            <p>And whereas on the fourth day of June Instant, I granted a respite of the execution of the said Samuel Forrester until <pb n="2" facs="sl700b.small.jpg"/> until the eighteenth day of August next:__ Now know ye that I the said John Sevier Governor <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>and et cetera</expan>
               </choice>, by virtue of the power and authority in one vested do grant a further respite and prolongations of the punishment and execution of the said Samuel Forrester and do by these presents respite and prolong the said punishment and execution of him the said Samuel Forrester until the Twentieth day of august next, and until between the hours of Twelve in the forenoon and four in the afternoon of the same day, at which time, to wit, on the Twentieth day of  august next, between the hours of twelve in the forenoon and four in the afternoon of the same day, execution of the Judgement of the judges of the Superior Courts of law and equity in and for the said State of Tennessee, be made and done upon him the said Samuel Forrester by the Sheriff of Davidson County at the same gallows and place assigned and decreed for that purpose <del>for those purpose</del>  by the judges aforesaid, to wit, the public gallows of <name>Davidson County</name>__</p>
            <p>In Testimony whereof I have hereunto set my hand and <pb n="3" facs="sl700c.small.jpg"/> and caused the Great Seal of the State to be affixed at Knoxville the <date>29th day of June</date> in the year of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and five, and of the Independence of the United States the twenty ninth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>John Sevier</name>
               </signed>
               <add>By the governor <lb/>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                        <expan>William</expan>
                     </choice> Mailin</name>, Secretary</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl700d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Copy <lb/>Respite of Samuel Forrester <lb/> 29 June 1805</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
