<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc103">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1815 Jan. 22, Washington [to] Colonel George Washington Sevier, Knoxville, Tennessee / John Sevier :a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Sevier, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc103</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1815 Jan. 22, Washington [to] Colonel George Washington Sevier, Knoxville, Tennessee / John Sevier</title>
               <author>Sevier, John</author>
               <date when="1815-01-22">January 22, 1815</date>
               <extent> 3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated January 22, 1815 from John Sevier to Colonel George Washington Sevier.  He communicates the news of passage of the bank bill by congress, and that he does not believe it will be useful to the government.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">John Sevier Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-1941 b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">15</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc103</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>United States --  Politics and government --  1815-1861</term>
               <term>Tennessee, East</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr89016779"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Sevier, John, 1745-1815</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc103a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Washington</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>22 January 1815</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your favor of the 8th instant has just come to Hand and am rejoiced to hear from you all, but am sorry to find that the ulcer in your neck seems to continue so obstinate, you will have to be very <choice>
                  <orig>carefull</orig>
                  <reg>careful</reg>
               </choice> how it is managed, and to be in time with it, no time ought to be lost.  I am very glad to hear that <name>Major McClellan</name> have arrived, and hope his <unclear>disorders</unclear> will leave him now he has got home-  the major is promoted to the 16 Regiment of Infantry commanded by <choice>
                  <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Pierce, and now on the lines, was raised in <name>Pensylvania</name>.  We have passed the bank bill, but it remains yet to be assented to by the President, It is not believed it will be <choice>
                  <orig>usefull</orig>
                  <reg>useful</reg>
               </choice> to the government, it has been modeled <choice>
                  <orig>intensly</orig>
                  <reg>intensely</reg>
               </choice> by the Minority.  additional Tax's is proposed to the secretary of Treasury. probably to makeup for the <choice>
                  <orig>deficency</orig>
                  <reg>deficiency</reg>
               </choice> in the bank, which wont afford any relief to the fiscal measures of government.  I need not give you any news from <name>orleans</name> as you will hear from that place before we can.  it is thought that there either have or will be, a number of black troops introduced into the Southern States.</p>
            <p>I fear we shall be much embarrassed respecting money to supply the army, and <choice>
                  <orig>dont</orig>
                  <reg>don't</reg>
               </choice> know in what way it can be guaranteed now <pb n="2" facs="sc103b.small.jpg"/> now the bank have so much failed, we before had calculated very much upon that institution, but the hope is wasted - It is supposed we must have <choice>
                  <orig>reconvine</orig>
                  <reg>reconvene</reg>
               </choice> to Treasury notes, and it is to be feared that so much paper will soon become Much depreciated - I wish you to write <choice>
                  <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice>. Sparks &amp; Rutha  to bring off their negroes &amp; property as quick as possible, and while they can pass in safety through  the Indian Country.  I shall be very uneasy about them till they arrive and shall fear much on their account.  I have observed what you say respecting my suit at <choice>
                  <orig>Moabile</orig>
                  <reg>Mobile</reg>
               </choice>, and shall <unclear>send</unclear> on by this mail a power to Willson making him my <choice>
                  <orig>attorny</orig>
                  <reg>attorney</reg>
               </choice> in fact.  Shall also write <name>General Gains</name> to have an <unclear>eye</unclear> to the business, and wish you also to do the same.  I dont apprehend there is any danger of your Regiment being transferred, as to the <choice>
                  <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> that wants to be at the head of it, I cant believe any thing like that of a gentleman - the secretary at war have been dangerously ill, and yet very much indisposed, so that no sickness can be <unclear>transmited</unclear> in that department.  I shall use all possible means to do something to settle that business with Kings <choice>
                  <orig>executon</orig>
                  <reg>execution</reg>
               </choice> -  I wish <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice>. Rheaculan make some sales - He wrote me some time ago he had made some, to the amount of four or five hundred dollars, and expected to make more If you <choice>
                  <orig>dont</orig>
                  <reg>don't</reg>
               </choice> come on until first of april, I suppose I shall not have an opportunity of <choice>
                  <orig>geting</orig>
                  <reg>getting</reg>
               </choice> my <choice>
                  <orig>mair</orig>
                  <reg>mare</reg>
               </choice> - I am still enjoying good health, but closely surrounded with sickness - </p>
            <closer>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Yr</abbr>
                  <expan>Your</expan>
               </choice> affectionate father My affectionate regards to all our friends <signed>John Sevier</signed>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Colo </abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice>Sevier</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sc103c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>P.S. Major A Sevier have set out for <name>charleston S carolina</name>, and from there to <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>N</abbr>
                        <expan>New</expan>
                     </choice>. Orleans</name> to take command of the Marines 23 <gap agent="damage"/> the snow in some <gap/> deep, <gap agent="damage"/> in common <gap agent="damage"/> &amp; half - we have not as much wood for 10 or 12 <unclear>Aiu</unclear> places as would make one fire for my room at home, nor do the House Keeper know where to get one single cord.  for my own part I expect perhaps I <gap agent="damage"/> some coal from the <unclear>Nuscan</unclear> minister, <choice>
                     <orig>otherways</orig>
                     <reg>otherwise</reg>
                  </choice> by night we shall have no fire</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sc103d.small.jpg"/>
               <name>John Sevier</name> Free <address>
                  <addrLine>Colonel George Washington Sevier <lb/>Knoxville <lb/>Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <date>22 <choice>
                        <abbr>Jany</abbr>
                        <expan>January</expan>
                     </choice> 1815</date> Bank Bill pass- <unclear>unperfect</unclear>pass. &amp; in the House &amp; send to the Senate</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
