<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl768">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> [Letter] 1825 Nov. 17, Murfreesboro, Tennessee [to] Newton Cannon, Murfreesboro, Tennessee / W[illia]m Carroll : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Carroll, William</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl768</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1825 Nov. 17, Murfreesboro, Tennessee [to] Newton Cannon, Murfreesboro, Tennessee / W[illia]m Carroll</title>
               <author> Carroll, William</author>
               <date when="1825-11-17">November 17, 1825</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Governor William Carroll to Colonel Newton Cannon, dated November 17, 1825. Carroll is informing Newton that he has been chosen to join a group of engineers. These men are to survey a route for a national road being built from Washington D.C. to New Orleans. The road will pass through Tennessee. Carroll gives some suggestions for routes. The engineers are also to survey for the proposed canal connecting the Hiwassee and Coosa Rivers. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor William Carroll Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">4</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl768</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Carroll, William, 1788-1844</term>
               <term>Surveying</term>
               <term>National road.</term>
               <term>Canals</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Carroll, William, 1788-1844</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl768a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Executive Office <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Murfreesboro</name>
                     <date>November 17 1825</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>In compliance with the inclosed resolution you are appointed to join the <name>United States</name> Engineers with as little delay as possible for the purpose of rendering such aid as may be in your power in the survey which is about to take place of a route through this State for the national road contemplated to be established from the city of <name>Washington</name> to <name>New Orleans</name>. </p>
            <p>Having no information of the extent of the examination which the Engineers are directed to make I am somewhat at a loss how to instruct you on the subject I shall however State what I conceive to be the wishes of Tennessee in relation to the matters leaving it with you to <choice>
                  <orig>inforce</orig>
                  <reg>enforce</reg>
               </choice> her claims, not doubting but that you will accomplish all that can be effected.</p>
            <p>In the Eastern section of the State it is desired and expected, that the road from the <name>Virginia</name> line through the counties of <name>Sullivan</name>
               <name>Hawkins</name> and <name>Granger</name> passing through <name>Rogersville</name> and <name>Rutledge</name> to <name>Knoxville</name> shall be examined, as well as the road through the counties of <name>Carter</name>
               <name>Washington</name>
               <name>Green</name>, <name>Cocke</name> and <name>Jefferson</name> to Knoxville. From Knoxville to <name>Kingston</name>, the best and I believe the only good route is along the main stage road From the latter place it is very desirable, that a survey should be made not only along the new road that has lately been run by commissioners on the part of this State to <name>sparta</name>, thence along the Stage road by way of <name>McMinnville</name>, <name>Winchester</name> and <name>Salem</name>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl768b.small.jpg"/> to <name>Huntsville</name>, but also through the counties of <name>Rhea</name> and <name>Hamilton</name> along the main road down what is called the Tennessee valley crossing the Tennessee river at Browns ferry, so as to admit the direct <choice>
                  <orig>continuence</orig>
                  <reg>continuance</reg>
               </choice> of the route in <name>Alabama</name> through <name>Well's Valley</name> There is an other route in the examination of which West Tennessee feels very deeply interested. Many are impressed with a belief that the great national road from Washington city South Westward should terminate at some point on the <name>mississippi river</name>, near the mouth of <name>big Hatchee river</name> If it is inconvenient for the Engineers to make the latter Survey on their way to New Orleans you will <choice>
                  <orig>indeavour</orig>
                  <reg>endeavour</reg>
               </choice> to prevail on them to do so as they return to Washington city.</p>
            <p>It is understood that the Engineers are instructed to make a survey of a route along which a canal would have to pass connecting the waters of the Hiwassee with those of the <name>Coosa</name>. To this subject so essential to the commerce of the Eastern part of the State your attention will be particularly directed.</p>
            <p>It will be proper for you to keep a Journal of the routes examined, noticing the quality of the land through which they pass- the <unclear>elevation</unclear> of the principal hills__ water courses and the convenience of  materials for the construction of good turn pike roads.</p>
            <p>Without adding any thing further the whole matter is submitted to your Judgment and direction</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am most respectfully <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>yr obt Servt</abbr>
                     <expan>your obedient Servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                        <expan>William</expan>
                     </choice> Carroll</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                        <expan>Colonel</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name>Newton Cannon</name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Murfreesboro.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Tennessee.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl768c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Governors Message <lb/> Extra Session <lb/> 1826</add>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>H. Reps</abbr>
                     <expan>House of Representatives</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/>
                  <date>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Oct</abbr>
                        <expan>October</expan>
                     </choice> 17th 1826</date>
                  <lb/> Read and ordered to be <lb/> transmitted to the Senate <lb/>
                  <name>Tho J. Campbell</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Clk</abbr>
                     <expan>Clerk</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
