<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm043">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Photograph of the interior of Fort Loudoun, British colonial
			 military post from 1756-1760, lower Little Tennessee River] / [by Gerald F.
			 Schroedl]: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Schroedl, Gerald F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Catherine Michelle Love</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Tara Hottenstein</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. 3k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>mm043</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 45096027</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Museum, University of
				Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Photograph of the interior of Fort Loudoun, British colonial
				military post from 1756-1760, lower Little Tennessee River] / [by Gerald F.
				Schroedl]</title>
               <author>Schroedl, Gerald F.</author>
               <date/>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This is a photograph of the interior of Fort
				Loudoun, a British colonial military post on the lower Little Tennessee River
				that was occupied from 1756-1760. It was built in Overhill Cherokee territory
				in what is presently Monroe County and named for John Campbell, the Earl of
				Loudoun, who was commander-in-chief of British forces in the colonies. William
				G. De Brahm designed the fort, but abandoned the project because of
				disagreements he had with Capt. Demerre who commanded the militia troops and
				British regulars stationed at the post. Survival of this frontier outpost was
				dependent on good relations with the Cherokees who supplied food for trade
				goods. During the French and Indian War, tensions began to mount between the
				Cherokees and the colonists. In March 1760 the Cherokees laid siege to the
				fort, cutting off supplies and forcing its surrender. Excavations of Fort
				Loudoun were conducted by the University of Tennessee from 1975-1977 in
				anticipation of the flooding of the lower Little Tennessee River by the Tellico
				Dam Reservoir. The excavations were conducted under contract with the National
				Park Service and the Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA). Principal investigator
				and Field Director, Carl Kutruff. </note>
               <note type="collection">Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note type="document">mm043</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Photographs</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</term>
               <term>Salvage archaeology</term>
               <term>Historic sites</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Fort Loudon (Knoxville, Tenn.)</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n78090514"
                        role="Photographer http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/pht">Schroedl, Gerald F.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mm043.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Interior of Ft. Loudoun, Lower Little Tennessee River,
				  reconstruction British military post occupied 1756-1760. Photograph by Gerald
				  F. Schroedl. This information was provided by the Frank H. McClung
				  Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
