<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl297">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1844 Nov. 21 [to] A. Fergusson, Carthage, Tennessee / R. M. Boyen   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Boyen, R. M.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl297</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1844 Nov. 21 [to] A. Fergusson, Carthage, Tennessee / R. M. Boyen</title>
               <author>Boyen, R. M.</author>
               <date when="1844-11-21">November 21, 1844</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from R. M. Boyen to A. Fergusson, dated November 21, 1844. Boyen wants to help convert Whigs to the Democratic party. He suggests they hand out newspapers personally to Whigs, that they can read quietly at home.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> IV-G-1 b2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">8</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl297</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Whig Party (Tenn.)</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Boyen, R. M.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl297a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <unclear>Gallatin</unclear>
                     <date when="1844-11-21">21st <choice>
                           <abbr>Nov</abbr>
                           <expan>November</expan>
                        </choice> 1844</date>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">A. <orig>
                           <choice>
                              <orig>Ferguson</orig>
                              <reg>Fergusson</reg>
                           </choice>
                        </orig>
                     </name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Having achi ⁁<add place="supralinear">e</add> ved one important victory is it not <unclear>well</unclear> at once to begin to say the <choice>
                  <orig>grannd</orig>
                  <reg>grand</reg>
               </choice> work to <unclear>which</unclear> into the Democratic ranks our Congressional district? This can be done by the August election if the proper means should be forthwith <unclear>adapted</unclear> I am no politician nor will ⁁ <add place="supralinear">I</add> be in the state, my business being in <name type="place">New Orleans</name> yet from the deep interest I feel in bringing back our patriotic state, and especially this congressional district I will take the liberty of suggesting a plan for quietly <choice>
                  <orig>organising</orig>
                  <reg>organizing</reg>
               </choice> the Democratic party before a new excitement is <unclear>again ?</unclear> and one of the plans I would suggest would be to get up and sustain a press in your <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                     <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>, or perhaps the better plan would be to quietly form <unclear>operations</unclear> all over your County and raise a fund in <unclear>cash</unclear> to procure suitable <unclear>increments for ?</unclear>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl297b.small.jpg"/> to wit; the <name type="place">Nashville</name> union or some other good paper or the <unclear>Dollar</unclear> Globe. I think however the <name type="place">New York</name>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Plebian</orig>
                  <reg>Plebeian</reg>
               </choice> considering how cheaply it is offered to <unclear>club on apriations</unclear> might be the best. The Plebian is ably <unclear><?xm-replace_text {unclear}?></unclear> and can be had for the <unclear>merest</unclear> trifle.</p>
            <p>By <unclear>adapting</unclear> some such plan as this and quietly handing out a paper to a Whig with a request that he would read and return the paper, it will be the means of making many converts, when a speech on  <unclear>politick ?</unclear> would but  harden them in  their resistance to the Democratic creed </p>
            <p>To read at their own fireside a well written article will afford them a <unclear><?xm-replace_text {unclear}?></unclear> that they have by an <unclear>impulse</unclear> of  their ⁁ <add place="supralinear">own</add> made the discovery of the true <unclear>position of the antagonist</unclear> principles of the parties. Then are both to be dictated to, and <unclear>prefer</unclear> if they change their <choice>
                  <orig>possitions</orig>
                  <reg>positions</reg>
               </choice> to have the credit of making the discovery themselves.</p>
            <p>The Democratic party in your County is as strong as the Whigs of <unclear><?xm-replace_text {unclear}?></unclear> and by the same <unclear><?xm-replace_text {unclear}?></unclear> with a liberal use of their means it will not require long to wheel into the Democratic ranks this District But to put this desirable object they must be waking men acting firmly <pb n="3" facs="sl297c.small.jpg"/> but quietly and never slumbering on their post</p>
            <p>I make this communication to you confidentially hoping you will appreciate my motion as I can have no object but an ardent desire which I know you cherish of witnessing a return of our state and especially this District to the Democratic fold And now is the time to act when there is no exciting canvas pending.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Respectfully</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">R. M Boyen</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl297d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>A. Ferguson Esqr</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Carthage</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
