<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl130">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1828 May 20, Pleasant Plains [to] Miss Ann J[ane] Bell, Charlotte, Dickson County, Tennessee / Ann T Barry : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Barry, Ann T.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl130</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50548081</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1828 May 20, Pleasant Plains [to] Miss Ann J[ane] Bell, Charlotte, Dickson County, Tennessee / Ann T Barry</title>
               <author>Barry, Ann T.</author>
               <date when="1828-05-20">May 20, 1828</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter, dated May 20, 1828, to Ann Jane Bell in Dickson County, TN from her friend Ann T. Barry in Pleasant Ridge, TN.  In the letter, Barry discusses her recent travels across the state, paying special attention to the landscape of the various counties and the variation in taste and color of their streams.  She also expresses great awe at traversing the Tennessee River, and she discusses other news of family and friends, including the high rate of sickness and death in the region.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">14</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl130</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Description and travel</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Barry, Ann T.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl130a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <name type="place">Pleasant Plains</name>. <date when="1828-05-20">May 20th 1828</date>
               <salute>My dear and affectionate friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <add place="left margin">I seldom go to <name type="place">Clarksville</name>  &amp; have forgotten the time of the courts in <name type="place">Charlotte</name> or I would send letters  by the lawyers</add>  Do not suffer yourself to do me the injustice of believing even for an instant that time or <choice>
                  <orig>absense</orig>
                  <reg>absence</reg>
               </choice> could efface your remembrance from my heart believe me your idea is too deeply impressed for any thing to eradicate.  Accident may prevent our intercourse as frequently by letter as I could wish, but nothing less than your neglect will prevent my continued <choice>
                  <orig>endeavours</orig>
                  <reg>endeavors</reg>
               </choice> to promote a constant correspondence by letter.  The sickness of one of my Brothers in law as well as that of my sister has prevented my answering your kind letter soon, but  you are too much the slave of duty if I may use the term to censure your less steady friend for complying with its dictates even though it has protracted any pleasure you might feel from an immediate answer to your letter.  My life is one unvaried routine of employment; <choice>
                  <orig>occasionly</orig>
                  <reg>occasionally</reg>
               </choice> but very seldom <choice>
                  <orig>releived</orig>
                  <reg>relieved</reg>
               </choice> by some little party of pleasure or visit to my young friends in the <choice>
                  <orig>neighbourhood</orig>
                  <reg>neighborhood</reg>
               </choice> so you may suppose I have nothing to communicate worthy your attention but <choice>
                  <orig>judgeing</orig>
                  <reg>judging</reg>
               </choice> of you by myself I would still write though I only said. My dear Ann I am I love you as well as ever &amp;  I hope I still retain the place I claim in your regard.  We have had an uncommon winter in more respects than one.   Since my recollection I have never heard of as much sickness and as many deaths.  Since my recovery from the fever last fall I have enjoyed, interrupted health &amp; I suppose <pb n="2" facs="sl130b.small.jpg"/> you would scarcely recognize the pale thin invalid of Charlotte in the blooming lass of Pleasant Plains.  My personal appearance has alone experienced a change for I still think of your lectures with the same gratitude.  I formerly felt &amp; look up to your superiority in talent &amp; information with the same admiration unmixed with envy.  As my letter concerning my trip to the District has miscarried I will in this as I have nothing better to write give you some account of it.  <name type="place">Montgomery</name> being my own county I scarcely noticed setting out like most travellers to see foreign wonders &amp; passing over perhaps  what is more worthy of remark near home.  I first began to look about me when it was announced that I was in <name type="place">Stewart</name> I was immediately all eye <choice>
                  <orig>an</orig>
                  <reg>and</reg>
               </choice> ear but nothing could I see but hill after hill almost as high as mountains &amp; in fact might so be termed as they served to fatigue both horse &amp; rider. There is something also uncommon in the streams in which the country abounds they being of a deep blue &amp; very clear I can scarcely describe my feelings on arriving in sight of the <name type="place">Tennessee river</name> it was a bright morning &amp; as we started early we arrived on its banks just as the mists had arisen sufficiently high to give us an unobstructed view of the rive &amp; its banks.  It appeared to me a world of water.  You who have crossed the  Ocean will laugh at my admiration and wonder being lavished on a stream inferior to many in our country but it is by far the largest I ever saw. From the sensation of awe I experienced in crossing I am convinced I am too great a coward   ever to cross the <name type="place">Atlantic</name>. The change in the appearance and taste <pb n="2" facs="sl130b.small.jpg"/> of the water as soon as we entered <name type="place">Henry County</name> in the District is surprising it had the <choice>
                  <orig>colour</orig>
                  <reg>color</reg>
               </choice> of <unclear>lye</unclear> &amp; a very disagreeable taste.  Had not the country been so flat I might have fancied myself in <name type="place">Scotland</name> from the number of morasses swamps <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;C.</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> in which it would have been very unsafe to venture had they not been causewayed. In <name type="place">Madison County</name> the water was of a chalky hue &amp; very warm &amp; unpleasant taste.  In <name type="place">Hardeman</name> the county in which my brother lives it is much better &amp; after I became used to it I liked it as well as our own— it is <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>freistone</orig>
                     <reg>firestone</reg>
                  </choice>
               </unclear> perhaps you have noticed the difference between it and limestone. My stay was short but my time was spent as agreeably as the united <choice>
                  <orig>endeavours</orig>
                  <reg>endeavors</reg>
               </choice> of all my acquaintances <gap agent="damage"/>use me could make it.  My brother in his last letter spoke <gap agent="damage"/>ing over this summer &amp; expects unless I write to the contrary for me to accompany him back I have not yet determined what I shall do. I do not go to <name type="place">Alabama</name> I have rejected one offer &amp; a second lies unanswered before me but it will meet with the same fate. How I wish I had your opportunity of getting books but it is best as it is as I have no pretention to your self command I should spend more time in the perusal of them than I could spare without neglecting other employment equally necessary.  <name type="person">Ann Jordan</name>  is married I hear from what I can understand badly. I have heard <choice>
                  <orig>notthing</orig>
                  <reg>nothing</reg>
               </choice> of <name> 
                  <reg>person</reg> Catherine</name> or <name type="person">Elizabeth</name> lately.  Our Old friend <name type="person">Mrs. Clements</name>  is still in bad health I am very anxious to see her &amp; indeed all my friends in <name type="place">Dickson</name>  Several weddings are talked of but whether or <pb n="4" facs="sl130d.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <add place="bottom of page, continues on top of page">  not they will be carried into effect time alone will determine. <name type="person">Eudora</name> has grown very much I still <choice>
                     <orig>endeavour</orig>
                     <reg>endeavor</reg>
                  </choice> to keep up her studies at home but I find it a very difficult task and I should never have succeeded in educating her on this plan too many interruptions occur When you write let me know whether you have heard lately from <name type="person">Mrs. Robertson</name> &amp; whether <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Majr.</abbr>
                        <expan>Major</expan>
                     </choice> Hicks</name> &amp; <name type="person">Miss Nancy</name> are married or not.</add> Present my love to <name type="person">Mr. &amp; Mrs. Collier</name> &amp; <name type="person">Mrs. Clinton</name> &amp; indeed all my friends not forgetting <name type="person">Mr. &amp; Mrs Vorh</name> — My best wishes will ever attend your family.  Write often <choice>
                  <orig>an</orig>
                  <reg>and</reg>
               </choice> forget not that you have ever a sincere and affectionate friend in</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Ann T. Barry</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="left of signature">One of my nieces have lost my knife, since I commenced this so that I have been unwillingly compelled to scribble as usual.</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Clarksville, <choice>
                           <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="--05-25">May 25</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Miss. Ann <choice>
                           <abbr>J.</abbr>
                           <expan>Jane</expan>
                        </choice> Bell</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Charlotte</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Dickson County</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="to bottom, right of address">Answered <date when="--07-07">July 7th</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
