<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl113">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> [Letter] 1826, Sept. 2nd, Philadelphia [to]    Miss Ann Jane Bell, Nashville, TN / [Dr.] John Bell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Bell, John, Dr.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl113</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50503770</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1826, Sept. 2nd, Philadelphia [to]    Miss Ann Jane Bell, Nashville, TN / [Dr.] John Bell</title>
               <author>Bell, John, Dr.</author>
               <date when="1826-09-02">September 2, 1826</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Dr. John Bell to his sister Ann Jane Bell dated Sept. 2, 1826. John gives Ann  advice about exercising and taking care of her health. He tells her that he thinks it is a good idea for her to work for a Mrs. Scott as an assistant. He is sending her some money and plans to send her more.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl113</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Students -- employment</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Bell, John</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl113a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>
                     <date when="1826-09-02">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Septr</abbr>
                           <expan>September</expan>
                        </choice> 2nd 1826</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear <name type="person">Ann Jane</name>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The course on which you have now entered evinces your good judgment and meets my entire approbation:  nor are the regrets which you felt at leaving home to be regarded as  at all indicative of irresoluteness of character or of a wavering disposition, they are on the contrary creditable to your heart and feelings. I have little to advise respecting the mode in manner in which you are to perform your present duties:—  you of course well know that the most assiduous attention to the correct wishes, &amp; desire to please and soothe the mind of your youthful charge are by no means <choice>
                  <orig>encompatible</orig>
                  <reg>incompatible</reg>
               </choice> with the preservation of dignity &amp; <choice>
                  <orig>independance</orig>
                  <reg>independence</reg>
               </choice> of conduct  — What I am most solicitous about and attention to which I must rigidly exact from you in <del type="overstrike">attention the</del> regard to your health.  Exercise  <pb n="2" facs="sl113b.small.jpg"/> on all fitting occasions must not by any means be omitted.— it is alike <choice>
                  <orig>indespensable</orig>
                  <reg>indispensable</reg>
               </choice> to bodily comfort and mental tranquillity — In your next you will please give me the detail of your occupations. They are in degree similar to my own though perhaps I have less actual confinement in teaching but then as compensation the drudgery of <choice>
                  <orig>practising</orig>
                  <reg>practicing</reg>
               </choice> medicine is greater than that of any other.— <unclear>I</unclear> in all as is your salary —  it is equal to my receipts for the first year of my residence here.—  The    inclosed $15 is less than I wish to send you but I prefer letting you have this at once to waiting for a larger sum.— By next month I hope to be able to repeat. Your orders on me for dress &amp; <unclear>will still</unclear> be duly <choice>
                  <orig>honoured</orig>
                  <reg>honored</reg>
               </choice> and of course you will not give up old habits in this respects I have really been remiss in not writing to <name type="person">Mrs. Guiart</name> .— my own own cares &amp; perplexities drive her completely out of my recollection:  this is <unclear>mine</unclear> than you will tell her —</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="sl113c.small.jpg"/>
            <p> Excuse the somewhat sententious style of this letter — originating from haste in order to be in time for the day's mail. Give my respects to<name type="person"> Mrs Scott</name>with a tender on my part to make such inquiries or execute commissions as may be useful  or necessary to her establishment.  If she finds you as conscientious an assistant and affectionate a teacher as I have always found you to be a good and intelligent sister she may not  only be satisfied but think herself fortunate. <unclear>Her run </unclear>
               <gap agent="damage"/> her your efforts my dear <name type="person">Ann Jane</name>
               <gap agent="damage"/> is <gap agent="damage"/> wish of  </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>  your affectionate Brother</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">John Bell</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Miss Ann <choice>
                           <abbr>J.</abbr>
                           <expan>Jane</expan>
                        </choice> Bell</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Care <name type="person">Mrs. Scott</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
