<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl356">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1837 Oct. 9, Cane Hill [Arkansas] [to] Finis Ewing, Lexington, M[issouri] / B. H. Pierson   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Pierson, B. H</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl356</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1837 Oct. 9, Cane Hill [Arkansas] [to] Finis Ewing, Lexington, M[issouri] / B. H. Pierson</title>
               <author>Pierson, B. H.</author>
               <date when="1837-10-09">October 9, 1837</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Rev. Benjamin H. Pierson to Rev. Finis Ewing, dated October 9, 1837. Pierson complains of not hearing from Ewing in a while.  Pierson writes about his reasons for connecting the Lexington Presbytery to the Arkansas Synod. He writes of the success of the local camp meetings.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Finis Ewing Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> I-A-4</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">14</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl356</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Arkansas</term>
               <term>Cumberland Presbyterian Church</term>
               <term>Religious facilities</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Pierson, B. H</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl356a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Cane  Hill</name>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Oct</abbr>
                           <expan>October</expan>
                        </choice> 9th AD 1837</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Uncle Finis</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>It has been a long- long time since I was <choice>
                  <orig>favoured</orig>
                  <reg>favored</reg>
               </choice> (should I not have said honored) with as much as a scrape of your pen. To be sure, I have not much strengthened any obligation resting on you to write, by keeping up the shot myself, and now that I am seated for the purpose of writing I am somewhat at a loss for something to say You learned months ago that I was at the General Assembly last spring and it may be, have already declared vengeance against the "Indian Chief." I mean on account of some of the transactions of the <gap/>
               <unclear>Assembly</unclear> respecting your presbytery <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> .</p>
            <p> I should perhaps have written on this subject long ago, but a press of business of various kinds (it may be, mixed with a good stock of mental laziness) has prevented me till now. My only reason for having, <name>Lexington</name> presbytery attached to <name>Arkansas</name> Synod was, to enable us to get in possession of  some more territory in the state of <name>Missouri</name> which we greatly needed and to which we were entitled by every law of prior occupancy. ____ I had been <choice>
                  <orig>apprazed</orig>
                  <reg>appraised</reg>
               </choice> that instead of your Synod wishing to lose any of her territory, she aimed at acquiring more, but for what reason I know not. Now sir, after your presbytery is <unclear>sheared</unclear> , which I hope will be done at the coming session of our Synod, if it be the wish of your presbytery to be reattached to <choice>
                  <abbr>Mo</abbr>
                  <expan>Missouri</expan>
               </choice> synod I pledge, that I will not be the first to oppose it, notwithstanding we very much need and would gladly <pb n="2" facs="sl356b.small.jpg"/> have the counsel of your presbytery in our Synod.</p>
            <p>My little family are well, and have been with very trifling exceptions since I saw you.</p>
            <p>Crops have been greatly shortened (I mean corn crops) by a unusual drought.</p>
            <p>The course of the Redeemer had been languishing for some time  until recently. The camp meeting season has rather changed the moral aspect of our country for the better. On last tuesday night our camp meeting on Cane Hill closed. It resulted in the hopeful conversion of not less than thirty one, out of which, I hope the Lord will make more or less preachers.</p>
            <p>May the Lord carry on his own good wor <gap/> We still have some <name>Cumberland</name>
               <choice>
                  <orig>destillers</orig>
                  <reg>distillers</reg>
               </choice> and <gap/> of the poisonous stuff! Our <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>sulery</orig>
                     <reg>sullied</reg>
                  </choice>
               </unclear> Elder!!!</p>
            <p>Let me hear from you and yours frequently. I am particularly anxious to hear from you now.</p>
            <p>Give my love to Aunt Peggy, <name>Mr &amp; Mrs Almond</name> and all others of our friends</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>yours <lb/> In the best of bonds</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>B H</abbr>
                        <expan>Benjamin Hogue</expan>
                     </choice> Pierson</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Uncle Finis }</addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl356c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Oct 9- 1837</add>
               <add>
                  <unclear>Per</unclear>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>Mr Wm Owen</name>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Rev <name>Finis Ewing</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>{ <name>Lexington</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Mo</abbr>
                           <expan>Missouri</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Ben Pearson <lb/> 1837</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
