<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl271">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Legal Document] 1850 Feb. 22 [between] John R. Wilson, Davidson County, Tennessee [and] the Trustees of Washington Institute   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl271</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1850 Feb. 22 [between] John R. Wilson, Davidson County, Tennessee [and] the Trustees of Washington Institute</title>
               <date when="1850-02-22">February 22, 1850</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a legal document dated February 22, 1850, exchanging a land deed in Davidson County, TN, between John R. Wilson and the trustees of the Washington Institute.  Wilson has conveyed for one dollar a piece of land to the Washington Institute for the establishment of a  school. In return, the trustees agreed that Wilson and his heirs will be able to attend classes for free and  will also retain a lien on the land. The witnesses are W. L. Wilson and Thomas B. Wilson.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">14</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl271</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Real property</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl271a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>This indenture, made <date when="1850-02-22">22nd February 1850</date>, between <name type="person">John R. Wilson</name> of <name type="place">Davidson county</name> and <name type="place">State of Tennessee</name> of the one part — and the Trustees of <name type="place">Washington Institute</name>  of the county and state aforesaid of the other part —</opener>
            <p>Witnesseth, that the said John R. Wilson, for and in consideration of the sum of one Dollar to him in hand paid, and for other considerations herein after mentioned, the acknowledgment of which is hereby made, hath given, granted aliened and conveyed; and doth by these presents give, grant, alien and convey unto the said trustees of Washington Institute and their legal successors in office, (according to the charter of said Institute, passed the <del type="overstrike">the</del> Legislature of Tennessee on <date when="1850-01-04">4th <choice>
                     <abbr>Jany.</abbr>
                     <expan>January</expan>
                  </choice> 1850</date>) a certain piece of land situate lying &amp; being in the state &amp; county aforesaid, on the north side of the <name type="place">Nashville</name> and <name type="place">Murfreesboro</name> Turnpike, and bounded as follows, to wit, Beginning at the <choice>
                  <abbr>S.</abbr>
                  <expan>South</expan>
               </choice> West corner of said Wilson's tract and running with the dividing line between his tract and the tracts of <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Tho.</abbr>
                     <expan>Thomas</expan>
                  </choice> S. King</name> &amp; <name type="person">Mrs Williams</name> Thirty One <add place="supralinear">31</add> poles to a stake in said line — thence East Thirteen poles to a stake — thence South 2 ° West thirty One <add place="supralinear">31</add> poles to a stake in the dividing line between <name type="person">Jesse Collins</name> and said Wilson thence with said line thirteen poles to the beginning, containing by estimation about Two acres and three fourths, be the same more or less.</p>
            <p>To have and to hold the aforesaid land with <pb n="2" facs="sl271b.small.jpg"/> with all its profits, rights and appurtenances to the only proper use and benefit of Washington Institute for the promotion of education. And the said John R. Wilson, for himself his heirs, executors and assigns, does covenant and <unclear>agree</unclear> that the before recited land he will warrant and forever defend against the rights, titles, and claims of all and every person or persons whomsoever claiming under him.</p>
            <p>But at the time of sealing and delivering these presents the said Trustees have bound them selves to carry out the provisions of the charter ⁁<add place="infralinear">there establishing &amp; ⁁</add>
               <add place="supralinear">erecting suitable building on said lot of ground</add> by continuing an institution of learning in the Sciences  and languages usually taught and have the same kept up regularly from year to year ⁁ <add place="supralinear">without any other intermission than the usual vacation so long a  <unclear>serial</unclear> corporation shall <unclear>extend</unclear>
               </add> and that said Wilson shall be entitled to one <choice>
                  <orig>schollarship</orig>
                  <reg>scholarship</reg>
               </choice> of each and every session free of charge, and the same shall be continued to his heirs and legal representatives. And it is agreed and understood between the parties that the said Wilson his heirs and assigns shall retain a lien on said land for the faithful performance of the above agreement and Such lien shall be good in law and equity.</p>
            <p>In testimony of which the said Wilson has hereunto set his hand and affixed his seal on the day and year first above written</p>
            <closer>Signed Sealed &amp; delivered in presence of <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                        <expan>William</expan>
                     </choice> L Wilson</name>
               </signed>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Thomas B. Wilson</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="right of signatures">{ <del type="overstrike">John R. Wilson</del>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>seal, deleted with overstrike</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl271c.small.jpg"/> John R. Wilson's <lb/>  Deed  { To  <lb/> Trustees of  <lb/> Washington Institute</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
