<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0036">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> [Letter] 1816 Jun. 29, Cherokee Agency [to William H. Crawford, Secretary of War] : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0036</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1816 Jun. 29, Cherokee Agency [to William H. Crawford, Secretary of War]</title>
               <date when="1813-06-29">June 29, 1816</date>
               <extent>6p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated June 29, 1816, possibly written to William H. Crawford, Secretary of War, from an unknown author.  The letter includes a detailed description of an incident in which a Cherokee named Goodwoman was murdered by a white man named Vincent Davis.  In revenge, two  Cherokees warriors  named Woodpecker and Connoclugh then killed Davis, and are now awaiting trial for the murder.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0036</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Trials (Murder)</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0036a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Cherokee Agency</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>29th June 1816</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>On the <add>morning of the</add> 18 of June <add>instant</add> five <choice>
                  <orig>waggoners</orig>
                  <reg>wagoners</reg>
               </choice> made a stop at <del>a small village at a place</del>
               <name>Rockcreek</name> a small village <add>consisting of eight Houses</add> in the interior of the <name>Cherokee nation</name>  to make some repairs of one of the <choice>
                  <orig>waggons</orig>
                  <reg>wagons</reg>
               </choice>
               <add>this village is situated on</add> the turnpike road leading from <name>Tennessee</name> to <name>Georgia</name>. one of the waggons <del type="overstrike">(unclear)</del> went to an Indian House to get some fire to cook their breakfast.  an Indian there called <name>Goodwoman</name> then in a partial state of intoxication <del type="overstrike">told</del>
               <add>swore that</add> the waggoner <del type="overstrike">that he</del> should have no fire; another indian <add>then</add> present gave the waggoner some fire &amp; he left the House: but was followed by the <choice>
                  <abbr>sd.</abbr>
                  <expan>said</expan>
               </choice> Goodwoman with a knife <add>of common size</add> in his hand.  the waggoner quickened his pace to keep out of <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear>His</unclear>
               </del> reach of the <del type="overstrike">sd Goodwoman</del> sd Indian but the Indian quickened his pace also.  when the waggoner had reached the waggons where he intended to make his fire.  this waggoner then asked the Indian what he meant to do.  the sd. indian then threw his knife at the <add>sd</add> waggoner which struck his elbow. but he received no hurt from the knife and the Indian picked it up.  the <add>sd</add> waggoner then called to the other waggoners to come to his relief_ a number other Indians <add>who</add> were  present  pushed away <add>the sd. Goodwoman</add> about 20 yard_ the <add>sd</add> waggoner in <choice>
                  <orig>runing</orig>
                  <reg>running</reg>
               </choice> had lost one of his shoes.  the sd. Goodwoman brought the shoe &amp; offered it  to the sd. waggoner.  the waggoner then went to cooking their breakfast.  as One of the waggoners &amp; his son named <name>Vincent Davis</name> were eating the sd. Goodwoman <pb n="2" facs="pa0036b.small.jpg"/> came to them <add>and offered</add> 12 ½ cents  piece of money for Bacon- the the first mentioned waggoner advised Davis not to let the indian have any meat: but the son Vincent Davis eat off a piece of meat about two pounds  &amp; handed it to the sd.  Goodwoman who then gave the said Vincent Davis the 12 ½ cents piece of money- the said G.woman looked at the meat &amp; handed it back to sd. Vincent Davis who then offered  back the sd. money.  the said G.woman would not receive the money.  it was then thrown <del type="overstrike">down</del> to his feet &amp; he took it up.  and took up <unclear>alo</unclear> a large pocket knife belonging to said Vincent Davis &amp; held it over sd. Davis' head in a threatening manner for four or five minutes as though he would stab him &amp; then look up the meat he had before refused &amp; carried it away &amp; the knife with it.  about an hour &amp; an half aftewards the sd. Good woman <add>with another Indian</add> came back to the waggon of sd. Vincent Davis- the indian said to Davis you can have your knife for 12 ½ cents David <choice>
                  <orig>replyed</orig>
                  <reg>replied</reg>
               </choice> that he had not lost his knife; &amp; only wanted his knife that was taken away that <del type="overstrike">is</del>
               <add>was</add> all he wanted._ The said Goodwoman then made an attempt to take up an axe_ One of the waggoners took hold of the axe &amp; prevented the indian from taking it.  The said Indian Goodwoman then put his hand to his head where he had a knife under  his Handkerchief_ opened the Knife &amp; made a threat with it at the neck of sd. Vincent Davis_ who avoided any injury by throwing himself out of the way of the thrust.  Sd. V. Davis &amp; another waggoner then rose up &amp; the waggoner took up an axe &amp; V. Davis took up a Hatchet.  the said waggoner then told sd. Vincent <pb n="3" facs="pa0036c.small.jpg"/> Davis to defend himself &amp; as the said Goodwoman approached sd. V. Davis threw the Hatchet &amp; cut the said Goodwoman Deeply in his neck &amp; throat- the sd Goodwoman then ran about 120 yards &amp; fell- an  indian woman then came <choice>
                  <orig>runing</orig>
                  <reg>running</reg>
               </choice> &amp; by signs made the said <add>V</add> Davis &amp; the other waggoner understand that the sd. Indian had received a bad wound &amp; that he would die <unclear>only</unclear> The waggoner then went to where the sd. wounded Indian lay.  there were several Indian women there.  they had washed the wound &amp; put on a dressing they took off the dressing &amp; showed the wound._  </p>
            <p>Some white men who were working on the turnpike road went to see the wounded Indian where a number of Indians had collected.  they told the sd white men that if the wounded Indian died they would kill the <del type="overstrike">white</del> the waggoner</p>
            <p>The information thus far I had from one of the waggoners, who at this stage of the transaction left the place to go after  a Chief who lived some miles from the place_ It appears by other testimony, of an <choice>
                  <orig>intellegent</orig>
                  <reg>intelligent</reg>
               </choice> white man that the Indians had taken the precaution to confine Vincent Davis the man who had thrown the Fatal Hatchet. they tied the hands of said Davis &amp; confined him in a house anxiously waiting for the death of the wounded Indian- which event happened in about an hour after he received the wound from the Hatchet thrown by sd. Vincent Davis- as soon as the Indian expired  they led said Davis out of the house by a rope- he was led out by a young Indian named <name>Woodpecker</name> who put a gun into the hands of an Indian named <name>Connoclugh</name>
               <pb n="4" facs="pa0036d.small.jpg"/> Connoclugh then put the muzzle of the Gun near to the body of said Vincent Davis &amp; shot him through the Body.  he fell &amp; expired in a few minutes.  the last part of this account I have from a White man &amp; from a Cherokee who speaks good English- these two men endeavored to dissuade Connoclugh <del type="overstrike">from his purpose</del> and Woodpecker from their purpose, they at last tried to induce them to wait <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> a Chief should arrive who had been sent for.  it was all in vain.  It appeared to me that WoodPecker was as culpable in the tragical affair as Connoclugh except that Connoclugh by pulling the trigger finished the catastrophe.  The father of Vincent Davis was present &amp; took his son by the hand &amp; bid him adieu.  The fortitude or  hardihood of Vincent Davis never appeard to forsake him &amp; the never appeared at all affected untill his father took him by the hand and then not greatly so. all the Indians of the village men &amp; women were present &amp; took no part in the tragedy and are only to blame for their apathy &amp; insensibility- this may partly be attributed to their ignorance of the   nature of the transaction- Connoclugh said to my Interpreter that when he did the act he thought he was acting in conformity to the Indian custom to take life 
for life: but that afterwards he began to doubt whether he had not done wrong.  and that he now thought that his being <add>taken</add> to be tried by our laws was right, &amp; that he was anxious to have it done soon.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="pa0036e.small.jpg"/>
            <p>Wood pecker the accomplice of Connoclugh is fine figure of a man, tall, strong, &amp; athletic.  his voice is deep and masculine_ He was one of the Cherokee warriors in the expeditions agains the hostile <name>creeks</name> in two Campaigns- he speaks english with a good pronunciation which he acquired at one of the schools in the Cherokee nation.  His mother is a Widow.  she came to me <del type="overstrike">we had</del> her son then present with his arms <choice>
                  <orig>pinnoned</orig>
                  <reg>pinioned</reg>
               </choice> she appeared affected so as to interrupt her speaking.  she appeared anticipate the loss of her son &amp; requested me to inform you that her son had fought for the United Sates by the side of our young warriors particularly at the Battle of the Horse shoe where the Cherokee warriors distinguished themselves in an eminent manner.  she said at last that she should have no bread that the weeds would spoil her cornfield.  I ordered <name>Major Walker</name> to give her to the amount of twenty dollars in such things as would be of most use to her that she might hire some help to work in her cornfield.</p>
            <p>I told her that I did not give these things to pay for the life of her son: but that she appeared want of some help- that we knew nothing about  the event of the trial.  that nobody could foresee what might be.  that the U. States would allow able Counsel for the prisoners in all cases <pb n="6" facs="pa0036f.small.jpg"/> I had omitted to mention that all the Indians <del type="overstrike">in this</del> The goodwoman Conneclugh &amp; Woodpecker were in a state of intoxication.  to this cause, to their ignorance of the nature of <add>their</add> connection with the U. States &amp; their misapplication of their criminal procedure substituting their ancient customs for our laws, may be attributed  the unhappy event on the 18th instant. at the Rockcreek</p>
            <p>The <choice>
                  <orig>charter</orig>
                  <reg>character</reg>
               </choice> of Conneclugh and of Woodpecker has always been good- But the character of Goodwoman has for many years been bad.  and <del type="overstrike">not an individual</del>
               <add>very few <del type="overstrike">if any</del> regret</add> regrets his exit.  he had for some time past behaved very bad on the road- he had in Sundry <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>instancs</orig>
                     <reg>instances</reg>
                  </choice>
               </unclear> exacted money from travellers generally a quarter of a dollar: but in one instance he so frightened a family that they gave him a dollar</p>
            <p>I could have abridged this account: but as the subject is of importance I thought that the war Department ought to be furnished of every circumstance that might have any bearing on the <del type="overstrike">result</del> final result</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
