<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl695">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1828 Jul. 21, Rutledge, Tennessee [to] Sam Houston, Nashville, Tennessee / James Whiteside : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Whiteside, James</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl695</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1828 Jul. 21, Rutledge, Tennessee [to] Sam Houston, Nashville, Tennessee / James Whiteside</title>
               <author>  Whiteside, James</author>
               <date when="1828-07-21">July 21, 1828</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated July 21, 1828 from James Whiteside to the governor of Tennessee, Sam Houston.  In the letter, Whiteside asks the governor his probability of commanding the legislature to an extra session, for fear that it may create chaos in his district.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Sam Houston Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl695</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</term>
               <term>Houston, Sam, 1793-1863.</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007057518"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Whiteside, Jas. A. (James A.)</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl695a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Rutledge</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>July 21st 1828</date>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Gov</abbr>
                     <expan>Governor</expan>
                  </choice>. Houston</add>
            </opener>
            <p>I understood yesterday in <name>Knoxville</name> that <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice>. Howard had stated that, on his return from <name>Nashville</name> a few days since that owing to the pressure on those indebted to the Nashville, and New State Bank, and some other causes, there was great probability that you would be constrained to convene the legislature,__ that you had so <unclear>expressed</unclear>   yourself, which if it be true, autherise the belief that there will be as extra session__ at least with me, as I know your feelings to be against it__ I would like to know certainly__ or if you have not determined on it to know from you whether there is a probability of it__ Perhaps I should not make the inquiry__ I will <unclear>hint</unclear>  to you my reason, you can then answer me on this subject or not as you think most prudent.  If you write your letter shall be confidential or not as you may direct.__</p>
            <p>
               <name>Turney</name> has left our district, and I have understood will resign should there be a called session, this I do not know <unclear>certainly</unclear> however I think it very <del>likely</del>   probable <pb n="2" facs="sl695b.small.jpg"/> should that be the case, we would have <gap agent="damage"/> elect another representative,__ I dislike to be a clerk more than once, A <unclear>hint</unclear> to the wise is sufficient <del>further</del>.__</p>
            <p>I would write more, but I have just arrived here and the mail is about closing__ Let me hear something from you as soon as you can conveniently__ direct to <name>Pikeville</name>__ I will write again when I hear from you.__ We of <unclear>Sigsatchee</unclear>  hope to have the pleasure of seeing you there soon</p>
            <p>Please remember me to your brother William &amp; <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice>
               <unclear>Vauwykle</unclear>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <add>Your friend &amp; servant</add>
               <signed>
                  <name>James A. Whiteside</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
