<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl358">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1834 Feb. 5, Nashville [Tennessee] [to] Finis Ewing, Lexington, Missouri / James Smith   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Smith, James</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl358</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1834 Feb. 5, Nashville [Tennessee] [to] Finis Ewing, Lexington, Missouri / James Smith</title>
               <author>Smith, James</author>
               <date when="1834-02-05">February 5, 1834</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to Rev. Finis Ewing from Rev. James Smith, dated February 5, 1834. Smith writes about some current disagreements that are going on between the Cumberland Presbyterians. Smith has been censured for publishing a letter written by Rev. Morgan. Smith complains that people are trying to create more newspapers than the church can support. Smith also laments his financial difficulties involving The Revivalist.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Finis Ewing Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">I-A-4</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">17</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl358</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>Cumberland Presbyterian Church</term>
               <term>Religious Life</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Smith, James</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl358a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <add>
                  <date>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Feb</abbr>
                        <expan>February</expan>
                     </choice> 8 1834</date>
               </add>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Since my return from the East I have been put in possession of a brief note of yours to myself &amp; which accompanied the last communication of yours published in the Revivalist.</p>
            <p>The very <choice>
                  <orig>disagreable</orig>
                  <reg>disagreeable</reg>
               </choice> controversy which has grown out of the publication of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Br,,</abbr>
                     <expan>Brother</expan>
                  </choice> Morgan</name>s letter has been to me a <choice>
                  <orig>sourse</orig>
                  <reg>source</reg>
               </choice> of pain &amp; mortification Yet I must say that I am not yet convinced that I did wrong in publishing that letter although I do not indorse; all its sentiments. Frequent complaints have been made and by Cumberland Presbyterians of high standing that we were in some instances running into injurious excesses and I then thought and still think that no disadvantage to the cause of <name>Christ</name> could possibly ensue from a fair and christian discussion of the subject. I am sorry however to find that <unclear>much bad</unclear> spirit prevails on account of it and that I am censured <choice>
                  <orig>severly</orig>
                  <reg>severely</reg>
               </choice> by both parties.</p>
            <p>In justice to myself I am bound to say <pb n="2" facs="sl358b.small.jpg"/> that I heartily <unclear>dissaprove of  Amicas</unclear>  and had I been at home his piece would not have been published I think you must have misunderstood <name>Br Anderson</name> who assures me he had no design to side with either party He is a <choice>
                  <orig>thurough</orig>
                  <reg>thorough</reg>
               </choice> Cumberland Presbyterian and the son of your former fellow <choice>
                  <orig>labour</orig>
                  <reg>labor</reg>
               </choice> of that name and as is natural strongly attached to the measures of the revival of 1800</p>
            <p>As  <unclear>regards</unclear> the <choice>
                  <orig>dessatesfaction</orig>
                  <reg>dissatisfaction</reg>
               </choice> of the Brethren in your country I am sorry it should exist but trust that they have more prudence than to attempt in the present state of the church to get up a paper there The Cumberland Church heretofore has not been able to give a liberal patronage to one paper and   if this be true she will only disgrace herself by attempting to have 3 or 4 as will be the case if the brethren of the east &amp; west put their threats into execution. But I would seriously advise the church to make this establishment her property and appoint some person to take charge of it in whose views and prudence &amp; they have confidence. For my own part I acknowledge that I am heartily sick of my situation and <pb n="3" facs="sl358c.small.jpg"/> nothing short of the firm conviction that the church would be without a paper and consequently sustain great loss <choice>
                  <orig>enduced</orig>
                  <reg>induced</reg>
               </choice> me at the earnest solicitations of the last assembly  to purchase the whole concern from <unclear>
                  <name>Mr Lenry</name>
               </unclear> to whom I paid $1500.00 and took upon myself all the debts owing by the establishment From that time to the present I have been <choice>
                  <orig>grapling</orig>
                  <reg>grapling</reg>
               </choice> with the most <unclear>serious</unclear> difficulties and to be enabled to meet the heavy demands <unclear>against</unclear> the press I have been travelling constantly Indeed from <gap/>
               <date>1st of June</date> I have been with my family on 3 sabbaths of <gap/> have paid debts owing by the press to the amount of <unclear>$5000.00</unclear> Indeed nothing short of the most rigorous exertions could have kept it alive until now. The Revivalist is a  <unclear>waking conun</unclear> all  my private resources are swallowed up by it &amp; my brethren making no exertions to promote its interests but in too many instances treating me in a most unchristian manner witness the defence of <name>Br Guthrie</name> From then and <unclear>ther underating</unclear> I have determined (and I think I will do duty) not to continue the publication of the Revivalist at my own risk longer than the assembly unless such measures are addressed as I have no expectations of And I  expect that the pledge of the assembly will be redeemed <unclear>Very</unclear> that the office will be better off my hands __ I deem it my <choice>
                  <orig>indespensible</orig>
                  <reg>indispensable</reg>
               </choice> duty to give you and other <unclear>influential</unclear>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl358d.small.jpg"/> And I would earnestly beg for the sake of the bleeding cause of Christ that if it is at all practicable you will be present at the next assembly __</p>
            <p>I am sorry that it will be my duty to engage with <name>Br Miller</name> I feel my <unclear>dessuncy</unclear> but with the fear of God before me and relying on his aid I will try to reply I trust in the spirit of Christ</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Yours affectionately</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>James Smith</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>5th <choice>
                           <abbr>Feby</abbr>
                           <expan>February</expan>
                        </choice> 1834</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Finis Ewing</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Lexington</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Missouri</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
               <add>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>miscellaneous scribbling</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Rev J</abbr>
                     <expan>Reverend James</expan>
                  </choice> Smith <lb/> Feb 5 1834</add>
               <add>members of the church due notice of the course I shall feel it my duty to pursue that they may adopt such measures as they may deem best calculated to secure the interests of the church__</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
