<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc133">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Agreement] 1827 Oct. 25, Smith County, Tennessee [between] David Burford and Jourdan M. Saunders : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc133</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Agreement] 1827 Oct. 25, Smith County, Tennessee [between] David Burford and Jourdan M. Saunders</title>
               <date>October 25, 1827</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a legal agreement dated October 25, 1827 between David Burford &amp; Jourdon M. Saunders of Smith County Tennessee to start a "negro speculating business."</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">David Burford Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS935</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc133</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Legal documents</term>
               <term>Slave Traders -- American history</term>
               <term>Business enterprises</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc133a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>Agreement made and entered into this 25th day of October 1827 between <name>David Burford</name> &amp; <name>Jourdon M. Saunders</name>, both of <name>Smith County</name> &amp; State of <name>Tennessee</name>, Witnesseth, that each of said parties agree to put in two thousand dollars in current money of the <choice>
                  <abbr>U</abbr>
                  <expan>United</expan>
               </choice> States as stock, or capital in the <choice>
                  <orig>negro</orig>
                  <reg>Negro</reg>
               </choice> speculating business, and that the one who makes the purchase of negroes shall keep a true and correct account of the purchase of each negro, or a lot of negroes; also an account of <choice>
                  <orig>cloathing</orig>
                  <reg>clothing</reg>
               </choice> for said negroes, traveling expenses of negroes and such other necessary contingent <choice>
                  <orig>expences</orig>
                  <reg>expenses</reg>
               </choice> as the purchaser may think right;_ also keep an account for hire of assistant, should it be necessary. all of which accounts shall be paid by the firm or out of the joint fund, and after paying said expences and refunding to each their respective sums advanced, then the balance shall be equally divided between the two share and share alike._And it is further understood and agreed that neither of the contracting parties are to charge any thing for their services individually._And it is further understood that should either of the parties die before the sale of any, or the whole negroes belonging to them jointly, or before the business is closed that the surviving, <add>partner</add> is to take charge of and close the business of said firm_ The name and stile of said firm shall be J. M. Saunders &amp; Co. And lastly it is understood that said Saunders is to take charge of the funds &amp; make the first purchase, and finally, that this partnership is to exist until one or the other, or both, with a discontinuance of the business. Witness our hands &amp; seals the day and year above written.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>David Burford<add>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>a hand drawn seal</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </add> J. M. Saunders <add>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>a hand drawn seal</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </add>
               </signed>
               <add>(signed duplicates)</add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sc133b.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Recd</abbr>
                     <expan>Received</expan>
                  </choice>. <choice>
                     <abbr>Nov</abbr>
                     <expan>November</expan>
                  </choice>. 5th 1827 of David Burford two thousand and five hundred dollars in <choice>
                     <abbr>U.S</abbr>
                     <expan>United States</expan>
                  </choice>. notes_ and ninety five dollars in <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>N</abbr>
                        <expan>North</expan>
                     </choice>. Carolina</name> paper to vest in negroes in pursuance of the written agreement. <figure>
                     <figDesc>mathematical equations drawn</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <signed>JM Saunders_</signed>
               <add>Recd, of DBurford at various times up to the 27 April 1828 exclusive of the foregoing sum nine hundred eleven dollars. $911</add>
               <signed>J.M Saunders</signed>
               <add>Agreement between David Burford &amp; Jourdan M. Saunders</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
