<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl387">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter]    1832 Feb. 26, Dresden [to] William Fitzgerald / E.A. Fitzgerald : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Fitzgerald, E.A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl387</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter]    1832 Feb. 26, Dresden [to] William Fitzgerald / E.A. Fitzgerald </title>
               <author>Fitzgerald, E.A.</author>
               <date when="1832-02-26">February 26, 1832</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated February 26, 1832 from E.A. Fitzgerald to her husband William Fitzgerald.  She writes to her husband of several political and social matters of the period including the establishment of a temperance society.  She also mentions prominent political figures such as Henry Clay, Daniel Webster, and Martin Van Buren.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fitzgerald - Williams - Greer Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl387</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Temperance and religion</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Fitzgerald, E.A.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl387a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Dresden</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Feb</abbr>
                     <expan>February</expan>
                  </choice>. 26th 1832</date>
               <salute>My Dear</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We have had very cold weather this week wind rain snow and sleet there is some appearance this morning of its moderating. - the information you gave me of your Brothers' family was very pleasing.  I have wished several times since that we lived more convenient to each other.  I am truly <choice>
                  <orig>glald</orig>
                  <reg>glad</reg>
               </choice> to find our fears were false relative to his intemperances.  I am rejoiced to find you have become so great a friend to temperance, I always hoped, and believed you would, <choice>
                  <orig>tho</orig>
                  <reg>though</reg>
               </choice> I think you were once a little opposed to the societies.  Whatever is right will prevail, from what you have written, to me I expect to see you much altered.  I hope with others you have cast aside as undeserving and sinful the practice of swearing which will have made you a moralist but I hope for still greater things my dear that I shall yet see you a christian then my greatest wish will be consummated.  I have have read with heartfelt pleasure the proceedings of the meeting at the capitol for the promotion of temperance the gentlemans speeches are handsome and appropriate much to the purpose indeed, I dont know which one of them is the best, I hope the cause will progress rapidly for I think with <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Wayne that it would bring upon us again, almost the golden brightness of the worlds first mornings _ I am much interested in this cause and greatly desire its promotion I have proposed to one or two the establishment of one here a temperance society they do not seem disposed to lend this aid.  I discover <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Van Burens appointment is rejected, I believe it is the only decisive act of congress I have seen yet, I have fell out with <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Clay and Webster more than ever since there appears to be a disposition among the members to have the public lands reasonably disposed of I am glad to see it I hope it may prove favorable to you in your land measure, I am in fine health and in pretty good spirits. . but very anxious for you to get home you may be assured I count the days as they come and go sometimes I think the time is passing off right fast and again it is very tedious so much so that I think I can <pb n="2" facs="sl387b.small.jpg"/> not pass it off with any degree of pleasure or patience. the arrival of the mail always revives me very much Adeline and Arabella talk as much of <del>the</del> of its coming as any person in town.  and make a great deal more noise when it does come.  arabella says she knows just how her pa looks that she is not going to forget him at all.  adeline wants to learn to write better before she writes to you again.  she is very proud of your praising her so much for writing to you they are both very well and growing very fast.  I am going to morrow to hoe the garden at the new place.  enclosed, and prepare for cultivating it, it will be an advantage to it if we should move there next year.  your plan for farming is a good one.  but do my dear never purchase another slave, I shall never have confidence in one of them I believe again.  but we will talk of this when you get home.  I think I have asked you in some of my letters before this to tell me when you thought congress would probably adjourn.  for fear I have not I ask you now.  write something about it soon.  I send you an ugly letter this week.  I forgot to get letter <add>paper</add> yesterday.  you know I do not like to break the__ Sabbath.  but if you are as glad to get my letters as I am yours, and I know you are, you will not care very much for the quality of the paper, I have no news at all I hope the report of the cholera being in <name>america</name> is unfounded, I have <add>seen</add> no account of it in the newspapers, your acquaintances are all well except C Bayliss.  he is yet confined to the house.  I have not been there since I wrote last the weather has been so bad, it is almost time for the mail, to come, I cant sit still long enough to write any more.  oh that we may meet again.</p>
            <closer>Your affectionate wife <signed>E A Fitzgerald</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
