<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0037">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1816 Nov. 4, Cherokee Agency [to] W[illia]m H. Crawford, Secretary of War / Return J. Meigs  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Meigs, Return J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0037</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1816 Nov. 4, Cherokee Agency [to] W[illia]m H. Crawford, Secretary of War / Return J. Meigs</title>
               <author>Meigs, Return J.</author>
               <date when="1816-11-04">November 4, 1816</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated November 4, 1816, from Return J. Meigs, Agent to the Cherokee Nation, to US Secretary of War William H. Crawford.  Meigs writes to request that mechanics be hired within the Cherokee Agency for use by the Native Americans.  Meigs specifically talks about the lack of blacksmiths available.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0037</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Meigs, Return Jonathan, 1764-1825</term>
               <term>Crawford, William Harris, 1772-1834</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n92008354"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Meigs, Return Jonathan, 1740-1823</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0037a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Cherokee Agency</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>4th November 1816</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have had the honor of receiving your letter of the 23rd of September last on the subject of employing persons in the various mechanical arts for the use of the Indians within this Agency with advantage to the natives and with Oeconomy to the Government.  When I came first into this Agency a single Blacksmith only was employed.  his pay &amp; rations amounted to 376 dollars <choice>
                  <abbr>pr.</abbr>
                  <expan>per</expan>
               </choice> annum besides the pay of a striker at the anvil, for which I paid from 8 to 10 dollars pr. month.  As the natives advanced in Agriculture it was found that a <add>single</add>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>B. smith</abbr>
                  <expan>Blacksmith</expan>
               </choice> only placed in any part of <add>the</add> great extent of Indian settlements was <del type="overstrike">of</del> only of very partial advantage: many had to come 100 miles for the smiths work.  to remedy this the present mode was adopted, that is, of permitting Blacksmiths to come into the nation who should have no <choice>
                  <orig>dependance</orig>
                  <reg>dependence</reg>
               </choice> on the Government except by compliance with my orders in favor of Indians  for Smiths work,  at the same price paid in the white settlements.</p>
            <p>There are now 15 Blacksmiths within this Agency.  5 of which are Cherokees, self taught.  they are so dispersed in the nation as to render great service to the natives.  Many of the Indians pay for their own smith work- the white B. smiths are allowed to till as much land as they please for raising corn &amp; to keep live stock.</p>
            <p>It appears to me sir that there cannot be a better plan adopted at present in this agency than the one used.  The <choice>
                  <orig>spining</orig>
                  <reg>spinning</reg>
               </choice> wheels are provided in the same way- there are two white men &amp; two real Cherokees who make spining wheels- they comply with my <pb n="2" facs="pa0037b.small.jpg"/> orders: and work for others on their private account.  The Looms for weaving are nearly all made by Indians. for which, the price is eight dollars only a piece.</p>
            <p>It is my opinion that if mechanics should be employed in the pay of Government_ a tin plate worker only excepted, that they <add>the indians</add> would place too much dependence on that source, which would lessen their own enterprize in  mechanical arts, &amp; retard their improvement.</p>
            <p>The present mode of furnishing them with B. smiths work is less expensive than any other, so it appears to me. I mean in this Agency- other Agencies may require other arrangements:  Necessity or interest has induced them to some exertions- many of them now tan their own leather- they make shoes- and there is one good saddler a Cherokee.  they have too many silver smiths. they make the rich <unclear>Hatbands</unclear>, Arm bands, &amp; other ornaments of dress, &amp; silver <choice>
                  <orig>spurrs</orig>
                  <reg>spurs</reg>
               </choice> equal to any I ever saw.  If a Tinplate worker could be employed for One or two years it would be of much  use.  who should be agreed with to instruct a number of young Cherokees in the art of his profession.  the Cherokees now <add>pay</add> a great deal of money <add>for</add> tin ware.  it being <choice>
                  <orig>usefull</orig>
                  <reg>useful</reg>
               </choice> in every family.  I estimate the expense of a good  workman in that business at at 305 $ pr. year he finding his own tools_ the tin plates to be provided by Government.  and the whole of this expense may be saved by <unclear>returning</unclear> the expense gradually from the present expense of other presents.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have the honor to be with great respect your Obedience Servant</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Return J Meigs</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Honble.</abbr>
                        <expan>Honorable</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Wm.</abbr>
                           <expan>William</expan>
                        </choice> H. Crawford</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Secretary of War</addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="3" facs="pa0037c.small.jpg"/> Letter to the Secretary of war. on the subject of employment of mechanics <del type="overstrike">in</del>
               <add>within</add>  the Cherokee Agency.  <lb/> 4th November 1816. </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
