<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mc006">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1834 Aug. 2, Columbus, McMinn C[oun[ty], E[ast] Tenn[esseee] [to] Charles F. Welcker, Talladega Court house, Ala[bama] /  Fred[erick] A. Welcker: a   machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Welcker, Frederick A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>mc006</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50442234</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1834 Aug. 2, Columbus, McMinn C[oun[ty], E[ast] Tenn[esseee] [to] Charles F. Welcker, Talladega Court house, Ala[bama] /  Fred[erick] A. Welcker</title>
               <author>Welcker, Frederick A.</author>
               <date when="1834-08-02">August 2, 1834</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a letter dated August 2, 1834, written to Charles F. Welcker by his brother Frederick A. Welcker in McMinn County, TN.  In the letter, Frederick writes of his departure from home in April and his journeys since across East Tennessee in search of employment.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Welcker Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1833</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mc006</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Description and travel</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Welcker, Frederick A.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mc006a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbus Mcminn <choice>
                           <abbr>Cty. E. Tenn.</abbr>
                           <expan>County East Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1834-08-02">August 2nd 1834</date>.—</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Brother;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I take my pen to give you a short narration of the most important particulars respecting myself since I left home (which was <date when="--04-16">april 16th</date>) together with a brief statement of the circumstances under which I left there —</p>
            <p>During my stay at home last winter father would not let me know certainly whether or not I could return to College; and thereby kept me in suspense until the <date when="--04-15">15th April</date>, at which time he commenced a quarrel with an individual, upon whom  he is accustomed to lay violent hands on every whimsical occasion; and would have injured her had it not been for my interference he being sober.— Shortly after on returning to the house, he expressed a desire of my departure and absence from home, going away at the same time with a view to its effectuation, and saying the would continue absent two days; whereupon I made the necessary preparations for parting, and went by stage the <choice>
                  <orig>ensueing</orig>
                  <reg>ensuing</reg>
               </choice> day to <name type="place">Knoxville</name>. — After learning through the private inquiry of some of my friends, that no <pb n="2" facs="mc006b.small.jpg"/> suitable employment could be had in that place, I went to <name type="person">S. Inmans</name>, <name type="place">Dandridge</name> , where I learned that he was in <name type="place">Baltimore</name>; and that it was probable he would employ some person on his return. — Now with the view to ascertain this I <choice>
                  <orig>endeavoured</orig>
                  <reg>endeavored</reg>
               </choice> to settle the <name type="unk">Jefferson</name> affair, and succeeded in <choice>
                  <orig>geting</orig>
                  <reg>getting</reg>
               </choice> uncles <name type="person">John</name> &amp; <name type="person">Jeremiah</name> to execute to father their note  payable, <date when="--01">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Janary</orig>
                     <reg>January</reg>
                  </choice>
               </date>   next, which I left with <name type="person">Heinds</name> , and in getting them to promise to pay your 1.00 <unclear>at</unclear> the following county Court, to <add place="supralinear">be</add> given over to Heinds agreeably to my instructions; then I return to Knoxville with the view of going to where you are, provided S. Inmans did not inform me by letter that he would give me employment. — While in Knoxville I was informed that <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                     <expan>William</expan>
                  </choice> Dickson</name> of <name type="place">Greenville</name> wished to employ 2 Clerks; upon receipt of this I procured an introductory  letter from <name type="person">
                  <unclear>Etheldrec</unclear> Williams</name> to him; not getting any other as Mr. <choice>
                  <abbr>D</abbr>
                  <expan>Dickson</expan>
               </choice>    is a very enthusiastic anti— <name type="person">Jackson</name>  man. — on arrival there he said he could not employ any person before three months, in consequence of his having thrown down a part of his house with the view of making an addition to it. — On my way I saw Inman but could make no reasonable arrangements with him. — In Greenville I <unclear>learned</unclear> from <name type="person">Joseph S. Chunn </name> whose residence is at the mouth of <unclear>Chucky</unclear> that his father <del type="overstrike">in  Asheville</del>
               <pb n="3" facs="mc006c.small.jpg"/>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Chunn of <name type="place">Asheville <choice>
                     <abbr>N.</abbr>
                     <expan>North</expan>
                  </choice> Carolina</name>, certainly wanted a Clerk, either to Continue in Asheville or to go to the <name type="person">Creek</name> Country;  then directing my course towards Asheville on a horse furnished by J. S. Chunn I received employment upon the following conditions (viz) <unclear>"</unclear> To continue together for 2 years probably, longer if it suited, and shorten at the options of either party; for which $75. is to be given for the first year 175 for the second and  perhaps, though at the option of Chunn 100 for the first and 200 for second. — Then one of <choice>
                  <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Chunn's sons and myself went to <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Augustia</orig>
                     <reg>Augusta</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> to receive about 8,000 worth of goods, convoyed up the <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Savanah</orig>
                     <reg>Savannah</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name>   from the <unclear>East</unclear>, understanding that I was to see them safely delivered at <name type="place">Jackson <choice>
                     <abbr>Ala.</abbr>
                     <expan>Alabama</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> — I went on horse back to <name type="place">Jacksonville,</name>, and then turned back to meet the <choice>
                  <orig>waggons</orig>
                  <reg>wagons</reg>
               </choice> to direct them on to <name type="place">Cassville <choice>
                     <abbr>Geo.</abbr>
                     <expan>Georgia</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> , which is about 100 miles <choice>
                  <abbr>So</abbr>
                  <expan>South</expan>
               </choice> of <name type="place">Athens</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                  <expan>Tennessee</expan>
               </choice>; when after <name type="person">Samuel L. Chunn</name>, who was in partnership with <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm.</abbr>
                     <expan>William</expan>
                  </choice> Gillespie</name> of <name type="place">Rhea <choice>
                     <abbr>cty</abbr>
                     <expan>county</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>   &amp; <name type="person">Dr. Patton</name>, who is a son in law of <choice>
                  <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Chunns, and myself had put up the goods, I came on with Dr. Patton here to his residence with the view of attending to his country store. — Whether I shall attend here at Asheville <choice>
                  <abbr>N.</abbr>
                  <expan>North</expan>
               </choice> Carolina or at Cassville <choice>
                  <abbr>Geo.</abbr>
                  <expan>Georgia</expan>
               </choice> I cannot tell <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice>
               <date when="--09">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>sept</abbr>
                     <expan>september</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date>  , at which time <choice>
                  <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Chunn will be here. — All of this family are very wealthy and respectable, and appear to be agreeable. — We did not enter into writing, but will settle yearly. <pb n="4" facs="mc006d.small.jpg"/> A few days since I received a letter from brother <add place="supralinear">
                  <name type="person">Henry</name>
               </add>  , inform me that, one from you and, also, another from brother <add place="supralinear">
                  <name type="person">Lewis</name>
               </add> had first come to, stating, that you both were well and in which he stated that father had supposed <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> I wrote from Asheville, that I was at College whereupon he requested Henry to solicit my return to College, and he is still  <unclear>willing</unclear> provided it be my desire, saying I could be prepared to commence studying law when Lewis does. —</p>
            <p>
               <add place="middle of page">
                  <add place="top" rend="different ink">
                     <address>
                        <addrLine>Columbus</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>
                           <date>1834</date>
                        </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>
                           <date when="1834-08-06">
                              <choice>
                                 <abbr>Aug</abbr>
                                 <expan>August</expan>
                              </choice> 6, 1834</date>
                        </addrLine>
                     </address>
                  </add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="person">Mr. Charles F. Welcker</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Talladega Court House</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <emph>
                           <name type="place">
                              <choice>
                                 <abbr>Ala</abbr>
                                 <expan>Alabama</expan>
                              </choice>
                           </name>
                        </emph>
                        <add place="left">
                           <emph>Mail</emph>
                        </add>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
            </p>
            <p>But I declined returning, thinking it best to get a Knowledge of this business first at any rate. — You will write me immediately to this place, giving a full statement of your situation <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Fred</abbr>
                        <expan>Frederick</expan>
                     </choice> A. Welcker</name>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>To Charles F. Welcker}</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
