<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mc051">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1838 Apr. 6, Kingston [to] C[harles] F. Welcker, Talladega, Alabama / Henry I. Welcker : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Welcker, Henry Inman</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">mc052</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1838 Apr. 6, Kingston [to] C[harles] F. Welcker, Talladega, Alabama / Henry I. Welcker</title>
               <author>Welcker, Henry Inman</author>
               <date when="1838-04-06">April 6, 1838</date>
               <extent>4 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated April 6, 1838, from Henry Inman Welcker in Kingston, Tennessee, to his brother Charles Frederick Welcker in Talladega, Alabama.  Henry writes about a trip he had recently taken up north to purchase goods for his mercantile business.  He describes his modes of travel, the fierce weather conditions, and the people he encountered along the way.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Welcker Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1838</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mc052</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Travel</term>
               <term>Tennessee, East</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Welcker, Henry Inman</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mc052a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Kingston</name>
                     <date>April 6th 1838</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Charles</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Returned home on the 4th <choice>
                  <abbr>Inst</abbr>
                  <expan>Instant</expan>
               </choice> from the East after a pretty long and tedious trip I left home for <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Balt</abbr>
                     <expan>Baltimore</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> on the <unclear>17th</unclear>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Feby</abbr>
                  <expan>February</expan>
               </choice> and Started with the intention of going the <name>Virginia</name>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Rout</orig>
                  <reg>Route</reg>
               </choice> but on arriving at <name>Knoxville</name> I fell in company with <name>Mr <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                     <expan>William</expan>
                  </choice> B French</name> of that place who was going to <name>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Pittsburg</orig>
                     <reg>Pittsburgh</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> to bring a Steam Boat up this river which he had previously purchased, and I also found the roads so tromped up and frozened that they were almost impassible.  I there changed my <choice>
                  <orig>deriction</orig>
                  <reg>direction</reg>
               </choice> for <name>Lexington <choice>
                     <abbr>Ky.</abbr>
                     <expan>Kentucky</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> and went across the mountains in the Coldest Snowy weather I ever traveled in my life.  at Lexington we took the Stage for <name>Mayeville</name> on <name>the Ohio</name>  expecting to go up it in a Steam boat but to our very great misfortune we found the ice running at such a rate that all the boats had stopped running.  and we were Compelled to continue in Stages all the way through Ohio, and pay the most exorbitant Charges for travelling and go ahead day and night while everything was frozen above and below,  but as good fortune would have it we arrived at <name>Wheeling <choice>
                     <abbr>Va.</abbr>
                     <expan>Virginia</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> safe at which place we parted  the weather remained very cold until after I got to <choice>
                  <abbr>Balto</abbr>
                  <expan>Baltimore</expan>
               </choice> at <choice>
                  <abbr>Baltmo</abbr>
                  <expan>Baltimore</expan>
               </choice> I met <name>Porrell</name>, <name>Barclay</name> &amp; <name>Buck Winslett</name>who were on their way to <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N</abbr>
                     <expan>New</expan>
                  </choice> York</name> after staying a few days at Baltimore we went to <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Phila</abbr>
                     <expan>Philadelphia</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> they Stayed a few days <pb n="2" facs="mc052b.small.jpg"/> at Philadelphia &amp; left for N York I Remained there Six or Eight days &amp; purchased some goods &amp; returned to Baltimore finished my purchases and put out for home I had <choice>
                  <orig>avery</orig>
                  <reg>a very</reg>
               </choice> pleasant trip back the weather being very fine &amp; the Roads good.  On arriving home I learned that Jane had been very unwell for some time, she was taken while in Kingston at School with the Influenza and for some days was <choice>
                  <orig>though</orig>
                  <reg>thought</reg>
               </choice> to be quite dangerous but recovered in about 2 weeks So that She could come out  home.  She is quite <choice>
                  <orig>harty</orig>
                  <reg>hearty</reg>
               </choice> at present.  one of <name>
                  <unclear>Seggets</unclear>
               </name> little daughters and several others have died with it this spring.  <name>Martin Watson</name> is very Sick of it at this time_ the balance of the family have enjoyed good health.  <choice>
                  <abbr>Fredk</abbr>
                  <expan>Frederick</expan>
               </choice> did not get back <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> after I left he did nothing with the land except appoint an agent to attend to it.  this is vacation month and the boys are all at home except monroe.  A letter was received from Lewis a short time since in which he states that his health has been good &amp; that he will be certain to be at home before Christmas he did not say whether he would remain or not_ I am  having my goods brought around by <choice>
                  <orig>warter</orig>
                  <reg>water</reg>
               </choice>. &amp; I am a little afraid <choice>
                  <orig>the</orig>
                  <reg>they</reg>
               </choice> will be delayed on the <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Ten.</abbr>
                     <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                  </choice> River</name> though they have keels in which will bring up goods when the warters are too low for Steam Boats_ I Saw <unclear>Duarmond</unclear> as I came home he gave me fur hives from you relative to business.  you were correct in the first instance as to the amount.  he has not heard from <name>Wright</name>_ Franklin was down to see Catharine a <pb n="3" facs="mc052c.small.jpg"/> few days  since she &amp; <name>Lenoir</name> &amp; their little daughter were well.  I am anxious to hear from you Caroline &amp; Betty you must all write me.  The family all send their love <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> Give my respects to all inquiring friends- my love to Caroline &amp; Mary.  and accept the same from yours &amp;C</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>Henry <choice>
                        <abbr>I</abbr>
                        <expan>Inman</expan>
                     </choice> Welcker</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>to <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>C F</abbr>
                           <expan>Charles Frederick</expan>
                        </choice> Welcker</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Talladega <choice>
                           <abbr>Ala</abbr>
                           <expan>Alabama</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>PS_ Fredk will be engaged from this time during the Summer in the Indian Emigrating business I suppose he will leave in a few days.  he will be engaged in the <choice>
                     <abbr>P</abbr>
                     <expan>Post</expan>
                  </choice> masters department <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>HIW</abbr>
                     <expan>Henry Inman Welcker</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <pb n="4" facs="mc052d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>postmark stamp: Apr. 6, Kingston, Te.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mr C F. Welcker</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Talladega</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Alabama</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Mail</add>
               <add>Single</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
