<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl652">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1837 Jun. 26, Readyville, Tenn[essee, to] Nashville, Tenn[essee]  / Albert Miller Sea : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Sea, Albert Miller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl652</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1837 Jun. 26, Readyville, Tenn[essee, to] Nashville, Tenn[essee] / Albert Miller Sea</title>
               <author> Sea, Albert Miller</author>
               <date when="1837-06-26"> 
			 June 26, 1837</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Chief Engineer Albert Miller Sea dated June 26, 1837. The letter is to the executive board members of, presumably, a rail road company. Sea is writing to describe his recent surveying of land for the proposed rail road.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Newton Cannon Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl652</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Rail Roads Design and construction</term>
               <term>Surveying</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Sea, Albert Miller</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl652a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Readyville</name>, <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>June 26 1837</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To the Executive Board</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name> Tenn</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Since I had the pleasure of meeting you at Nashville, on 8 <choice>
                  <abbr>inst</abbr>
                  <expan>instant</expan>
               </choice> I have <del type="overstrike">rec</del> examined the country from the vicinity of <name>Columbia</name> Eastward towards <name>Shelbyville</name>, 15 miles; several days have been spent about Columbia, in endeavoring to find a practicable route through it; and I have also examined the country as far east as the head of <name>Stone's River</name>, passing near <name>Gideonville</name>, <name>Versailles</name>, <name>Murfreesboro</name>, Readyville and <name>Woodbury</name> A large part of this route has been actually surveyed, and a large scope of country examined</p>
            <p>The party arrived here yesterday, (Sunday) and are now engaged in making a survey of the ridge between <unclear>Cripple Cr</unclear> and Stone's River <name>Mr Nance</name> is behind, engaged in continuing the examination of the route heretofore examined by him from <name>Cherryville</name> by mouth <name>Duck River</name>
               <name>Franklin</name>
               <unclear>&amp;c</unclear> He in expected here tomorrow.</p>
            <p>I shall move on tomorrow beyond Woodbury and set the party to running a line up one of the branches of Stone's River, and down Charles <choice>
                  <abbr>Cr.</abbr>
                  <expan>Creek</expan>
               </choice> whilst I extend still further my examinations. There is no doubt but that the route must go either down this creek, or on the contiguous ridge if it ever touches the valley of Stones River. It will <add>be</add> impracticable for a Rail Road to cross Caney Fork below the Falls.</p>
            <p>From some point near the mouth of Charles <pb n="2" facs="sl652b.small.jpg"/> Creek, I shall return with the party towards the Forks of Duck River, and survey the route from mouth of Noahs Cr. to intersect the route down Charles Cr. either at the head or near <name>McMinnville</name> I shall myself have to return to the vicinity of Cedar Spring in <name>Maury County</name>, to resume my examination of the southern Route. It will probably be two weeks before <add>I</add> finally leave the vicinity of McMinnville, and it will require three or four weeks more to cross the Mountains.</p>
            <p>There has been some sickness in the party for a week or two past, owing chiefly to our exposure to the weather, which has been very <choice>
                  <orig>unfavourable</orig>
                  <reg>unfavorable</reg>
               </choice>. But I anticipate a much better state of health for all the party when we get into the mountain regions.</p>
            <p>Every member of the party seems to do his duty cheerfully and industriously.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Very Respectfully</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Albert Miller Sea,</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Ch Engr</abbr>
                     <expan>Chief Engineer</expan>
                  </choice> State Tenn.</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl652c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Executive Board</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
