<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0322">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Affidavit of James Johnston]  1837 Nov. 12, Roane County, Tennessee : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0322</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Affidavit of James Johnston]  1837 Nov. 12, Roane County, Tennessee</title>
               <date when="1837-11-12"> 
			 November 12, 1837</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is an affidavit given by James Johnston regarding land that belonged to The Pathkiller, a Cherokee Indian. The Pathkiller was dispossessed of his land during the Cherokee removal and fought for years to gain it back.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0322</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Legal document</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Land tenure</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0322a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>State of <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Roane County</name> Nov 12th 1838</addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>This day personally appeared <name>James Johnston</name> before me <name>John Blair</name> one of the acting Justice for said County and being duly sworn recording to law <orig>deposeth</orig>  and saith: That the first acquaintance I had with the <name>Pathkiller</name> was in the Spring of the year 1820 that he then Resided at what is now called Blairs ferry on the South Side of the <name>Tennessee River</name> about one hundred and fifty yards from the River within the lines of a <choice>
                  <orig>Resservation</orig>
                  <reg>Reservation</reg>
               </choice> he then Claimed as Surveyed by <name>Major Robert Armstrong </name>as I have heard Said Armstrong Swear he had Surveyed___ in the month of November 1820 James Blair became the purchaser of Said fraction at the River from the State of Tennessee in the Spring of 1821 <name>James Blair</name> got the Sheriff of Roane County <name>General John Brown</name> to Remove the PathKiller off the <add>part of the</add>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Resservation</orig>
                  <reg>Reservation</reg>
               </choice>
               <del type="overstrike">he</del> then sold <del type="overstrike">Claimed</del>and put James Blair in <del type="overstrike">Possesive</del>
               <choice>
                  <orig>possision</orig>
                  <reg>possession</reg>
               </choice> some short time afterwards the pathkiller brought suite against James Blair for said Resservation in the Circuit Court of Roane County and Said suite Continued in Court <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> about the year 1831 when the PathKiller recovered the land by law and <choice>
                  <orig>dispossed</orig>
                  <reg>dispossessed</reg>
               </choice> the Heirs and widow of James Blair   who Died during the progress of Said Suite in the year 1827 Pathkiller Ejected <name>William Tunell</name> and the writ was Returned to the March Term at  <name>Kingston </name>in the Same year the PathKiller Ejected <pb n="2" facs="pa0322b.small.jpg"/> John Blair and myself all holding land within the Resservation Claimed by the PathKiller and the writ Served on Blair and myself was Returned to the September term in 1827 <name>Judge White</name> was then acting as agent for the State and Consolidated Blairs Suite and mine into one suite the Suits progressed for some years that is Blairs and mine with an understanding <del type="overstrike">with the</del>  between the Counsel that Tunells Suite was to abide the <unclear>Issue</unclear> of the decision of ours_ the Suite went up to the Supreme Court three times before finally decided and went in our favour <del type="overstrike">then</del> in 1836 as well as I now <choice>
                  <orig>Recolect</orig>
                  <reg>recollect</reg>
               </choice> in January 1837 the PathKiller had one <add>other</add> writ of Ejectment Served on <name>Tunell Blair </name>and myself and during the progress of our first Suits the Heirs of James Blair had a writ of Ejectment Served on PathKiller in the name of <name>Wilie Blair</name> by his next friend Jane Blair and at the October Term of the Circuit Court 1837 all parties agreed to try Wilies Blairs Suite and the Rest was to abide the law of Said Suit Wilie Blair gained his Suite and a writ Issued by the Clerk to disposess the PathKiller and all his tenants which was in the hands of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Ballard </name>one of the <choice>
                  <orig>deputee</orig>
                  <reg>deputy</reg>
               </choice> Sheriff__ PathKiller moved away in the winter of 1837 or 1838 I think in January <add>him</add> and all his tenants went  off voluntary Except <name>Andrew McNabb</name> I think the deputy Sheriff told me he had to move him and further this deponent saith not <pb n="3" facs="pa0322c.small.jpg"/> Sworn to and Scribed to the Date above <choice>
                  <orig>writen</orig>
                  <reg>written</reg>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>James Johnston</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Acct</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>John Blair acting</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Justice of the <choice>
                        <orig>peas</orig>
                        <reg>peace</reg>
                     </choice> for</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Roane County</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Justice <unclear>fee</unclear>
                  <lb/> witness <unclear>fee</unclear>
               </add>
               <add>$1.00 <lb/> .50 <lb/> $1.50</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="pa0322d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>1837 PathKiller after 17 <lb/> years of contest <choice>
                     <orig>looses </orig>
                     <reg>loses</reg>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/> his Land___ <lb/> 3</add>
               <add>James Johnston <lb/> Affidavit <lb/> Respecting PathKiller's <lb/> Reservation</add>
               <add>60 <lb/> 4th Comm.</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
