<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl231">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1850 Sep. 18, Macon, Tennessee [to] Mary House, Nashville, Tennessee / C. A. Newborn   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Newborn, C. A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl231</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51236164</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1850 Sep. 18, Macon, Tennessee [to] Mary House, Nashville, Tennessee / C. A. Newborn</title>
               <author>Newborn, C. A.</author>
               <date when="1850-09-18">September 18, 1850</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated Sep. 18, 1850, from C. A. Newborn to Mary House. Newborn has heard of the death of Mary's husband George W. House, and wants to know the details of his life, illness, and death. Newborn also wants a lock of George's hair. Newborn also writes about a nearby boarding school for girls, run by Mrs. Miller and her husband, Rev. Miller.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl231</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding schools</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Death notices</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Newborn, C. A.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl231a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Macon</name>, <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn.</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                     <date when="1850-09-18">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Sept.</abbr>
                           <expan>September</expan>
                        </choice> 18th. 1850</date>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Mrs. <name type="person">Mary House</name>,</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Friend: —</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>In the "Tennessee Organ" of the 14th <choice>
                  <abbr>inst</abbr>
                  <expan>instant</expan>
               </choice> which Sarah sent us from school last evening, we see, with painful regret, announced the death of your husband <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Geo. W.</abbr>
                     <expan>George Washington</expan>
                  </choice> House</name> We therefore take an early opportunity to write in order to earn from you something more in regard to it — We were pleased to learn he died in the full possession of his mental faculties and ⁁ <add place="supralinear">with</add>
               <del type="overstrike">of</del> a bright prospect of a blissful immortality. How long was he sick? of what disease did he die? Were any of his relatives from <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Ala.</abbr>
                     <expan>Alabama</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> present? Where is he buried? Did he ever attach himself to any church When did he join the Sons of Temperance? An answer to these interrogations, together with such other information as you may deem of interest would be thankfully <choice>
                  <abbr>recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> by Mary &amp; me— During the last twelve months <unclear>I</unclear>⁁<add place="supralinear">have</add> written two letters —  the last I ever recd was written some five or six months ago in which he gave an account of a trip which you and he had just <pb n="2" facs="sl231b.small.jpg"/> taken to <name type="place">Cincinnati</name> If I am not mistaken I have written twice since I recd this last letter from you — I have been at a loss to account for the silence During the prevalence of cholera in <name type="place">Nashville</name> we often noticed the names of those who had fallen victims to it but never saw any of your family — On one occasion I saw your name given as one of the visitors at ⁁ <add place="supralinear">the</add> springs — Has <name type="person">
                  <unclear>Tho</unclear> Haughton</name> left Nashville? — If not how is he doing? We are all in the enjoyment of good health — Our youngest daughter was quite reduced in July, but she is now very healthy. This little creature has a greater resemblance of Geo. House than any other person has I have ever seen — Were you to see her I guess you would concur with me — Mary wishes you, if you have it to spare, to send her a small portion of George's hair — We have a good <unclear>Female</unclear> school at Macon taught by <name type="person">Mrs. Miller</name>. She went north and procured two females as assistants — The boarding house is new and large and is kept by Mrs. Miller  and husband <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Rev.</abbr>
                     <expan>Reverend</expan>
                  </choice> B. Miller</name> a Cumberland presbyterian minister — They <pb n="3" facs="sl231c.small.jpg"/> have some 25 young Ladies boarding with them — We are boarding Sarah although we could Let her ride from <unclear>home</unclear> the distance being only about 1 ¾ miles, but we prefer keeping her <unclear>under</unclear> ⁁ <add place="supralinear">the</add> care of the principal constantly. She is permitted to come out the 4th saturday in each month — Mrs. <choice>
                  <abbr>M.</abbr>
                  <expan>Miller</expan>
               </choice> is a northern Lady of great <choice>
                  <orig>intillegence</orig>
                  <reg>intelligence</reg>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <p>If you were to notice "M Makin's American Courier" of the 31st <choice>
                  <abbr>Augst</abbr>
                  <expan>August</expan>
               </choice> you would find a communication written by a gentleman of our village giving an account of the village — of the Masonic male school, and of this female school Mary sends her love to you &amp; little Sallie — Make our Respects to your mother</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>a hand-drawn hand pointing to "please"</figDesc>
               </figure> Please write me immediately and believe me to be with great Respect</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your friend</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">C. A. Newborn</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl231d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mrs Mary House</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Nashville</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="up the right margin">within is another <lb/> lock of our <choice>
                     <orig>babis</orig>
                     <reg>babies</reg>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/> hair</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
