<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0029">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1813 Jan. 28, Fortville [to] Col[onel] Metcalf / Charles Hicks : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Hicks, Charles</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0029</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1813 Jan. 28, Fortville [to] Col[onel] Metcalf / Charles Hicks</title>
               <author>Hicks, Charles</author>
               <date when="1813-01-28">January 28, 1813</date>
               <extent> 2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by Charles Hicks, a Cherokee Indian, to a Colonel Metcalf. Charles Hicks complains that some of Colonel Metcalf's men killed a Cherokee man and whipped other Cherokee men. Hicks writes that the action violates the existing treaty between the Cherokee Nation and the United States. The letter appears to have been forwarded to Return J. Meigs, agent to the Cherokee Nation.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0029</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Treaties</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Crimes against</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr2001025844"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Hicks, Charles R.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0029a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Fortville</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>January 28th 1813</date> Duplicate }<salute>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Col</abbr>
                        <expan>Colonel</expan>
                     </choice>. <choice>
                        <orig>Madcalf</orig>
                        <reg>Metcalf</reg>
                     </choice>
                  </name>My friend__</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have this day been informed <unclear>an</unclear> that you have been at Mr. Lowrys with an armed force upwards of fifty men and that your self &amp; a part of your company had gone home but a part of your company remained behind and I understand they have <choice>
                  <orig>whipt</orig>
                  <reg>whipped</reg>
               </choice> a <choice>
                  <orig>negro</orig>
                  <reg>Negro</reg>
               </choice> and an Indian &amp; killed another Indian in consequence of the <unclear>burning</unclear> of <name>Mr. Tally</name> who I understand is yet <choice>
                  <orig>a live</orig>
                  <reg>alive</reg>
               </choice> &amp; well <name>Mr Lowry </name> &amp; the other Chiefs would have given Mr. Tally any satisfaction he may have Demanded for the abuse he had received from Brown without raising men to come amongst us because we have a law provided amongst us in such cases of abuse with one another our people &amp; I presume that you know that <unclear>Y</unclear> the Treaty takes <choice>
                  <orig>cogniziance</orig>
                  <reg>cognizance</reg>
               </choice> in cases of murder In Either party &amp; in a formal demand but If you want to Kill us up for what little property we have then the strong can only improve on the weak but we claim the protection of the <name>United States</name> according to the Existing Treaty &amp; I shall report to the council of the breach of the <choice>
                  <orig>Entercourse</orig>
                  <reg>Intercourse</reg>
               </choice> law that they may communicate <add>this</add> to the Secretary of War of the Conduct of the Citizens of the State of <name>Tennessee</name>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am Sir respectfully</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Charles Hicks</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <name>Colo. Madcalf}</name>
               </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="pa0029b.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N.B.</abbr>
                     <expan>Nota Bene</expan>
                  </choice> a true copy of the above duplicate from Hicks drawn by <name>A. McCay</name> assistant <choice>
                     <abbr>clk</abbr>
                     <expan>clerk</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <add>Charles Hicks' letter to Col. Metcalf 28. January 1813 relating to a party of whitemen marching into the Cherokee nation &amp; killing an Indian &amp; <choice>
                     <orig>whiping</orig>
                     <reg>whipping</reg>
                  </choice> others</add>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>For Colo. Return J. Meigs Highwassee Garrison</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
