<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc184">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Land Grant] 1790 Tennessee Company : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc184</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Land Grant] 1790 Tennessee Company </title>
               <date when="1790"> 
			 1790</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a Land Grant dated in 1790 for the Tennessee Company owned by Zachariah Cox and Mathia Maber.  It grants lands along the Tennessee River.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Land Grant</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-1898</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc184</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Land grants</term>
               <term>Tennessee River</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc184a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>Whereas, the state of <name>Georgia</name>, on the <date>twenty-fourth day of January, in the year of our Lord one thousand seven hundred and ninety-five</date>, DID give and grant unto <name>Zachariah Cox</name> and <name>Mathia Maber</name>, 2nd their associates, called the Tennessee Company, their heirs and assigns forever, in fee simple, as tenants in common, and not as joint tenants, all that tract or parcel of LAND, including islands, situate, lying and being within the following boundaries, that is to say__ BEGINNING at the mouth of <name>Bear Creek</name>, on the south side of the <name>Tennessee river</name>__ thence up the said creek to the most southern source thereof__ thence a due fourth course to the latitude of thirty four degrees and ten minutes north of the Equator__ thence a due East course, one hundred and twenty miles__ thence a due north course to the great Tennessee river__ thence up the middle of the said river, to the northern boundary line of this state__ thence a due west course, along the said line, to where it intersects the great Tennessee river, below the <name>Muscle-Shoals</name>__ thence up said river to the place of beginning; together with all and singular the rights, members and <choice>
                  <orig>appartenances</orig>
                  <reg>appurtenances</reg>
               </choice> whatsoever to the said parcel of land being, belonging, or in an wise apperaining; to hold to them the said Zachariah Cox and Matthias Maber, and their associates, called the Tennessee Company, their heirs and assigns forever, in fee simple, as tenants in common, and not as joint tenants, as in and by the said recited grant.</p>
            <p>NOW this Indenture witnesseth, that the laid Zachariah Cox, for and in consideration of the sum of__ Dollars, to him in hand paid, the receipt whereof is hereby acknowledged, HATH granted, bargained, fold, aliened, released and confirmed, and by these presents, DOTH grant, bargain, sell, alien, relate and confirm, unto__ heirs and assigns, __ acres of land, in the said Tennessee Company's purchase, to be located and surveyed on the main stream, or tributatries of__ a tributary of water of the Great Tennessee river, emptying in on the north side__ the Muscle Shoals, (included by the Tennessee Comapny's purchase) to be surveyed or laid off in an equilateral or oblong square, the length of which shall not exceed doubt the breadth: Together with all and singular the rights, members and appurtenances whatsoever, thereunto belonging, or in any wise appertating, and the remainders, reversious, rents, issues and profits thereof, TO HAVE AND TO HOLD the said__ acres of land, to __ the said__ heirs and assigns, to the only proper safe, benefit and behoof of__ the said__ heirs and assigns forever, the said tract or parcel of land aforesaid, against them the said Zachariah Cox and Matthias Maber, and their associates, their heirs and assigns, and all and every other person or persons whatever, claiming or to claim under them by these presen shall and will warrant and forever defend, IN WITNESS whereof, the said Zachariah Cox, hath hereunto set his band and seal this<date>__ day of__  <choice>
                     <abbr>A.D</abbr>
                     <expan>Anno Domini</expan>
                  </choice>. one thousand Seven hundred and ninety</date>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Zach Cox</signed>
               <add>Signed, Sealed and Delivered in Presence of <unclear reason="crease in document"><?xm-replace_text {unclear}?></unclear>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
