<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl127">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1838 Nov. 4, Clover Dale, [TN] [to] Mr Samuel Bell, Cornplanter, Venango County, PA / William B. Bell : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Bell, William B.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl127</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50541026</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1838 Nov. 4, Clover Dale, [TN] [to] Mr Samuel Bell, Cornplanter, Venango County, PA / William B. Bell</title>
               <author>Bell, William B</author>
               <date when="1838-11-04">November 4, 1838</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated November 4, 1838, from William B. Bell in Dickson County, TN to his brother Samuel Bell in Cornplanter, PA.  In the letter, William primarily discusses business matters related to iron works and farming.  He explains that the dry weather has left the iron furnaces in Dickson County non-operational.  He also comments on the increasing price of corn, which is expected to be between 75 cents and a dollar per bushel in the spring.  William also expounds on other farming matters.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">15</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl127</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Iron -- works</term>
               <term>Crop losses</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Bell, William</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl127a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Clover Dale</name>
                     <date when="1838-11-04">November 4. 1838</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I ought to apologize for not answering your letter sooner, being so much engaged in making and getting in the crop that I did not have leisure to write to my friends.  You and sister <name type="person">Jane</name> write so seldom now to what you formerly done, that I sometimes think you have forgotten your friends in <name type="place">Tennessee</name>. This has been a very bad year on Iron masters, the summer and fall has been so remarkably dry that the furnaces had to lay idle for the want of water.  I have Just finished getting in our corn, although it has been very much injured by the  drought, we have housed about one hundred and thirty barrels, our wheat and oats crops were very good.  I have a very hard piece of clearing to do this fall and winter, it is a field of about thirty acres, which has grown up entirely with <orig resp="#briars">bryars</orig> and bushes, probably you remember seeing it, as you passed <pb n="2" facs="sl127b.small.jpg"/> through it going to <name type="place">Charlotte</name>. I should like to hear from you soon, and know whether you had <choice>
                  <orig>raines</orig>
                  <reg>rains</reg>
               </choice> sufficient to keep the furnaces in blast all summer.  I expect that corn will command a better price here next spring than it will with you, it is thoug <add place="supralinear">ht</add> to be worth from seventy-five <choice>
                  <abbr>cts.</abbr>
                  <expan>cents</expan>
               </choice> to one dollar per bushel.  I <add place="supralinear">have</add>  sowed fifteen acres in wheat this year, which looks very flourishing at present.  There is such a quantity of fruit on the chest-nut and oak trees this year that it will fatten the hogs without the assistance of corn, but there is one evil attending large fruit years, the hogs become very wild and have to be hunted with dogs and shot like you would a deer.  Tell <name type="person">Wylie</name> , and <name type="person">Theodore</name> that I wish they had been here this fall to gather chestnuts, as they were very plenty.</p>
            <p>It was with deep regret that I heard of <name type="person">Miss Gormly</name>'s low state of health, and knowing her worth I sympathize with you all, you have parted with many of your friends, and I think you ought not to grieve for them as those who have no hope. I hope Sister Jane's sickness is nothing dangerous, and is now well.  I think a visit to <name type="place">Dickson</name> would improve <pb n="3" facs="sl127c.small.jpg"/> you and Sister very much, I think you ought to pay us a visit when the river rises, as you can come in six or eight <del type="overstrike">hours</del>
               <add place="supralinear">days</add> Tell Wylie and Theodore that I would be glad to hear from them, and say I will ⁁ <add place="supralinear">write</add> to them soon.  Each member of the family join with me in love to you all.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I remain Your affectionate Brother</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <emph>William B. Bell</emph>
                  </name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl127d.small.jpg"/>
               <add rend="different hand, ink">
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Charlotte <choice>
                              <abbr>Tn</abbr>
                              <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <date when="1838-11-06">
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Nov</abbr>
                              <expan>November</expan>
                           </choice> 6</date>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
               <add place="right of address" rend="different hand, ink">25</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mr Samuel Bell</name> P.M.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Cornplanter</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Venango County</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Pa.</abbr>
                           <expan>Pennsylvania</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
