<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0032">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1813 Oct. 30, Highwassee Garrison [to John Armstrong] / [Return J. Meigs]  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Meigs, Return J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0032</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 44930310</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1813 Oct. 30, Highwassee Garrison [to John Armstrong] / [Return J. Meigs]</title>
               <author>Meigs, Return J.</author>
               <date when="1813-10-30">October 30, 1813</date>
               <extent>4 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated October 30, 1813 from Cherokee agent Return J. Meigs to John Armstrong, the Secretary of War.  This letter was written after the Creek War of 1813 had begun, and Meigs informs Armstrong that he had supplied the Cherokee with blankets and other supplies in compensation for their cooperation against the Creeks.  Meigs also explains his philosophy regarding working with the Cherokee; he believes that keeping them dependent on the US for support and assistance is beneficial to both the US and the Cherokee.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0032</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letter</term>
               <term>Meigs, Return Jonathan, 1764-1824 Correspondence</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Government relations</term>
               <term>Creek Indians -- Wars</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n92008354"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Meigs, Return Jonathan, 1740-1823</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0032a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Highwassee Garrison</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>30th October 1813</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>On receiving your letter of the 26th August on the subject of a co-operation of the <name>Cherokees</name> with the U.S. troops against the hostile <name>Creeks</name>, a number of Chiefs came to me to inform me that they were taking measures, unknown to me, in anticipation of the object; expecting every day that the hostile Creeks would make an attack on the friendly Creeks who had found an <choice>
                  <orig>assylum</orig>
                  <reg>asylum</reg>
               </choice> within the Cherokee boundary line at <name>Turkeystown</name>, to whom the Cherokees had promised protection-</p>
            <p>As advised by your letter I addressed the Governors of Georgia &amp; Tennessee on the subject of a co-operation of the Cherokees in the expeditions against the enemy. I received a letter from the Governor of Tennessee approbating the measure, &amp; requesting me to correspond with the Generals <name>Jackson</name>, <name>Cocke</name>, &amp; <name>White</name> commanding the Tennessee troops; in the meantime the the leading young Cherokee Chiefs were enrolling their young men for the expedition and applied to me for Blankets &amp; some other articles of <choice>
                  <orig>Cloathing</orig>
                  <reg>Clothing</reg>
               </choice> to enable those who were destitute to march with them in co.operation with our troops.  there was no time to consult the war Department.  there was no time to <choice>
                  <orig>hessitate</orig>
                  <reg>hesitate</reg>
               </choice>; the frontiers were menaced with a formidable savage force, become so only by their desperation we have nothing to fear while we estimate the utmost they can do. in this kind of war it was considered that the service of the Cherokees would be of great value &amp; I furnished the most needy whose names were enrolled at that time with articles of Cloathing to the amount of ten dollars each: not as a gift, or present; but to <pb n="2" facs="pa0032b.small.jpg"/> to be accounted for at the end of the Campaign, presuming that the Government will consider them intitled to some compensation:  And as I may expect repeated applications for Blankets &amp; other articles to enable them to do their duty as the cold weather advances. I respectfully ask for advice &amp; directions.  Whatever they receive in this way can be deducted from their pay-if they shall be allowed pay- they will expect pay or compensation in some shape.  I never have had an idea that they will be considered as allies having always rejected an idea of their sovereignty, for there is no way to save them or to make them of use to the Government: but to keep them dependent- they cannot stand alone- and by paying them for their service they will feel themselves under control: besides it will flatter their pride to be considered in some degree on a footing with our troops.  If the war should be protracted they may be made of great service especially in combatting Indians.  there is no way to save the people from annihilation as a nation but to employ them_. they have some enemies who observe with regret their Arming to act with our troops: these illiberal people wish for an opportunity to divide out their pleasant Country amongst them.</p>
            <p>I have frequently compared the <add>condition of the</add> Cherokee to that of a Foundling laid at the door of Charity: if spurned from the door it will perish; if taken in it may one day help to defend the house._ Keep them dependent.  It will not be understood that  I would deprive them of their national rights as human beings, my  mind would revolt at such a sentiment.  Their state in their relation to the United States is that <pb n="3" facs="pa0032c.small.jpg"/> of a minority,  to this State they conceded after the English were driven from our Coasts: it was the price of their preservation &amp; by this concession their existence as a distinct tribe has been secured to the present time.  By convention we owe them protection, &amp; in return they <add>owe</add> us fidelity._ It would be a cruel act <add>to</add> make them politically independent; the effect would be their extinction within a short period,_ I conceive that the Indian tribes within the limits of the U.S. can never be considered as distinctly independent communities. they are by their local &amp; moral condition appendages only, not necessary to us, but absolutely necessary for them, &amp; the mild constituent principles of our Government has reached the Indian tribes every where within our limits, &amp; it is not one of its least estimable traits that, it has expended since the revolution millions for the amelioration of the condition of the Indian tribes: notwithstanding which, the never ceasing envy &amp; malice of the English having deceived &amp; corrupted them, they have turned their arms against us. &amp; we are now suffering from their recent barbarity. &amp; yet we receive their acknowledgments of their errors; we bring them back &amp; compel them to be happy; it may almost be said against their will. _ The magnanimity of our Government rises above the passions of <choice>
                  <orig>revinge</orig>
                  <reg>revenge</reg>
               </choice>. and looks down on treason, fraud, &amp; barbarity of the Indians in the "calm light of mild philosophy" considering justly that, the English, the savages of Europe, are the cause of the defection of Indians &amp; that what we have suffered from them ought principally to be attributed to the present <choice>
                  <orig>Brittish</orig>
                  <reg>British</reg>
               </choice> ministry.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="pa0032d.small.jpg"/>
            <closer>Outlines of a letter to the Secretary of war 30 October 1813 <lb/> arming Cherokee warriors <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice>.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
