<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl722">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> [Letter] 1797 Jul. 6 [to] Senate of the United States / Sam[uel] A. Otis : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Otis, Sam[uel] A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl722</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1797 Jul. 6 [to] Senate of the United States / Sam[uel] A. Otis</title>
               <author> Otis, Sam[uel] A.</author>
               <date>July 6, 1797</date>
               <extent>5p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter  to a Senate select committee from the secretary of the U.S. Senate, Samuel Otis dated July 6, 1797. Otis includes a copy of a letter written by William Blount to James Carey, an interpreter to the Cherokee Nation, dated  April 21, 1797. This is a copy of the the letter that causes Blount's expulsion from the U.S. Senate. Blount is conspiring with a Captain Chesholm, the Creeks, Cherokees, and the British minister to take West Florida and Louisiana away from Spain to give to Great Britain.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor John Sevier Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">8</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl722</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>United States</term>
               <term>Blount, William 1749-1800.</term>
               <term>Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814</term>
               <term>Law and legislation</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n92050415"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Otis, Samuel Allyne, 1740-1814</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl722a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>In Senate of the <name>United States</name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>July 6th, 1797</date>.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <note>
                     <p>The Committee to whom was referred that part of the President's message which relates to a letter purporting to have been written by  <name>William Blount</name>, <choice>
                           <abbr>Esq.</abbr>
                           <expan>Esquire</expan>
                        </choice> one of the Senators from the State of <name>Tennessee</name>, together with the papers accompanying the fame, having had the fame under their confidence beg leave to make a farther report.</p>
                     <p>That Mr. Blount having declined an acknowledgment or denial of the letter imputed to him; and having failed to appear or give any satisfactory respecting it, your committee sent for the original letter which accompanies this report and is in the following words.</p>
                  </note>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Colonel King's Iron-works,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>April 21st, 1797</date>.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear <name>Carey</name>,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I wished to have seen you, before I returned to <name>Philadelphia</name>; but I am obliged to return to the session of Congress, which commences on the <date>15th of May</date>.</p>
            <p>Among other things that I wished to have seen you about, was the business <name>Captain Chesholm</name> mentioned to the British Minister last winter at Philadelphia.</p>
            <p>I believe, but am not quite sure, that the plan then talked of will be attempted this fall; and if it is attempted, it will be in a much a larger way than then talked of; and if the Indians act their part, I have no doubt but it will succeed. A man of consequence has gone to <name>England</name> about the business, and if he makes arrangements as he expects, I shall myself have a hand in the business, and probably shall be at the head of the business on the part of the British. You are, however, to understand <pb n="2" facs="sl722b.small.jpg"/> that it is not yet quite certain that the plan will be attempted: yet you will do well to keep things in a proper train of action in case it should be attempted, and to so so will require all your management. I say require all you management, because you must take care, in whatever you say to <name>Rogers</name>, or any body else, not to let the plan be discovered by <name>Hawkins</name>, <name>Dinsmore</name>, <name>Byers</name>, or any other person in the interest of the United States or <name>Spain</name>.</p>
            <p>If I attempt this plan, I shall expect to have you and all my Indian country and Indian friends with me; but you are now in good business, I hope, and you are not to risk the loss of it saying any thing that will hurt you until you again hear from me. Where Captain Chesholm is I do not know: I left him in Philadelphia in March, and he frequently visited the Minister, and spoke upon the subject; but I believe he will go into the <name>Creek nation</name>, by way of <name>South Carolina</name> or <name>Georgia</name>. He gave out he was going to England, but I did not believe him. Among things that you may safely do, will be to keep up my consequence with <name>Watts</name>, and the Creeks and <name>Cherokee</name>s generally, and you must by no means say any thing in favour of Hawkins, but as often as you can with safety to yourself, you may teach the Creeks to believe he is no better than he should be. Any power or consequence he gets will be against our plan. Perhaps Rogers, who has no office to lose, is the best man to give out talks against Hawkins. Read the letter to Rogers, and if you think it best to send it to him, put a wafer in it, and forward it to him by a safe hand, or perhaps you had best send for him to come to you, and speak to him yourself, respecting the state and prospect of things.</p>
            <p>I have advised you in whatever you do take care of yourself. I have now to tell you to take care of me too, for a discovery of the plan would prevent the success, and much injure all parties concerned. It may <pb n="3" facs="sl722c.small.jpg"/> be that the Commissioners may not run the line as the Indians expect, or wish, and in that case it is probable the Indians may be taught to blame me for making the Treaty.</p>
            <p>To such complaints against me, is such there are, it may be said by my friends, at proper times and places, that Doublehead confirmed the Treaty with the President, at Philadelphia, and receives as much as 5000 dollars a year to be paid to the nation over and above the first price: Indeed it may with truth be said, that though I made the treaty, that I made it by the instructions of the President, and in fact it may with truth be said, that I was by the President instructed to purchase much more land than the Indians would agree to sell. This  sort of talk  will be throwing all the blame off me, upon the late President, and as he is now out of office, it will be of no consequence how much the Indians blame him. And among other things that may be said for me, is, that I was not at the running of the line, and that if I had been, it would have been run more to their satisfaction. In short, you understand the subject, and must take care to give out the proper talks to keep up my consequence with the Creeks and Cherokees. Can't Rogers contrive to get the Creeks to define the President to take Hawkins out of the nation, for if he stays in the Creek nation, and gets the good-will of the nation, he can and will do great injury to our plans. When you have read this letter over three times then burn it. I shall be at Knoxville in July or August, when I will send for Watts, and give him the whiskey I promised him, <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c.</abbr>
                  <expan>etcetera</expan>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>William Blount</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <note>
                     <p>Two Senators now present in the Senate have declared to the committee that they are well acquainted with the hand writing of Mr. Blount and have no doubt that this letter was written by him, your Committee have examined many letters from Mr. Blount to the <pb n="4" facs="sl722d.small.jpg"/> Secretary of War, a number of which are herewith submitted as well as the letter addressed by Mr. Blount to <name>Mr. Cocke</name> his colleague in the Senate and to this Committee respecting the business now under consideration; and find them all to be of the same hand writing with the letter in question. Mr. Blount has never denied this letter, but on the other hand when the copy transmitted to the Senate was read in his presence on the 3d. instant, he acknowledged in his place that he had written a letter to Carey of which he had preserved a copy, but could not then decide whether the copy read was a true one. Your Committee are therefore fully persuaded that the original letter now produced was written and sent to Carey by Mr. Blount. They also find that this man Carey to whom it was addressed, is, to the knowledge of Mr. Blount, in the pay and employment of the United States, as their Interpreter to the Cherokee nation of Indians and an assistant in the public factory at <name>Tellico</name> Blockhouse.___ That Hawkins who is so often mentioned in this letter as  a person who must be brought into suspicion among the Creeks, and if possible driven from his station, is the Superintendant of Indian affairs for the United States among the Southern Indians; Dinsmore is agent for the United States in the Cherokee nation; and Byers, one of the agents in the public factory at Tellico Blockhouse.</p>
                     <p>The plan hinted at in this extraordinary letter to be executed under the auspices of the British, is so capable of different constructions and conjectures that your committee at present forbear giving any decided opinion respecting it; except that to Mr. Blount's own mind it appeared to be inconsistent with the interests of the United States and of Spain, and he was therefore anxious to conceal it from both. But when they consider his attempts to seduce Carey from his duty, as a faithful interpreter, and to employ him as an engine to alienate the affections and confidence of the Indians from <pb n="5" facs="sl722e.small.jpg"/> the public officers of the United States residing among them; the measures he has proposed to excite a temper which must produce the recall or expulsion of our Superintendant from the Creek nation, his insidious advice tending to the advancement of his own popularity and consequence at the <choice>
                           <orig>expence</orig>
                           <reg>expense</reg>
                        </choice> and hazard of the good opinion which the Indians entertain of this government, and of the treaties subsisting between us and them; your committee have no doubt that Mr. Blount's conduct has been inconsistent with his public duty, renders him unworthy of a further continuance of his present public trust in this body, and amounts to a high misdemeanor. They therefore, unanimously, recommend to the Senate an adoption of the following resolution:</p>
                     <p>Resolved, That William Blount, Esquire, one of the Senators of the United States, having been guilty of a high <choice>
                           <orig>misdemeanour</orig>
                           <reg>misdemeanour</reg>
                        </choice> entirely inconsistent with his public trust and duty as a Senator, be, and he hereby is expelled from the Senate of the United States.</p>
                  </note>
               </add>
               <add>
                  <unclear>I as</unclear>  Senate <choice>
                     <abbr>U</abbr>
                     <expan>United</expan>
                  </choice> States <lb/>
                  <date>July 8th 1797</date>
                  <lb/>  a true Copy <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>attest</abbr>
                     <expan>attested</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Sam A</abbr>
                        <expan>Samuel Allyne</expan>
                     </choice> Otis</name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Secty</abbr>
                     <expan>Secretary</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
