<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mc049">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1837 Sep. 20, Terre Haute, Indiana [to] Mr. Charles F. Welcker, Talladega, Alabama /  Geo[rge] L. Welcker : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Welcker, George L.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">mc049</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1837 Sep. 20, Terre Haute, Indiana [to] Mr. Charles F. Welcker, Talladega, Alabama /  Geo[rge] L. Welcker</title>
               <author>Welcker, George L.</author>
               <date when="1837-09-20">September 20, 1837</date>
               <extent>4 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated September 20, 1837, from George L. Welcker in Terre Haute, Indiana, to his brother Charles F. Welcker in Talladega, Alabama.  The Welckers were a prominent family in Roane County, Tennessee.  In this letter, George writes mostly about family matters.  He also discusses Mississippi, describing it as an unhealthy and destitute country.  George further updates his brother on events in his own life in Indiana.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Welcker Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-12, b2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1837</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mc049</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Welcker, George Lewis</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mc049a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Terre Haute, Indiana</name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Sept</abbr>
                           <expan>September</expan>
                        </choice> 20th 1837</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Brother;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>It has been some time since I have heard any thing directly from you; and I suppose it has been equally long since you have heard from me. _ And now that I have commenced to write; it is not because I have any thing new, strange, or interesting to communicate that I do so; but rather because I know you will be pleased to receive a few lines from me, even though they should contain but little._</p>
            <p>I have received but one letter from brother Henry since I had the pleasure of seeing you, and that informed me of the great loss you had sustained in the death of your little daughter: from yourself I have received nothing.</p>
            <p>It is but a short time since I received letters from sisters Catharine and Mary Jane: Catharine was at <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Majr.</abbr>
                     <expan>Major</expan>
                  </choice> Lenoir</name>s when she wrote__ she had been nearly a month in <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>E. Tenn.</abbr>
                     <expan>East Tennessee</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> and expected to set out for home in a short time.__ Mary Jane was at school in <name>Kingston</name>_ she had just been out at home, and left all the family well_ I say all the family, which was Father, Mother, Albert &amp; Clinton_ things have been much changed since our day __</p>
            <p>Frederick, Monroe &amp; Franklin were at Knoxville, and from what I saw &amp; heard, when last at Knoxville, I have no doubt they are doing well ____ In fact, there <pb n="2" facs="mc049b.small.jpg"/>  are none of the family who have not, thus far, done well__ And I think it is incumbent upon us, as the elder of the family, to do, each in his own way, the best we can: for I have no doubt, that the conduct and character of the elder members, have a great influence in farming the character and fixing the destiny of the younger members of any family.</p>
            <p>I have not heard any thing of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Mitchell</name> or family since Henry wrote to me _ I should be glad to hear from them; and I am particularly anxious to know what disposition is to be made of our little nephews__ That <name>Mississippi</name>  is a new &amp; unhealthy country_ it is, &amp; perhaps ever will be, an extravagant country_ it is now <choice>
                  <orig>labouring</orig>
                  <reg>laboring</reg>
               </choice> under a calamity, mainly to be attributed to the wildness &amp; excess with which every thing has been conducted; a calamity from which it will not soon recover__ its society is unorganized &amp; unsettled _ it is destitute of the comforts of life; it is destitute of schools; it is destitute of good &amp; social feelings__   In short, it is not a country in which children should be raised_ and it is fit to be inhabited by those only who are willing to live but few years, and who are willing to spend those few years in killings mules &amp; negroes, in raising Cotton, &amp; in endeavoring to make money._ Those children could be raised and educated in E. Tenn. for one tenth of the expense, and would have better Constitution, better health, better sense, stronger minds &amp; stronger bodies, more energy of Character, and would, in fact, be entirely different &amp; better men.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="mc049c.small.jpg"/>
            <p>I want to hear from you_ I want to know how you are getting along in the world_ What kind of a crop did you make?_ What are your Calculations &amp; prospects? Have you settled with <name>Sharp</name> so that you will not be loser?_ Will you be able to pay him? Sister Catharine wrote to me that you would be in E. Tenn. in <choice>
                  <abbr>Oct.</abbr>
                  <expan>October</expan>
               </choice> &amp; wanted to know if we could not all meet there at that time__ For my own part, I have no idea that I shall be able to be there before winter; perhaps not even then.  I shall Come as soon as I can, be it soon or late_ But I should like, above all things, to meet the whole family once more around the old fireside__ It would recall to our minds the recollection of by gone days_ it would awaken in our bosoms the remembrance of former times &amp; former associations_  hours which, if they were not hours of perfect happiness, were at least the hours of innocence and youth.</p>
            <p>I have been very much occupied with my duties since my return to this place_ <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Capt</abbr>
                     <expan>Captain</expan>
                  </choice> Ogden</name>  has been along the line of the road, putting out Contracts, the whole season_ and is absent at this time._ I have remained here, &amp; have been engaged with the business in this section of the Country, and in corresponding with the departments at <name>Washington</name>, &amp; with the different agents &amp; assistants along the whole line of the Road <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c.</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> &amp;c,_</p>
            <p>I have thus far enjoyed uninterrupted good health_ I think I shall leave Edmond at home the first opportunity I have_ He is more plague than profit_ My horse is coming on finely_  I have been endeavoring to read Law this summer, but my other engagements have been such, that I have done little at it. <add>It was with regret that I lately learned the death of <name>Col <unclear>Standefor</unclear>
                  </name> _ he died at Kingston on his way to Washington City_ </add>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="mc049d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>The Crops in this country are the finest that I have ever seen any where__ The country is rather new to be a good fruit country_ apples are pretty good_ peaches are scarce &amp; of an inferior quality._ In point of all acquaintances I stand alone_ there is not an individual in the country whom I have ever known before</p>
            <p>
               <add>
                  <add>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>postmark stamp: Sept. 21, Terre Haute, Ia.</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </add>
                  <add>25</add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Mr. Charles F. Welcker</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Talladega</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Alabama</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
            </p>
            <p>This country is not healthy_ Bilious fevers, fevers &amp; agues, &amp;c are quite common__  Give my respects to <name>Capt. shelly</name> &amp; <name>Mr Rutlege</name>, <name>Col Hogan</name>  I suppose will not remember me_ Give my love to Caroline, Henry, &amp; Elizabeth, &amp; accept the same from your brother</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Geo.</abbr>
                        <expan>George</expan>
                     </choice> L. Welcker</name>
               </salute>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To Charles F. Welcker</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Talladega, <choice>
                        <abbr>Ala.</abbr>
                        <expan>Alabama</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
