<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl347">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>    [Letter] 1823 June 4, Henderson County, K[entuck]y [to] Finis Ewing, Boonville, Missouri / W[illia]m Barnett : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Barnett, Wm.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl347</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1823 June 4, Henderson County, K[entuck]y [to] Finis Ewing, Boonville, Missouri / W[illia]m Barnett</title>
               <author>Barnett, Wm.</author>
               <date when="1823-06-04">June 4, 1823</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from William Barnett to Finis Ewing, dated June 4, 1823. Barnett writes about the Cumberland Presbyterian Church and its various members. He is concerned about the legitimacy of some of the preachers. He writes about some pamphlets that the old style Presbyterians have been circulating that are slanderous to the new style, Cumberland Presbyterians. Barnett plans to propose a formal split between the Cumberlands and other Presbyterians  at the next synod,  and asks for Ewing's support. He mentions a possible move to Forked Deer. Barnett also writes that he and others want Ewing to write a history about the origins of the Cumberland Presbyterians. Many people have been expressing curiosity, but cannot find  information them because Buck's Theological Dictionary is out of print.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Finis Ewing Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">I-A-4</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl347</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Kentucky</term>
               <term>Presbyterian Church</term>
               <term>Religious Life</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Barnett, William</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl347a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Henderson County</name>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Ky</abbr>
                           <expan>Kentucky</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                     <date>June 4th 1823</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My very dear Brother Ewing.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>It has been a long, long time since I either saw you, or received or wrote a scrape to you; I can forbear no longer.</p>
            <p>I returned a few days ago, from the <name>Forked deer</name>, and eager <add>ly</add> went to the Post office in hopes to have received a letter from you, But <choice>
                  <orig>alass</orig>
                  <reg>alas</reg>
               </choice> ! there was none; I called at your <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Bro</abbr>
                     <expan>Brother</expan>
                  </choice> young</name> they were all well, and <name>Thompson</name>s Family were also ___</p>
            <p>I saw <name>Bro Cassett</name> he has corrected a part of your <choice>
                  <orig>peac</orig>
                  <reg>piece</reg>
               </choice> , &amp; said he <choice>
                  <sic>would would</sic>
                  <corr>would</corr>
               </choice> finish it as soon as <choice>
                  <orig>posable</orig>
                  <reg>possible</reg>
               </choice> ; and send it on to <name>Russelleville</name>.</p>
            <p>I saw young <name>Guthre</name> he says that a great many of the Preachers feels much disappointed; (and I suppose displeased) that your Book was <del type="overstrike">
                  <add>not</add>
               </del> examined before Synod; (I supposed some of them wished it graced with their <choice>
                  <orig>tallents</orig>
                  <reg>talents</reg>
               </choice> )</p>
            <p>From what I can learn the old <choice>
                  <abbr>P,s</abbr>
                  <expan>Preachers</expan>
               </choice> in the lower part of this state are now of opinion that long as their <unclear>cannon was loading</unclear> that it has fired too soon for their good; I have not learned much of the popular opinion about it; and I am not clear whether it would not be best for it to answer its self.</p>
            <p>I do not believe I ever read a Pamphlet where there was as much spirit in it that was as <choice>
                  <orig>intirely</orig>
                  <reg>entirely</reg>
               </choice> free of the spirit of candor, and truth.</p>
            <p>If it were answered, I would wish to enquire at the <unclear>Mad,,</unclear> of the Synod; (as they are great sticklers for <choice>
                  <orig>decipline</orig>
                  <reg>discipline</reg>
               </choice> ) How often <choice>
                  <sic>an an</sic>
                  <corr>an</corr>
               </choice> offending Brother; or Presbytery, ought to be sighted, before a Synod, <choice>
                  <abbr>Presb</abbr>
                  <expan>Presbyterian</expan>
               </choice> or Session; could adjudicate on their case And how often <name>Mcadow</name> , <name>King</name>, and yourself had been regularly summoned to appear, and before What <choice>
                  <abbr>P,,</abbr>
                  <expan>Preacher</expan>
               </choice> They say that you, &amp; King never had any authority; if so, how did they know it? Is there any other way for a Synod, to know whether a P,, has done right, or <choice>
                  <orig>rong</orig>
                  <reg>wrong</reg>
               </choice> only by their <choice>
                  <orig>Minuts</orig>
                  <reg>Minutes</reg>
               </choice> ? If so, does the minuts of the old Cumberland P state that you and <choice>
                  <abbr>K</abbr>
                  <expan>King</expan>
               </choice> were not regularly set apart by the <unclear>imposeteon <add>of hard</add>
               </unclear>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl347b.small.jpg"/> That Pamphlet <choice>
                  <orig>stats</orig>
                  <reg>states</reg>
               </choice> that things were thus &amp; so; <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c &amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>and etcetera and etcetera</expan>
               </choice> but I did not know that either in <name>America</name>, or the Presbyterian church (where laws rule, and not men) That it was ever known, or could be known whether a criminal was <choice>
                  <orig>eithe</orig>
                  <reg>either</reg>
               </choice> justified, or condemned,  until they were tried; But in this case there can be evidence of a <choice>
                  <orig>descision</orig>
                  <reg>decision</reg>
               </choice> , and that published to the big world, without any trial,</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Por</orig>
                  <reg>Poor</reg>
               </choice> old Bro Mcadow was tried several months, after he was in an other Church; ( <unclear>I think</unclear> , this will do for hope) But <choice>
                  <orig>Illegetemate</orig>
                  <reg>Illegitimate</reg>
               </choice> as you swore, if you would take <choice>
                  <orig>draught</orig>
                  <reg>drought</reg>
               </choice> of the confession; or a swig of Predestination, as did <name>Nelson</name> &amp;c it would <choice>
                  <orig>legetitimatized</orig>
                  <reg>legitimatized</reg>
               </choice> , or sanctified you and <unclear>made</unclear> you good Presbyterians;</p>
            <p>They tell us the close in their decipline "in <choice>
                  <orig>extrordinary</orig>
                  <reg>extraordinary</reg>
               </choice> cases" <choice>
                  <orig>aludes</orig>
                  <reg>alludes</reg>
               </choice> altogether to the length of time they study divinity, and nothing else; They harp much on the case of poor old <name>Haw</name> ; There is an exact <choice>
                  <orig>parrellel</orig>
                  <reg>parallel</reg>
               </choice> case in the west <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Ten,,</abbr>
                     <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> P so the man who was received to <add>ld</add> me himself, a <name>Mr,, Lanear</name> of <name>Nashville</name>; who was a Methodist, without learning, he joined that P,, and he told me they near proposed to him the confession of Faith at all, he had for something been turned out of his old Church, he produced his papers showing his trial and his previous licensure, and ordination; and <choice>
                  <orig>perhapse</orig>
                  <reg>perhaps</reg>
               </choice> he had withdrawn after his trial; they deliberated on his case for sometime and finally invited him to take a seat; and never asked him a question on <choice>
                  <orig>doctrins</orig>
                  <reg>doctrines</reg>
               </choice> ; this is what none of  our P,, would have done I know; and I know of nothing that can make that act right, only that <name>DD Blackburn</name> was at the head of it so Lanear told me!!!</p>
            <p>I apprehend the Nashville <choice>
                  <abbr>Pres,,</abbr>
                  <expan>Presbytery</expan>
               </choice> will oppose a division which I will propose at next Synod; I wish you to lend me some aid, in your P,, and write to <name>Calhoon</name> &amp;c &amp;c My Plan is for young Guthrie; <name>Beard</name>, <name>Tom Porter</name>, and myself to constitute the new P,, with some Boys; then there will be K,, Guthrie  <name>Foster</name>
               <name>Cloyd</name> &amp;c left in the old N. P, and the rest of us will make the new P,, as Tom Porter says he will move to the <name>Forked deer</name>, and so will I if god <unclear>we</unclear>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl347c.small.jpg"/> We had a very solemn, and harmonious Presbytery this spring; Times in the general <choice>
                  <orig>seam</orig>
                  <reg>seem</reg>
               </choice> dull in this country; O! that god would grant us repentance and <choice>
                  <orig>remision</orig>
                  <reg>remission</reg>
               </choice> of sins; our Pride and wickedness I have no doubt is one of the reasons why the old P,, are suffered to pour their venom upon us; I asked Lanear; if in faithfulness the Synod wrote that Pamphlet? why they did not do  it long ago? he says that they <choice>
                  <orig>beleaved</orig>
                  <reg>believed</reg>
               </choice> we would die a natural death, But now their fears are excited: This is a truth that the more sensible, and less honest of them would not have told.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole it is <choice>
                  <orig>reather</orig>
                  <reg>rather</reg>
               </choice> my opinion that there had better be something written, whether in the form of an answer to the Pamphlet, or a correct history of our church, the latter appears reather most to my mind;</p>
            <p>It appears more necessary because there are so many enquiring, at our Preachers and People about our origin if we refer them to <name>Buck</name>'s <choice>
                  <abbr>D</abbr>
                  <expan>Dictionary</expan>
               </choice>, they reply Buck has ceased to publish it: and from this late scorching poor Buck has got; &amp;c &amp;c Also I am clearly of opinion that it would be right for you to write, as you were better acquainted with facts &amp;c than any other man living or that ever will live; the last looks strong but I do believe it is <choice>
                  <orig>unequivically</orig>
                  <reg>unequivocally</reg>
               </choice> the truth.</p>
            <p>We are all well thank God for his mercies to our Family; Do my dear old Brother please to write me a long and closely written good religious letter.</p>
            <p>Give my love to all the brethren, <name>R Morrow</name> &amp; <name>Robert steel</name>s wife; let my connection know we are all well; <name>Stoneman</name>s Family particularly.</p>
            <p>Give Aunt Peggy and little Barnet a hug for me. My Wife and Libby joins in love to you and family.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wm Barnett</signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Finis Ewing</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl347d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Henderson Ky</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>June 20th 1823</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Rev</abbr>
                        <expan>Reverend</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name>Fines Ewing</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Boonville</name>
                     <name>Missouri State</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Rev Wm</abbr>
                     <expan>Reverend William</expan>
                  </choice> Barnett <lb/>
                  <lb/> June 4 1823 </add>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>PS,,</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> I have conversed with several of my <choice>
                     <orig>Breathren</orig>
                     <reg>Brethren</reg>
                  </choice> since I wrote the above all of whom are decidedly of opinion that <choice>
                     <orig>an</orig>
                     <reg>a</reg>
                  </choice> history ought to be written &amp; we are anxious you should write it and they think in it you could write what would be all sufficient, or better answer the P as though you answered it note <name>Bro,, Ingram</name> is looking for you to comply with the promise you made <unclear>him</unclear> , of writing to him, - <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>WB</abbr>
                     <expan>William Barnett</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
