<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl371">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1835 Oct. 26, Tallahassee, [Florida to] Andrew J[ackson] Donelson, Washington City, D.C.  / Gen[era]l D[aniel] S. Donelson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Donelson, Daniel S.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl371</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1835 Oct. 26, Tallahassee, [Florida to] Andrew J[ackson] Donelson, Washington City, D.C.  / Gen[era]l D[aniel] S. Donelson </title>
               <author>Donelson, Daniel S.</author>
               <date when="1835-10-26">October 26, 1835</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated October 26, 1835, to Andrew Jackson Donelson in Washington, D.C. from his brother Daniel S. Donelson in Tallahassee, Florida.  Daniel writes urgently to report that he was accosted about a political scandal involving Andrew and two men by the names of Bell and Barrow.  Daniel fears that his brother's image is being tarnished in order to reflect negatively on the President, their uncle Andrew Jackson.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bettie M. Donelson</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> III-E-2-3 b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl371</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>Donelson, Andrew Jackson 1799-1871</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Political scandals</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Donelson, Daniel S.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl371a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Tallahassee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Octr</abbr>
                     <expan>October</expan>
                  </choice> 26th 1835</date>
               <salute>My Dear Brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Meeting with <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Butler</name> in the streets of Tallahassee today, he accosted me thus, when did you hear from your Brother?  my reply was, some days ago- I saw from his manner that he had something which he considered important to communicate, pausing but for a moment he expressed himself thus: I fear your Brother will in the course of the winter be engaged in an unpleasant affair.  With whom Bell, was my reply?  no.  Barrow-he then proceeded to say that you had gotten a friend in <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Ten.</abbr>
                     <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> to call on <name>Mr. Barrow</name>  to know when he would be out of the limits of the State of Ten. and as a reason for the enquiry the laws of the State; he stated that he understood to what allusion was made, and that he would or expected to spend a month or <pb n="2" facs="sl371b.small.jpg"/> two in <del type="overstrike">in</del> Washington this winter. Col. Butler also mentioned that <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Gen.</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Jackson</name> knew nothing of what was transpiring, and that you wished the whole affair should be kept from him until it was <add>settled</add> upon the field this was the idea.  Mr. Butler, stated that he got his information from a very confidential source therefore could not mention the author's name.  Now Andrew if there be any truth in all this I feel not a little mortified that you should have kept it so profoundly secret from me I am your Brother and as such I now demand <add>it</add> as a right to know how you stand in relation to this matter- give me a detailed account of the whole, and if there be anything like a fair prospect for a meeting such as I have described, of course I will be with you.  When I left Ten. I resolved in my own mind to have  as little to do with the political world as pos- <pb n="3" facs="sl371c.small.jpg"/> sible, this determination up to this time I have complied with, as my letters to you and others will show- not long since I was informed by a friend in Tallahassee of the charges <add>which</add> were pressed against you by the <name>Nashville</name> papers and of the bitterness with which you were assailed- <del/> I forthwith made an examination into the matter and at once saw the dastardly design in view, that of effecting the President through to you- I believed then and do still believe that <name>John Bell</name>, a man then whom there is none <add>more</add>
               <unclear>base</unclear>, was the prime mover and manager in the plot- and here I take the liberty of suggesting that he, Bell, is the man <add>who</add> should be punished, Barrow is an Editor whose avocation it is to lie and misrepresent, therefore nothing can be gained by having an affair with him suffer him then, if you are not too far committed, to pass, and strike at the fountain head- if it can be so arranged suffer <pb n="4" facs="sl371d.small.jpg"/> me to take your place in regard to Barrow on the consideration that you must attend to Bell- these are suggestions for your consideration.  Let me hear how you <unclear>forthwith</unclear>
               <gap/>  on the reception of this- you can imagine my anxiety of mind.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl. D.</abbr>
                     <expan>General Daniel</expan>
                  </choice> S Donelson</signed>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>ansd.</abbr>
                     <expan>answered</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <date>7 <choice>
                        <abbr>Nov.</abbr>
                        <expan>November</expan>
                     </choice> 1833</date>-</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Andrew <choice>
                           <abbr>J.</abbr>
                           <expan>Jackson</expan>
                        </choice> Donelson </name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Esq.</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Washington City</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>D. C.</abbr>
                        <expan>District of Columbia</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>postmark: Tallahassee, Florida</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <add>I am making my arrangement to leave here for <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Mis.</abbr>
                        <expan>MIssissippi</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>  as soon as my crop is gathered my white family will I expect set out next month for Ten.- the <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>S.</abbr>
                        <expan>South</expan>
                     </choice> Carolina</name>  Negroes will go directly to Mis.</add>
            </closer>
            <closer>
               <add>My love to Sister Emily and the children.  Remember me kindly to the Genl.</add>
               <salute>your affectionate Brother</salute>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Dan.</abbr>
                     <expan>Daniel</expan>
                  </choice> S. Donelson</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
