<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um077">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1841 June 1, Columbia Female Institute [to] Mrs Elizabeth Chester,  Jackson, Tennessee /  Mary Jane Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um077</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50316551</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1841 June 1, Columbia Female Institute [to] Mrs Elizabeth Chester,  Jackson, Tennessee /  Mary Jane Chester</title>
               <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
               <date when="1841-06-01">June 1, 1841</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a letter dated June 1, 1841, from Mary Jane Chester to her mother Elizabeth Chester.  Mary Jane writes about her upcoming examination and her hopes that many members of her family will come to Columbia to attend the examination.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers MS-25 (May/Jun 1841)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">9</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um077</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Mary Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um077a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia</name> Female Institute</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1841-06-01">June 1st 1841</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear Mama</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>O! I was so much delighted to receive your very affectionate letter, and also my dear Father's.  You do not know how much distressed I was to hear that he had so severe an attack.  Mama you know when you are at so great a distance as I am from the only Persons on earth you love, that when you hear that they are Sick, you generally imagine that they are worse than they in reality are.  I am precisely that way, now I have imagined that is still very Sick although your letter assured me that he was nearly well.  I do not <choice>
                  <orig>disbeleive</orig>
                  <reg>dibelieve</reg>
               </choice> your word, nor would I do it for the whole world, but I am <choice>
                  <orig>affraid</orig>
                  <reg>afraid</reg>
               </choice> that he has had a relapse since then.</p>
            <p>You desired me to tell you the Uniform of the Institute at the Examination: We are not permitted to wear any thing but white, no Embroidery, no <choice>
                  <orig>coloured</orig>
                  <reg>colored</reg>
               </choice> Ribbon but blue, no Jewelry excepting a <emph>Plain</emph> Breast Pin, and if we break any of these rules, <name type="person">Mr or Mrs Smith</name> will say to the Audience that such things were positively forbidden to be worn and she will then point out the young lady who has broken them.  I showed Mrs Smith <pb n="2" facs="um077b.small.jpg"/> the part of your letter that you requested me to show her; She says that the white dress that I am having made now with the addition of the two that I brought with me will be a sufficient number for the Examination and Concert, I expect that I shall play the Russian Dance with Variations.  I think that it is a very pretty <choice>
                  <orig>peice</orig>
                  <reg>piece</reg>
               </choice>, and Mrs Smith thinks that I play it very well.  As my Books are waiting patiently for me to attend to them I must close my letter, I could say a great ⁁ <add place="supralinear">deal</add> more but time will not permit.  Give my love to all my dear Aunts Uncles and Cousins, all my Brothers &amp; sister, and to my dear <emph>dear</emph> Papa</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your ever <choice>
                     <abbr>affectiont</abbr>
                     <expan>affectionate</expan>
                  </choice> Daughter</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Mary Jane Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mrs Elizabeth Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="bottom">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P. S.</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> Mr &amp; Mrs Smith request me to give their Respects to you and Papa and tell you that must be sure to come up to the Examination.  I need not say how much I want ⁁ <add place="supralinear">you</add> to come.  Tell <name type="person">Aunt Narcissa</name> &amp; Sis, and brother <name type="person">John</name>  that I expect we will have a very pleasant trip, but I am <choice>
                     <orig>affraid</orig>
                     <reg>afraid</reg>
                  </choice> that I shall be so anxious to get home that I cannot take time to travel that far.</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="um077c.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="left of address">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>postmark for June 1</figDesc>
                  </figure> 18</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mrs Elizabeth Chester</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left of address">Mail }</add>
               <add place="below address" rend="different hand, ink">
                  <date when="1841-06-01">1st June 1841</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
