<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um050">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1847 Nov. 30, Memphis [to] Edward E Porter, Bridg[e]port, Con[necticut]  /   E. H. Porter: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Porter, E. H.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um050</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50286765</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1847 Nov. 30, Memphis [to] Edward E Porter, Bridg[e]port, Con[necticut]  /   E. H. Porter</title>
               <author>Porter, E. H.</author>
               <date when="1847-11-30">November 30, 1847</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a letter, dated November 30, 1847, from E. H. Porter in Memphis to his son Edward E. Porter in Bridgeport, Connecticut. In the letter, the elder Porter discusses financial matters with his son and encourages him to maintain his commitment to quit smoking.   </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Porter-Rice Family Letters MS-154 (letters 1846-1849)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um050</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Finance, Personal</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Porter, E. H.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um050a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Memphis</name>
                     <date when="1847-11-30">30th <choice>
                           <abbr>Nov</abbr>
                           <expan>November</expan>
                        </choice> 1847</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Edward—</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>We have been much pleased in <choice>
                  <orig>Recieving</orig>
                  <reg>Receiving</reg>
               </choice> Letters from you so frequently and have to regret that our Letters to you have not been more numerous, I wrote the day after we reached Home &amp; <name type="person">Benjamin</name> the week following and the next week I should have written so that you would have got a Letter from one of us every week my Business on my <choice>
                  <orig>arival</orig>
                  <reg>arrival</reg>
               </choice> was so pressing that I neglected to write one week longer than I should but my purpose is to give you 2 letters a month from this forward — We <choice>
                  <abbr>recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> a Letter from <name type="person">Mary</name> last <choice>
                  <orig>Saterday</orig>
                  <reg>Saturday</reg>
               </choice> at the same time yours of the 15th came to hand  She said she had <choice>
                  <abbr>recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> a Letter from you a few days before.  She was well and well pleased with her Home &amp; School.  It affords us <choice>
                  <orig>Hapiness</orig>
                  <reg>Happiness</reg>
               </choice> that you are both so well pleased and have so good an <choice>
                  <orig>oportunity</orig>
                  <reg>opportunity</reg>
               </choice> for Improving your minds and fitting yourselves for future <choice>
                  <orig>usfulness</orig>
                  <reg>usefulness</reg>
               </choice>.— In your Letter you Mention <choice>
                  <orig>recieving</orig>
                  <reg>receiving</reg>
               </choice> a Protest for Non payment of <name type="person">Mr Hinds</name> Acceptance for 100$ It gives me no further trouble than that <name type="person">Mr Jones</name> should be delayed the <choice>
                  <abbr>paymt</abbr>
                  <expan>payment</expan>
               </choice> due him for a few days believing as I do that there must have been some Mistake in the acceptance having been presented to Mr Hinds in Person for I <choice>
                  <orig>remited</orig>
                  <reg>remitted</reg>
               </choice> to him the amount on my <choice>
                  <orig>arival</orig>
                  <reg>arrival</reg>
               </choice> Home and whether He had <choice>
                  <orig>recieved</orig>
                  <reg>received</reg>
               </choice> it or not He would have <choice>
                  <orig>payed</orig>
                  <reg>paid</reg>
               </choice> the <choice>
                  <abbr>amt</abbr>
                  <expan>amount</expan>
               </choice> on Presentation.  I feel confident the money is Paid before this.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="um050b.small.jpg"/>
            <p>While I am on the Subject of <choice>
                  <orig>mony</orig>
                  <reg>money</reg>
               </choice> I will say that the prospect of my Ever getting any thing of the Farmer &amp; merchant Bank on their Protested Check of 600$ is every day becoming worse &amp; the amount of 250$ <name type="person">Mr Starr</name>
               <choice>
                  <orig>remited</orig>
                  <reg>remitted</reg>
               </choice>  to me in <name type="place">Connecticut</name> has never been returned here or even heard from, What can have become of the Letter is a <choice>
                  <orig>Mistery</orig>
                  <reg>Mystery</reg>
               </choice>.</p>
            <p>The low price of Cotton (it <choice>
                  <orig>haven</orig>
                  <reg>having</reg>
               </choice> fallen one half in six weeks) makes business very dull Here, and money very Hard to be obtained.  There has been no failures among our Merchants as yet, and Houses continue to Rent, <name type="person">Mr Mead</name> Retains the Store He had last year— so does <name type="person">Mr Lamb</name>. The New store built this <choice>
                  <orig>Sumer</orig>
                  <reg>Summer</reg>
               </choice> is finished and <name type="person">Mr Hinkle</name> is moving into it today The Foundry is <choice>
                  <orig>caried</orig>
                  <reg>carried</reg>
               </choice> on as it was last year — “That little piece of Humanity,” as you call her in the Letter before the last <choice>
                  <abbr>recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice>, and which was entirely neglected to be mentioned in your last is growing finely, is very <emph>Healthy</emph> &amp; very <emph>Handsome</emph>, I wonder how you could have forgotten Her, She lets no one forget where she is but claims much attention.  Your Mother has hardly left the House Except on <choice>
                  <orig>sabaths sinc</orig>
                  <reg>sabbaths since</reg>
               </choice>  we reached Home.</p>
            <p>The Same Day of the Month was set apart as a day of Thanksgiving &amp; Prayer in this state as in <name type="place">Connecticut</name>
               <name type="person">Mr Coons</name> gave us an <name> 
                  <reg>Excellent</reg> Excelent</name> discourse from the 1 <choice>
                  <abbr>V</abbr>
                  <expan>Verse</expan>
               </choice> of the 118 Psalm I think it one of his best efforts we have solicited a Copy for Publication if He consents I will send you one when Printed</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="um050c.small.jpg"/>
            <p>Yourself &amp; Sister were missed from our Thanksgiving Dinner, but our <choice>
                  <orig>Harts</orig>
                  <reg>Hearts</reg>
               </choice> were filled with Adoration and Thankfulness for the Evidence we have for believing that although <choice>
                  <orig>seperated</orig>
                  <reg>separated</reg>
               </choice> by space our <choice>
                  <orig>Harts</orig>
                  <reg>Hearts</reg>
               </choice> were united in sincere Thanksgiving to <choice>
                  <orig>Almity</orig>
                  <reg>Almighty</reg>
               </choice> God for his many Blessing the past year to us as a <choice>
                  <orig>Famely</orig>
                  <reg>Family</reg>
               </choice>, In sustaining through Dangers seen &amp; unseen.. <choice>
                  <orig>Temperal</orig>
                  <reg>Temporal</reg>
               </choice>, &amp; Spiritual, In giving <emph>us</emph> another Child, <emph>you</emph> another Sister, In having guided us in the selection of Places for your future Instruction which if Properly improved, will fit you both for Exerting <del type="overstrike">an</del> Influences for good which will not end with time but reach far on in Eternity.</p>
            <p>We were truly glad to <choice>
                  <orig>heare</orig>
                  <reg>hear</reg>
               </choice> of your determination to Leave of smoking — I pray God to Sustain you in this Resolution, and More Especially are we <choice>
                  <orig>anxous</orig>
                  <reg>anxious</reg>
               </choice> Since by your acknowledgment you had become so much under the Influence of <choice>
                  <orig>Tobaco</orig>
                  <reg>Tobacco</reg>
               </choice>, as to effect your nerves, your <choice>
                  <orig>Apetite</orig>
                  <reg>Appetite</reg>
               </choice> and your spirits, As you Value your own Health, Your and Our <choice>
                  <orig>Hapiness</orig>
                  <reg>Happiness</reg>
               </choice>, never <orig resp="#break">breake</orig> the Pledge you have signed against Smoking — <emph>never, never</emph>, — As to a Guardian I am at a loss to know who to appoint not knowing the <choice>
                  <sic>The</sic>
                  <corr>the</corr>
               </choice> special duties devolving on that Office, I had thought of appointing your <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Unkle</orig>
                     <reg>Uncle</reg>
                  </choice> Bradley</name> as He is Most frequently in <choice>
                  <orig>Bridgport</orig>
                  <reg>Bridgeport</reg>
               </choice> But your Mother <choice>
                  <orig>Sugests</orig>
                  <reg>Suggests</reg>
               </choice> that <name type="person">Miss Julia</name> be charged with that most important Office. And as to Monthly Pocket Money, I now send you $5.00 &amp; you &amp; Mr Jones must fix the monthly allowance and if there is an Arbiter Necessary Call in Miss Julia, &amp; when you write let me know the <choice>
                  <abbr>amt</abbr>
                  <expan>amount</expan>
               </choice> concluded on.  I think the  <choice>
                  <abbr>amt</abbr>
                  <expan>amount</expan>
               </choice> Should not Exceed 2$</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="um050d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>I have not written to your <name type="person">Uncle &amp; Aunt Scoville</name>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Scince recieving</orig>
                  <reg>Since receiving</reg>
               </choice> the sad news of Little <name type="person">Henrys</name> Death I shall write tomorrow if Possible —</p>
            <p>Your Mother Joins me in kind Regards to Mr. Mrs Jones &amp; Daughter &amp; Love for yourself.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>E. H.</abbr>
                        <expan>Ethel Henry</expan>
                     </choice> Porter</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Edward E Porter</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <orig>Bridgport</orig>
                           <reg>Bridgeport</reg>
                        </choice>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Con</abbr>
                           <expan>Connecticut</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>care of <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Revd</abbr>
                           <expan>Reverend</expan>
                        </choice> H Jones</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Within is your Letter from this Church.  Join <choice>
                     <orig>Imediately</orig>
                     <reg>Immediately</reg>
                  </choice> Some Church in <choice>
                     <orig>Bridgport</orig>
                     <reg>Bridgeport</reg>
                  </choice> where you will Have a Home, your Friends here are all well, The young Converts appear to be doing well those who have Joined our Church especially — Give our Love to <name type="person">Harriet Bradly</name> give her Many direction and ask her to write —</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
