<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl448">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter]   1806 Aug. 18, Natchez, Mississippi [to] Humane Society for Abolition of Slavery, Richmond, Virginia / Seth Lewis: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Lewis, Seth</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl448</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter]   1806 Aug. 18, Natchez, Mississippi [to] Humane Society for Abolition of Slavery, Richmond, Virginia / Seth Lewis</title>
               <author>Lewis, Seth</author>
               <date when="1806-08-18">August 18, 1806</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated August 18, 1806 from Seth Lewis, writing from Natchez, Mississippi to the Humane Society for the Abolition of Slavery in Richmond, Virginia.  Lewis is acting on behalf  of a family of slaves as their legal counsel.  In the letter, he asks the members of the society for assistance as he prepares and argues the  case for the freedom of fourteen individuals unjustly held in the bond slavery.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Hardeman Family Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">Correspondence</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">10</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl448</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Slavery</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no94034142"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Lewis, Seth, 1764-1848</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl448a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Natchez</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>18th august 1806</date> To the humane Society for the abolition of Slavery <salute>Gentlemen</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Having been engaged as Counsel in prosecuting a Suit to recover the freedom of a family of people of <choice>
                  <orig>colour</orig>
                  <reg>color</reg>
               </choice> whose case in our opinion calls aloud for assistance we take the liberty, though not personally known to you, of addressing you on the occasion and requesting your friendly aid in the cause we have undertaken </p>
            <p>Our friend <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice>
               <name>Peter Hardeman</name> is the bearer of this and also of Commission to take the Depositions of same Witnesses in your Country, and by assisting him <choice>
                  <orig>withe</orig>
                  <reg>with</reg>
               </choice> business <add>you</add> will be relieving the injured &amp; oppressed and may essentially contribute to the restoring to freedom of no less than fourteen human beings whom we <choice>
                  <orig>verely</orig>
                  <reg>verily</reg>
               </choice> believe to be unjustly held in Slavery Their story is shortly this        They are part of the <choice>
                  <orig>decendants</orig>
                  <reg>descendants</reg>
               </choice> of an Indian Woman named Judith, formerly in the possession of one <name>Francis Coleman</name> of <name>Virginia</name>.  Old Sue the mother &amp; grand mother of those now here <pb n="2" facs="sl448b.small.jpg"/> in the year 1786 brought her suit in the District Court of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Petersburgh</orig>
                     <reg>Petersburg</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> against <name>Buddy Coleman</name>, otherwise called <name>Cuthbert Coleman</name>, who then held her as a slave to recover her freedom, which she finally recovered in the 1797 in the general Court at <name>Richmond</name>, to which Court the cause had been removed.  But whilst that suit was pending coleman as we are assured run them (ie old Sue and her children,) off to <name>South Carolina</name>, where he kept them several years, and then removed them to <name>georgia</name>; where suit was again brought against him by Sue and her children for their freedom; but that suit having abated by the Defendant being misnamed in the writ, he immediately sent them off to this Country, where they now are On their <choice>
                  <orig>arival</orig>
                  <reg>arrival</reg>
               </choice> they applied to us, and we have found their story confirmed by letters of gentlemen to whom we wrote for information, and by the record of Sues recovery of her freedom.  For further particulars we refer to Mr Hardeman and the papers in his hands What we chiefly want is proof of the identity of their persons, and in this we flatter ourselves you may give us some useful information__ In fine <pb n="3" facs="sl448c.small.jpg"/> we are convinced that those unfortunate persons are fairly and legally entitled to be free, and we feel confident that you will readily give us your assistance in freeing them from the shackles of an unjust and cruel slavery__ </p>
            <p>We are gentlemen respectfully</p>
            <closer>Your <choice>
                  <abbr>Obed</abbr>
                  <expan>Obedient</expan>
               </choice>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Servts</abbr>
                  <expan>Servants</expan>
               </choice>
               <signed>Seth Lewis</signed>
               <lb/>
               <unclear>J Druelope</unclear>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl448d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>The President &amp; Members of <lb/> The humane Society for the <lb/> abolition of Slavery <lb/> Richmond Virginia</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
