<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl446">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1815 Jan. 27 [to] Peter Hardeman, New Orleans, Louisiana / John Hardeman   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Hardeman, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl446</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title/>
               <author>Hardeman, John</author>
               <date when="1815-01-27">January 27, 1815</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter from John Hardeman of Tennessee to his brother Peter in New Orleans. John writes of their various business ventures that he is tending to while Peter serves in the military.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Hardemen Family Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl446</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Business enterprises</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Louisiana</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Hardeman, John</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl446a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Crabstick</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>27th January 1815</date>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                     <expan>Dear</expan>
                  </choice>. Brother </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Yesterday I received your letter of the 11th instant.  The news which it contained I had heard but a little time before, <choice>
                  <orig>tho</orig>
                  <reg>though</reg>
               </choice> I had anticipated some good news <gap agent="damage"/> for I actually heard the detail, as the day before I heard such at this place, the sound of cannon fired in <choice>
                  <orig>rejocing</orig>
                  <reg>rejoicing</reg>
               </choice> at <name>Nashville</name>__  The capture of our Brothers was new  to me and to all of your guards men, but I can say they had much same hear they were prisoners than that they had been killed in battle, as in the former case tis hoped a speedy exchange will be affected; and the <choice>
                  <orig>lattre</orig>
                  <reg>latter</reg>
               </choice> is only preferable   to perpetual slavery   May I be damned if I had not rather die then become a subject to the King of Great Britain, and I will do it before such a circumstance can take place <unclear>again</unclear> business I have incurred little as <gap agent="damage"/> been <gap agent="damage"/> &amp; ability would find__ you money I have not been able to <unclear>collect of Crofton as Wilkerson</unclear> not yet returned__ Crofton Newman borrowed <unclear>30 Dollars opad me for you</unclear> Your pork I have salted up often paying <unclear>Powers</unclear> 10__ Peter 2 &amp; I myself end up making $19 in pork the balance I collect for you about 14 hundred <unclear>weight</unclear>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl446b.small.jpg"/> your shoats were very small some not weighing more than 30 pounds    Susan wasted money to purchase pork I wrote to her to use my money <unclear>all from her Mother &amp; Hrny</unclear> I have not heard from her since which time  was about Christmas I will close this read by observing your business in this state and give you no uneasiness all is well and shall be so if I can make it</p>
            <p>As I had not heard from you since your departure from <name>Nashville</name> until by this last mail, I two or three posts ago wrote to <name>General Coffee</name> to you on <unclear>confirmation</unclear>  of you &amp; <unclear>
                  <name>Tom Ogleman</name>
               </unclear>, perceiving your time was devoted entirely to arms, as the enemy was in sight, and hourly skirmishes with you</p>
            <p>Should you see Mr. Lewis during your stay in that country try and settle my business with him as <gap agent="damage"/> cannot find it convenient to pay_ one has note in favor of N.P.H. for the 200 dollars, he having the interest in it for I was not to appropriate to my use any of the earnings of our joint labors in trade, and I know he is more necessitous than I am <pb n="3" facs="sl446c.small.jpg"/> Let me hear from you as often as convenient though I should not write to you_ Your news will be interesting there is some here &amp; my silence may open you all such as soon as any thing turns out of the ordinary way I shall advise you of it Try and remember what handsome flower seeds you can bring up, and whatever else you may judge I want as a curiosity for my garden</p>
            <salute>Your Brother</salute>
            <signed>
               <name>John Hardeman</name>
               <add>
                  <note>
                     <name>Peter Hardeman</name>
                     <p>by God you will have hard work to read this_ I asked if <unclear>Mrs. Sutter and opelent out of sunday</unclear>
                     </p>
                     <p>Bailey is with me</p>
                     <p>You can see I have named my plantation Crabstick <pb n="4" facs="sl446d.small.jpg"/>
                        <unclear>Frauleline Sis</unclear>
                        <date>
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Jany</abbr>
                              <expan>January</expan>
                           </choice> 31815</date> 25<address>
                           <addrLine>Leuit. <name>Peter Hardeman</name>
                              <lb/> New Orleans</addrLine>
                        </address>
                     </p> mail}</note>
               </add>
            </signed>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
