<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl427">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1846 Feb. 20, Carthage, Tennessee [to] Mr. [and] Mrs. Mc Nabb, Canada / Adam Fergusson   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Fergusson, A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl427</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1846 Feb. 20, Carthage, Tennessee [to] Mr. [and] Mrs. Mc Nabb, Canada / Adam Fergusson</title>
               <author>Fergusson, A.</author>
               <date when="1846-02-20">February 20, 1846</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Adam Fergusson to Mr. and Mrs. Mc Nabb, dated February 20, 1846. Fergusson is writing because he has not heard from the Mc Nabbs in a while. Fergusson gives a glowing report of current economic conditions, owing them to James K. Polk's administration. He writes about seeing their son, Dugald C. and his uncle on their trip. Fergusson reports helping them  financially on their promise of reimbursement. He writes that he has still not received any news or money from them. Fergusson asks Mc Nabb to repay him, and to reply to the letter immediately.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">IV-G-1, B6</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl427</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Politics, society, and economy</term>
               <term>Debts.</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Fergusson, Adam</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl427a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Carthage</name>
                     <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>20 <del>17</del> th february 1846</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>It has been a long time since I heard from you and <name>Mrs McNabb</name> and I hope in breaking silence I shall not be considered intruding myself on your happiness and retirement. I have not heard from cousin Robert since he left and I have <choice>
                  <orig>recived</orig>
                  <reg>received</reg>
               </choice> but one short letter from your son <name>Dugald C McNabb</name> since he in company with his uncle Robert bid us farewell to return shortly. That letter was written last April or thereabouts and stated in a few words that he had arranged his business to his satisfaction and would start shortly for our country since when I have not heard from him or any of you I now Inform you that our family has enjoyed tolerable <add>good</add> health also all my Brothers families and sisters are well when last heard of. Our country seems to be in a prosperous condition trade and every employment seems to have greatly revived under <name>Mr Polk</name>s administration and our country is advancing rapidly in bettering the condition of all classes During the stay of your son and his uncle I had at their request advanced several sums of money which they greatly needed particularly in paying their passage here your son had to pledge his watch which I redeemed for him at <name>Nashville</name> and Robert had to draw on me from the time he landed at <name>Philadelphia</name> until I met him at Nashville and his delay on the route cost double as much as the expences usually <pb n="2" facs="sl427b.small.jpg"/> amounts  to for a single person travelling and during their <choice>
                  <orig>soujourn</orig>
                  <reg>sojourn</reg>
               </choice> here I had to furnish several sums as well as enough to carry them back to you this I done freely as without my assistance they could not obtain the means in this country and it was expressly understood between us that Dugald C was to return and pay me as he and Robert both represented that he had a large amount left him as well as other means to repay me Thus it was agreed and further as Robert had no means but his land which he expected to get Dugal C was to pay the amount of money advanced to him and make himself whole again out of his land for which they executed to me their Joint Obligation for $286..72 ½ all this was money advanced to them. I told them that I had use for all the money I could raise and was deeply in debt and of  course I had to borrow the money out of Bank. Owing to this I had no other expectation than getting back the money before  the same fell due in Bank; but to my great <choice>
                  <orig>desapointment</orig>
                  <reg>disappoinment</reg>
               </choice> I have had to pay it long Since and no word when I am to be remunerated. I have wrote <unclear>twice</unclear> to your Son in the most pressing manner but can get no answer and this is the reason I make known to you the facts and I respectfully ask of you that you inform him of his neglect and I hope you will use your influence with him to do me Justice. my much respected had deeply impressed me with the high <add>and <choice>
                     <orig>Honourable</orig>
                     <reg>Honorable</reg>
                  </choice>
               </add> Character of the family She Sprung from their high minded and Honourable feelings their Sacred regard for truth and Justice and above all in redeeming their Just obligations. consequently <pb n="3" facs="sl427c.small.jpg"/> when I saw any of their descendants my house was free &amp; open to their reception and they made sensible that they were with their real friends and when they wanted money I had no hesitation in lending it to them on their word and honor to repay me now I am convinced that this relation of their conduct is unpleasant to you to hear but I assure you it is more unpleasant for me to make it known but sir necessity <choice>
                  <orig>compells</orig>
                  <reg>compels</reg>
               </choice> me and I hope you will use your best exertions to have the money sent to me even if you see proper to advance it to him on account that he is your son and that he can repay  you or further you can easily retain that much out the portion you allow him I want you or Mrs McNabb to answer this letter <choice>
                  <orig>imediately</orig>
                  <reg>immediately</reg>
               </choice> and let me know how you all are and let me know the <unclear>what</unclear> Robert <add>and</add> your son are doing and all other enquiring friends I have now come so close to end of my paper that I have no room to give you any further particulars from our parts or even to say anything about the relations between the <name>United States</name> and <name>Great Britain</name> But I hope you will write to me very fully on all matters and let my know whether any of you are going to move to <name>missouri</name> or <name>Oregon</name> I wish you also to write me all about our friends in <name>Scotland</name> the winter here <unclear>commenced</unclear>
               <choice>
                  <orig>verry</orig>
                  <reg>very</reg>
               </choice> cold but turned mild after the christmas Holidays and has continued mild and warm ever since <name>Mrs Fergusson</name> Joins <choice>
                  <orig>withe</orig>
                  <reg>with</reg>
               </choice> me in our best wishes for your Health &amp; welfare</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Respectfully <lb/> yours truly</salute>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>A.</abbr>
                     <expan>Adam</expan>
                  </choice> Fergusson</signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Mr &amp; Mrs McNabb</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Canada</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
