<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl706">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Bond] 1807 Mar. 13, Camden County, Georgia [to] State / Eli Whitney : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Whitney, Eli</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl706</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Bond] 1807 Mar. 13, Camden County, Georgia [to] State / Eli Whitney</title>
               <author> Whitney, Eli</author>
               <date when="1807-03-13">March 13, 1807</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a bond dated march 13, 1807 in the amount of ten-thousand dollars.  Its purpose is for entitling the state of Tennessee to purchase the Patent Right of Eli Whitney's and Phineas Miller's Saw Gin.  The bond also outlines the conditions of the obligation.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor John Sevier Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">10</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl706</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Sevier, John, 1745-1815</term>
               <term>Cotton gins and ginning</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50020366"
                        role="Associated name http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/asn">Whitney, Eli, 1765-1825</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl706a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Georgia Camden County</addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>Know all Men by these presents that <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice>
               <name>Eli Whitney</name> &amp; <name>Catharine Miller</name> Executors of <name>Phineas Miller</name> decease are held &amp; firmly bound unto His Excellency <name>John Sevier</name> Governor of the State of <name>Tennessee</name> and his successor in office in the sum of Ten Thousand Dollars, to be paid to the said John Sevier or to his Successors in office.  To which payment well and truly to be made.  We bind ourselves of each of us, our and each of our Heirs Executors &amp; Administrators firmly by these presents signed with our hands &amp; sealed with our Seals__  Dated this <date>13th day of March 1807</date>__</p>
            <p>Whereas by an Act passed at <name>Knoxville</name> on the <date>22nd day of October 1803</date> Entitled an act to purchase for the State of Tennessee the Patent Right of Eli Whitney &amp; Phineas Miller of a Machine or new invention for cleaning of Cotton, commonly called the Saw Gin__ </p>
            <p>Now the condition of this obligation is <pb n="2" facs="sl706b.small.jpg"/> such that if it should hereafter appear that the said Miller of Whitney had not at the time of passing the said Act, and as the time of assigning the said Patent Right to the said State of Tennessee the sole of &amp; exclusive right of making using &amp; vending the said Saw Gin within the State of Tennessee or that any other person had a better right thereto, and that if then in that case of its being made <add>so</add>  to appear the said Miller &amp; Whitney or their representatives shall refund any &amp; all monies they may have received from the State of Tennessee by virtue of said Act, then this obligation to be voice, otherwise to remain in full force__</p>
            <closer>
               <add>Signed Sealed in presence of <name>Ray Sands</name>
                  <name>Russell Goodrich</name>
                  <name>Catherine Miller</name>
               </add>
               <signed>
                  <name>Eli Whitney</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl706c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Whitney &amp; Millers Bond To Tennessee $10,000.00 Recorded</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
