<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl490">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1823 Apr. 20, Cragfont, Tennessee [to] J[ohn] Overton, Nashville, Tennessee / J[ames] Winchester: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Winchester, J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl490</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1823 Apr. 20, Cragfont, Tennessee [to] J[ohn] Overton, Nashville, Tennessee / J[ames] Winchester</title>
               <author>Winchester, J.</author>
               <date when="1823-04-20">April 20, 1823</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from General James Winchester to the Honorable John Overton, April 20, 1823. Winchester is writing to discuss the court situation in Memphis. They, along with Andrew Jackson, are the founders of Memphis. Winchester lists the ways to establish a court in Tennessee. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">James Winchester Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl490</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Winchester, James, 1752-1826 Correspondence.</term>
               <term>Courts</term>
               <term>Overton, John, 1766-1833</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n96115844"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Winchester, James, 1752-1826</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl490a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Cragfont</name>
                     <date>20th April 1823</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear <unclear>Jno</unclear>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have had the pleasure to receive your <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice> dated at <name>Nashville</name> the 13th instant I know very well that it is important to the prosperity of <name>Memphis</name> that the courts should be kept there, I believe too that <choice>
                  <orig>powerfull</orig>
                  <reg>powerful</reg>
               </choice> exertions  are in <unclear>embraced</unclear> to remove them and the propriety and policy of counter acting such exertions and that we must <add>not</add> hesitate at a little expense and trouble to nourish, encourage, and protect our little establishment. You know there is three ways of locating sites for Court houses the first directly by act of the General assembly, the second by Commissioners, and the third by a vote of the people of the county, Now behelst on the spot it will be well for you to ascertain which of them ways the opposition are aiming at, in order to be the better able to frustrate their plans But I still think when they come to fix on a site to rally round in opposition to Memphis, that they well find it a <choice>
                  <orig>dificult</orig>
                  <reg>difficult</reg>
               </choice> point to agree upon and that many of their forces will desert their cause, <name>Big Creek</name> and the center I expect will be in nomination but surely  one but the north west corner of the county will stick to Big Creek the center in my opinion will be found to be the most formidable point to be dreaded by the friends of M_. here all you <choice>
                  <sic>skill  skill</sic>
                  <corr>skill</corr>
               </choice> and persevering industry will <add>be</add> in requisition excited by interest the most powerfull stimulant on earth</p>
            <p>I have communicated to <name>George Roberts</name> your advice on the subject of his suit with Ring. I will attend at <name>Lebanon</name> on sunday proceeding the Court in order to get a continuance of the <name>Searcy</name> &amp; <name>Eaton</name> suit, but I fear it has been so  long hung up in Court, If Seareys counsel presses for a trial that it cannot be effected, and no one understands this case half as well as you do, I wish most sincerely it had been tried at last fall term, even without Smiths testimony rather than at the ensuing term in your absence as counsel. all that can be done <del type="overstrike">however</del> in my power, shall be done, to procure a continuance</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am Dear Sir <lb/> Very respectfully <lb/> Your <choice>
                     <abbr>obt</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient</expan>
                  </choice> servant</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>J</abbr>
                        <expan>John</expan>
                     </choice> Winchester</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Judge <name>John Overton</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl490c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Cairo</name>
                     <date>29th</date>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>April 1823</date>  }</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Forwarded</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Judge John Overton</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <del type="overstrike">Memphis</del>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>State of <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Winchester <lb/> 20th <choice>
                     <abbr>Apl</abbr>
                     <expan>April</expan>
                  </choice> 1823</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
