<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mp009">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1826 Apr. 14 Jackson [Tennessee], [to] Rhea &amp; McCrabb / Charles Barth : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Barth, Charles</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>mp009</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50335703</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Memphis Public Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Memphis Public Library, 3030 Poplar Avenue, Memphis, TN 38111</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1826 Apr. 14 Jackson [Tennessee], [to] Rhea &amp; McCrabb / Charles Barth</title>
               <author>Barth, Charles</author>
               <date when="1826-04-14">April 14, 1826</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written from Charles Barth to fellow merchants Rhea &amp; McCrabb on April 14, 1826. In the letter, Barth discusses business practices and prospects are to be found for merchants in Jackson, Tennessee. Barth states that business prospects are good in Jackson, but that goods and rent are expensive, due mostly to the influx of wealthy citizens into the area.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Historical Genealogical Documents</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">9</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mp009</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Business enterprises</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Barth, Charles L.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mp009a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson</name>
                     <date when="1826-04-14">April 14th 1826</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear friends!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Since my Last of the 31st <choice>
                  <abbr>inst</abbr>
                  <expan>instant</expan>
               </choice>, I am  in <choice>
                  <orig>possision</orig>
                  <reg>possession</reg>
               </choice> of your <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice> of the <date when="--03-23">23 of March.</date>
            </p>
            <p>In reply of your questions about business in general here, I reply, that I think there is great &amp; good prospects, for men of <emph>Capital</emph> in this place as well as in the surrounding country.</p>
            <p>At this time there are Seven Stores in Jackson, they are all doing a good <choice>
                  <orig>buseniss</orig>
                  <reg>business</reg>
               </choice>, beside <name type="place">Madison County</name> (our county) which is settled mostly by wealthy people, there are from three to four Counties more, who do their trading in this Place — Jackson has considerably the Start of another town in the district, &amp; I have no doubt will keep it for many years to come</p>
            <p>At present there is no Store Rooms or house to be had immediately on the Public Square; but as one of the Merchants is about to sell out, there might be a probability of getting his house, which is a good Stand on the Square near the courthouse yet unless application be made shortly, <choice>
                  <orig>some body</orig>
                  <reg>somebody</reg>
               </choice> else will rent it, as there is a talk of some new Store to come here; house rent is very high and not less than from 12 to 15 dollars or more a <pb n="2" facs="mp009b.small.jpg"/>
               <sic>a</sic> month by the year; Board &amp; Lodging is three dollars &amp; a half &amp; without <choice>
                  <orig>Lodgen</orig>
                  <reg>Lodging</reg>
               </choice> three dollars per Week. — We get our goods by the way of the <name type="place">Mississippi River</name>, they ⁁ <add place="supralinear">are</add> landed at <name type="person">George C. Barfields</name> at the <name type="place">Canadian Reach, Arkansas</name>. <unclear>T.</unclear> four miles above the mouth of <name type="place">Forked Deer River</name>, on the Mississippi from there they ⁁ <add place="supralinear">are</add> forwarded in Reel Boats to this place; the freight from the <choice>
                  <abbr>Miss.</abbr>
                  <expan>Mississippi</expan>
               </choice> to Jackson is from 62 ½ cents to 75 per hundred pounds — they are landed one mile from town, and have to be hauled in wagons that short distance —</p>
            <p>The distance from the mouth of the Forked <choice>
                  <abbr>D</abbr>
                  <expan>Deer</expan>
               </choice> to Jackson is two hundred miles by water and one of the <choice>
                  <orig>disagreablest</orig>
                  <reg>most disagreeable</reg>
               </choice> River to navigate I ever Saw. — The nearest point <del type="overstrike">from here</del> to Tennessee River is about Sixty miles from here, &amp; the best Landing would be <name type="place">Reynoldburg</name> on <choice>
                  <abbr>Tens.</abbr>
                  <expan>Tennessee</expan>
               </choice> River, from which place good would have to be wagoned at the rate of $1.50 to $1.75 or $ 2 per  <unclear>100</unclear>. — The Forked Deer is not <choice>
                  <orig>navagable</orig>
                  <reg>navigable</reg>
               </choice> all the year, but only in Spring and at the time of high <unclear>freskes</unclear>, yet it keeps up <choice>
                  <orig>generaly</orig>
                  <reg>generally</reg>
               </choice>
               <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> some time in May. — My advise would be, for one of you, to come first to this country &amp; see yourself &amp; take a <choice>
                  <orig>rout</orig>
                  <reg>route</reg>
               </choice> through the district and see the little Towns &amp; their <choice>
                  <orig>prospecks</orig>
                  <reg>prospects</reg>
               </choice>. —<pb n="3" facs="mp009c.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>The last news from <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N.</abbr>
                     <expan>New</expan>
                  </choice> Orleans</name>are very discouraging cotton is selling there from 6 to 9 ¢ — this will have some influence in selling of goods, as money will be <choice>
                  <orig>scarse</orig>
                  <reg>scarce</reg>
               </choice>. Besides the Land office will open here on the <date when="--05-01">1st day of May</date> to enter land at 50 ¢ per acre and will swap a great part of our circulating medium — yet after all this, there is still a great opening for men of Capital in sundry Speculation, &amp; if I had only the funds, I could make money here, but the way I am situated from hand to mouth, I have to tipple the best way I can, yet hope to come out yet some day —</p>
            <p>I have told you now enough to give you some <choice>
                  <orig>ensight</orig>
                  <reg>insight</reg>
               </choice> of the Situation of this country &amp; you can take your measures accordingly —</p>
            <p>In your letter I might have <choice>
                  <orig>exspected</orig>
                  <reg>expected</reg>
               </choice> something about my business I <unclear>left</unclear> with you, but ⁁<add place="supralinear">you</add> did not even mention it — in my Last I requested you to collect the Notes and amounts the shortest way possible, I repeat the same, &amp; would thank you when you write to me again to let me know what the prospects are —</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I remain your friend</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Charles L. Barth</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="bottom of page">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P.S.</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> If the <unclear>French cook</unclear> of <name type="person">Elliot Bachee</name> would still be about there ask him if he would come <unclear>&amp; live</unclear> with me as a Baker &amp; confectioner?? C.L.B—</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="mp009d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="above address">Jackson <choice>
                     <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                     <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/>
                  <date when="1826-04-21">21 April 1826</date> } 18 ¼</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Messrs</abbr>
                        <expan>Messeiurs</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name type="person">Rhea &amp; McCrabb</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Athens</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <unclear>Ala</unclear>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address">Mail }</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
