<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl756">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1820 Oct. 18, Murfreesboro, Tennessee [to] N. Starry / Joseph McMinn : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>McMinn, Joseph</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl756</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> 1820 Oct. 18, Murfreesboro, Tennessee [to] N. Starry / Joseph McMinn</title>
               <author>McMinn, Joseph </author>
               <date when="1820-10-18">October 18, 1820</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated October 18, 1820 from the governor of Tennessee, Joseph McMinn to N. Starry.  The subject of the letter is the crafting of two swords of quality and workmanship to be inscribed with the names of Major Generals Andrew Jackson, and Edmund P. Gaines, and a brief note of esteem for their service in the war against Great Britain.  The swords are intended to be gifts from the state of Tennessee; McMinn offers Starry $1800 for the crafting, inscription, and delivery of the two swords to Washington, City. (D.C.)</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Joseph McMinn Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl756</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>McMinn, Joseph, 1758-1824</term>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr94022129"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">McMinn, Joseph, 1758-1824</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl756a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Murfreesboro</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>18th <choice>
                     <abbr>Oct</abbr>
                     <expan>October</expan>
                  </choice> 1820</date>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letter of the <date>20th august</date> last, did not reach my hand until 14th <choice>
                  <abbr>inst</abbr>
                  <expan>instant</expan>
               </choice>, owing in part to my being Absent, from the Seat of government for the space of 4 weeks past</p>
            <p>I am greatly obliged by your attention to my request, relative to the description of <choice>
                  <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Johnson Sword; but Sir your price so far exceeds any sum which has been spoken of here, that, I am induced almost to negative the proposition for sir the price of one sword Say $1200 is at least <del>double</del>   equal to what has been thought by men of some information, would be the cost of both__</p>
            <p>But as I am willing to admit that Colo Johnsons <add>Sword</add>    agreeable to your description, must be one of first rate, I will propose giving you eighteen hundred Dollars for two Sword, equal in Size, and equal in richness of mounting &amp; <pb n="2" facs="sl756b.small.jpg"/>   workmanship to the one just alluded to, and <add>each</add>  to contain (in addition) the following inscription, "This Sword presented by the State of Tennessee to major General <name>
                  <add>Andrew</add>  Jackson</name>      for <choice>
                  <orig>meritonous</orig>
                  <reg>meritorious</reg>
               </choice> services performed <del>by</del>   in the late war with <name>Great Briain</name>"  The same inscription to be engraved on the second sword except to use the title <del>to</del>   "Major General <name>Edmund P. Gaines</name>"__</p>
            <p>If this proposition suits your interest, you can enter on the work as soon as you please__ and in any event <add>I will thank you to</add>   give one the earliest notice of whatever may be your determination on the subject, and should you conclude to make the sword, and deliver them at <name>washington</name> city as you have proposed, you will please deliver them to the <choice>
                  <abbr>Honl</abbr>
                  <expan>Honorable</expan>
               </choice>. <name>Newton Cannon</name> one of the Representatives from this state in Congress, who will receipt you accordingly upon the production of which the money will be paid to you on order by Draught on the Treasury of this state, on sight, <pb n="3" facs="sl756c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>very respectfully<name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr> Jos</abbr>
                        <expan>Joseph</expan>
                     </choice>. McMinn</name>
                  <date>9 <choice>
                        <abbr>Decr </abbr>
                        <expan>December</expan>
                     </choice>1820</date>
                  <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                     <expan>Mister</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <name>N. Starry</name>
                  <pb n="4" facs="sl756d.small.jpg"/> Copy <lb/> Letter to N. Starry <lb/> Sword maker <choice>
                     <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                     <expan>and et cetera</expan>
                  </choice> &amp;c<lb/> 18 <choice>
                     <abbr>Oct</abbr>
                     <expan>October</expan>
                  </choice> 1820</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
