<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl452">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Writings] "To the Sumner Volunteers"   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl452</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Writings] "To the Sumner Volunteers"</title>
               <date when="1812">ca. 1812</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a song/poem entitled "To the Sumner Volunteers."</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Lauderdale Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">Correspondence</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">10</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl452</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</term>
               <term>Van Buren, Martin, 1782-1862</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl452a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>To the Sumner Volunteers.</opener>
            <p>Go! Sumner, Go! And quell the Savage Foe; <lb/> Go! Sumner, Go! Your Country bid you go; <lb/> Go! Sumner, Go! And lay the Indian low: <lb/> Go! Sumner, Go! Your <name>Jackson</name> orders so.</p>
            <p>Cheer! Sumner, Cheer! Our hearts with you We bear; <lb/> Cheer! Sumner, Cheer!  <unclear>Aloft your Banner rear</unclear>; <lb/> Cheer! Sumner, Cheer!   To evry Freeman dear: <lb/> Cheer! Sumner, Cheer! For you we breathe the prayr.</p>
            <p>Ride! Sumner, Ride! To aid the Southrons ride; <lb/> Ride! Sumner, Ride! And spread the havock wide; <lb/> Ride! Sumner, Ride! And swell the purple tide: <lb/> Ride! Sumner Ride! Your God is on your side.</p>
            <p>Fight! Sumner, Fight! For <name>Van Buren</name>, nor for White; <lb/> Fight! Sumner, Fight! Tis <name>Jackson</name> bids you fight;  <lb/> Fight! Sumner, Fight! Maintain your Country's Right, <lb/> Fight Sumner, Fight! And soar to Glory's height.</p>
            <p>Drive! Sumner, Drive! To <name>Rocky Mountains</name> drive: <lb/> Drive! Sumner, Drive! In Deserts Indians thrive: <lb/> Drive! Sumner, Drive! The murd'rous Indian Hive, <lb/> Drive! Sumner, Drive! Or leave not One alive.</p>
            <p>Now homeward Sumner wind your way, <lb/> With Victory perch'd on Banners gay: <lb/> When <name>Georgia's</name> Bard shall Patriot Deeds proclaim <lb/> Sumner shall proudly swell the book of Fame.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="sl452b.small.jpg"/>
            <closer>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Robt</abbr>
                  <expan>Robert</expan>
               </choice> English <choice>
                  <abbr>Capt</abbr>
                  <expan>Captain</expan>
               </choice> gibson company <add>miscellaneous scribbling</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
