<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um066">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1841 Jan. 7,    Columbia Female Institute, [Tennessee] [to] Elizabeth Chester / M[ary] J[ane] Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um066</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50314210</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1841 Jan. 7,    Columbia Female Institute, [Tennessee] [to] Elizabeth Chester / M[ary] J[ane] Chester</title>
               <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
               <date when="1841-01-07">January 7, 1841</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by Mary Jane Chester to her mother, Elizabeth Chester, on January 7, 1841. In the letter, Mary discusses events taking place at the Female Institute in Columbia, Tennessee. She mentions classes she is taking and planning to take, making clothes for herself and her sister, and a story involving a mail carrier.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers MS 25 (January 1841)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um066</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Mary Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um066a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia</name> Female Institute</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1841-01-07">January 7th 1841</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My <emph>dear dear</emph> Mama</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I would have answered your very kind ⁁ <add place="supralinear">letter</add> sooner but I thought that Papa would give you all the news. As I want to receive a letter very much indeed from home. I will <sic>will</sic> write so that you will have to answer it. You cannot imagine how much pleasure it gave me to see my Papa; he told me so much about you all. I made him tell me <del type="overstrike">what</del>
               <emph>how</emph> all the children were employed when he left home and all about Aunt <choice>
                  <abbr>N's</abbr>
                  <expan>Narcissa's</expan>
               </choice> sickness. <choice>
                  <orig>O</orig>
                  <reg>Oh</reg>
               </choice>! Mother I disliked for him to leave me so much. he promised me that he would visit me again in March. I do sincerely <choice>
                  <orig>hop</orig>
                  <reg>hope</reg>
               </choice> that he will remain with me longer. I sent by <name type="person">Miss Littlefield</name> to <name type="place">Nashville</name> for my Dress in Box but there was none there but w <add place="supralinear">h</add> at cost 20 or 30$ and certainly she did not purchase it. She got me a little trunk which will answer my purpose just as well. Mama <name type="person">Mr Smith</name> has requested all of us girls to <pb n="2" facs="um066b.small.jpg"/> subscribe to the Organ. he says that 2, 3, 4, or 5 dollar will be sufficient for each one. He told us about it four or five weeks ago but I forgot to mention it to Papa until now, for my mind has been so much occupied with other things. Tell Papa as much as he is willing for me to subscribe please to send it in any next letter &amp; I will give it to him.</p>
            <p>Dear Mama this day two week is the examination. <choice>
                  <orig>O</orig>
                  <reg>Oh</reg>
               </choice>! I do try so hard to be prepared for it. This morning I was out of my bed two hours before day Break. <unclear>studying</unclear>. I think that I could do very well if it was not for my Composition. There is one consolation no person will know who the compositions belongs to. I wish that Papa or some one of my relations would come up to it. If it was not for my French. I would have more time to study my other Studies. My Music Teacher has not concluded what <choice>
                  <orig>peice</orig>
                  <reg>piece</reg>
               </choice> I shall play at the Examination. I want to take under some other teacher next session for I do not think that <name type="person">Mrs Boardman</name> does me justice, as I told Papa.</p>
            <p> We are engaged all day <choice>
                  <orig>Sundy</orig>
                  <reg>Sunday</reg>
               </choice> (except when we are at Church) in reciting our Moral Philosophy and Some Prayers, out of the Prayer Book. I <choice>
                  <orig>entend</orig>
                  <reg>intend</reg>
               </choice> to study all next Saturday.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <orig>O</orig>
                  <reg>Oh</reg>
               </choice>! that was such a pretty Book that Papa sent me; it gave me so much pleasure to receive it. Yesterday you know it <del type="overstrike">rained</del>
               <add place="supralinear">rained</add> very hard. When <name type="person">Uncle Jim</name> came from the Post Office  with the letters all the girls <choice>
                  <orig>crowed</orig>
                  <reg>crowded</reg>
               </choice> around him to see who had one. his hat being very wet. one of the girls out of mischief knocked off his hat. When he gave Mr Smith the letters he told Mr <choice>
                  <abbr>S</abbr>
                  <expan>Smith</expan>
               </choice> — that one of the girls had knocked his hat off. and he asked him why did <pb n="3" facs="um066c.small.jpg"/> not he return the compliment and knock them down. Now <choice>
                  <abbr>dont</abbr>
                  <expan>do not</expan>
               </choice> you think that was wrong in Mr Smith.</p>
            <p>Please excuse my wretched writing for I am such a hurry. If Mr <choice>
                  <abbr>S</abbr>
                  <expan>Smith</expan>
               </choice> — knew that I was writing he would not like it.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your affectionate Daughter</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>M. J.</abbr>
                        <expan>Mary Jane</expan>
                     </choice> Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mrs <choice>
                        <abbr>E</abbr>
                        <expan>Elizabeth</expan>
                     </choice> Chester</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P. S.</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> Write soon &amp; often. I received a letter from <name type="person">Beth</name> the other day. She is enjoying herself so much. She says that she has <del type="overstrike">has</del> not  received one line from any of her relations since she left <name type="place">Jackson</name>.  She requests to ask them to write to her. Kiss little <name type="person">Sam</name> and all the children for me &amp; Papa. Give my love to all my relations. Tell <name type="person">Aunt Nancy</name> and all the servants <choice>
                     <orig>how'dye</orig>
                     <reg>howdy</reg>
                  </choice> for me. I can assure you that I wish that ⁁ <add place="supralinear">Aunt</add> Nancy was here. to do up my clothes &amp; help me <emph>Dress</emph>. but I do not have much of that to do. Mama can <name type="person">Samuel</name> talk yet Papa told me that he could nearly Speak Mind the first word that he speaks must be Sister Janey. Tell sister <name type="person">Martha</name> that I am Working her some Pants. of Saturday and will send them the first opportunity that I get. They are very small <choice>
                     <orig>preasents</orig>
                     <reg>presents</reg>
                  </choice> but I want to do something for her. I wish that I could see <emph>her</emph>, and all of <emph>you</emph>; how is little <name type="person">Mary Ormand</name>. does she remember me. and cousin <name type="person">Jane Rawlings</name> children. I <choice>
                     <abbr>dont</abbr>
                     <expan>do not</expan>
                  </choice> want any of them to forget me. Give my love to Aunt N. &amp; P. Your Daughter <choice>
                     <abbr>M. J.</abbr>
                     <expan>Mary Jane</expan>
                  </choice> Chester <lb/> Mrs. <choice>
                     <abbr>E.</abbr>
                     <expan>Elizabeth</expan>
                  </choice> Chester</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="um066d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mrs Elizabeth Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address, upside down">
                  <date when="1841-01-07">7th <choice>
                        <abbr>Jany</abbr>
                        <expan>January</expan>
                     </choice> 1841</date>
               </add>
               <add place="right of address, sideways">I have not time to write this letter over or I should certainly do it. Please excuse me. I do not expect that I can write next Week for I shall so busy</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
