<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc005">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1837 Dec. 11 [to] Jesse Abernathy Esq[ui]r[e], Pulaski,
			 Tennessee / W[illia]m R Brown : a machine-readable transcription of an
			 image</title>
            <author>Brown, William R.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Mays</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno>sc005</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 49961017 </idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1837 Dec. 11 [to] Jesse Abernathy Esq[ui]r[e],
				Pulaski, Tennessee / W[illia]m R Brown</title>
               <author>Brown, William R.</author>
               <date when="1837-12-11">December 11, 1837</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary"> This document is a letter dated December 11,
				1837, to Jesse Abernathy in Pulaski, TN, from William R. Brown. In the letter,
				Brown expressed concern regarding the influence of the Whigs in the state of
				Tennessee, particularly in Giles County, where Whigs had obtained control of
				the press. He stated that Henry Clay would be the presidential candidate of the
				Whigs to rival current president Andrew Jackson. Brown further stated that he
				had relinquished his political aspirations and had no plans to run for office.
				He also discussed the issues of banks and a pending bill in the Tennessee
				legislature that would funnel bond money into the creation of a state bank in
				Middle Tennessee. Another bill proposing to charter a bank was earlier rejected
				by the Tennessee senate.</note>
               <note type="Collection">William R. Brown</note>
               <note type="Box">n/a</note>
               <note type="Folder"> MS-224</note>
               <note type="Document">sc005</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Brown, William R.</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Tennessee Politics and government to 1865</term>
               <term>Clay, Henry, 1811-1847</term>
               <term>Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Brown, William R.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc005a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville </name>
                     <date when="1837-12-11">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Decr</abbr>
                           <expan>December</expan>
                        </choice> 11th
					 1837</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I admit in the onset that I owe you an apology for not several weeks
			 since acknowledging the <unclear>recut</unclear> of your truly gratifying
			 letter  At that time the proceedings of the <choice>
                  <orig>legeslature</orig>
                  <reg>legislature</reg>
               </choice> aside from the <choice>
                  <orig>Senatoreal</orig>
                  <reg>Senatorial</reg>
               </choice> election were uninteresting, and of that
			 election I know you had all the information worthy your attention. I have
			 <choice>
                  <orig>defered</orig>
                  <reg>deferred</reg>
               </choice> from time to time writing hoping that I
			 should be able to give the details of the most important subjects before us, of
			 this however I am still denied the opportunity in part, The bill to establish a
			 state bank and for other purposes <choice>
                  <orig>emalgamating</orig>
                  <reg>amalgamating</reg>
               </choice>
			 internal improvement education 
			 <choice>
                  <abbr>c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> is still pending and from
			 appearances is most likely to prove a troublesome and <choice>
                  <orig>vextious</orig>
                  <reg>vexatious</reg>
               </choice> subject the friends of this measure are quite
			 unwilling to separate the bank from the other provisions of the bill, while the
			 friends of the bank cannot support it with them attached to it The bill
			 proposes to sell the bonds of the state amounting to six millions one million
			 seven hundred thousand to be applied in 
			 <choice>
                  <abbr>E</abbr>
                  <expan>East</expan>
               </choice>
               <name type="place">Tennessee</name> to internal
			 <choice>
                  <orig>emprovement</orig>
                  <reg>improvement</reg>
               </choice> one million 3 hundred thousand to
			 the same purpose in the 
			 <choice>
                  <abbr>Ne</abbr>
                  <expan>Northeast</expan>
               </choice> District 2 millions to be vested in
			 a state bank in Middle 
			 <choice>
                  <abbr>Tenn.</abbr>
                  <expan>Tennessee</expan>
               </choice> and the remainder left as a
			 <choice>
                  <orig>bate</orig>
                  <reg>bait</reg>
               </choice> held out to us in this portion of the state for
			 the purposes of internal <choice>
                  <orig>emprovement</orig>
                  <reg>improvement</reg>
               </choice>, and the
			 proceeds of the bank relied on for the payment of the whole debt, and this is
			 urged as if the benefits of the were not to diffuse itself over the whole
			 state, if there should be benefits derived from a bank, the policy of which
			 remains yet to be tried, in all these project, of improvement by the provisions
			 of the bill the Governor is to subscribe for half of the stock, not satisfied
			 with the law of 35 authorizing one third to be taken by the state but another
			 <add place="supralinear">step</add> reaching to one half is made of this latter
			 policy you have often heard my opinion, and I fear I may have cause to regret
			 that I did not vote for a repeal of the law of 
			 <date when="1835">1835</date> above alluded to. You have no
			 doubt heard much of the Whig rejoicing at the news from 
			 <name type="place">New York</name> the accounts of the illumination
			 here are much <choice>
                  <orig>exagerated</orig>
                  <reg>exaggerated</reg>
               </choice> not more than one half
			 of the houses on the square were illuminated and as far as my observation
			 extended not that many in other places or parts of this great
			 <del type="overstrike">would be</del> Whig city the point in 
		  <name type="place"> Tennessee </name>at which <pb n="2" facs="sc005b.small.jpg"/>
               <name type="person"> Henry Clay</name> has been fairly put in
		  nomination for the next presidency by the once pretended friends of 
		  <name type="person">Andrew Jackson</name>, yes sir it can no longer be
		  disguised that Henry Clay is the candidate of the Whigs in Tennessee for the
		  first office in this nation and selected by those who but a short time since
		  were crouching and paying homage at the feet of the venerable
		  <choice>
                  <orig>expresident</orig>
                  <reg>ex-president</reg>
               </choice> who would have thought this a few
		  short months ago? Not a man in five hundred in this state.
               </p>
            <p>The Presidents message has reached us, and is generally spoken of as
			 an able document, I have read it with much care and am fully prepared to say
			 to use a common phrase it is as plumb as a line, you will see it for
			 yourself soon I shall therefore suspend further remarks <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> we shall see each other. I am told that friend Estes
			 has sold his press and that it is still in the hands of the Whigs, What a pity
			 is this, how much to be lamented it is that we have no one in Giles possessed
			 of public spirit enough to vest a few dollars in rescuing so formidable an
			 engine as the press from the hands of our enemies, it is useless to to tell me
			 that that paper has had no influence in shaping the politics of 
			 <name type="place">Giles County</name> there are many
			 <add place="supralinear">in that county</add> who read no other paper and whose
			 minds <del type="overstrike">are</del>
               <add place="supralinear">have been</add>
		  influenced by it to take the course the have done, and all that is wanting to
		  redeem Giles is to expose the tricks, so to speak, of the enemies of republican
		  principles, Giles County is republican in her principles and might be restored
		  to her first love if the proper means were brought into requisition. I know the
		  people there too well to indulge a different thought for a single moment, of
		  them,</p>
            <p>As to the <choice>
                  <orig>entimation</orig>
                  <reg>intimation</reg>
               </choice> in yours relative
			 to my again presenting myself before the people in the capacity of a candidate
			 for office I at this time have not the most distant idea of doing so my
			 political aspirations are entirely cured and the fever for such pursuits
			 perfectly cooled off for even in my short experience I have learned that few
			 men can engage in politics without feeling the thorns that are always strewed
			 along his path prick him sorely at almost every turn again men with whom one
			 has to act in the discharge of his public duties too often <choice>
                  <sic>look look</sic>
                  <corr>look</corr>
               </choice> ahead to promotion at the expense of public good
			 and I now say to you that if in anything I have contributed an humble
			 <choice>
                  <orig>mite</orig>
                  <reg>might</reg>
               </choice> to the welfare of those who sent me here however
			 humble that <choice>
                  <orig>mite</orig>
                  <reg>might</reg>
               </choice> may be <pb n="3" facs="sc005c.small.jpg"/> I am amply
			 rewarded for all my efforts to do so and at the expiration of the time for
			 which I was elected shall cheerfully surrender the charge confided to me and
			 will never again undertake or desire so important a station though I know it to
			 be and humble one. The reasons I have for this determination are may and strong
			 I shall not undertake here to give but am ready on any proper occasion when I
			 see you to do so
               </p>
            <p>General Jackson was in town a few days since. The old Hero talks as
			 fluently about banks and in fact on all subjects whatever  his head is
			 clear and mind strong apparently as if he were in the prime of life his health
			 has much <choice>
                  <orig>emproved</orig>
                  <reg>improved</reg>
               </choice> since he was here about 4 weeks
			 since he is a venerable looking man  his person much altered since I saw
			 him 10 or 12 years ago. You have no doubt seen in the Union an extract of 
			 <name type="person">John Bells</name> speech in 
			 <name type="place">Massachusetts </name> he is in fine
			 business <choice>
                  <orig>apologysing</orig>
                  <reg>apologizing</reg>
               </choice> for the sins of 
			 <choice>
                  <abbr>Tenn.</abbr>
                  <expan>Tennessee</expan>
               </choice> though she is march back in
			 solid <choice>
                  <orig>colums</orig>
                  <reg>columns</reg>
               </choice>. Now it is my opinion that when 
			 <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Bell sees that the bill to charter
			 Yeatman  Woods bank was rejected by the senate of a Tennessee legislature
			 and his plan of getting a <gap agent="damage"/> N Bed<gap agent="damage"/> US bank of 
			 <name type="place"> Pennsyl</name>
               <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>vania</unclear> is defeated
			 <gap agent="damage"/> confidence in the states returning to the good
			 old republican of Massachusetts as speedily as he anticipated</p>
            <p>I have just 
			 <choice>
                  <abbr>recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> a letter from 
			 <name type="person">Charles</name>  you may read this to him
			 and other of our friends if you think proper. Tell Charles his allusion to
			 futurity as far as I am concerned in a political point of view is of no
			 importance to me but it is truly gratifying to hear that my constituents are
			 pleased with my course thus far  I have no views or ends to accomplish
			 other than the good first of those that sent here and second the general
			 welfare of the state if all my acts here does not redown to promote that end it
			 shall be an error of the head and not of the heart. When I say friends to whom
			 this may be read I only mean 
			 <name type="person">Charles W D Abernathy</name>
               <name type="person">L E Abernathy</name> and such only I once
			 indulged the hope of getting home by Christmas the prospect of doing so is at
			 this time gloomy. I hope however that we shall adjourn by the 
			 <date when="--01-10">10th of 
				<choice>
                     <abbr>Jany.</abbr>
                     <expan>January</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date> even this is
			 uncertain</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Respectfully</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                        <expan>William</expan>
                     </choice> R
				  Brown</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="sc005d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Jesse Abernathy </name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Pulaski</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Polite Attention of 
		  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Capt.</abbr>
                        <expan>Captain</expan>
                     </choice>
			 Rhea</name>
               </add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
