<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch037">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter, 1816 May 14, War Department to Rev[erend] C[yrus] Kingsbury / W[illia]m H. Crawford, Sec[retar]y of War : a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Crawford, William Harris, 1772-1834</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch037</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44806226</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Letter, 1816 May 14, War Department to Rev[erend] C[yrus] Kingsbury / W[illia]m H. Crawford, Sec[retar]y of War</title>
               <author>Crawford, William Harris, 1772-1834</author>
               <date when="1816-05-14">May 14, 1816</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">Copy of a letter dated May 14, 1816 from Secretary of War William H. Crawford to American Board missionary Cyrus Kingsbury in response to Kingsbury's request for aid in establishing schools in the Cherokee Nation. Crawford reports that President Madison approves of the project, and he will give aid within the limits of the law. Crawford sets forth instructions for the application and receipt of supplies and equipment for the schools and informs Kingsbury that the president expects an annual report on their progress. </note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">29</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch037</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Missions</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Education</term>
               <term>United States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n84054922"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Crawford, William Harris, 1772-1834</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch037a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>B.<lb/>Letter from <name type="person">Wm. H. Crawford</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Secy.</abbr>
                  <expan>Secretary</expan>
               </choice> of War in reply to <name type="person">Mr. Kingsbury</name> dated
               </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>War Department</addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <date when="1816-05-14">14th May 1816</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letter of the <choice>
                  <abbr>2d.</abbr>
                  <expan>2nd</expan>
               </choice> instant upon the subject of establishing schools in the <name>Cherokee Nation</name> has been received.  The President approves of the undertaking  will direct such aid to be given as the laws will permit.</p>
            <p>In the first instance the agent will be directed to erect a comfortable school house,  another for the teacher  such as may board with him, in such part of the nation as shall be selected for that purpose.  He will also be directed to furnish two ploughs, six hoes  as many axes, for the purpose of introducing the art of cultivation among the pupils.</p>
            <p>Whenever he is informed that female children are received  brought into the school,  that a female teacher has been engaged capable of teaching them to spin, weave sew, a loom  half a dozen spinning wheels  as many pair of cards will be furnished.  He will be directed, from time to time, to cause other school houses to be erected, as they shall become necessary,  as the expectation of ultimate success shall justify the expenditure.</p>
            <p>The houses thus erected  the implements of husbandry  of the mechanic arts which shall be furnished will remain public property to be occupied  employed for the benefit of the nation.  If the persons who are about to be <add place="supralinear">engage</add> employed in this enterprize<pb n="2" facs="ch037b.small.jpg"/>should abandon it, the buildings  utensils which shall have been furnished may be occupied by any other teachers of good moral character.
               </p>
            <p>The only return which is expected by the President is an Annual Report of the state of the school, its progress  future prospects.  This Report should present the mode of teaching  the deviations from that practised in civilized life, which experience shall render necessary.  Should you succeed according to your expectations, it is probable that the attention of congress will be attracted to the subject; and that the means of forwarding your beneficent views will be more directly  liberally bestowed by that enlightened body.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have the honor to be Your most <choice>
                     <abbr>obedt.</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient</expan>
                  </choice>  very humble <choice>
                     <abbr>servt.</abbr>
                     <expan>servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute> (signed)<signed>
                  <name type="person">Wm H. Crawford</name>
               </signed>
               <lb/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Rev. C. Kingsbury</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
