<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl296">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1828 Apr. 4, Lebanon [to] Mr. Fergusson / T. C. Anderson   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Anderson, T. C.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl296</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1828 Apr. 4, Lebanon [to] Mr. Fergusson / T. C. Anderson</title>
               <author>Anderson, T. C.</author>
               <date when="1828-04-04">April 4, 1828</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from T. C. Anderson to A. Fergusson, dated April 4, 1828. Anderson is informing Fergusson that his son, William,  received an admonition from his school's faculty. He was found guilty of spreading false and slanderous rumors. Anderson counciled Fergusson to give William parental advice when he returns home.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers IV-G-1</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">7</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl296</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Anderson, T. C.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl296a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Lebanon</name>
                     <date when="1828-04-04">April 4 1828</date>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mr <choice>
                           <orig>Furguson</orig>
                           <reg>Fergusson</reg>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>A letter has been placed in the hands of the Faculty written by your son William, to a gentleman in <name type="place">Alabama</name> who had two daughters in the Female Academy. It was found to contain several notoriously false and highly slanderous statements respecting <unclear>new J. N.  Roach</unclear> , late principal of said school, and a young Lady who has taught music in the School An investigation was made when it appeared that rumors were in circulation in certain quarters charging, in substance, what was stated in the letter, to have transpired you son was therefore <choice>
                  <orig>acquited</orig>
                  <reg>acquitted</reg>
               </choice> of fabricating the false statements, but was convicted of having taken up idle and slanderous rumors and retailed them, not as rumors, but as facts He was also found guilty of imprudent officiousness in communicating these slanderous reports to a stranger and an old gentleman <choice>
                  <orig>whith</orig>
                  <reg>with</reg>
               </choice> whom he had no acquaintance. As an explanation of this strange officiousness it was ascertained that your son had made his <unclear>address</unclear> to one of the young ladies in the School who was boarding with <name type="person">Mr Roach </name>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl296b.small.jpg"/> The Faculty decided that I should <choice>
                  <orig>community</orig>
                  <reg>communicate</reg>
               </choice> to you all the facts of the case, that you might join with the Faculty in giving your son such advice and admonition as you might deem proper. Also that I should publicly admonish your son, commenting upon the highly <unclear>misurable</unclear> conduct of detailing rumors in the form of facts; the imprudent officiousness of addressing a stranger and an aged man upon such subjects; and the ridiculousness of his fancied relation to the young lady</p>
            <p>The admonition was administered on saturday, and I have now given you the details of the case, which <unclear>consummates</unclear> the award of the Faculty</p>
            <p>In justice to your son I will inform you that his general department has hitherto been creditable to him, with the exception of his gallantry which must be regarded as ridiculous in one of his age.</p>
            <p>As his Dulcena has left for Alabama, it is hoped that his days of gallantry are over for a time at least, and a little parental advice just at this juncture may be profitable</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Very respectfully</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">T. C. Anderson</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
