<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0228">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Claim] 1837 Jan. 13 / Edward and   Sarah Graves : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0228</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 45957123</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Claim] 1837 Jan. 13 / Edward and   Sarah Graves</title>
               <date when="1837-01-13">January 13, 1837</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a spoliation claim made by Edward and Sarah Graves requesting that the United States government pay them the sum of forty-eight dollars for 12 hogs that were killed by troops under the command of General White during the Creek War.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> pa0228</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Claims</term>
               <term>Creek War, 1813-1814</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0228a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>The claim of Edward &amp; Sarah Graves for Spoliation committed by the citizens of the <name>United States</name>, and which is provided to be paid under the late treaty between the United States &amp; the <name>Cherokees</name>. They the said Edward &amp; Sarah Graves allege that during the war with the <name>Creek</name> Indians, about the year 1824, a body of troops under the command of <name>General White</name> of Tennessee, encamped <add>in the neighborhood of the</add>
               <del type="overstrike">at the</del> House of the <unclear>Pheasant</unclear> , the father of said <name>Sarah Graves</name>, and while so encamped, killed and used twelve Head of Hogs of two years old and valued Four Dollars a head. They allege further that the claim has never been <unclear>liquidated</unclear> . <add>12 Head of Hogs estimated <lb/> at $4.00 per head $48.</add>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>Edward Graves</name>
               </signed>
               <add>During the War with the Creek Nation about the year 1813 or 1814 I lived in <name>Wills Valley</name> in the neighborhood of where <name>Mr. Bell</name> now lives. A body of troops under the command of General White on their way to the Creek Nation, <add>encamped</add> at the foot of the Mountain about two miles from my house. A gang of hogs belonging to my daughter, now Sarah Graves, and her Mother, <unclear>raised</unclear> in that neighborhood. A day or so after the troops had passed on, I went to where they had encamped, and found the heads of 12 hogs which had been killed, strewed about the camp. I knew the hogs from the mark_ They were very gentle, and two years old__ and valued about $4 a head. Other hogs disappeared, and were probably also killed, but I did not discover any remains of them. The claim has never before been presented.</add>
               <salute>Sworn to &amp; Subscribed before me <lb/> in Committee this <date>18th <choice>
                        <abbr>Oct.</abbr>
                        <expan>October</expan>
                     </choice> 1836</date>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>John Ridge</name>
                  <add>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Prest.</abbr>
                        <expan>President</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <lb/>
                     <unclear>Committee</unclear>
                  </add>
               </signed>
               <signed>P Pheasant <add>his</add> x <add>mark</add>
               </signed>
               <add>of  <lb/> Wills Valley</add>
               <add>After the troops had passed, <del type="overstrike">
                     <unclear/>
                  </del> , as stated by Pheasant, on their way to the Creeks Nation, my father came home and told us that a number of Hogs belonging to Pheasant's family had been Killed by the Soldiers. A number of us went to the encampment, and discovered the <del type="overstrike">the</del>
                  <pb n="2" facs="pa0228b.small.jpg"/> remains of some hogs, such as heads entrails <choice>
                     <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                     <expan>etcetera</expan>
                  </choice> scattered about. I examined the heads &amp; I Know from the work that they belonged to Pheasants family. My father lived a neighborhood to Pheasant</add>
               <salute>Sworn to &amp; Subscribed before <add>me</add> in <lb/> Committee this 18th day of Oct. 1836</salute>
               <signed>John Ridge Prest.</signed>
               <signed>A yee. sah, dat Skee <add>his</add> x <add>mark</add>
                  <add>or the man <lb/> who shakes off the dew</add>
               </signed>
               <add>no___ 9____  <lb/> Edward &amp; Sarah Grave <lb/> Registered <lb/> Book A <lb/> Page 3 <lb/> allowed 13 <unclear>June</unclear> 1837</add>
               <add> after Examination <lb/> By the <choice>
                     <abbr>Comm.</abbr>
                     <expan>Committee</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
