<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mc051">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1838 Feb. 13, Knoxville, TN [to] Henry I. Welcker, Kingston, Tennessee / James M. Welcker  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Welcker, James Monroe</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">mc051</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1838 Feb. 13, Knoxville, TN [to] Henry I. Welcker, Kingston, Tennessee / James M. Welcker</title>
               <author>Welcker, James Monroe</author>
               <date when="1838-02-13">February 13, 1838</date>
               <extent> 3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated February 13, 1838, from James Monroe Welcker to his brother Henry Inman Welcker in Kingston, Tennessee.  The Welckers were a prominent family from Roane County.  James writes this letter from Knoxville, where he is studying law and their younger brother Albert is attending school.  James responds to Henry's earlier enquiry regarding merchants going east, and he discusses family matters as well.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Welcker Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-12, b2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1838</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mc051</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Tennessee, East</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Welcker, James Monroe</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mc051a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Knoxville Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1838-02-13">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Feb.</abbr>
                           <expan>February</expan>
                        </choice> 13th 1838</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Through the politeness of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Ramsey</name> I have just received your letter of the 11th, <choice>
                  <abbr>inst</abbr>
                  <expan>instant</expan>
               </choice>, which I now proceed in haste to answer.</p>
            <p>I was truly gratified to hear something from yourself, sister Catharine and the rest of the family, as they are sources from which I have <add>been</add> anxiously expecting to hear for some time past.  Since your letter Came to hand <add>I have</add>  made considerable enquiry among the <choice>
                  <orig>mirchants</orig>
                  <reg>merchants</reg>
               </choice> of this place in order to learn when they intend going to the east for their goods Many of them have already gone, Viz Messrs. <name>Jackson</name>, <name>Dickenson</name>, <name>Armstrong</name> and <name>Gaines</name>; and I can hear of no one else who intends going on before about the middle of March.  <name>Mr. G. M. <unclear>Hayen</unclear>
               </name> will leave here about that time; but as he will be in Considerable haste I expect he will take the stage from this place.  In fact I have heard of no one going any other way as they all wish to perform the trip as soon as possible.</p>
            <p>We have no news here that is worth <pb n="2" facs="mc051b.small.jpg"/>
               <choice>
                  <orig>writeing</orig>
                  <reg>writing</reg>
               </choice>.  There will be Circuit Court in this place <choice>
                  <orig>dureing</orig>
                  <reg>during</reg>
               </choice> this week and next; and we have a very disagreeable time for it, for our streets are so made that they are almost impassible</p>
            <p>Albert is very industrious and progresses well.  I scarcely find him at any other place except in his room or at school.  His teacher has a very high opinion of him.</p>
            <p>I could not be better pleased with any situation than my own.  The family with whom I board is a very agreeable and <choice>
                  <orig>respectible</orig>
                  <reg>respectable</reg>
               </choice> one; and it is in a retired part of town where I have no interruption at all In addition to this <name>Judge Scott</name> takes great pleasure in <choice>
                  <orig>giveing</orig>
                  <reg>giving</reg>
               </choice> me instruction and I am convinced he has paid more attention to me than is generally given to law students.  He says I am getting along quite well and indeed has given me considerable encouragement.  Albert and myself are well I conclude here because I have nothing more to write.  You will excuse the hand write as I am in great haste.</p>
            <p>Give our love to each and every one of the family And acknowledge for yourself the esteem of your most affectionate brother</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>James <choice>
                        <abbr>M.</abbr>
                        <expan>Monroe</expan>
                     </choice> Welcker</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To <name>Mr. Henry <choice>
                           <abbr>I.</abbr>
                           <expan>Inman</expan>
                        </choice> Welcker</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="3" facs="mc051c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mr. Henry I. Welcker</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Kingston</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
