<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um087">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1843 Feb. 17, Columbia, Tenn[essee] [to] Miss Martha B. Chester, Jackson, Tenn[essee] / Mary J[ane] Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um087</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50323438</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1843 Feb. 17, Columbia, Tennessee [to] Miss Martha B. Chester, Jackson, Tenn[essee] / Mary J[ane] Chester</title>
               <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
               <date when="1843-02-17">February 17, 1843</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a letter addressed to Martha B. Chester from her sister Mary Jane Chester, dated February 17, 1843.  Mary Jane updates her sister on her past examination and her current endeavors at the Female Institute in Columbia, TN.  Mary Jane also encloses a letter to her brother John, in which she scolds him for not writing to her more frequently.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers MS-25 (Jan-June 1843)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um087</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Mary Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um087a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia, <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1843-02-17">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Feby.</abbr>
                           <expan>February</expan>
                        </choice> 17th 1843</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Sister,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>You have no idea how much pleasure your kind letter afforded me, more I suppose, from being unexpected, for by your delay in writing, I had concluded that I was so unfortunate as to be forgotten by you.  You can imagine with what delight  I was undeceived.  I hasten to answer yours, hoping that you will follow my example.  From your many promises before I left home,  I satisfied myself with the idea that in you, I should certainly find a regular <choice>
                  <orig>correspondant</orig>
                  <reg>correspondent</reg>
               </choice>; but the excuse which you offer, I consider a very good one, also, in this case acceptable.</p>
            <p>As I have not written home since the Examination I shall devote a few lines of this letter in giving you a partial description of it.  I have no doubt, but that you feel some anxiety to hear.  <name type="person">Mr. Smith</name> thinks that all the girls acquitted themselves very much to their credit.  It lasted three days, commenced on Friday and continued until Tuesday evening.  only two days <pb n="2" facs="um087b.small.jpg"/> vacation were given us to recover from our fatigue.  There was a concert every night. The Music was considered very fine by persons in general.  I am delighted to hear that Papa has promised to bring you up in the summer. I know you will be pleased with the Institute, and willing to come yourself to school.</p>
            <p>I took my first lesson on the Guitar yesterday, and am very much pleased with it, I think that I shall like it more than the Piano, but am determined not to neglect <add place="supralinear">the</add> Piano, as I know <emph>that</emph> is Papa's favorite Instrument.  I intend trying to improve my voice this session, for the Guitar Music is very poor, without it is accompanied with a good voice.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Alice Bennis</name> complains very often, because you dont write to her, I think she is learning very rapidly.  she also appears to be very well satisfied, with the school, although she is <choice>
                  <orig>sepparated</orig>
                  <reg>separated</reg>
               </choice> from her Parents.  She received a letter from her Mother last week, saying that <name type="person">Aunt Butler</name>  intended returning to Jackson in a few weeks, but was then on a visit to her relatives, who, I believe, reside in the <choice>
                  <orig>neighbourhood</orig>
                  <reg>neighborhood</reg>
               </choice>. I expect you all are very anxious that she should return.</p>
            <p>I had almost forgotten to give you an important piece of news.  Cousin<name type="person"> Knox</name> has a <emph>fine</emph> daughter.  He thinks her the most beautiful child in the world.  It <choice>
                  <sic>is is</sic>
                  <corr>is</corr>
               </choice> now past twelve oclock, and for fear of breaking the sabbath, I must bid you an <choice>
                  <abbr>afft.</abbr>
                  <expan>affectionate</expan>
               </choice> Good night,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Mary <choice>
                        <abbr>J.</abbr>
                        <expan>Jane</expan>
                     </choice> Chester</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="um087c.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>My dear Brother <name type="person">John</name>,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Taking advantage of the blank sheet in Sister's letter, I shall write you a few lines, but can tell you, that you need not expect, any thing more than a <emph>scolding</emph>. I console myself with the idea that although I have the <emph>pleasure</emph> of receiving so <emph>very</emph> few letters from you, <emph>perhaps</emph> you think of me sometimes.  I have various speculations, concerning the cause of your not writing, It may be be that your time is too much occupied with your school duties, in Hunting, or you dislike to writing is the reason, notwithstanding all these reasons, I do think, that you might have taken time to write to me at least once.  Tell brother <name type="person">Robert</name> I <choice>
                  <abbr>dont</abbr>
                  <expan>do not</expan>
               </choice> know any excuse, he could have for not writing.  It would give me great pleasure to receive a letter from him.  he must give me a description of every thing relating to <emph>Home</emph> — How you all come one, if <name type="person">King</name> &amp; <name type="person">Will</name> have grown any, and if little <name type="person">Sam</name> is as fine a fellow as ever, &amp; if he talks much about his sister Janey, and wants to see me.</p>
            <p>Since I have been boarding with <name type="person">Mrs. Wormely</name> I have had a great deal of pleasure.  I suppose you recollect <name type="person">Kate</name> I find ⁁ <add place="supralinear">her</add> a very agreeable companion. We walk out almost every evening, generally accompanied by two or three other girls. I have just commenced the study of Botany I think it more interesting than either of my other studies.  Tell Papa that <name type="person">Uncle Walker</name> has not been at home since christmas nor is he expected for a month, I believe, I have never gotten any money from him. I should like for him to get Cousin Sam <pb n="4" facs="um087d.small.jpg"/> to make some arrangements in the store for me. I promise him I shall be very economical.  I suppose you are tired of this scolding letter, or at least I am, so giving your <emph>fair</emph> warning that this is my last letter to you; until you write, &amp; hoping to receive one very soon, from both you &amp; Brother Robert.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your ever <choice>
                     <abbr>afft.</abbr>
                     <expan>affectionate</expan>
                  </choice> Sister</salute>
               <add place="left of address">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>postmark for Feb. 20</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Miss Martha B. Chester</name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson</name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <emph>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn.</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </emph>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address">I did not perceive that my writing would be seen, until I had finished it. so you will please <unclear>excuse</unclear> it.</add>
               <add place="below address" rend="different hand, ink">My Dear Mary Jane <lb/>
                  <date when="1843-02-17">17 <choice>
                        <abbr>Feby</abbr>
                        <expan>February</expan>
                     </choice> 1843</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
