<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl729">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> [Letter] 1796 Apr. 18, Philadelphia [Pennsylvania, to] John Sevier, Jonesboro, Tennessee / James White : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>White, James</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl729</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1796 Apr. 18, Philadelphia [Pennsylvania, to] John Sevier, Jonesboro, Tennessee / James White</title>
               <author> White, James</author>
               <date when="1796-04-18">April 18, 1796</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated April 18, 1796 to John Sevier from James White. White is congratulating Sevier on being the new governor of the new state. White writes that he is glad that the governor is going to be someone that the inhabitants of the territory chose for themselves. White mentions some treaty negotiations between the federal government and Great Britain are not completed.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor John Sevier Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl729</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Philadelphia</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Politics</term>
               <term>Sevier, John, 1745-1815</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">White, James</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl729a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Philadelphia</name>
                     <date>18th April 1796</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear General,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I hope I may safely by this time salute you as Governor of the State of <name>Tennessee</name>; or of the Territory of the <name>united states</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr> So</abbr>
                  <expan>South</expan>
               </choice> of <name>Ohio</name>. I congratulate you, in either case. For, if the united states should be of opinion that a census taken without their concurrence should be invalid; yet I have a strong confidence that you will be commissioned, &amp; paid as an officer of the United States: at least, your friends, here, will push it in your favor; &amp; I make no doubt will succeed. They have been looking for the latter case, because it is perceivable that it is a matter of some doubt whether for fear, of the precedent, it may not be policy in this Government to have some share in the census. For my own part I think it a great point for us that the Governor of our Territory should be a man who is decidedly the choice of the people. I mention <gap/> thing in confidence to you as something questionable: <gap/> I rather hope, <unclear>&amp;</unclear> expect that <unclear>our</unclear> Government <add>of Tennessee</add> will be allowed to proceed on the plan established by our convention: particularly as the committee appointed to consider on the case, in the House of Representatives have made a favorable report. The Senate, have also appointed a Committee for the consideration of the same subject; but the latter, I am told, will be clear that a census in which Congress had no share ought not to be looked upon as valid. The question will be taken up in the course of the work, &amp; as soon as decided shall be sent you, for your information. I thought it an act of friendship to inform You of the true state of the business; but as I have no certain grounds on which to found an opinion, I wish this loose surmise to be to yourself in Confidence <add>
                  <unclear>Mero</unclear>
               </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl729b.small.jpg"/> There is nothing new, here. The appropriations for the treaty with <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>G.</abbr>
                     <expan>Great</expan>
                  </choice> Britain</name> have not yet been made: but some of my acquaintance who were very adverse to that Treaty are coming to. As it regards us, I do not see why we should wish to see the executive of government disturbed on this score. I am therefore glad that the people of our Territory have not been forward in joining the general clamor, on that score. But our friend Parker, for whom we both entertain so much esteem, is bitterly opposed to it. So indeed are all the <name>Virginia</name> Representatives.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am <lb/> with great Respects <lb/> your <choice>
                     <abbr>obed servt</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>James White</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Governor Sevier</addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl729b.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Free</add>
               <add>James White <lb/> 10th april <lb/> 1796</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>James White</addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>John Sevier</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>esqr.</abbr>
                        <expan>esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Jonesboro</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>So. western Territory</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
