<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mp011">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Land Grant] 1840 Mar. 26 [to] James S. Porter / John Easton : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Easton, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>mp011</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50335902</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Memphis Public Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Memphis Public Library, 3030 Poplar Avenue, Memphis, TN 38111</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Land Grant] 1840 Mar. 26 [to] James S. Porter / John Easton</title>
               <author>Easton, John</author>
               <date when="1840-03-26">March 26, 1840</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a land grant given to James S. Porter from John Easton dated March 26, 1840. The grant specifies what sections of land Porter will get from the lands ceded to the United States from the Chickasaw Nation and John Easton, their commissioner, in the Treaty signed at Pontotoc Creek.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Goodman Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mp011</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Legal documents</term>
               <term>Chickasaw Indians -- Treaties</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>Land tenure</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Associated name http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/asn">Easton, John</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mp011a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>
               <emph>THE <name type="place">UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.</name>
               </emph>
            </head>
            <head>
               <emph>To all to whom these presents shall come, Greeting:</emph>
            </head>
            <p> Whereas under the <hi rend="written text">Fifth</hi> Article of the Treaty made at the CITY OF <name type="place">WASHINGTON</name>, on the <date when="1834-05-24">twenty fourth day of May, in the year of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and thirty four</date>, between the <name type="place">United States</name>, by their Commissioner <name type="person">JOHN H. EATON</name>, and the <name type="person">CHICKASAW INDIANS</name>, <name type="person">
                  <hi rend="written text">James S. Porter</hi>
               </name> became entitled out of the Lands ceded to the UNITED STATES by the Treaty concluded at <name type="place">Pontotoc Creek</name>, on the <date when="1832-10-20">twentieth day of October, one thousand eight hundred and thirty two</date>, with the CHICKASAW NATION, to <hi rend="written text">Five Sections</hi> of Land, and <emph>Whereas the President of the United States</emph> having approved on the <date when="1837-07-27">
                  <hi rend="written text">twenty seventh of July 1837</hi>
               </date> of the location of`<hi rend="written text">Fractional Sections Twenty six, Twenty Seven and Twenty eight, and the North half and South West quarter of Section Twenty five, in Township Six, of Range Thirteen, West, containing one thousand two hundred and seventy nine acres and forty eight hundredths of an acre, in the District of Lands subject to <gap agent="damage"/> at <name type="place">Pontotoc, Mississippi</name>
               </hi> entered as number <hi rend="written text">1018</hi> in the abstract of Reservations under the <hi rend="written text">Fifth</hi> Article of the aforesaid Treaty, of the <date when="1834-05-24">24th May, 1834</date>:</p>
            <p>
               <emph>NOW KNOW YE</emph>, That the <emph>United States of America</emph>, in consideration of the Premises, and in conformity with the provisions of the said Treaty of 1834, <emph>HAVE GIVEN AND GRANTED</emph>, and by these presents <emph>DO GIVE AND GRANT</emph>, unto the said <hi rend="written text">
                  <name type="person">James S. Porter</name>
               </hi>  and to <gap agent="damage"/> heirs, the said tract above described: <emph>TO HAVE AND TO HOLD</emph> the same, together with all the rights, privileges, immunities, and appurtenances of whatsoever nature, thereunto belonging, unto the said <hi rend="written text">James S. Porter</hi> and to <hi rend="written text">his</hi> heirs and assigns forever.</p>
            <p>
               <emph>In Testimony Whereof, I, <name type="person">MARTIN VAN BUREN</name>
               </emph>, PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA,  have caused these Letters to be made PATENT, and the SEAL of the GENERAL LAND OFFICE to be hereunto affixed. <emph>GIVEN</emph> under my hand at the CITY OF WASHINGTON, the <date when="1840-03-26">
                  <hi rend="written text">twenty sixth</hi> day of <hi rend="written text">March</hi> in the Year of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and <hi rend="written text">forty</hi>
               </date> and of the INDEPENDENCE OF THE UNITED STATES the Sixty <hi rend="written text">fourth</hi>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>seal</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <closer>BY THE PRESIDENT: <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <hi rend="written text">Martin Van Buren</hi>
                  </name>
               </signed>By <unclear>
                  <hi rend="written text">
                     <name type="person">Miltan Brirtnip</name>
                  </hi>
               </unclear>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Sec'y</abbr>
                  <expan>Secretary</expan>
               </choice>
               <lb/>
               <unclear>
                  <hi rend="written text">
                     <name type="person">HM Garland</name>
                  </hi>
               </unclear> RECORDER of the General Land Office. <add place="bottom left corner">Recorded <choice>
                     <abbr>Vol.</abbr>
                     <expan>volume</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>seal</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
