<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mc046">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1837 May 13, E[ast] T[ennessee] College [to] Mr. Charles F. Welcker, Talladega, Alabama / James M. Welcker : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Welcker, James M.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">mc046</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1837 May 13, E[ast] T[ennessee] College [to] Mr. Charles F. Welcker, Talladega, Alabama / James M. Welcker</title>
               <author>Welcker, James M.</author>
               <date when="1837-05-13">May 13, 1837</date>
               <extent>4 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated May 13, 1837, from James Monroe Welcker at East Tennessee College to his brother Charles F. Welcker in Talladega, Alabama.  James writes to his brother about personal and family matters.  He speaks of the latest news of their siblings, two of whom--Frederick and Benjamin Franklin--are also attending school in Knoxville.  James also talks of his displeasure in hearing of the recent sickness in his brother's family.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Welcker Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-12, b2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1837</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mc046</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>East Tennessee College</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Welcker, James Monroe</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mc046a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>E. T.</abbr>
                           <expan>East Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice> College</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>May 13th, 1837</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>You doubtless have expected a letter from me long before this time.</p>
            <p>When I left <choice>
                  <orig>Taladega</orig>
                  <reg>Talladega</reg>
               </choice> last fall I intended to have written soon after I arrived home; but owing to some cause or other, not to be attributed in any degree, either to any coolness or indifference for any of you, I have deferred it <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> this late period.  And now when I have set down to write to you; I have to say in the beginning, that I can write nothing that will be of interest to you, except that, which relates particularly to the family.  A few days past Father sent us your letter of March the 31; In regard to which, I have truly to say, that no <choice>
                  <orig>inteligence</orig>
                  <reg>intelligence</reg>
               </choice>, ever reached us, from you, from which we derived so little pleasure.  To hear that any of you is well, is indeed, to us, at all times the greatest  satisfaction; but to hear of your <unclear>distresses</unclear> of sickness and death is equally grievous.  And I have only to <add>state</add> that they do not reside upon you alone, but are mutual;  Further more they are such as none can change <add>or</add> amend.</p>
            <p>We have a letter here, that was written by brother Lewis to Father a few days after he reached <name>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Taroahote</orig>
                     <reg>Terre Haute</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name>.  He <pb n="2" facs="mc046b.small.jpg"/> informs us, that journey was a very pleasant one, that had seen many of his acquaintances on his way and has reached his place of destination without any difficulty.  He farther stated, that he was attending to his official duty <choice>
                  <orig>dureing</orig>
                  <reg>during</reg>
               </choice> the day, and studying the law at night.  His health is also very good.  Sister Catharine wrote to me a few days since she is well and very well pleased with <name>New Echota</name>; <name>Mr Lenoir</name> will remain there untill fall, when they expects to return to <name>Roane County</name>.__ Mary <choice>
                  <abbr>J.</abbr>
                  <expan>Jane</expan>
               </choice> is boarding with <name>Dr Jordan</name>, and is attending the <choice>
                  <orig>accadamy</orig>
                  <reg>academy</reg>
               </choice> in <name>Kingston</name>. Franklin is going  to school here.  Frederick and myself, as you <choice>
                  <orig>perhapse</orig>
                  <reg>perhaps</reg>
               </choice> have learned, did not return home this last vacation at all.   This was owing to our being very busily engaged in a review of some of our studies;  and we supposed we could employ our time here more advantageously <del type="overstrike">here</del> than elsewhere.  Our College commenced about a week ago, with prospects of a fine school.  we have students here from  many of the different states; but most of those who are from a distance are from <choice>
                  <abbr>Ala.</abbr>
                  <expan>Alabama</expan>
               </choice> It is my intention at present to complete my education <choice>
                  <orig>dureing</orig>
                  <reg>during</reg>
               </choice> the present <choice>
                  <orig>sesion</orig>
                  <reg>session</reg>
               </choice>; but what I shall do next winter I can not say with  <pb n="3" facs="mc046c.small.jpg"/> certainty; <choice>
                  <orig>thoug</orig>
                  <reg>though</reg>
               </choice> I would prefer reading history next winter preparatory to the study of a profession in the spring.</p>
            <p>You can see from the hand write and diction of this letter, that I have  been in great haste; you will therefore excuse many of the more gross errors.- -- I hope you will not be backward to write to me as soon as you receive this communication, as I am <choice>
                  <orig>verry</orig>
                  <reg>very</reg>
               </choice> anxious to know how sister Caroline is, and how all the rest of you are doing.  Tell them all they must write to us often, I have not received a line from any of you <gap agent="damage"/> I left you.  They were all well last week <gap/> home; but were complaining very much of the drouth. Fred, Franklin &amp; myself wish to be remembered to you all; and as to yourself <choice>
                  <orig>pleas</orig>
                  <reg>please</reg>
               </choice>
               <choice>
                  <orig>except</orig>
                  <reg>accept</reg>
               </choice> my best wishes as a testimony of an affectionate brother,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>James M. Welcker</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To <name>Charles F. Welcker</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="4" facs="mc046d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>postmark stamp: May 14, Knoxville, Ten.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <add>18</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mr. Charles F. Welcker</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Talladega</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Alabama</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Mail</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
