<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl737">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1796 Jul 7, Knoxville [Tennessee]   / John Sevier : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Sevier, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl737</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1796 Jul 7, Knoxville [Tennessee]   / John Sevier</title>
               <author> Sevier, John</author>
               <date when="1796-07-07">July 7, 1796</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Governor John Sevier dated July 7, 1796. The letter may be to the Cherokee Nation. Sevier writes that he is glad that they have signed a peace treaty. Sevier believes it to be the best thing for the survival of the Natives. He also writes that according to the treaty the Natives should be returning some people to the U.S. that have been held prisoner.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor John Sevier Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">B</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl737</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Indians of North America -- treaties</term>
               <term>Sevier, John, 1745-1815 Correspondence.</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr89016779"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Sevier, John, 1745-1815</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl737a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Knoxville</name>
                     <date>7 July 1796</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Friends &amp; brothers</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Since peace has taken place between us I shall always be happy to hear of your welfare_ I am rejoiced to find your people have seen their folly of going to war, and have concluded to keep deep under ground the hatchet and Scalping knife__ by such measures and conduct of your nation, you may become strong, numerous, and have all the good things you stand in need of.</p>
            <p>This letter will be delivered unto you by <name>Colonel Whitly</name> from_ the state of <name>Kentucky</name> who is going into your country to <del type="overstrike">hunt</del> See and get some white people, that some of your people took prisoners from that country some time ago, also to get some black people, that was taken from the same place, (a woman and three children that belonged to <name>General Logan</name> of that Country) now my brothers I shall earnestly expect that you will <choice>
                  <orig>immeadiately</orig>
                  <reg>immediately</reg>
               </choice> give up all these people, and let them be conveyed home to their own Country, which in our last treaty <pb n="2" facs="sl737b.small.jpg"/> of peace you have promised you would do; I shall also do the same, if any of your people is among us, but I know of none but one boy, who is now going to School and he told me a few days ago, that he did not want to go home until he could learn to read and write, which <del type="overstrike">I thought</del> was very good in him, and when ever he wants to return he shall be sent safe to you</p>
            <p>If <choice>
                  <orig>their</orig>
                  <reg>there</reg>
               </choice> is any more I dont know of them, I have but lately come <del type="overstrike">here</del>
               <add>into office</add> and am not acquainted with all things that have happened in the time of <name>governor Blount</name>
            </p>
            <p>Colonel whitly is a beloved warrior among the white people, and a friend of mine, I shall Expect your people will Treat him <del type="overstrike">well and</del> like a brother, as he does your people when they go to his home, and I shall hope to see him return safe with all his people, that he is now going after</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>your friend &amp; Brother</salute>
               <add> (<choice>
                     <abbr>signd</abbr>
                     <expan>signed</expan>
                  </choice>)</add>
               <signed>
                  <name>John Sevier</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
