<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc025">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Commission of John N. Westin to the Tennessee Militia] 1828
			 March / [signed by Sam Houston] : a machine-readable transcription of an
			 image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Mays</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno>sc025</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50036971</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Commission of John N. Westin to the Tennessee Militia] 1828
				March / [signed by Sam Houston]</title>
               <date when="1828-03">March 1828</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This document is a commission appointing John N.
				Westin First Lieutenant of the Kingston Rifle Company in the Tennessee Militia.
				It is signed March 1828, by Sam Houston, Governor of Tennessee.</note>
               <note type="Collection">Samuel Houston</note>
               <note type="Box">n/a</note>
               <note type="Folder"> MS-1217</note>
               <note type="Document">sc025</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Militia</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Tennessee History, Military</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc025a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>State of 
			 <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
            </head>
            <p>To all who shall see these presents...Greeting:</p>
            <p>Know ye, That reposing special trust and confidence in the
			 patriotism, valor, conduct and fidelity of 
			 <name type="person">John N. Westin</name> of the county of 
			 <name type="place">Roane</name> We commission him First Lieutenant of
			 the 
			 <name type="place">Kingston</name> Rifle Company attached to the
			 <unclear/> Regiment of the Militia of this State; and do authorize and
			 empower him to execute and fulfil the duties of Lieutenant as aforesaid in the
			 said Regiment, agreeably to law, and the rules and directions of Military
			 Discipline; to have and to hold the rank and command of Lieutenant as aforesaid
			 in the said Regiment, during good <choice>
                  <orig>behaviour</orig>
                  <reg>behavior</reg>
               </choice>, with
			 all the powers, privileges and emoluments thereto of right appertaining, And
			 the said John N. Westin is hereby required to obey his superior Officers'
			 lawful orders and commands, and all officers and privates under his command,
			 are to be obedient to him as aforesaid. </p>
            <p>In testimony whereof, We have caused the Great Seal of the State to
			 be hereunto affixed.</p>
            <p>Witness, 
			 <name> 
                  <reg>person</reg> Sam Houston</name>, Esquire, our Governor and
			 Commander in Chief, at 
			 <name> 
                  <reg>place</reg> Nashville</name>, the <gap agent="damage"/> day of 
			 <date>March</date> in the fifty second year of our
			 Independence, and and in the year 
			 <date when="1828">1828</date>.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>By the Governor</salute>
               <signed>Sam Houston</signed>
               <add place="left">
                  <name type="person">Daniel Graham</name>
               </add>
               <add place="bottom, center">Secretary of State</add>
            </closer>
            <pb n="2" facs="sc025b.small.jpg"/>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <p>I do solemnly swear, that I will support the Constitution of the
			 United States, and the State of Tennessee, and that I will faithfully discharge
			 the duties of the Militia of Tennessee, as prescribed by law, to the best of my
			 abilities.</p>
            <p>Sworn to and subscribed before me, this </p>
            <p>
               <gap agent="damage"/> day of <gap agent="damage"/>
            </p>
            <p>I, <gap agent="damage"/> do solemnly <gap agent="damage"/> that I will
			 not give or accept a challenge, either written or verbal, to fight a duel-nor
			 will I be the bearer of a challenge for such purpose-nor will I fight a duel,
			 nor be second to fight a duel, during my continuance in office, so help me
			 GOD.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
