<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0214">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1813 July 23, Creek Path [to] Colonel Return J. Meigs, Highwassee / Kanchestaneskee et al. : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Kanchestaneskee</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0214</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 45869546</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1813 July 23, Creek Path [to] Colonel Return J. Meigs, Highwassee / Kanchestaneskee et al.  </title>
               <author>Kanchestaneskee</author>
               <date when="1813-07-23">July 23, 1813</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document appears to be a letter to Return J. Meigs dated July 23, 1813 composed by several Cherokee chiefs at the request of Pathkiller, the principal chief, to inform Meigs of the growing Creek civil war. The letter tells that the town of Tooquachee (Toocabatchee) in the Creek Nation, where four different tribes of Indians once held friendly conferences, has been taken from Creek chief Big Warrior and destroyed. While Big Warrior is considered a "friendly" Creek, the letter states that the majority of Creek Nation has gone against him to join the rebel party. The Cherokees indicate that they have information that one of the prophets partly responsible for the uprising has escaped to the Choctaw Nation. Included is a warning from Big Warrior to the Cherokees to arm themselves against the rebellious Creeks along their borders.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> pa0214</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Cherokee Indians</term>
               <term>Creek War, 1813-1814</term>
               <term>Tookabatchee (Ga.)</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Warfare</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Kanchestaneskee</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0214a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Creek Path</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>July 23rd, 1813</date>
               <salute>Brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>This is wrote from the request of Your Friend &amp; Brother the <name>Pathkiller</name> (our chief) to acquaint you <del type="overstrike">of</del> with the rebellion in the <name>Creek Nation</name>, the principal Town <name>Tooquachee (Toocabatchee)</name> of the Creek Nation where four different tribes of Indians generally had their friendly conferences, is now destroyed &amp; taken from the <name>Big Warrior</name>, the principle chief thereof, by the rebellious &amp; hostile party of the that Nation. They <del type="overstrike">have broke</del>
               <add>are endeavoring to</add>
               <choice>
                  <orig>brake</orig>
                  <reg>break</reg>
               </choice> the chain of friendship between <del type="overstrike">that &amp;</del> the <name>U.S</name>. &amp; that Nation-The Big Warrior together with all the friendly Indians have dispersed from <name>Too,ca,batch,ee</name>  to the <name>Cowata</name> &amp; <name>Caseta</name> Towns, &amp; it is said that the greatest body of the <add>the</add> Creek Nation have joined <pb n="2" facs="pa0214b.small.jpg"/> the rebellious party. the <choice>
                  <orig>Scrimages</orig>
                  <reg>Scrimmages</reg>
               </choice> which <add>have</add> taken place between them appears to terminate to the Success &amp; <choice>
                  <orig>honour</orig>
                  <reg>honor</reg>
               </choice> of the friendly party-as it is stated that only 5 have been killed on the friendly side &amp; 43 on the <del type="overstrike">other</del> Rebellious side, It appears that <del type="overstrike">our</del>
               <add>the</add> situation <add>of our villages</add> on <add>the</add> borders of the Creek Nation is not altogether safe, as we <add>have</add> been advised by the Big Warrior &amp; his friendly Chiefs, to furnished ourselves with guns. <del type="overstrike">&amp; be on our guard for fear that the</del> to be guarded against the rebellious <name>Creeks</name> , that they should be suppressed, in case an attempt to invade our Country-a number of Creeks of the Notchy tribe have come to <name>Turkey's Town</name>  for refuge from the <choice>
                  <orig>mercyless</orig>
                  <reg>merciless</reg>
               </choice> rebels their friendly <unclear>
                  <del type="overstrike">&amp;</del>
               </unclear> disposition <del type="overstrike">for a continuation</del> towards the U.S. appears to be <del type="overstrike">firm</del> usually firm, their number consists of nearly 200 men besides their women &amp; Children. we hope <del type="overstrike">you</del> the White People will not think that we have <del type="overstrike">taken</del> suffered those Indians to come amongst us with any hostile intentions towards <pb n="3" facs="pa0214c.small.jpg"/> them as they are part of those who have suffered their friends &amp; relations to spill their blood in giving <choice>
                  <orig>sattisfaction</orig>
                  <reg>satisfaction</reg>
               </choice> to the US. for the murder which was committed on the <name>Ohio</name>_</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your Friends &amp; Brothers</salute>
               <lb/> } Chiefs <lb/>
               <signed>
                  <name>Kan,che,stan,es,kee X mark</name>
                  <name>Was,sa,see X mark</name>
                  <name>Richard R <add>his mark</add>Brown</name>
                  <name>Bear Meat x mark</name>
               </signed>
               <lb/>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N.B.</abbr>
                     <expan>Nota Bene</expan>
                  </choice> One of false prophets who have <del type="overstrike">have</del> seduced those deluded Creeks, is said to be killed, another is said to <add>be </add> gone toward the <name>Choctaws</name>_</add> at the request of the Big Warrior &amp; others, we have wrote <add>to</add> the <name>Chickasaws</name> requesting <add>them</add> to make it known to the choctaws &amp; that in case he should make his appearance amongst <add>them</add> to put him to death_</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1">
            <pb n="4" facs="pa0214d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>An address from Path Killer &amp; other Chiefs relating to the Creek civil war dated 23rd July 1813</p>
            <p>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Colonel Return J Meigs</name> Agent for <name>Cherokees </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Highwassee</addrLine>
               </address>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
