<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl041">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1829 May 15, Washington [to] Reverend Herdy M. Gryer / Andrew Jackson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Jackson, Andrew</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl041</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50029506</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1829 May 15, Washington [to] Reverend Herdy M. Gryer / Andrew Jackson </title>
               <author>Jackson, Andrew</author>
               <date when="1829-05-15">May 15, 1829</date>
               <extent> 4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated May 15, 1829 from President Andrew Jackson to the Reverend Herdy M. Gryer. Jackson discusses the many applicants he has for the new administration and how much he misses his late wife Rachel.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Tennessee Historical Society</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">Miscellaneous documents J1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">37J</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl041</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>United States -- Politics and government -- 1825-1829</term>
               <term>Jackson, Rachel Donelson, 1767-1828</term>
               <term>United States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79088888"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl041a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Washington</name>
                     <date when="1829-05-15">May 15th 1829</date>—</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My <choice>
                     <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                     <expan>Dear</expan>
                  </choice> Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your kind letter of the 20th <choice>
                  <abbr>ult,,</abbr>
                  <expan>ultimo</expan>
               </choice> has been some days before me—The great press of business has prevented me from attending to it sooner, and even now I can only say to you as it regards our mutual friend <name type="person">Mr Gwinn</name> that he had better remain where he is, <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> you hear from me again. There is more distressed people here, than any person could imagine who were not an eye witness to the various applications for relief— My feelings have been severely <choice>
                  <orig>coroded</orig>
                  <reg>corroded</reg>
               </choice> by the various applications for relief, and as far as real charitable objects presented themselves, I have  yielded my might to their relief — Would you believe it, that a lady who once rolled in wrath, but whose husband was over taken by <pb n="2" facs="sl041b.small.jpg"/> misfortune &amp; reduced to want, and is &amp; has been an applicant for office, &amp; well recommended, applied to me with tears in her eyes, soliciting relief, assuring me that her children was starving, &amp; to buy them a morsel of bread she had to sell her thimble the day before— an office I had not to give &amp; my cook was nearly out, but I could not withhold from⁁<add place="supralinear">her half</add>
               <del type="overstrike">half</del>of the pittance I had with me. I name these things to bring your mind, that the extravagance of this place, how small a prospect is <emph>$1000</emph>
               <choice>
                  <abbr> pr </abbr>
                  <expan>per</expan>
               </choice> anum for the support of a family here, &amp; the moment they are out of office, starvation presents itself to the view—</p>
            <p>We have not had leisure yet, to make the necessary arrangements of reform— we are progressing, and such is the press for office, &amp; the distress here, that there are for the place of messengers (for the Departments) at least twenty  applicants for each station, and <pb n="3" facs="sl041c.small.jpg"/> many applicants who have been men of wealth &amp; respectability— Still if our friend Gwinn <del type="overstrike">still</del> wishes to come on here, when we finally <choice>
                  <orig>organise</orig>
                  <reg>organize</reg>
               </choice> the Departments, and turn out the spurs from our camp, I will preserve an office for him— but we are now having a thorough investigation, into the situation of all  the Departments, and the inquiry will be made how many, if any clerks, can be dispensed with.</p>
            <p>I wrote my overseer the other day on the subject of sending my mares to Stockholder— I would like to hear how many colts I have from <name type="person">Sir William</name>— I learn that the cotton mare &amp; <name type="person">Major Donelsons</name>, has not proved with food. </p>
            <p>In the day I am laboriously employed, and it is only when late in the night I retire to my chamber, that I have time to think of, or write to, my friends—  it is then I feel the great weight of the late affliction <pb n="4" facs="sl041d.small.jpg"/> of providence in the bereavement I have been visited with in the loss of my dear wife, I find myself a solitary mourner, depraved of all hope of happiness this side of the grave, and often wish myself at the Hermitage there to spend the remnant of my days, &amp; daily drop a tear on the tomb of my beloved wife, &amp; be prepared, when providence wills it, to unite with her in the realms above— But providence has otherwise<del type="overstrike">willed it &amp;</del>⁁ <add place="supralinear">ordered</add> to his will I must submit.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>present me affectionately to your amiable wife &amp; family &amp; believe me <choice>
                     <abbr>yr</abbr>
                     <expan>your</expan>
                  </choice> friend</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <emph>Andrew Jackson</emph>
                  </name>
               </signed>
               <add place="below signature">The <choice>
                     <abbr>Revd</abbr>
                     <expan>Reverend</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <name type="person">Herdy M. Cryer</name>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
