<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um082">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1842 Nov. 13, Columbia, Tennessee [to] Col[onel] R[obert] J Chester, Jackson, Tennessee / M[ary] J[ane] Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um082</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50316853</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1842 Nov. 13, Columbia, Tennessee [to] Col[onel] R[obert] J Chester, Jackson, Tennessee / M[ary] J[ane] Chester</title>
               <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
               <date when="1842-11-13">November 13, 1842</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by Mary Jane Chester to her father, Robert J. Chester, on November 13, 1842. In the letter Mary Jane tells Robert of events going on in Columbia, Tennessee, where she is attending school at the Female Institute, and inquires about events happening at home in Jackson. She tells him how upset she is that he did not visit her when he promised, and she also speaks of their cousin's new baby, visiting with Governor Polk, and the death of her mother. Mary Jane concludes the letter by asking him to bring her a black muslin when he comes to visit her.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers MS 25 (January-December 1842)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">10</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um082</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Mary Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um082a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1842-11-13">13th <choice>
                           <abbr>Nov.</abbr>
                           <expan>November</expan>
                        </choice> 1842</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Father,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I received yours of the 5th <choice>
                  <abbr>Ult.</abbr>
                  <expan>Ultimo</expan>
               </choice> with very great pleasure, and hasten to answer it, as some time has elapsed since I last wrote, knowing that you would have an opportunity of hearing from me of <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Gov.</abbr>
                     <expan>Governor</expan>
                  </choice> Polk</name>, I thought it not necessary to write before. I saw him a day or two  <choice>
                  <sic>before before</sic>
                  <corr>before</corr>
               </choice> he left, he said that he would call to see me, and carry a letter, but I suppose that he either was in too great a hurry or forgot it.</p>
            <p>You cannot imagine how much disappointment I felt when <name type="person">Cousin  Sam</name> received your letter saying that you could not make it convenient to visit me at the time you intended. I had promised myself the happiness <emph>that saturday</emph>, (for you remember it is the day that you <emph>told</emph> me to look for you) of seeing you and hearing from your own <emph>mouth</emph> how all at home were. I begin to feel impatient to see you. so do, as soon as you return  from <name type="place">Memphis</name>, come up to see me. <pb n="2" facs="um082b.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>I am happy to hear that my Brothers are so well supplied with their winter clothing; indeed I have experienced <choice>
                  <orig>eneough</orig>
                  <reg>enough</reg>
               </choice> of my dear Aunts kindness myself to know that they will supply as much as is in their power the <emph>dreadful loss</emph> of our Beloved Mother. I <choice>
                  <orig>feell</orig>
                  <reg>feel</reg>
               </choice>
               <emph>very</emph> grateful to them, and always shall for the great interest that they have taken in us. I have the pleasure of informing ⁁ <add place="supralinear">you of the</add>
               <emph>arrival</emph> of another little stranger in <name type="person">Cousin Elens</name> family. he about three weeks old, they have named him Sam, he is a very sweet little baby.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Cousin Jane</name> started to <name type="place">Arkansas</name> last week. We all miss her company very much. she will not return until next summer. Tell Sister that I shall answer her <emph>kind</emph> letter very soon, and that I hope she will continue to write me often, as you and her are the ⁁ <add place="supralinear">only</add> ones of my relations that write to me at all. I think that you ought to write me very often. Indeed I have become weary of asking <name type="person">Brother John</name>.</p>
            <p>Give my best love to all my relations, and kiss little <name type="person">Willie B</name> — and <name type="pereson">Sam</name>.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your ever affectionate Daughter</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>M. J.</abbr>
                        <expan>Mary Jane</expan>
                     </choice> Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="below signature">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P. S.</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> I have sent to <name type="place">Nashville</name> by <name type="person">Cousin Knox</name> for a Shawl. Cousin Jane purchased a very pretty one for 8$.  Mine will be of the same kind. I tell you that, for fear that you would bring one. I should be pleased if you could bring me a nice Black Muslin de Lane, when you come, get it in Nashville that is I believe the only article that I shall need this winter. I have concluded to <choice>
                     <orig>weare</orig>
                     <reg>wear</reg>
                  </choice> my old <choice>
                     <orig>Bonnit</orig>
                     <reg>Bonnet</reg>
                  </choice>, &amp; get a new one next <pb n="3" facs="um082c.small.jpg"/> Spring.</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="um082d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="above address">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>post mark seal</figDesc>
                  </figure> 18</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Col R</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel Robert</expan>
                        </choice> J Chester</name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson</name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address, upside down" rend="different hand, ink">My Dear Mary Jane <lb/>
                  <date when="1842-11-13">13 <choice>
                        <abbr>Nov.</abbr>
                        <expan>November</expan>
                     </choice> 1842</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
