<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc175">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>  [Land Grant] 1827 Nov. 24, Nashville, Tennessee [for] William Polk / Sam Houston: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Houston, Sam</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc175</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Land Grant] 1827 Nov. 24, Nashville, Tennessee [for] William Polk / Sam Houston</title>
               <author> Houston, Sam</author>
               <date when="1827-11-24"> 
			 November 24, 1827</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a land grant dated November 24, 1827, signed by Governor Sam Houston. It gives three acres of Haywood County to William Polk, assignee of  H. Trott, H.D. McBroom, and James Barkley.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Sam Houston Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS 365</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc175</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Land Grants</term>
               <term>Houston, Sam, 1793-1863</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n82151189"
                        role="Autographer http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ato">Houston, Sam, 1793-1863.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc175a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>State of <name>Tennessee</name> --- <choice>
                        <abbr>No</abbr>
                        <expan>Number</expan>
                     </choice> 819</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>To all to whom these presents shall come... Greeting:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Know ye, That By virtue of Certificate No 6698 dated the <date>20th day of September 1824</date> Issued by the Register of West Tennessee to <name>H Trott</name>, <name>H.D. McBroom</name> and <name>James Barkley</name> for three acres and Entered on the <date>3d day of May 1825</date> by No 1712 there is granted by the said State of Tennessee, unto <name>William Polk</name> assignee of said Trott, Broom, &amp; <add>Barkley</add> a certain tract or parcel of Land, containing three acres by Survey bearing date the <date>19th day of January 1827</date> lying in the Tenth District in <name>Haywood County</name> in range four and Section six and bounded as follows (to wit) Beginning at a Stake the South East Corner of R. Hightowers 18 acre entry on C. Jones West boundary line Thence South fifteen and a half poles to a Stake in the <choice>
                  <orig>bason</orig>
                  <reg>basin</reg>
               </choice> with two white Oaks and a small beech pointers. Thence west thirty one poles to a stake. Thence north fifteen <del type="overstrike">and</del> and a half poles to a stake. on Hightowers line. Thence East thirty one poles to the Beginning <pb n="2" facs="sc175b.small.jpg"/> With the hereditaments and <choice>
                  <orig>appertenances</orig>
                  <reg>appurtenances</reg>
               </choice> To Have And To Hold the said tract or parcel of Land, with its appertenances, to said William Polk and his heirs forever.</p>
            <p>In witness whereof <add>
                  <name>Sam Houston</name>
               </add>
               <del type="overstrike">William Carroll,</del> Governor of the State of Tennessee, hath hereunto set his hand, and caused the Great Seal of the State to be affixed, at <name>Nashville</name>, on the <date>24th day of November</date> in the year of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and twenty Seven, and of the Independence of the <name>United States</name> the 52d By the Governor.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sam Houston</signed>
               <add>Secretary <lb/>
                  <name>David Graham</name>, <lb/> Secretary</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sc175c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Recorded in the Registers office of the western District <date>July 30th 1828</date>. <lb/>
                  <name>A.G. Neilson</name> Register <lb/> of the western District</add>
               <add>No 819 <lb/> William Polk <lb/> 3 Acres <lb/> Tenth District</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sc175d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>William Polk is entitled to the within mentioned tract of land.___ <lb/> A.G. Neilson Register of the Western District</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
