<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0018">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1806 Feb. 17, Chickamaga [to] Return J. Meigs / Pathkiller and John Lowrey : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Pathkiller</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>pa0018</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1806 Feb. 17, Chickamaga [to] Return J. Meigs / Pathkiller</title>
               <author>Pathkiller</author>
               <date when="1806-02-17">February 17, 1806</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written February 17th 1806 by Pathkiller, Principle Chief to the Cherokees and signed by John Lowrey. The letter is written to Return J. Meigs, Agent to the Cherokee. Pathkiller requests the help of Meigs to forcefully remove Dempsey Fields from the Cherokee Nation. Pathkiller also requests a doctors care for his people who have small pox.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0018</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Indian agents</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Claims against</term>
               <term>Small Pox</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Path Killer</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0018a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <orig>Chickamaga</orig>
                        <reg>Chickamauga</reg>
                     </choice>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Feby</abbr>
                           <expan>February</expan>
                        </choice>17th 1806</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Friend <choice>
                     <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <name>Meigs</name>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>My views for sending you this talk is to request you to use your authority <unclear>so as</unclear>
               <choice>
                  <orig>compell</orig>
                  <reg>compel</reg>
               </choice>
               <name>Dempsy Fields</name> to leave bounds of the <name>Cherokees</name>, he is guilty of all the charges given against <add>him</add> last fall at <choice>
                  <abbr>S.W. point</abbr>
                  <expan>South West Point</expan>
               </choice> &amp; more too, He has not only imposed on <name>John Lowrey</name> so as to give him his Daughter in Marriage, but has defrauded him out property to a considerable amount, He has left his wife &amp; three children in<choice>
                  <orig>Bunkom</orig>
                  <reg>Buncombe</reg>
               </choice> County (N.C.) by the information of <name>John Welsh</name> of said place, report says he left another in <name>Cumberland</name>, His conduct are very <choice>
                  <orig>agravating</orig>
                  <reg>aggravate</reg>
               </choice> to us, it has <pb n="2" facs="pa0018b.small.jpg"/>
               <sic>has</sic> the appearance of making game of us, He has been ordered out of the Nation but I find he still remains, he appears to defy your authority, by his refusal of going a step further than<name> Dick Fields</name>, I expect you will convince of his error, we never wish to <add place="supralinear">see</add> him again in our country. I am much in earnest in this request &amp; beg you will not listen to the talks of any that may take his part I view him as a dangerous man, he has confessed that Dick Fields proposed the plan of <choice>
                  <orig>runing</orig>
                  <reg>running</reg>
               </choice> off horses, one to take &amp; the other to find sale for them, this is one of my reasons among many for wishing him <choice>
                  <orig>intirely</orig>
                  <reg>entirely</reg>
               </choice> away. I am much surprised that Major Lovely should step forward in <choice>
                  <orig>defence</orig>
                  <reg>defense</reg>
               </choice> , of Fields, by <choice>
                  <orig>recommeding</orig>
                  <reg>recommending</reg>
               </choice> him to favour, he has opposed your intentions of sending <sic>a way</sic>
               <pb n="3" facs="pa0018c.small.jpg"/> away, Friend the small pox are spreading through nation &amp; is got as low as <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                     <expan>Mister</expan>
                  </choice> Browns</unclear> , do Friend procure as quick as possible some of the cowpox &amp; send it to <name>Mr. Ross</name> with out loss of time, we wish a Doctor to come on also possibly some of the Doctors of <name>Knoxville</name> or <name>Maryville</name> May be in position of the matter, if <add place="supralinear">not</add> procure it from the North and by the Post in complying with this request you will be instrumental in Saving many lives,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>we are with much regard your friends &amp;c</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Pathkiller</name> principle <add place="supralinear">chief</add>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Jno</abbr>
                        <expan>John</expan>
                     </choice>Lowry</name>
               </signed>
               <add>N.B. please to pay the bearer six dollars &amp; charge it to the Nation Be so kind as forward <unclear>Mr Blackburs </unclear> letter, without delay</add>
               <signed>Jno Lowry <lb/> Pathkiller</signed>
               <name>Col. Meigs</name>}<pb n="4" facs="pa0018d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Pathkiller &amp; J. Lowry's letter. Small Pox, Dempsey Fields &amp;c. <date>February 17th 1806</date>
                  <name>Mr Ross</name>letter by<name> Lontee</name> a young Cherokee</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
