<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl644">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1836 Sep. 9, Jasper, Tennessee [to] Newton Cannon, Nashville, Tennessee / John C. Haley : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Haley, John C.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl644</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> 1836 Sep. 9, Jasper, Tennessee [to] Newton Cannon, Nashville, Tennessee / John C. Haley</title>
               <author> Haley, John C.</author>
               <date when="1836-09-09"> 
			 September 9, 1836</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from John C. Haley to Governor Newton Cannon, dated September 9, 1836. Haley has begun to clear the Tennessee River of it's obstructions. He writes that the payment he has received so far is not enough.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Newton Cannon Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl644</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee River</term>
               <term>Business enterprises</term>
               <term>Cannon, Newton, 1781-1841</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Haley, John C.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl644a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Jasper</name>
                     <name>Marion County</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>E.</abbr>
                        <expan>East</expan>
                     </choice> Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To his excellency <name>Newton Cannon</name> Governor of the State of <name>Tennessee</name>__</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>It appears that you thought it most advisable to have a call session for the year 1836. I presume it is generally known throughout Tennessee that myself and son removed the first rocks for steam Boat navigation at the Suck and Boiling Pot in the <name>Tennessee River</name> in the years 1831 and 2 on our own private <choice>
                  <orig>funs</orig>
                  <reg>funds</reg>
               </choice> and it has so turned out that we have never received the first cent It is true that the commissioners offered us $1421-75 for the work done by us at those rapids in the year 1831- We refused to accept that sum because it fell short of paying <add>us</add> and the work done by us in 1832 left out_ Believing it was the design of the Legislature to pay us what would be right_ We appealed to the call session of 1832 the honorable members passed a special act for our benefit on <date>19th of october 1832</date> making it the duty of <name>R.P. Baker</name> and <name>David A. Dedrick</name> to meet us at those <pb n="2" facs="sl644b.small.jpg"/> rapids and settle with us for all the work done by us in the years 1831 and 1832 with interest on our money_ We accordingly notified Baker and Dedrick to meet us in behalf of the state and settle with us accordingly to the act but those commissioners refused to meet and act on the part of the state_ We trust that the pride of the state will not suffer our claim to pass off in this way_ In your address to both houses of the Legislature should you deem it advisable to recommend some course whereby our claim can be settled and <choice>
                  <orig>despensed</orig>
                  <reg>dispensed</reg>
               </choice> with the favor will be acknowledged at all times by me_</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>John C. Haley</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <date>September 9th 1836</date>
               </add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl644c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To His Excellency Newton Cannon</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Governor of the State of Tennessee</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>pr. mail</add>
               <add>John C. Haley</add>
               <add>1836 <lb/> claims for <lb/> Improvement <lb/> of the Tennessee <lb/> River,</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
