<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl199">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1837 Oct. 1, Plain Dealing [to] Sarah M. Claybrooke / John S. Claybrooke   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Claybrooke, John S.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl199</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51196923</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1837 Oct. 1, Plain Dealing [to] Sarah M. Claybrooke / John S. Claybrooke</title>
               <author>Claybrooke, John S.  </author>
               <date when="1837-10-01">October 1, 1837</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated October 1, 1837 to Sarah M. Claybrooke from her brother John Claybrooke. John writes to the family that he and his wife just had a son and cannot decide what to name him. He also writes about his small farm in Tennessee.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl199</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Claybrooke, John S.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl199a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Plain Dealing</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date when="1837-10-01">October 1, 1837</date>
               <salute>My Dear Sisters,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>On several of my last letters to <name type="place">Brookville</name>, I made a promise, or mentioned, that I would write to you in some short time, in case <name type="person">Mary</name>'s health, did not permit her writing to you. The state of her mind, rendered so, by her peculiar situation, unfitted her for anything  like social correspondence, though she frequently expressed a wish to write to you, yet she never carried her desire into execution, therefore at this time I write at her request and in her behalf, and situated as she  has been for more than three months, with a greater or less degree of uneasiness pressing her mind, she, I know, will be excusable with you, who have charity abundant enough, to overlook even faults, much like reasonable excuses. Now her trouble is  over she <gap agent="damage"/> will? have no excuse. She has a fine looking boy, that was born on the <date when="--09-21">21st day of <choice>
                     <abbr>Sept.</abbr>
                     <expan>September</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date> She is setting up at present attending in a partial degree, to her <choice>
                  <orig>domestick</orig>
                  <reg>domestic</reg>
               </choice> concerns, and the little baby is quite hearty. We have not named it as yet, as we are at a loss, what name we shall adopt, being disposed to give him some name of which no little boy in the <name type="person">Perkin</name>'s family has the same. Three already, have been called after the grandfather, and you know, it is my disposition, to be a little different, and to depart from common customs, for to name him, John Samuel, would be after myself and after his two grandfathers; a name the least objectional, if it were not, the common custom. I admire the name Charles or Frederick, <choice>
                  <sic>and and</sic>
                  <corr>and</corr>
               </choice> as ⁁ <add place="supralinear">an</add> evidence thereof, I call all my horses Charley, without <choice>
                  <orig>acception</orig>
                  <reg>exception</reg>
               </choice> .</p>
            <p>I propose then to call him Frederick, rather than Charles, so as <pb n="2" facs="sl199b.small.jpg"/> to distinguish and rather to prevent confounding the name of horses and human beings on the same plantation (excuse me for occupying time &amp; space with reasons, already too tedious)</p>
            <p>I received by last mail, a letter from brother, which informs me of the safe arrival of <name type="person">Thomas</name> at Brookville. I was truly sorry to hear of his indisposition, but I hope he has recovered long before this time, and he has been enjoying himself, in the society of those with whom he formerly lived. I wrote to not to hurry himself back, that all things which concerned him here, were going on well. I got a letter from Miss <name type="person">Patsy Noel</name> this morning, she informs me all things are going on well at Brooklia, and the negroes in good health. <name type="person">Dr Stith</name> lost one of his <choice>
                  <orig>likliest</orig>
                  <reg>likeliest</reg>
               </choice> young fellows. Tell Thomas at his plantation near Brooklia His overseer <unclear/> too much I expect <gap agent="damage"/> a great many sick. I am getting tired of being confined, so closely at home, I shall leave home, as I have some business abroad that needs my attention, when I shall leave home, I unable at present to say.</p>
            <p>Brother mentioned something about a revisal of Campbellism among the <choice>
                  <orig>neighbours</orig>
                  <reg>neighbors</reg>
               </choice>. O, how strange it is to look back and behold what changes take place in the world! But a few short years ago, I was a student at school, at the gate near <name type="person">Mr. Harris'</name>, now I am in <name type="place">Tennessee</name>, living at a house of my own, and have charge of a small family, with all the cares &amp; responsibilities attending it. Thomas no doubt has told you, how I have <choice>
                  <orig>laboured</orig>
                  <reg>labored</reg>
               </choice> and expended money to have every comfort and convenience about me, which this country affords. I have a beautiful little farm, rather a <pb n="3" facs="sl199c.small.jpg"/> source of amusement and expense, than a matter of profit. I would say of it ; that it is just such a summer retreat, as would suit a wealthy <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Louisiania</orig>
                     <reg>Louisiana</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> planter.  It does not suit a poor man like myself for it consumes all my time &amp; income in keeping up appearances. You know I am fond of <unclear>pleasing my eye, even at a ? <gap agent="damage"/> price.</unclear> Now I feel, that I would feel; that I was fully compensated for expense &amp; trouble, if the family at Brookville could spend one short year with me, and enjoy themselves in these strange woods. Tell father, I am glad to hear he enjoys such fine health, I am in hopes yet, he will visit Tennessee.</p>
            <p>Crops of corn &amp; cotton are worse in this neighbourhood than they were ever known to be. Crops in the District are <gap agent="damage"/> have been picking out cotton about two weeks. Cottons opens slowly. I have employed an overseer for next year at $150. The same man I had when Thomas was here. I expect to start to the District in 3 weeks. Hoping these lines may find you enjoying the blessing of health is ⁁ <add place="supralinear">the</add> prayer of your brother. Mary unites with  me in sending her love to you, and every member of the family. You must write often to me, and I will answer all your letters with great pleasure, Though I am not in the habit of writing, in the night time, as formerly, owing to the want of eyesight, and thereby, am deprived of one of my greatest earthly enjoyments, I mean corresponding with my friends.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Yr.</abbr>
                     <expan>Your</expan>
                  </choice> Brother affectionately</salute>.<signed>
                  <name type="person">John S. Claybrooke</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl199d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top portion and bottom portion of address page">
                  <note>
                     <p>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>N.B.</abbr>
                           <expan>Nota Bene</expan>
                        </choice> Tell <name type="person">James</name> &amp; <name type="person">Sally O.</name> I wish they were here, with their <name type="person">Aunt Mary</name> &amp; <name type="person">Uncle John</name> to keep us company, for I know of nothing at present, that would afford me more pleasure than the society of some of my own kindred.</p>
                     <p>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>P.S.</abbr>
                           <expan>Post Script</expan>
                        </choice>  Send us a name for our little boy, or let us know how you like Charley or Frederick } as we have not named him yet.</p>
                  </note>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Via <name type="place">Washington City</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Miss Sarah M. Claybrooke</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Pottiesville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Louisa County</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Virginia</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>mail }</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
