<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc067">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Book] 1793, A Short Description of the Tennassee [Tennessee] Government :a
                    machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Carey, Mathew</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sc067</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51317366</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of
                        Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
                        teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
                        included in the text. For all other use contact the Special Collections
                        Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue,
                        Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Book] 1793, A Short Description of the Tennassee [Tennessee]
                        Government</title>
               <author>Carey, Mathew</author>
               <date when="1793">1793</date>
               <extent>20p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a book
                        titled "A Short Description of the Tennassee (Tennessee) Government" and was
                        written in 1793. The term 'Government' can be understood to refer to the
                        term 'state' or 'area'. The book discusses many aspects of Tennessee,
                        including topics concerning the land and the livelihood of the inhabitants
                        of the various areas of the state. The topics covered in the book that
                        discuss the topography of the land include rivers, climate, plants, animals,
                        and land and soil composition. The book also discusses how the inhabitants
                        of Tennessee farmed their land, used the rivers to gain access to supplies,
                        and related with the Indian tribes in the state.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">A Short Description of the Tennassee
                        Government</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">F436.S65</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc067</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1
                    spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward
                    which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Books</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Description and travel</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50035124"
                        role="Printer http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/prt">Carey, Mathew, 1760-1839</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc067a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>A <lb/> SHORT DESCRIPTION <lb/> OF THE <lb/>
               <choice>
                  <orig/>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice> GOVERNMENT <lb/>
               <date when="1793">1793</date>
               <pb n="2" facs="sc067b.small.jpg"/>SHORT DESCRIPTION <lb/> OF THE <lb/>
               <choice>
                  <orig/>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice> GOVERNMENT,
                    <lb/> OR THE <lb/>
               <name type="place">TERRITORY <lb/> OF THE <lb/>
                  <name type="place">UNITED STATES</name>
                  <lb/> SOUTH OF THE RIVER OHIO</name>, <lb/> TO ACCOMPANY AND EXPLAIN A <lb/>
                    MAP OF THAT COUNTRY. <lb/>—<lb/>
               <name type="place">PHILADELPHIA</name>: <lb/> PRINTED BY <name type="person">MATHEW CAREY</name>, BOOKSELLER, <lb/> No. 118, HIGH-STREET.
                    <lb/>—<lb/> — <date when="1793">1793</date> —</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="sc067c.small.jpg"/>
            <head>A<lb/> SHORT DESCRIPTION, <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c.</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice>
            </head>
            <p>THE <choice>
                  <orig/>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice> government,
                    or the territory of the United States, south of the river Ohio, is that tract of
                    country, which was ceded to the United States by the state of <choice>
                  <orig/>
                  <reg>North Carolina</reg>
               </choice>, in the
                    year 1789. It is situated between the parallels of 35 degrees and 36 degrees 30
                    minutes, extending from the great Iron mountain to the river <name type="place">Mississippi</name>.</p>
            <p>WHEN we cast our eyes on the map of any country, especially the map of a new
                    country, in which little else is seen than the situation of mountains, rivers,
                    and plains, we are desirous to know what is the state of its soil and climate;
                    what are the advantages its inhabitants may be expected to enjoy, or the
                    difficulties under which they must <choice>
                  <orig>labour</orig>
                  <reg>labor</reg>
               </choice>. A general
                    answer to these questions, as they respect the <choice>
                  <orig>Tennassee</orig>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice> government, is the object of this publication.</p>
            <p>WE discover, at first sight, that the southern territory is cut into eastern and
                    western divisions, by Cumberland mountain, a ridge near thirty miles broad; and
                    it is probable, that the commercial <choice>
                  <orig>connexions</orig>
                  <reg>connections</reg>
               </choice> of
                    people who live in the eastern division, may be different <pb n="4" facs="sc067d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top of page">(4)</add> from those of the western inhabitants. The
                    great island on the Holston river, is not <choice>
                  <orig>abve</orig>
                  <reg>above</reg>
               </choice> 340
                    miles from <name type="place">Richmond</name> in <name type="place">Virginia</name>, along a good <choice>
                  <orig>waggon</orig>
                  <reg>wagon</reg>
               </choice> road, whence
                    we may conclude that the settlers on Holston will preserve a considerable
                    intercourse with the Atlantic states: but people who live to the westward of
                    Cumberland mountain, will send their produce to market by means of the
                    Mississippi. This remarkable difference in their situation will probably induce
                    the inhabitants of those districts to employ themselves differently, for the
                    most proper or profitable productions in one settlement, may not be most
                    profitable in the other.</p>
            <p>THE Holston settlement contains 28,649 inhabitants, though in the year <date when="1775">1775</date> it hardly contained 2000. The land in this
                    settlement is generally fertile; but the face of the country is much broken.
                    Placed, as it is, between two large mountains, we may readily suppose that the
                    farmer never suffers by the want of rain. The soil produces wheat, barley,
                    Indian corn, hemp, and flax, in great perfection. Physicians have not hitherto
                    found their way to that country, for the people have not been sick. They enjoy a
                    temperate climate, ease, and abundance.</p>
            <p>IRON ore abounds in that country. A capital furnace and forge have lately been
                    erected on Holston, near the Virginia line. There is a bloomery below the mouth
                    of <choice>
                  <orig>Wataga</orig>
                  <reg>Watauga</reg>
               </choice>, and another 25 miles above the mouth of
                    French Broad. There are also sundry leadmines in the settlement, one in
                    particular on French Broad river, that produces seventy five <choice>
                  <orig>per cent</orig>
                  <reg>percent</reg>
               </choice> in pure lead.</p>
            <p>THE greatest part of the <choice>
                  <orig>Tennassee</orig>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice> government lies
                    on the west side of Cumberland mountain; and though that country has hardly been
                    settled ten years by civilized men, it naturally claims the greatest share of
                    our attention, because it is extensive, and will probably become the residence
                    of a numerous and powerful colony.</p>
            <p>THE mean distance between Cumberland mountain and the Mississippi is about 230
                    miles. This, at 103 <pb n="5" facs="sc067e.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top of page">(5)</add> miles broad, gives fifteen millions of acres;
                    and it is generally agreed, that eleven or twelve millions of that land may be
                    cultivated to advantage; such is the proportion of arable land. The natives, who
                    formerly inhabited that country, must have been very numerous; we seldom go more
                    than five or six miles along the banks of Cumberland river, without finding a
                    large burying-place, the evident remains of a considerable town. As the Indians
                    had their choice of land, and do not appear to have been equally numerous in
                    other places, we may suppose they found this to be a soil on which they could
                    live with greatest ease.</p>
            <p>Of the Rivers.<lb/> FROM the face of the map it appears, that this country is
                    well intersected by rivers, and most of those rivers are navigable by large
                    boats; some of them by ships.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <orig>TENNASSEE</orig>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice> river is navigable by vessels of great
                    burden to the Muscle Shoals; those shoals are only to be passed in small boats
                    or batteaux; from the Muscle Shoals the river is navigable in boats of 40 or 50
                    tons burden, to the Virginia line.</p>
            <p>CUMBERLAND river is navigable in large vessels to <name type="place">Nashville</name>, and thence in boats to the mouth of Obas river.</p>
            <p>DUCK river is navigable in boats about 90 miles. The waters of Harpath,
                    Cany-fork, Stones, Roaring and Red river, have uniformly a gentle current
                    towards the mouth, whence they are all navigable in boats for a considerable
                    distance. In a word, no spot can be marked in that country, that is more than 20
                    miles from a boatable stream, so great are its advantages of
                    water-conveyance.</p>
            <p>THERE are five navigable rivers in this territory which discharge themselves
                    immediately into the Mississippi, <choice>
                  <abbr>viz</abbr>
                  <expan>to wit</expan>
               </choice>. Wolf,
                    Hatchee, Forked-deer, Obion, and Reel-foot. <pb n="6" facs="sc067f.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <add place="top of page">(6)</add> WOLF river, seven miles from the mouth, is
                    about 50 yards wide; Hatchee 80 yards; Forked-deer 60 yards; Obion 70 yards; and
                    Reel-foot 30 yards. These rivers in general are deep, and flow with a gentle
                    current, unincumbered with rocks or rapids, until they reach the barren or
                    broken tract in which they rise. Each of those rivers is bordered by a small
                    strip of low ground, 60 or 80 wards wide, and this again is terminated by a
                    gentle slope or secondary bank. In order to understand the use, perhaps the
                    cause of this remarkable circumstance, an inner and an outer bank to each of
                    those rivers, it should be remembered that the river Mississippi, during the
                    month of May, rises perpendicularly near 25 feet, at which season the low ground
                    on both sides of that river is covered with water, to the depth of 12 or 18
                    inches. This inundation, on the west side of the river extends to a great
                    distance, for the country seems to be lower in that direction, and some of the
                    waters of that river find their way to the ocean by other channels. On the east
                    side of the river, the inundation hardly extends above five miles; at that
                    distance the waters are restrained by a secondary bank, which runs parallel to
                    the general course of the river. This outer bank is properly the beginning of
                    high and dry land. It is obvious, that during those spring floods, the rivers,
                    which run into the Mississippi, must suffer a considerable interruption. Their
                    current is affected 10, 15, or 20 miles from the mouth, and they overflow their
                    banks. On those occasions, the secondary bank of those small rivers becomes
                    necessary, for it prevents the adjacent land from being overflowed, except the
                    narrow border above described. The industry of a small French colony at <name type="place">New Orleans</name> has given a sufficient proof that the
                    inundations of the Mississippi may be restrained by artificial banks, by which
                    means arable land has been and may be secured, that is hardly equaled in value
                    by any known lands, except in <name type="place">Egypt</name>. <pb n="7" facs="sc067g.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <add place="top of page">(7)</add>Of the Timber, Plants, Animals, <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c.</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice>
               <lb/> THE land on the waters of <choice>
                  <orig>Tennassee</orig>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice> and
                    Cumberland rivers is generally well timbered. In some places, there are glades
                    of rich land without timber; but these are not frequent nor large. The general
                    growth is popular, hickory, black-walnut, buck-eye, or the horse-<choice>
                  <orig>chesnut</orig>
                  <reg>chestnut</reg>
               </choice>, sycamore, locust, and the sugar-maple. The
                    under growth, in many places, is cane 15 or 20 feet high, so close together, as
                    to exclude all other plants; where the cane does not abound, we find red-bud,
                    wild-plumb, spice-wood, red and white mulberry, <choice>
                  <orig>gensang</orig>
                  <reg>ginseng</reg>
               </choice>, Virginia and <choice>
                  <orig>Seneka</orig>
                  <reg>Seneca</reg>
               </choice> snake-root,
                    angelica, sweet-anise, ginger, and wild-hops. The glades are covered with
                    clover, wild-rye, buffalo-grass, and peavine. On the hills, at the heads of
                    rivers, we find stately red-cedars; many of these trees are four feet in
                    diameter, and forty feet clear of limbs. In those hills there is abundance of
                    iron-ore, lead-ore, and coals. Copperas and alum fit for use have been gathered
                    in caves near Nashville.</p>
            <p>ON the rivers that run into the Mississippi, the growth is nearly the same as on
                    the waters of Cumberland river.</p>
            <p>IN speaking of a new country, that is extremely fertile and well covered with
                    herbage, it can hardly be necessary to say that it abounds in wild game. The
                    buffalo, elk, deer, and bear, are numerous, nor is there an scarcity of wolves,
                    panthers, wild-cats, foxes, beavers, and otters. They have pheasants, partridges
                    or quails, and <choice>
                  <orig>turkies</orig>
                  <reg>turkeys</reg>
               </choice> in abundance through the year.
                    During the winter, their waters are covered with the swan, wild-goose, brant,
                    and duck. Cat-fish have been caught in those rivers, that weighed above 100
                    pounds, and perch that weighed above 20 pounds. Nature seems to measure her
                    works on a different scale on the opposite sides of the <choice>
                  <orig>Apallachian</orig>
                  <reg>Appalachian</reg>
               </choice> mountains.</p>
            <p>IN the year <date when="1780">1780</date>, a small colony under the
                    direction of <name type="person">James Robertson</name>, crossed the mountain,
                    and settled <pb n="8" facs="sc067h.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top of page">(8)</add> on Cumberland river, at the place now called
                    Nashville. In year 1783, the state of <choice>
                  <orig>North-Carolina</orig>
                  <reg>North Carolina</reg>
               </choice> laid off a tract of land to be reserved for the
                    discharge of military bounties; this reservation included the infant colony, a
                    small tract having been allotted to each of the settlers. A county was also laid
                    off on those waters, called Davidson, to commemorate a brave and popular officer
                    who fell in the service of his country. The bounty lands were run off by
                    surveyors appointed for that purpose; and in a few years a considerable number
                    of the original grantees fold their titles to other persons, and the settlement
                    has lately been increasing very fast. There were 7000 people on that river in
                    September 1791, and their number, since that time, is much increased. We
                    frequently hear of emigrants from the parent state 2 or 300 at a time crossing
                    the mountain.</p>
            <p>Of the Soil. <lb/> THE farmers on Cumberland river, for the sake of describing
                    their lands, distinguish them by first, second, and third quality. Land of the
                    first quality will bear Indian corn or hemp; but it will not bear wheat without
                    great reduction. Land of the second quality does not bear wheat to advantage
                    until it has been reduced by two or three crops of corn, hemp, tobacco, or
                    cotton. Land of the third quality bears every kind of grain, that is usually
                    sown on dry ground, in the Atlantic states. It is agreed by all who have visited
                    the Cumberland settlement, that 100 bushels of Indian corn are frequently
                    gathered from an acre of their best land. Sixty or seventy bushels from an acre
                    is very common; but the farmer who expects to gather such a crop must be
                    careful, while the corn is soft, to guard it against bears and <choice>
                  <orig>racoons</orig>
                  <reg>raccoons</reg>
               </choice>. This, however, is a trouble that must cease
                    when the country is well settled. Wheat, barley, oats, rye, buckwheat, Indian
                    corn, <choice>
                  <orig>pease</orig>
                  <reg>peas</reg>
               </choice>, beans, potatoes of both forts, flax, hemp,
                    tobacco, indigo, rice, <pb n="9" facs="sc067i.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top of page">(9)</add> and cotton, have already been planted in that
                    settlement, and they all thrive in great perfection. The usual crop of cotton is
                    800 pounds to the acre; the staple is long and fine. It is alleged, however,
                    that the lands on the small rivers that run into the Mississippi, have a decided
                    preference to those on the Cumberland river, for the production of cotton and
                    indigo. No experiments have been made on land near the Mississippi, within the
                    ceded territory; but there is a small settlement further down the river, within
                    the limits of the United States, on a similar soil, where the growth and quality
                    of cotton is so remarkable, that its culture is more profitable than any other
                    crop. The soil on those rivers is deep and light, having a small mixture of sand
                    with a black earth; hence, as the planters allege, it proves <choice>
                  <orig>favourable</orig>
                  <reg>favorable</reg>
               </choice> to the culture of all kinds of roots, as
                    well as of indigo and cotton.</p>
            <p>Of the Climate.<lb/> THE climate in this country is very temperate; and the
                    experience of ten years assures us, that it is healthy. The piercing northerly
                    winds that prevail, during the winter, in the Atlantic states, seldom molest the
                    inhabitants on Cumberland river for they have no great mountains to the north or
                    the westward. The inhabitants of the Atlantic states are also subjected to
                    sudden changes in the atmosphere, arising from their vicinity to the ocean; the
                    air that comes from the surface of the sea, especially from the war Gulf-stream
                    in winter, must by very different in its temperature from the air that comes
                    across cold and high mountains; but the great distance between the Cumberland
                    settlers and the ocean, considering that many great mountains are interposed,
                    effectually secures them against the bad effects of those sudden changes.
                    North-easterly storms never reach this country. <lb/> B <pb n="10" facs="sc067j.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <add place="top of page">(10)</add> OTHER circumstances present themselves, by
                    which we may account for the remarkable healthiness of this settlement.
                    Lime-stone is common on both sides of Cumberland mountain. The bottom of a river
                    on the west side of the mountain, is frequently a continued stratum of this
                    rock. It is generally known that small streams of water are apt to disappear in
                    countries that abound in <choice>
                  <orig>lime-stone</orig>
                  <reg>limestone</reg>
               </choice>: this is
                    occasioned, doubtless, by the great fissures that are common in those rocks;
                    from the same cause it probably arises, that we seldom find marshes or stagnant
                    waters where there is much lime-stone. In this territory we find no stagnant
                    waters; and this is certainly one of the reasons why the inhabitants are not
                    afflicted with those bilious and intermitting fevers, which are so frequent, and
                    often fatal, in the same latitude near the coast in <name type="place">Carolina</name>. Whether it proceeds from the goodness of the water, the
                    purity of the air, the temperature of the climate, or whatever else may have
                    been the cause, the inhabitants of that country have certainly been remarkably
                    healthy, ever since they settled on the waters of Cumberland river, whence it
                    appears that the climate is healthy and pleasant.</p>
            <p>MEN frequently change their habitations in quest of a better place; and the man,
                    who can enjoy the greatest degree of health, ease, and plenty, is generally
                    supported to have the most desirable habitation. Keeping this remark in view,
                    perhaps there are few places that present fairer prospects to the man who is
                    looking for a settlement. Few places are more healthy; there is none more
                    fertile; and there is hardly any other place, in which the farmer can support
                    his family in such a degree of affluence. The soil is not only fertile, but
                    easily cultivated. Six hogsheads of tobacco for one man does not require more
                        <choice>
                  <orig>labour</orig>
                  <reg>labor</reg>
               </choice>, than three hogsheads in the Atlantic
                    states; and a difference similar to this appears in every other crop. In the
                    culture of corn, the difference is greater. This circumstance alone would secure
                    abundance to the industrious man; but we must <pb n="11" facs="sc067k.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top of page">11</add> also recollect, that, in cold climates, the
                    farmer is shut up or prevented from working several months in the year, during
                    which cold season he is consuming his stores, and his cattle are making greater
                    destruction. When we consider the quantity of food that must be laid up for the
                    necessary support of stock in cold climates, we may fairly calculate, that half
                    of the farmer's time is spent in making provision for his cattle, or in
                    sheltering himself from the weather. In the southern territory, cattle at
                    present support themselves among the reeds, pea-vines, rye-grass, and clover;
                    but when the progress os cultivation shall have destroyed the wild range, it is
                    obvious, that the sodder and straw obtained from the ordinary crops, will be
                    more than sufficient to support the cattle.</p>
            <p>LET us review this account. It is granted, that, in cold climates, more than half
                    of the farmer's time is lost from <choice>
                  <orig>labour</orig>
                  <reg>labor</reg>
               </choice> by intemperate
                    weather, or taken up in working for the support of his cattle; this gives an
                    odds of two to one in <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice> of the country that has
                    been described. We are next to recollect, that one day's <choice>
                  <orig>labour</orig>
                  <reg>labor</reg>
               </choice>, in this country, produces more than twice as much grain, or
                    other provisions, as it produces in common land, and in a northern climate; this
                    gives another difference of two to one, which makes four to one throughout the
                    year. But, considering that industry, in all countries, bears some proportion to
                    the necessities of the inhabitants, we shall suppose, that the farmer, in this
                    territory, during the year, raises only twice as much provision for his family,
                    as he could raise on common land in a colder climate; and the difference, as it
                    respects himself, must be immense. In this country, he would live in great
                    affluence, or become rich, by that measure of industry, which, in the other
                    situation, would hardly be sufficient to the support of a miserable life.</p>
            <p>PEOPLE, however, are seldom contented with the mere necessaries of life. There
                    are certain luxuries, which the progress of society has taught us to consider
                        <pb n="12" facs="sc067l.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top of page">12</add> as necessary. Sugar, coffee, and tea belong to
                    this class; as do sundry articles of foreign dress. What is the farmer to sell
                    in the western part of the <choice>
                  <orig>Tennassee</orig>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice> government,
                    that he may be enabled to buy foreign articles? He lives at a great distance
                    from sea; how is he to be provided with salt?</p>
            <p>IT is very remarkable, that the farmer has more use for salt in the western
                    country, than in the Atlantic states. His cattle, in that country, will not
                    thrive without salt; and this is the only thing, at present, he has occasion to
                    give them. It has already been observed, that limestone abounds in the western
                    country; this stone is not found in the southern states, until we approach the
                    first ridge of mountains. As we travel westward, we find lead ore and salt
                    springs in abundance. Does this country abound in articles that are seldom found
                    in the Atlantic states, because it is composed of the original mother earth;
                    whereas the land near the coast, in the middle and southern states, is
                    adventitious? Be this as it may, the salt-springs that are found in every part
                    of the western country, afford the utmost relief to the inhabitants, whose
                    cattle, from the quality of their food, have more need of salt than those who
                    are nearer the sea. Hitherto the salt-works have not been judiciously managed,
                    either at <name type="place">Kentucky</name> or the Cumberland settlement: and
                    yet salt, made from the water of salt-springs, may be purchased for one dollar
                    the bushel. As the source can never fail, and the mode of preparing it is
                    capable of great improvement, we may reasonably suppose, that the average price
                    of salt made on Cumberland river, will be three fourths of a dollar the
                    bushel.</p>
            <p>THE settlers have not had much experience of bringing loaded boats up the
                    Mississippi; but they calculate, from the trips they have made, that salt may be
                    freighted from New-Orleans to Nashville, at rather less than three eights of a
                    dollar the bushel; and it appears from similar experiments, that pork, flour, or
                    other produce, may be taken from Nashville to New Orleans at less than <pb n="13" facs="sc067m.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top of page">13</add> three eights of a dollar the bushel. Those
                    calculations regard the river Mississippi in its present state, with all its
                    circular bendings, the banks covered with trees, and no part of the upper
                    country settled; but the river, at present, is more than double the necessary
                    length. From the mouth of the river Ohio to New-Orleans, the present distance by
                    water is supposed to be 1000 miles; the direct distance is considerably short of
                    500 miles. In navigating that river we often find places like a horse-shoe,
                    where we do not gain more than a mile by failing or rowing five miles. Every one
                    of those bends may be cut off at a small expense. Let a common ditch, three or
                    four feet deep, be dug across those necks of land, the roots being cut away when
                    the river is low, and the next flood, by the rapidity of the stream through the
                    short passage, will change the ditch to a navigable channel. An experiment of
                    this kind has been made with success, at a place called <name type="place">Point
                        Coupe</name>. Two great benefits will arise from this process of giving the
                    river a straight course; one half of the time and labour in ascending the river,
                    will be saved by shortening the distance. This case supposes that vessels ascend
                    the river by the help of oars, and poles, without sails, which is generally the
                    case at present, because the river is so crooked, that no wind can be fair; but
                    in case the chief bendings of the river should be cut off, as a southerly wind
                    prevails there for the greater part of the year, every vessel would ascend by
                    the use of sails, and the difficulties of that navigation would be reduced to a
                    trifle. Considering what would be the utmost expense of transporting salt from
                    New-Orleans to Nashville, and considering that Nashville is 2 or 300 miles by
                    water farther from New-Orleans, than some other parts of the territory, and
                    presuming that a great share of the present expense may be saved by practicable
                    improvements in the navigation of the Mississippi, we may readily conclude, that
                    the mere freight of the luxuries of life must be a small object to the
                    inhabitants of that territory. As matters are now circumstanced, provided the
                        <choice>
                  <orig>navi  gation</orig>
                  <reg>navigation</reg>
               </choice>
               <add place="top of page">14</add> of the Mississippi was free, the <choice>
                  <orig>setters</orig>
                  <reg>settlers</reg>
               </choice> on Cumberland river would take their produce
                    to a shipping port, at less expense than it can be <choice>
                  <orig>waggoned</orig>
                  <reg>wagoned</reg>
               </choice> fifty miles in any country.</p>
            <p>As the country that has been described, is capable of producing, in great
                    perfection, every article that grows in the Atlantic states, there are no
                    leading circumstances, by which we can possibly determine, what is like to be
                    the general course of its trade, or the particular articles in which its most
                    valuable exports will consist. Iron, lead, pot-ash, pork, bacon, butter, cheese,
                    corn, wheat, barley, flax, hemp, rice, indigo, and cotton, have all been
                    mentioned by different persons from that country, as articles of export. Each of
                    these articles will doubtless be exported in greater or less quantity, according
                    to the demand; but it appears most probable, that the inhabitants will make
                    their chief remittances in tobacco, hemp, rice, indigo, and cotton. The low
                    grounds on the Mississippi must produce great crops of rice, and it has already
                    been observed, that the high grounds near that river are particularly <choice>
                  <orig>favourable</orig>
                  <reg>favorable</reg>
               </choice> to the culture of indigo and cotton. The
                    article last mentioned must be a constant source of wealth to the planter,
                    because its value is considerable when compared with its weight, and it must be
                    in constant demand in foreign markets. It is hardly necessary to observe, that
                    in a country where timber of the best and most durable quality, and all other
                    materials abound, necessary for shipping, the inhabitants will doubtless build
                    ships for a distant market.</p>
            <p>EVERY thing that has been said concerning the advantages to be expected by people
                    who settle in the Tennassee government, is founded on a supposition that all the
                    country may be settled, and the inhabitants permitted to navigate the
                    Mississippi. At present they are greatly restrained on both those heads; but
                    there does not seem to be any violence offered to common sense, nor any great
                    departure from probability, in supposing that the case will be materially
                    altered within a few years. It <pb n="15" facs="sc067o.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top of page">15</add>
                    is hardly worth while to observe, that the navigation of the Mississippi is ours
                    by the express words of treaties; because paper promises are seldom very binding
                    on nations, unless they are supported by other arguments; but it happens in the
                    present case, that arguments more conclusive than treaties present themselves to
                    every attentive mind. Necessity is invincible, and a nation so well informed as
                    the Spaniards must discover, that our fellow citizens on the western waters
                    cannot remain quiet without the use of the Mississippi. The progress of
                    population in that country is no more to be prevented or restrained than the
                    flowing of the rivers. It cannot be retarded by laws, not by treaties, nor by a
                    stronger cure- the fear of death. The proofs are recent and clear. There was not
                    a single family settled in Kentucky before the year <date when="1775">1775</date>, and the first colony migrated to that country in the face of
                    numerous and hostile savages, when they were more openly supported than of late
                    years, by the British. It is known, that they have continued, from the
                    beginning, in a constant state of war; and yet the settlement, at this hour,
                    contains near one hundred thousand inhabitants. The first adventurers were men,
                    and the increase for several years was chiefly occasioned by emigrants; but
                    women are now become numerous, and the settlement begins to enjoy the benefit of
                    a rapid increase from early marriage and constant emigration. This observation
                    is also applicable to the settlers in the <choice>
                  <orig>Tennassee</orig>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice>
                    government; wherefore, it is a very moderate computation, that supposes four
                    hundred thousand settlers on the western waters by the end of twenty years from
                    this time. Are the inhabitants of such a country to be restrained from going to
                    sea by means of a river that washes their land? Is the little colony of
                    New-Orleans, by the help of a few soldiers, to sustain the weight of such a
                    people, and prevent them from descending? We could as readily believe with the
                    poets, that Mount Atlas sustains the heavens. To say that they are citizens, and
                    must be restrained by the laws of the Union, is to suppose that <pb n="16" facs="sc067p.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top of page">(16)</add> men will submit to the dominion of
                    laws that are destructive of property — that they will endure oppression,
                    when they can emancipate themselves; that they will suffer under the want of
                    common necessaries, when they have comfortable supplies and riches before their
                    eyes; a case that is not like to happen in America. There are people of such a
                    stamp in the world, but this race does not thrive in the Atlantic states; much
                    less can such a race of animated machines be expected to grow in the western
                    country. Viewing the subject in this point of light, and considering the natural
                    effect of this most unnatural obstruction, events that are very unpleasing
                    present themselves to the mind.</p>
            <p>THE western people consider the navigation of the Mississippi as the light of the
                    fun, a birth-right that cannot be alienated. They believe that the national
                    government is bound to support this claim. Let them be told, that their claims,
                    for certain political reasons, cannot be admitted, and they will discover no
                    strength in the argument. They will think of taking by force, the thing that
                    seems to be retained by finesse. Let them be told, that such conduct would be
                    treasonable, and they will reply, that obedience and protection are mutual. If
                    those people should commit a single act of violence on that head, they could not
                    afterwards be restrained by all the powers of the national government. It is
                    true, that the capture of New-Orleans and every port on the Mississippi, would
                    not secure them the navigation of that river. A single frigate at the mouth of
                    the river, would blast the mercantile schemes of all the people in the western
                    country; but we know, that men who have once dipped their feet in treason, are
                    apt to proceed. The penalty is alike for little and for much. Hardy, adventurous
                    men, who are prevented from cultivating the soil, because they are not suffered
                    to carry their produce to sea, may look for some other employment; they may
                    think of a more easy way of getting money. Objects of ambition will not fail to
                    present themselves. Considering, therefore, <pb n="17" facs="sc067q.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top of page">(17)</add> that the settlement of the western country
                    cannot possibly be retarded; that no human eloquence can dissuade those people
                    from claiming the Mississippi, which is their chief avenue to wealth; that the
                    commerce of Spain might be greatly increased by permitting them to enjoy the
                    free use of that river, and that consequences, unpleasing to both nations, must
                    infallibly arise, from a perseverance in shutting up the river; we may consider
                    the free navigation of the Mississippi as a certain event. By tracing the short
                    lines which mark the Indian boundary, we discover, that all lands on Duck river
                    and Elk river, as well as on the several rivers which run into the Mississippi,
                    continue to be claimed by the Indians; and those lands are among the best in
                    that country. It may be observed, at the same time, that all those lands are
                    claimed by the <name type="person">Chickasaws</name>, a small tribe of friendly
                    Indians. We may be assured, that the government of the United States will not
                    permit those lands to be settled, without the consent of the Indians; but we
                    must discover, that the natural progress of things, in a short time, will render
                    a considerable part of that country, especially the lands on the Mississippi,
                    useless to the Indians, and necessary to the Whites. Numerous boatmen, passing
                    up and down the river, will have frequent occasion to go on shore; they will
                    need refreshments. Many who go down on rafts or boats, will return by land; they
                    will destroy the game. In a word, every man who lives on the western waters must
                    be interested in having settlements on the Mississippi. There can be little
                    difficulty in making a bargain for a country that is of great use to the Whites,
                    and little use to the Indians. The true interest of the United States would
                    point out a price for those lands, that would enable the <name type="person">Chickasaws</name> to live in a degree of ease and affluence, which
                    otherwise they can never expect. Suppose the Indians should cede all the lands
                    to the northward of Wolf river; in that case, the amount of the North-Carolina
                    grants being deducted, the United States will have at least six millions of <add place="bottom of page">C</add>
               <pb n="18" facs="sc067r.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top of page">(18)</add> acres of good land for sale;
                    lands of such a quality, and so near the sea, will hardly be sold, even by the
                    public, for less than one third of a dollar the acre. Six millions of acres at
                    one third of a dollar, would bring two millions of dollars, by which a debt to
                    that amount must be extinguished, and 120,000 dollars per annum saved to the
                    national treasury. Suppose the twelfth part of the money thus saved, ten
                    thousand dollars, was paid annually to the Chickasaws; one half, in corn or
                    other provisions at a stipulated price; and the other half in clothing; is it
                    not obvious, that their condition would be greatly mended, and equally clear,
                    that the state of our finances would be much improved by such a regulation? It
                    is true, that Indian lands have commonly been obtained on terms much less
                    profitable to the Indians, and more expensive to the Whites; but it may be
                    presumed, that experience will teach us to forsake the old plan, since it is
                    neither recommended by the dictates of humanity nor the rules of economy.</p>
            <p>SUCH is the territory south of the Ohio. The eastern division, as we have
                    observed, is composed of small mountains and <choice>
                  <orig>vallies</orig>
                  <reg>valleys</reg>
               </choice>,
                    which are extended in the direction of the rivers. There is no plain, or tract
                    of arable land, of any considerable width, in that settlement; but the <choice>
                  <orig>vallies</orig>
                  <reg>valleys</reg>
               </choice> are generally fertile. In the great western
                    division, there is not a single eminence or ridge, that claims the name of a
                    mountain. This country, nevertheless, is sufficiently diversified by rising
                    ground, and bears no resemblance to the continued plain, which is found near the
                    coast, in the middle and southern states. The rich lands near the Cumberland
                    river are considerably broken by knobs or short hills; but those hills have
                    lime-stone for their basis, and are fertile and fit for cultivation to the very
                    top. Streams that run in opposite direction to the very top. Streams that run in
                    opposite directions are uniformly divided by rising ground, and some of the
                    ridges are considerably elevated; but they are generally covered with good soil,
                    and are seldom too steep for the plough. There are two remarkable ridges or
                    broken tracks, in that country of considerable <choice>
                  <orig>di  mensions</orig>
                  <reg>dimensions</reg>
               </choice>, <add place="top of page">(19)</add> which
                    are not included in the above description; for they are stony or barren in many
                    places, the first of those ridges divides the waters of Cumberland river from
                    those of the <choice>
                  <orig>Tennassee</orig>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice>; it is broad as it
                    approaches the foot of Cumberland mountain, or rather, diversified in that part
                    by alternate hills and plains; but the plains, being chiefly without timber, are
                    called barrens. The second remarkable tract of broken or barren land, begins
                    near the mouth of <choice>
                  <orig>Tennassee</orig>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice>, dividing the waters of
                    that river from those of the Mississippi, and extending southerly towards the
                    Chickasaw towns. The small rivers that run into the Mississippi, have their
                    heads in this ridge. It is, in some parts, above twenty miles broad, rising at
                    the very margin of the <choice>
                  <orig>Tennassee</orig>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice>. It is covered
                    with long grass, having little or no timber, except a small growth on the
                    watercourses, which are numerous.</p>
            <p>THE territory west of Cumberland mountain has been stated at fifteen millions of
                    acres; but this calculation leaves eight millions for the Holston settlement,
                    which is certainly too much. The amount that may remain for sale on that side of
                    the mountain, has, in round numbers, been stated at six millions; but the
                    quantity, in all probability, will be considerably greater, without incident the
                    great tract of vacant land south of the French Broad, nor the considerable
                    tracts of arable land that are found in Cumberland mountain, nor those in the
                    Cumberland barrens, so called, where the land, though without timber, is
                    frequently very good; the Indians formerly, in burning the long grass, must have
                    destroyed the trees.</p>
            <p>IT is probable, that all the lands to the northward of the great bend of the
                        <choice>
                  <orig>Tennassee</orig>
                  <reg>Tennessee</reg>
               </choice>, may hereafter be joined to those
                    ceded by North-Carolina, so as to form one state; such a state would have a
                    natural boundary. And when we consider that the Creeks and <choice>
                  <orig>Chactaws</orig>
                  <reg>Choctaws</reg>
               </choice> live to the southward, who are numerous nations, together
                    with the Chickasaws, we shall be apt to mark the latitude of the south bend, for
                    a long series of years, <pb n="20" facs="sc067t.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top of page">(20)</add> as our southern boundary for the purpose of
                    settlement.</p>
            <p>THE reader has been informed, that the soil, climate, and productions of the
                    country on the western waters, are different from those in the Atlantic states;
                    and it has been intimated, that the whole face of nature in that country bears a
                    different appearance. Observations concerning things that are new or uncommon,
                    should be made and received with caution; but the reader cannot fail to realize
                    the narrative, if he takes the trouble of recollecting two or three remarkable
                    facts, to which reference has already been had.</p>
            <p>IN the Atlantic states, the strata of lime-stone are broken, and inclined
                    considerably to the horizon, being, at a medium, nearly parallel to the axis of
                    the earth. In the western country, the strata are constantly found parallel to
                    the horizon.</p>
            <p>IN the Atlantic states, salt springs are seldom or never found. In the western
                    country, they abound in every part.</p>
            <p>IN the Atlantic states, pit-coal is very scarce, and is obtained with difficulty.
                    In the western country, it is common, and frequently appears within a few feet
                    of the surface.</p>
            <p>ONE of those countries must have suffered prodigious convulsions; the other may
                    be supposed to retain more of its original form. Is it at all surprising, that a
                    country, so different in its structure, its appearance, and essential qualities,
                    should produce more plentiful crops, or that it should engage a considerable
                    degree of public attention? <add place="below text">THE END.</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
