<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl212">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1833 Apr. 14, Nashville [to] Sarah B. Hamilton, Russellville, K[entuck]y / Mortimer Hamilton   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Hamilton, Mortimer</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl212</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51212757</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1833 Apr. 14, Nashville [to] Sarah B. Hamilton, Russellville, K[entuck]y / Mortimer Hamilton   </title>
               <author>Hamilton, Mortimer </author>
               <date when="1833-04-14">April 14, 1833</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated April 14, 1833 to Sarah B. Hamilton from her son Mortimer Hamilton. Hamilton informs his mother of a murder in Nashville, a friends desire to purchase a young girl, and writes in length about his desire to become a Christian.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection-IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl212</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Religious life</term>
               <term>Communication in family</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Slavery</term>
               <term>Murder</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Hamilton, Mortimer</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl212a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                     <date when="1833-04-14">Sunday Morning April 14th 1833</date> To<name type="person"> Mrs T. B. Hamilton</name>
                     <name type="place">Rock Cave</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear Mother—</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I know that there is but few things that affords you so much pleasure as to hear from your children and for this reason I now take ⁁<add place="supralinear">my</add> pen to write you a few lines— Brother and myself have enjoyed perfect health since I wrote to you last and hope that these lines will find you enjoying the same blessing I received a letter from John O and <name type="person">L S Gilbert</name> a week or two ago I was glad to hear that they were enjoying good health and that they still expressed a warm regard of friendship for me.— They stated that you had received my letter I wrote to them about the murder that had been committed in this town and by referring to that you will see a detail of the crime the murderer is in jail and is to have his trial in May next. The father of the young man that got killed was a gambler. When the father is of a dissipated character the son is apt to follow the example <choice>
                  <orig> let</orig>
                  <reg>led</reg>
               </choice> before him. Had the father been an upright and correct man and had <choice>
                  <orig>let</orig>
                  <reg>led</reg>
               </choice> ⁁ <add place="supralinear">a</add> good example before son it is very probable that he would not have been killed by a merciless assassin. He was a young man just in the prime of life and had left his home to visit West Point and perhaps he expected some future period to be some <pb n="2" facs="sl212b.small.jpg"/> great man — But alas just as the bud hath put forth its flower it is withered by the <choice>
                  <orig>schorching</orig>
                  <reg>scorching</reg>
               </choice> sun I feel thankful that my father <choice>
                  <orig>let</orig>
                  <reg>led</reg>
               </choice> a good example before his children and for so doing the Lord blessed him about five years ago he entered in to the joy of his Lord and is now singing around the throne of his redeemer I think I sustain some of the principles which he had and which carried him through this world with such respect— But the Christian principles which he passed and which bore him through the dark valley and shadow of death and which landed him safe in the port of heaven I do not possess But I am seeking for it and by the assisting grace of God I am determined to have it The assurance that I have of his being there and my little brother and my Christian relations Also ought not this to teach me to persevere to try and meet them yes Mother it does and I feel resolved never to give up the struggle <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> I shall come that <choice>
                  <orig>conquerer</orig>
                  <reg>conqueror</reg>
               </choice> Oh may the Lord help me on and enable me by faith to believe on him and obtain this blessing Oh Mother pray for me that I may be delivered from the bondage of sin shortly—</p>
            <p>Tell brother James that he must <choice>
                  <abbr>W</abbr>
                  <expan>Write</expan>
               </choice> to me shortly Give my love to him kiss brother Joseph and tell him <pb n="3" facs="sl212c.small.jpg"/> to be a good boy and that he must say something in brother James letter give my love to my little sister brother Oscar sends his love to you and brothers James and Joseph and sister and says we would be glad to see you— I expect to get into school some time in next month— We will leave an abundant crop of fruit this year I expect the peach trees are— fuller than I ever saw them before— Give my love to all of my relations and — all enquiring friends— and except the same yourself I still remain your affectionate son</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Mortimer Hamilton</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <note>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>N. B.</abbr>
                        <expan>Nota Bene</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <p>Mrs. Word requested me to write to you and ask you if you would select her a smart young girl from 14 to 18 years old If you could get <name type="person">Mr Ewing</name>Betsy I think she would suit her very well  She <unclear>whis (wish)?</unclear> one of a good character and to know the price— She sends her respects to you and says she wishes you to come in May— Tell Aunt Maria that I have not heard from Stef ⁁<add place="supralinear">for</add> some time give my respects <gap agent="damage"/>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl212d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mrs. Sarah B. Hamilton</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Russelville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Logan <choice>
                           <abbr>Cty</abbr>
                           <expan>City</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Ky</abbr>
                           <expan>Kentucky</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
