<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl184">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1844 Oct. 18 [to] Joseph Brown, Columbia, Tenn[essee] / C.B. Frazier   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Frazier, C. B.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl184</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51173673</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1844 Oct. 18 [to] Joseph Brown, Columbia, Tenn[essee] / C.B. Frazier   </title>
               <author>Frazier, C. B. </author>
               <date when="1844-10-18">October 18, 1844</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated October 18, 1844 to Colonel Joseph Brown from C. B. Frazier. Frazier writes to inform Colonel Brown of the death of his son, Joseph Porter Brown. Joseph Porter Brown died in Galveston Texas of yellow fever. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Joseph Brown Papers THS-JB</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">202-205</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl184</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Death Notices</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Frazier, C. B.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl184a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Randolph </name>
                     <date when="1844-10-18">Oct. 18th 1844</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Col. Jas.</abbr>
                        <expan>Colonel Joseph</expan>
                     </choice> Brown</name>
               </salute>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>A few days since I received the painful <choice>
                  <orig>inteligence</orig>
                  <reg>intelligence</reg>
               </choice> of the death of your son <name type="person">Joseph P. Brown</name> who died at <name type="place">Galveston Texas</name> with the yellow fever on the <date when="1844-07-30">30th July</date>after an illness of   nine days. his wife two of his children and all of his servants were down with this <unclear>file</unclear> disease at the same time but on the fourteenth of August, the date of the letter my Mother wrote me from there— all were out of danger and mending slowly— My Mother was with the family at the time. She escaped entirely. Sister Jane was very anxious to return to the United States and will probably do so this winter</p>
            <p>Mother wrote that your son left ready means sufficient to defray all immediate and necessary <choice>
                  <orig>expences</orig>
                  <reg>expenses</reg>
               </choice>. he though I think was owing some six or seven hundred dollars in that country what arrangements he made about <unclear>begun (illegible word)</unclear> these claims I do not know they may be <choice>
                  <orig>setled</orig>
                  <reg>settled</reg>
               </choice> but I rather think not, his Brother Franklin I hope will attend to his business and manage his affairs so as to let his wife bring <pb n="2" facs="sl184b.small.jpg"/> the negroes along with her to the U. S. if he could make sale of some of the land belonging to the estate there would be no <choice>
                  <orig>dificulty</orig>
                  <reg>difficulty</reg>
               </choice> about paying off the debts. I am afraid he did not procure from you a deed <del type="overstrike">for</del> or bill of sale for the negroes you let him have while in this state. In the name of his children if he did not the family may be put to some trouble. you will please write upon this subject and advise how to act with the family <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>and et cetera</expan>
               </choice>— My Brother George will leave Texas shortly and it is our wish that Sister Jane should return with him— you have better write to <name type="person">Dr. Brown</name> who I understand has gone to <name type="place">Texas</name>, and advise him what course to pursue.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Very respectfully</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">CB Frazier</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl184c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel</expan>
                        </choice> Joseph Brown</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="cover page">miscellaneous writings near address</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
