<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl076">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1838 Nov. 25, Hartsville, [Tennessee] [to] Doctor Ja[me]s L. Alexander / D. W. Mentto : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Mentto, D. W.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl076</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50133563</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1838 Nov. 25, Hartsville, [Tennessee] [to] Doctor Ja[me]s L. Alexander / D. W. Mentto</title>
               <author>Mentto, D. W.</author>
               <date when="1838-11-25">November 25, 1838</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by D. W. Mentto to Doctor James L. Alexander on November 25, 1838. In the letter, Mentto expresses his relief that Transylvania College, in Lexington, Kentucky, will be able to sustain itself with the help of several donors. He mentions several deaths, births, and marriages of people that are acquaintances of Alexander's. He concludes the letter by naming several of the candidates running for the lower house seats in the government.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Alexander Papers Correspondence</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">VI-G-2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl076</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Mentto, D. W.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl076a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Hartsville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1838-11-25">25th <choice>
                           <abbr>Novr.</abbr>
                           <expan>November</expan>
                        </choice> 1838</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear James</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>As I have a few leisure moments from professional engagements, I concluded I would answer your very interesting letter <choice>
                  <abbr>recvd.</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> a few days since. I was highly gratified to hear that Transylvania would sustain herself notwithstanding it was so confidently believed by some, she must  go down. But so long as she has  such a pillow as <name type="person">B. W. Dudley</name> and such girders as <name type="person">Cross</name> and <name type="person">Smith</name> there is no danger to be entertained by its inn mates.</p>
            <p>My family are all well — so is your Father and all the relations so far as I know. There is still some sickness in this our land, I ride more or less every day, so does my partner <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Dr.</abbr>
                     <expan>Doctor</expan>
                  </choice> Dibon</name> There has been one death since you left Hartsville old <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Capt.</abbr>
                     <expan>Captain</expan>
                  </choice> Winston</name>, he died on last Sunday was a week ago in the morning; with diseased lungs. Some births have taken place <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                     <expan>Esquire</expan>
                  </choice> Donoho</name> has a very fine boy weighed 10 pound after it was dressed. One marriage your Cousin <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm.</abbr>
                     <expan>William</expan>
                  </choice> Hall</name> to <name type="person">Miss C. Berry</name> and some others in anticipation</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Doctor Henry Brooks</name> is anxious to sell his land, he says he will not stay any longer there for many reasons too numerous to mention. It is said he desires coming to Hartsville. If he should I know of only two families in which he will give pills the two Donoho's.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Z.  G. Goodall</name> is a candidate for the lower house so is <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Thos.</abbr>
                     <expan>Thomas</expan>
                  </choice> Berry</name> and <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Dr.</abbr>
                     <expan>Doctor</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <unclear>Douglass</unclear>
               </name>. I cannot speak as to their respective claims. Goodall will get most of the votes in this neighborhood, <sic>notwith</sic> — <pb n="2" facs="sl076b.small.jpg"/> notwithstanding they have quite a serious charge against him which is this; that he was seen at one time in private conversation with me, and it was supposed we were talking on <emph>Campbellism</emph> I know this charge will make you smile, <choice>
                  <orig>altho</orig>
                  <reg>although</reg>
               </choice> the squire seems to mind it somewhat.</p>
            <p>I wish you to send me all the introductory lectures so soon as they are printed. Write me frequently as a few lines from you will be cordially <choice>
                  <abbr>recvd.</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> at any time. I wish you to attend the Christian Church, hear <name type="person">Brother Hall</name> and let me ⁁ <add place="supralinear">know</add> by your next letter what kind of a speaker he is. Say to <name type="person">Cunningham</name> his mother and family are well, and nothing strange, or, uncommon has happened to any of them since he left.</p>
            <p>My little son James sends his love to you and says I must write his name in this letter, he was much gratified to learn his name was written in the letter you sent me. He has not forgotten about them boots you promised him, he speaks of them frequently.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have nothing more But remain yours Truly</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">D. W. Mentto</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="left of address">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P. S.</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <name type="person">Mary</name> sends her love to you and <name type="person">Tim</name>. }</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl076c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Hartsville <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="--12-01">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Dec</abbr>
                           <expan>December</expan>
                        </choice> 1st</date> }</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="above address">18¾</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Doctor <choice>
                           <abbr>Jas.</abbr>
                           <expan>James</expan>
                        </choice> L. Alexander</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Lexington</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <emph>
                        <name type="place">Kentucky</name>
                     </emph>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left of address">
                  <emph>Mail</emph> }</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
