<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl353">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1826 Feb. 14, Princeton, Kentucky [to] Finis Ewing, Boonville, Missouri / F[ranceway]. R. Cossitt   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Cossitt, F. R.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl353</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1826 Feb. 14, Princeton, Kentucky [to] Finis Ewing, Boonville, Missouri / F[ranceway]. R. Cossitt</title>
               <author>Cossitt, F. R.</author>
               <date when="1826-02-14">February 14, 1826</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to Rev. Finis Ewing dated February 14, 1826. It is signed by Franceway R. Cossitt, David Lowry, John Barnett,  John W. Ogden. They represent the Cumberland Presbyterian College, which this letter is about. Cossitt describes the school, its land and buildings. He writes at length about the need for funding, asking Ewing if  he will solicit donations for the Institution. Cossitt mentions that there are   rival sectaries who are eager for the school to fail in order to improve their own positions.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Finis Ewing Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">I-A-4</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">7</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl353</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Kentucky</term>
               <term>Cumberland Presbyterian Church.</term>
               <term>Religious study and teaching</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Cossitt, Franceway R.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl353a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Princeton</name>, <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Feby.</abbr>
                           <expan>February</expan>
                        </choice> 14th. 1826</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The commissioners have located our college at Princeton <name>Kentucky</name>. For the sum of $6000. Specie, we have purchased a farm consisting of 450 acres of Good land, 180 of which are in cultivation, on which are an elegant framed house, two hewed log houses, with other out houses, affording conveniences for the residence of private families, a horse mill, a cotton gin, 600 fine apple trees and an excellent spring of never failing water. A few friends have been so kind as to unite with us, in borrowing money to make the first payment.</p>
            <p>Two <choice>
                  <orig>anual</orig>
                  <reg>annual</reg>
               </choice> payments are still due, for which we and our friends are bound. All the subscriptions we have received are payable in one, two and three years, but  <gap/> least three <choice>
                  <orig>forths</orig>
                  <reg>fourths</reg>
               </choice> of them are payable in land or property, such as cannot be converted in to cash without a Great Sacrifice; and <choice>
                  <orig>consiquently</orig>
                  <reg>consequently</reg>
               </choice> will not aid us much in paying the purchase we have made. we have now to procure horses, stock, farming utensils, furniture for the boarding house, and provisions for the present year, together with some necessary buildings, which will require ready cash. Brother, we have launched our bark on the ocean of experiment. we must weather the storm. "We must not lie on our oars; but tug for our lives", until we reach the desired haven. But after all we must eventually sink without assistance. Some of our oldest, most-experienced and influential Preachers, must reach forth a helping hand, in  this our time of extreme necessity; and spend their time, between this and the  commencement of the camp meeting season, in riding and collecting funds. Strong exertions must be made. <pb n="2" facs="sl353b.small.jpg"/> unless we do receive a prompt and vigorous support from our <choice>
                  <orig>Breatheren</orig>
                  <reg>Brethren</reg>
               </choice> abroad, our college, and the credit of our body must inevitably sink in the view of the world. Other Sectaries are even now waiting our downfall, and anticipating their own triumph. But where are the men to spend three or four months in soliciting donations? where ever the friends of science, religion and humanity are to be found. "There art the man", or at least one of them. So we most ardently hope, and confidently believe you will, to aid me, and support so Good a cause, to accomplish so valuable an object. you will sacrifice some of your worldly interest, it is true; but the interest of the church are far dearer and we trust you will not hesitate. other in this section have made much Greater sacrifices, than any expected of you. Could you Know our situation and behold our difficulties, it would be enough: you would want no other excitement. For the sake of that Glorious cause, so dear to us all, aid us by your prompt exertions, your prayers to God, and your solicitations among men. we shall commence all the business of the Institution, on the <date>first of march</date> next. we shall expect the people in your presbytery, to send on their students as soon as possible, with their money in their hands, according to an article in the Constitution, requiring payment half yearly in advance. The whole <choice>
                  <orig>expence</orig>
                  <reg>expense</reg>
               </choice> will not be less than $60. during the first year. Every student must bring with him, a Blanket, a pair of sheets, a Towel, and either a bed tick, or bed cover. all may be of a course, but durable quality. At all events, an arrangement must be made at each of the presbyteries at their spring session, for immediately sending on their candidates, and as many others a they can, as <pb n="3" facs="sl353c.small.jpg"/> the farming arrangements will render it indispensably necessary. We are decidedly of the opinion, that (besides your own donation, which you will bring up to the next Synod) you, by your individual exertions, can <choice>
                  <orig>verry</orig>
                  <reg>very</reg>
               </choice> conveniently obtain, at least, $200.00, which you will send to the <choice>
                  <orig>Treasuerer</orig>
                  <reg>Treasurer</reg>
               </choice> of the Cumberland Presbyterian College, by the <date>first of June</date>, or as soon as you can by a safe <choice>
                  <orig>oppertunity</orig>
                  <reg>opportunity</reg>
               </choice> .___</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your Breatheren in the Lord</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr> F. R.</abbr>
                        <expan>Franceway Ranna</expan>
                     </choice> Cossitt</name>
               </signed>
               <signed>David <gap/>
               </signed>
               <signed>John <gap/>
               </signed>
               <signed>John W. <gap/>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl353d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Rev'd</abbr>
                        <expan>Reverend</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name>Finis Ewing</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Boonville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Missouri</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>FR Cossitt, <lb/>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>D.</abbr>
                        <expan>David</expan>
                     </choice> Lowry</name>, <lb/>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>J.</abbr>
                        <expan>John</expan>
                     </choice> Barnett</name>, <lb/>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>J.</abbr>
                        <expan>John</expan>
                     </choice> W Ogden</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <date> Feb 4/ 1826</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
