<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl704">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1803 Oct. 22 [to]  John Sevier, Nashville, Tennessee / Thomas Claiborne: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Claiborne, Thomas</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl704</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1803 Oct. 22 [to]  John Sevier, Nashville, Tennessee / Thomas Claiborne</title>
               <author> Claiborne, Thomas</author>
               <date when="1803-10-22"> 
			 October 22, 1803</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated October 22, 1803 from Thomas Claiborne, Chairman of the state House of Representatives to the governor of Tennessee, John Sevier.  The purpose of the letter is to propose cooperation between the house and executive office, as well as to promise diligent awareness of constituent concerns.  Also in the letter, Claiborne makes a point to note the importance of a careful investigation into the American code of laws for any trace of British common law.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor John Sevier Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl704</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Sevier, John, 1745-1815</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2013104647"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Claiborne, Thomas Augustine, 1777-1817</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl704a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <add>To his Excellency John Seveir</add>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The general assembly have received, duly weighed, and have well appreciated your very interesting communication of the 7th instant.</p>
            <p>The general assembly, feel in all <add>its</add> force, the weighty obligations imposed upon them by the calls of their constituents, whose interests will ever be near to them, and they will use every effort to adopt the salutary means, by which those interests are to be cherished__</p>
            <p>The statutes of <name>Great Britain</name> it is true, were enacted in an age of Tyranny &amp; usurpation, yet having been <del type="overstrike">on</del>  in a great measure <choice>
                  <orig>ingrafted</orig>
                  <reg>engrafted</reg>
               </choice> into the american code of laws, will require the most accurate investigation to separate them from our civil code__ Happily our wise constitution has guarded against their influence in religious concerns, equally happy for america is it, that the constitutions of the several states are founded on republican principles, and that grand Bulwark of all, the constitution of the United States has guaranteed those invaluable blessings to them.  The Legislature is proud to say, that the shackles of british common law, is as little felt here, as in any state <del type="overstrike">of</del>
               <add>on</add> the union, and this legislature pledge themselves that the Sons of Tennessee, will be foremost in breaking all such improper barriers to freedom__</p>
            <p>The Legislature feel with you Sir, the necessity of providing for that valuable &amp; worthy class of citizens resident worth of Tennessee, whose services in the cause of their country, are too deeply impressed, on the minds of every one <del type="overstrike">acquainted</del>   acquainted with the settlement of this country to be early forgotten.  Their case shall be promptly &amp; early laid before the general government, by the <choice>
                  <orig>deligation</orig>
                  <reg>delegation</reg>
               </choice> from this state.  <sic>The</sic>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl704b.small.jpg"/> The finances of the state on under investigation, and will meet with due attention.__</p>
            <p>It is with extreme <del type="overstrike">regret</del> pain, that the Legislature have to notice the most atrocious <add>murder</add>  of Runion__ Every aid in the power of the general assembly, will be cheerfully ordered__ in cooperation with the Executive to bring the perpetrator to <unclear>condign</unclear>   punishment.  The importance of communication between this state and its sister states, is of a too <choice>
                  <orig>permenent</orig>
                  <reg>permanent</reg>
               </choice> nature to be overlooked, the <unclear>mortryid</unclear> attention to this point will meet legislative observation__</p>
            <p>The general assembly will with pleasure cooperate with you, in every measure that will <del type="overstrike">tend</del> tend to promote the honor, dignity &amp; prosperity of the state of Tennessee__</p>
            <closer>
               <add>Signed</add>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Thos</abbr>
                        <expan>Thomas</expan>
                     </choice> A Claiborne</name>
               </signed>
               <add>Chairman</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl704c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>His Excellency Governor Sevier</addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <lb/> House of representatives <choice>
                     <abbr>Oct</abbr>
                     <expan>October</expan>
                  </choice> 21st__ 1803 <choice>
                     <abbr>rasd</abbr>
                     <expan>raised</expan>
                  </choice> orders to be entered on <unclear>journal</unclear> seat__ to the senate <unclear>Ealerd</unclear>
                  <lb/> Senate <date>22d__ October 1803</date>.__ Read and ordered to be entered on the Journal <name>Jas. Paimble</name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>clk</abbr>
                     <expan>clerk</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
