<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0231">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Petition] 1838 Oct. 5, Cherokee Agency : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0231</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 45957185</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>  [Petition] 1838 Oct. 5, Cherokee Agency</title>
               <date when="1838-10-05">October 5, 1838</date>
               <extent> 4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document, dated October 5, 1838, is a petition from William Smith, Sally Bank, Cut Bread, Big Ratlinggoard, The Bank, and Laugh at Mush. The petiotion concerns the proceeds and net income of a Turnpike and main gate on the road from the Head of Coosa to Alabama. The petition concerns also discusses the fact that when the laws of Alabama were extended to cover a portion of the Cherokee country, these petitioners were dispossessed of ownership of the Turnpike and main gate.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> pa0231</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Petitions</term>
               <term>Alabama</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Government relations</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Claims</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0231a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>The petition of <name>William Smith</name>
               <name>Sally Bank</name>, <name>Cut Bread</name>, <name>Big Ratlinggoard</name>, <name>The Bank</name>, &amp; <name>Laugh at Mush</name>, respectfully represent that they an a Turnpike company who can <choice>
                  <orig>autheryse</orig>
                  <reg>authorize</reg>
               </choice> by an act of the National Committee &amp; Council which paper is herewith submitted, to establish a Turnpike on the main Road heading from the <name>Head of Coosa</name> to <name>Alabama</name>  via <name>Turkey Town</name> &amp; <name>Mills Vally</name>. Said company established their gate at place on said road set far from a place where <name>Daniel <unclear>Griffins son</unclear>
               </name> lived. Said company continued in possession of said Turnpike &amp; Road from the turn that said charter was granted to them by the Council up to <date when="1832-01">January 1832</date> at which time the laws of the state of <name>Alabama</name> was extended <del type="overstrike">over</del> by an act of her legislation over all that portion of the <name>Cherokee</name> country within his chartered limits. And you petitioners were in <choice>
                  <orig>consiquence</orig>
                  <reg>consequence</reg>
               </choice> of said act of the Legislature aforesaid dispossessed of their Turnpike &amp; Road. At the time your petitioners were dispossessed of said Road <name>Tassel Cambell </name>was keeping said gate &amp; reported that the proceeds of it was $1500. per anum.  Commencing there in the month of January 1832 &amp; calculating the time from that date up to <del type="overstrike">May</del> 23 day of May 1836 will make the time of 4 years &amp; 2 months adding the whole of which <choice>
                  <orig>to gether</orig>
                  <reg>together</reg>
               </choice> will make the sum of $6300. From this deduct the expenditures of keeping up the Road &amp; Gate &amp; the Salary of the <del type="overstrike">Inn</del> Gate keeper &amp; you have the <unclear>net</unclear> proceeds of said Gate &amp; Road. Say $214, &amp; 30. for the gate keeper which is the 7th of $1500. &amp; the actual sum given to said gate keeper, by said company making <pb n="2" facs="pa0231b.small.jpg"/> &amp; making him equal to one of the company. Then deduct the sum of 286.70 cents for repairing &amp; keeping up, &amp; which you petitioners think is a fair estimate of the all the expenditures in keeping up said road, &amp; it leave the net sum of $1000. per anum for 4 years. add this together &amp; it makes a sum <del type="overstrike">of the</del> total for 4 years $4000. Then calculate the 4 months which is one third of a year at the same ratio, &amp; you have the net income for the whole time.</p>
            <closer>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Cherokee Agency</name>
                     <date>October 1, 1838</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <signed>
                  <del type="overstrike">Signed</del>
               </signed>
               <signed>Signed}</signed>
               <signed>
                  <name>William Smith</name> x <add>his mark</add>
               </signed>
               <signed>
                  <name>Cut Bread</name>x <add>his mark</add>
               </signed>
               <signed>
                  <name>Big Ratlinggourd</name>x <add>hix mark</add>
               </signed>
               <signed>
                  <name>The Bank</name>x <add>his mark</add>
               </signed>
               <signed>
                  <name>Laugh at Mush</name> x <add>his mark</add>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <name>Tassell Cambell</name> being sworn states upon oath that he was employed by the above named Turnpike Company to keep the gate of said company at or near Daniel Grifffens old place on said Road. His <choice>
                     <orig>sallery</orig>
                     <reg>salary</reg>
                  </choice> for keeping said gate was <add>over</add> seventh part of the Anum received at said Gate. Affiant further states that he was dispossessed of said gate by the authorities of the state of Alabama in the month of January 1832. Affiant also states that the <unclear>road</unclear> &amp; gate at the time he was dispossessed of it by the authorities afore said was worth the sum of $1500 per anum. The road was worth that sum the year previous, &amp; would have yielded that sum or more the year that he was dispossessed. Affiant further states that he does not think that the <add>sum </add>expended by said company <add>in</add>
                  <pb n="3" facs="pa0231c.small.jpg"/> in keeping up the road &amp; paying affiant his sallery for attending to the Gate amounted to more than three or four hundred dollars, affiant is certain from his knowledge of the expenditures, that it did not cost more than $400.</add> Sworn to &amp; Subscribed <lb/> before me Oct. 1 1838 } Tassel Cambell <add>his x mark</add>
               <signed>
                  <name>D. M. Foreman </name>
               </signed>
               <signed>
                  <name>M. Cont.</name>
               </signed>
               <add>Examined &amp; allow for 200. <choice>
                     <abbr>pr</abbr>
                     <expan>per</expan>
                  </choice>. year for the term of 4 years &amp; 4 months making $866.66 <unclear>at</unclear> 4th October 1838</add>
               <signed>
                  <name>A. Bell</name>
               </signed>
               <unclear>Prest. Comt.</unclear>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1">
            <pb n="4" facs="pa0231d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>The Claim of William Smith &amp; others for a Turnpike Gate &amp; Roads —<lb/>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Amt</abbr>
                  <expan>Amount</expan>
               </choice> $6500 —―<add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>No</abbr>
                     <expan>Number</expan>
                  </choice> 1370—</add>
               <lb/>
               <add>Allowed for $866.66 ―</add>
               <add>upon on consideration of the proof in this case &amp; all the circumstances The Commissioners allow Six hundred Dollars 5th <choice>
                     <abbr>Oct</abbr>
                     <expan>October</expan>
                  </choice>. 1838 &amp; no more</add>
               <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jno</abbr>
                     <expan>John</expan>
                  </choice> Kennedy</name>
               <name>
                  <unclear>Th W Willow</unclear>
               </name>
               <name>
                  <unclear/>
               </name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
