<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD"[
<!ENTITY pg1 PUBLIC "pg1" "wch013a.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg2 PUBLIC "pg2" "wch013b.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg3 PUBLIC "pg3" "wch013c.djv" NDATA TIFF>
]>
<TEI.2 ID="ch013"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>[Letter] 1785 Sept. 19, Chotee to Gov[ernor of North Carolina, Richard] Caswell / Col[onel] Joseph Martin: a machine-readable transcription of an image</TITLE><AUTHOR>Martin, Joseph</AUTHOR><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>ch013</IDNO><IDNO>OCLC: 44759910</IDNO><AVAILABILITY STATUS="FREE"><P>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>[Letter] 1785 Sept. 19, Chotee to Gov[ernor of North Carolina, Richard] Caswell / Col[onel] Joseph Martin</TITLE><AUTHOR>Martin, Joseph</AUTHOR><DATE VALUE="1785-09-19">September 19,1785</DATE><EXTENT>3p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">This document is a copy of a letter from Colonel Joseph Martin, at Chotee, to Richard Caswell, Governor of North Carolina (1776-1780, 1784-1787), dated September 19, 1785.  Martin reports that he has assumed the duties of Indian agent (to the Cherokees) and has a considerably difficult summer due to frequent encroachments by inhabitants of the state of Franklin, as well as meddlesome talks from the Spaniards and the western Indians.  He mentions the former British agent, Mr. McDonald and his relationship with the Chickamauga Cherokees, Alexander McGillivray, and the Creeks.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box"> 1</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder"> 17</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">ch013</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Creek Indians--Government relations</ITEM><ITEM>Indian agents</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Government relations</ITEM><ITEM>Southern States</ITEM></LIST> </KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><PB N="[1]"><OPENER><NAME TYPE="place">N.C.</NAME> State &amp;<LB><NAME TYPE="person">Col. Joseph Martin</NAME> to <NAME TYPE="person">Gov. Caswell</NAME><LB><DATELINE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE><NAME TYPE="place">Chotee</NAME>,<DATE VALUE="1785-09-19">19 Sept., 1785.</DATE></ADDRLINE></ADDRESS></DATELINE><SALUTE>Dear Sir: etc.-</SALUTE></OPENER><P>"I am now on the duties of the office (Indian Agent) and have had more trouble with the Indians in the course of the Summer, than I ever had, owing to the rapid encroachment of the people from the New State (<NAME REG="State" TYPE="place">Franklin</NAME>), together with the Talks from the <NAME TYPE="person">Spaniards</NAME> and the western Indians.</P><P>Two <NAME TYPE="person">Wyandot</NAME> Chiefs are now at <NAME TYPE="place">Chickamagga</NAME>, etc.-</P><P>The Indians here are much concerned at the people living on <NAME TYPE="place">Little River</NAME>, I refer your Excellency <PB N="[2]">to their talks which they have <ORIG REG="counseled">counciled</ORIG> on for six days.</P><P>I have with much pains and some artifice prevailed on <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. McDonald</NAME>, the former <NAME TYPE="person">British</NAME> Agent, to correspond with me.  I have enclosed a copy of his letter to your Excellency in case of a war with any foreign power. he may be very service<ADD PLACE="supralinear">a</ADD>ble or very dangerous.</P><P>He lives about <HI>25 miles south west</HI> from <NAME TYPE="place">Chickamagga</NAME>.  Which is the <UNCLEAR><ORIG REG="Hugest">Hougest</ORIG></UNCLEAR> part of the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME>.  He has great influence with the Indians  on that quarter, deals at <NAME TYPE="place">Pensacola</NAME>, corresponds with <NAME REG="McGillivray" TYPE="person">Mr. Gilvry</NAME>, in the <NAME TYPE="place person">Creek Nation</NAME> and one <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. McClatchey</NAME> at the mouth of <NAME REG="River" TYPE="place">St. Mary's</NAME>, a <NAME TYPE="person">British</NAME> Merchant who furnishes some part<PB N="[3]">of the Towns near him with goods.   I flatter myself that with his Assistance I shall be able to furnish your Excellency with the earliest and best Intelligence that can be had from that quarter.</P></DIV1></BODY></TEXT></TEI.2>
