<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD"[
<!ENTITY pg1 PUBLIC "pg1" "WCH023a.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg2 PUBLIC "pg2" "WCH023b.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg3 PUBLIC "pg3" "WCH023c.djv" NDATA TIFF>
]>
<TEI.2 ID="ch023"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>Letter, 1828 June 20, Head of Coosa [to] Colo[nel] H[ugh] Montgomery / Jno [i.e., John] Ross: a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><AUTHOR>Ross, John, 1790-1866</AUTHOR><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>ch023</IDNO><IDNO>OCLC: 44771909</IDNO><AVAILABILITY STATUS="FREE"><P>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>Letter, 1828 June 20, Head of Coosa [to] Colo[nel] H[ugh] Montgomery / Jno [i.e., John] Ross</TITLE><AUTHOR>Ross, John, 1790-1866</AUTHOR><DATE VALUE="1828-06-20">June 20,1828</DATE><EXTENT>3p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">This document is a letter from John Ross, Principal Chief of the Cherokee Nation, to Colonel Hugh Montgomery, U.S. agent to the Cherokees, dated June 20, 1828.  Ross writes regarding several legal cases related to reservations instituted at the court in Jasper, Tennessee.  Ross comments on the particularly strong claims of Peggy Shorey and Eight Killer who were abused and dispossessed of their homes by white settlers.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box"> 1</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder"> 23</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">ch023</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Letters</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Legal status, laws, etc.</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Claims</ITEM></LIST> </KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><PB N="[1]"><OPENER><DATELINE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE><NAME TYPE="place">Head of Coosa</NAME> <NAME TYPE="place person"><ABBR EXPAN="Cherokee Nation">CN.</ABBR></NAME></ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE VALUE="1828-06-20">June 20th 1828.</DATE></DATELINE><LB><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Colonel">Colo.</ABBR>  H. Montgomery</NAME></ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE><NAME TYPE="place">U.S.</NAME> Agent.</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><SALUTE>Sir</SALUTE></OPENER><P>The <NAME TYPE="person">Eight Killer</NAME> was here a few days since, And he requested me to inform you that he has been correctly told, the reservation suits which were instituted by <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Williams</NAME>, by order of the <ABBR EXPAN="Secretary" TYPE="suspension">Secry</ABBR> of War, in behalf of <NAME TYPE="person">Peggy Shorey</NAME>, <NAME TYPE="person">The Pigion</NAME> &amp; himself, at the Court in <NAME REG="TN" TYPE="place">Jasper</NAME> <NAME TYPE="place"><ABBR EXPAN="Tennessee">Ten</ABBR></NAME>, have been dismissed at the late term, in consequence of <ADD PLACE="supralinear">the</ADD> nonattendance <ADD PLACE="supralinear">of the agents</ADD> on the part of the prosecutor <DEL TYPE="overstrike">on the</DEL>. The <NAME TYPE="person">Eight Killer</NAME> desires his case to <ADD PLACE="supralinear">be</ADD> received as soon as circumstances will permit, and no doubt, the others feel the same solicitude &mdash; It is best known to yourself why these cases have been permitted to meet this unexpected fate &mdash; of all the reservation claims arising out of the late Treaties, I do not hesitate to say, in my opinion, there is not a single one more strong or just than the claims of <NAME TYPE="person">Eight Killer</NAME> and <NAME TYPE="person">Peggy Shorey</NAME><PB N="[2]">and the Cruel treatment they <ABBR EXPAN="received">recd.</ABBR> from some of the first white settlers, and the manner in which they were forcibly dispossessed of their houses &amp; homes, entitles them to your notice &amp; official attention, and to the justice if not the sympathy, of the government, <ADD PLACE="left">And</ADD> as the <HI>Supreme law of the land</HI> is in their favor, I hope this appeal in their <DEL TYPE="erasure">favour</DEL> behalf will not be in vain&mdash;</P><P></P><CLOSER>I am Sir <ABBR EXPAN="Your Obedient Servant">Yr. Obt. Servt.</ABBR><LB><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="John">Jno</ABBR> Ross</NAME></SIGNED></CLOSER><CLOSER>P.S.<LB> for the information &amp; satisfaction of the <NAME TYPE="person">Eight Killer</NAME> you will please to drop me a line, respecting his case, <DEL TYPE="overstrike">and</DEL> also the other <DEL TYPE="overstrike">two</DEL>.  <ABBR EXPAN="your et cetera">yrs. &amp;c</ABBR><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="John">Jno</ABBR> Ross</NAME></SIGNED></CLOSER></DIV1></BODY><BACK><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><PB N="[3]"><P><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE><NAME TYPE="place">Head of Coosa</NAME> <NAME TYPE="place person"><ABBR EXPAN="Cherokee Nation">CN.</ABBR></NAME></ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE VALUE="0000-06-24">June 24</DATE></P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><P><UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR> <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="John">Jno</ABBR> Ross</NAME> <UNCLEAR>PM</UNCLEAR></P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><P><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Colonel">Colo.</ABBR> Hugh Montgomery</NAME></ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE><NAME TYPE="place">U.S.</NAME> Agent for the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME></ADDRLINE></ADDRESS></P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><P>Letter from <NAME TYPE="person">John Ross</NAME><LB><DATE VALUE="1828-06-26">26th June 1828</DATE><LB>Subject  <NAME TYPE="person">Eight Killer</NAME> &amp; others<LB>Reservations<LB><UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR> received <DATE VALUE="1828-07-09">9th July 1828</DATE></P></DIV1></BACK></TEXT></TEI.2>
