<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD"[
<!ENTITY pg1 PUBLIC "pg1" "wch024a.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg2 PUBLIC "pg2" "wch024b.djv" NDATA TIFF>
]>
<TEI.2 ID="ch024"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>[Letter] 1830 Oct. 3, Red Clay, Cherokee Nation [to David] Irwin and [Thomas G.] Barron / John Ross: a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><AUTHOR>Ross, John, 1790-1866</AUTHOR><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>ch024</IDNO><IDNO>OCLC: 44772095</IDNO><AVAILABILITY STATUS="FREE"><P>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>[Letter] 1830 Oct. 3, Red Clay, Cherokee Nation [to David] Irwin and [Thomas G.] Barron / John Ross</TITLE><AUTHOR>Ross, John, 1790-1866</AUTHOR><DATE VALUE="1830-10-03">October 3, 1830</DATE><EXTENT>2p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">This document is a letter from Principal Chief John Ross to David Irwin and Thomas G. Barron, lawyers retained by the Cherokee Nation to pursue their claims against the state of Georgia, dated October 3, 1830.  Ross indicates that the Cherokee people have rejected a recent treaty proposed by John F. Schermerhorn, regarding it as unjust and oppressive.  They intend to press their arguments further and express good faith in their legal representation.  Ross writes that he still has faith in the magnanimity of the U.S. government and maintains hope that removal can be avoided.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box"> 1</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder"> 23</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">ch024</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Letters</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Treaties</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Relocation</ITEM><ITEM>Georgia</ITEM></LIST> </KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><PB N="[1]"><OPENER><DATELINE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE><NAME TYPE="place">Red Clay</NAME> <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME></ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE VALUE="1830-10-03">October 3rd 1830</DATE></DATELINE><SALUTE><DEL TYPE="erasure"><ABBR EXPAN="Messieurs" TYPE="contraction">Messrs</ABBR></DEL> Majors <NAME REG="Major" TYPE="person">Irwin</NAME> &amp; <NAME REG="Major" TYPE="person">Barron</NAME>-<LB>Gentlemen-</SALUTE></OPENER><P>The <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> people in General Council assembled have disclaimed and most solemnly rejected the <NAME TYPE="person">Schermerhorn</NAME>'s nefarious <Q>treaty</Q> and declared it to be a fraud upon the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> and an act of oppression on the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME>, and they have appointed another delegation with full powers to bring the subject again before the Govt of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> for a final and satisfactory adjustment- this delegation are instructed to confer with the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> West with the view of acting in Concert with us on this important occasion-</P><P>It is to be hoped, that we may, in the end be able to Convince the high officers of Govt that they have been too long deceived and misled by the joint exertions of some of their own Agents and certain designing individuals, in reference to <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> affairs, if so, some thing decisive will be done, more to the honor of the <NAME TYPE="place">U.S.</NAME> Govt. and to the <ORIG REG="satisfaction">sattisfaction</ORIG> and welfare of the suffering <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME>- Policy, common justice and the claims of humanity under existing circumstances, surely cannot longer turn a deaf <DEL TYPE="overstrike"><UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR></DEL> ear<PB N="[2]"> to the Cries of the oppressed- If we succeed, you may depend upon the integrity of the Nation to act with liberal justice towards you for your legal Services to the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME>&mdash;. Nevertheless, <Q>it is hard to kick against the pricks.</Q> but my abiding confidence in the magnanimity and ultimate justice of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, will not yet permit me to believe that the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> will <DEL TYPE="overstrike">be</DEL> be drove away from their homes, their Native land, under the provisions of <DEL TYPE="overstrike">of</DEL> a fraudulent &amp; unrighteous <Q>treaty</Q>-  I feel it incumbent upon me, therefore, to comply with the Wishes of the great mass of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> to make a further effort in their behalf&mdash;. In doing so, I claim to be vindicating the faith and integrity of the <NAME TYPE="place">US.</NAME> Govt. as well as the rights and salvation of a weak and dependant people- <DEL TYPE="overstrike">but</DEL> If I fail, the disgrace will not be at my hands- nor, will the sting of retributive justice pierce my heart-.</P><CLOSER><SALUTE>I am Gentlemen, very respectfully <ABBR EXPAN="your obedient Humble Servant" TYPE="contraction">yr. obt Hble Servt.</ABBR></SALUTE><LB><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="John">Jno</ABBR> Ross</NAME></SIGNED><LB>PS.  There are certain cases pending in floyd Court in which I am a party &amp; have never been tried- the illegal fees collected from me by the sheriff on account of the clerk has never been paid to me according to the decries of <NAME TYPE="person">Judge Hooper</NAME>, all of which I trust you will attend to <UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="John Ross">JR</ABBR></NAME></SIGNED></CLOSER></DIV1></BODY></TEXT></TEI.2>
