<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD"[
<!ENTITY pg1 PUBLIC "pg1" "WCH022a.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg2 PUBLIC "pg2" "WCH022b.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg3 PUBLIC "pg3" "WCH022c.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg4 PUBLIC "pg4" "WCH022d.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg5 PUBLIC "pg5" "WCH022e.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg6 PUBLIC "pg6" "WCH022f.djv" NDATA TIFF>
]>
<TEI.2 ID="ch022"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>[Letter] 1829 Aug. 29, New Echota [to] Gov[erno]r of Tennessee, William Carroll / Jno [i.e., John] Ross ... [et al.] : a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><AUTHOR>Ross, John, 1790-1866</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hicks, William</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lowrey, George</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ridge, Major, ca. 1771-1839</AUTHOR><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>ch022</IDNO><IDNO>OCLC: 44771591</IDNO><AVAILABILITY STATUS="FREE"><P>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>[Letter] 1829 Aug. 29, New Echota [to] Gov[erno]r of Tennessee, William Carroll / Jno [i.e., John] Ross ... [et al.] </TITLE><AUTHOR>Ross, John, 1790-1866</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Hicks, William</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Lowrey, George</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Ridge, Major, ca. 1771-1839</AUTHOR><DATE VALUE="1829-08-29">August 29, 1829</DATE><EXTENT>6p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">This is a letter from a delegation of Cherokee leaders, including John Ross, William Hicks, George Lowrey, and Major Ridge, to William Carroll, Governor of Tennessee (1821-1827,1829-1835), dated August 29, 1829.  The  Cherokees express their unwillingness to convene a meeting with commissioners for the purpose of hearing proposals regarding removal to a territory west of the Mississippi River.  They indicate that they have already informed the President and the Governor that they do not intend to sell more land now or in the future and convening a meeting for that purpose would be pointless.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box"> 1</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder"> 23</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">ch022</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Letters</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Land tenure</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Relocation</ITEM><ITEM>Southern States</ITEM></LIST> </KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><PB N="[1]"><OPENER><DATELINE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE><NAME TYPE="place">New Echota</NAME> <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME></ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE VALUE="1829-08-29">August 29th 1829</DATE></DATELINE><LB><SALUTE>Dear Sir,</SALUTE></OPENER><P>Your communication of this date Containing the object of your visit to the Nation under instruction from the Secretary of War is received and maturely deliberated <DEL TYPE="overstrike"> in</DEL> on in Executive Councils Convened for the express purpose.  The deep interest felt on the part of the President of the <NAME TYPE="place">U. States</NAME> for the removal of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> West of the <NAME REG="River" TYPE="place">Mississippi</NAME> is Known to the Nation, It is a subject that has often &amp; long since been submitted for consideration and been deliberated by the Councils of the Nation with all that solemnity its importance deserves, and the conclusion and result of those deliberations have been expressed in soberness &amp; sincerity to the Govt. of the <NAME TYPE="place">U States</NAME>, adverse to a removal-  And  We declare that those sentiments and disposition remain the same and are unchangeable; you state that you are instructed simply to propose, that <Q> We will agree to meet Commissioners to be appointed<PB N="[2]">by the President, at such time as may best suit the Convenience of both parties for the purpose of discussing the subject of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> removing West of the <NAME REG="River" TYPE="place">Mississippi</NAME>; and that we would then have an opportunity of hearing the propositions of the Government.</Q>-</P><P>It is deemed inexpedient to enter into a special agreement to meet Commissioners for the purpose of discussing the subject of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> removing West of the <NAME REG="River" TYPE="place">Mississippi</NAME>.  When it is well known that the disposition of the Nation is adverse to a removal and that no proposition could be made to change their disposition as to induce them ever to enter into a treaty on the Subject- Especially as the proper authorities of the Nation are ever ready at all times to receive in the most friendly manner all public <DEL TYPE="overstrike">public</DEL> functionaries of the <NAME TYPE="place">U States</NAME> that may be appointed by the President for the purpose of Submitting Subjects for our consideration.</P><P>The Executive Department of the Nation will never neglect to attend to such business<PB N="[3]">during the recess of the <ABBR EXPAN="General">Genl.</ABBR> Council (as is manifest on the present occasion) and the Legislative Department during its session (which is convened annually on the second Monday of October) in like manner will always receive and act upon all Subjects submitted for their consideration &amp; decision  &mdash;. The right of Individual States exercising jurisdiction over the Territory solemnly secured &amp; Guarantied to the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> by treaty, is a subject that is certainly questionable&mdash; The principles contained in <ADD PLACE="supralinear">the</ADD> Constitution of the <NAME TYPE="place">U. States</NAME> &amp; the Treaties establishing relationships between the <NAME TYPE="place">U. States</NAME> &amp; the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> are in variance to the exercise of such a power by the State Government.  We are aware that a decision on this important Subject must <ADD PLACE="supralinear">seal</ADD> our fate in prosperity &amp; happiness or in <ORIG REG="misery">missery</ORIG> and <ORIG REG="destruction">distruction</ORIG>-  But Confiding in the magnanimity &amp; justice of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, we place our dependence upon their plighted faith &amp; await the result  &mdash; We are happy<PB N="[4]">to hear that <ADD PLACE="supralinear">it</ADD> affords you much <ORIG REG="satisfaction">sattisfaction</ORIG> to find that the best feelings exist every where towards the <NAME TYPE="place">U. States</NAME> in the Nation And that you will take occasion to Communicate this fact to the <ABBR EXPAN="President" TYPE="contraction">Prest.</ABBR> of the <NAME TYPE="place">U. States</NAME> in contradiction to the slanderous reports circulated by the frontier News Papers prejudicial to the best interest of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> People. Permit us Sir in addition to say that so far from the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> entertaining any hostile feelings toward the Citizens of the <NAME TYPE="place">U. States</NAME> &mdash; that in our opinion, no people could be  found in the <NAME TYPE="place">U. States</NAME>, who would, in case of actual war, prove more loyal to the cause of the <NAME TYPE="place">U. States</NAME> that the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> &mdash;.  Yourself as well as the President of the <NAME TYPE="place">U States</NAME> have witnessed this fact realized during the late war &mdash;  With great pleasure we reciprocate your wishes for the future happiness of this Nation.  In return you will please to accept the best wishes for your health &amp; happiness &amp; for the peace<PB N="[5]">and prosperity of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>&mdash;.  In behalf of the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME></P><CLOSER>We have the honor to be Sir Very Respectfully <ABBR EXPAN="Your Obedient Servants" TYPE="suspension">Yr.Obt. Servts</ABBR>.<LB><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="John">Jno</ABBR> Ross</NAME></SIGNED><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="George">Geo.</ABBR> Lowrey</NAME></SIGNED><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person">William Hicks</NAME></SIGNED><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person">Major Ridge</NAME></SIGNED> his<SIGNED>X</SIGNED> mark</CLOSER></DIV1></BODY><BACK><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><PB N="[6]"><P><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>To His <ABBR EXPAN="Excellency" TYPE="contraction">Ex.cy</ABBR></ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE><NAME TYPE="person">William Carroll</NAME></ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE><ABBR EXPAN="Governor">Govr.</ABBR> of <NAME TYPE="place">Tennessee</NAME> Present.</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS></P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><P><UNCLEAR>n</UNCLEAR></P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><P><HI REND="b">B</HI></P></DIV1></BACK></TEXT></TEI.2>
