<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD">
<TEI.2 ID="ch044"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>Letter, 1831 May 16, Milledgeville, [Georgia] to Rev[erend] Samuel A. Worcester /  George R. Gilmer: a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><AUTHOR>Georgia. Governor (1829-1831 : Gilmer)</AUTHOR><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>ch044</IDNO><IDNO>OCLC: 44843996</IDNO><AVAILABILITY STATUS="FREE"><P>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>Letter, 1831 May 16, Milledgeville, [Georgia], to Rev[erend] Samuel A. Worcester /  George R. Gilmer</TITLE><AUTHOR>Georgia. Governor (1829-1831 : Gilmer)</AUTHOR><DATE VALUE="1831-05-16"> May 16, 1831</DATE><EXTENT>2p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">A copy of a letter in which George R. Gilmer, Governor of Georgia, writes to Reverend Samuel A. Worcester informing him that all white persons who refuse to take the oath to support the constitution and laws of the state are requested to vacate Cherokee lands and that the United States does not recognize missionaries acting under the direction of the American Board of Foreign Missions as government agents, May 16, 1831.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box">1</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder">29</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">ch044</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Letters</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Missions</ITEM><ITEM>Georgia--Politics and government--1775-1865</ITEM></LIST> </KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><PB N="[1]"><P><ADD PLACE="top" CERT="appears to be different ink and hand"><HI REND="o">H.</HI></ADD></P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><HEAD><ADD PLACE="top" CERT="appears to be different ink">Letter from his Excellency <NAME TYPE="person">George R. Gilmer</NAME>, governor of the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, to <NAME TYPE="person">Rev. Samuel A Worcester</NAME>, dated at <ADDRESS><ADDRLINE><NAME TYPE="place">Milledgeville</NAME>,</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS> <DATE VALUE="1831-05-16">May 16th, 1831.</DATE></ADD></HEAD><OPENER><SALUTE>Sir,</SALUTE></OPENER><P> It is a part of my official duty to cause all white persons residing within the territory of the State, occupied by the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> to be removed therefrom, who refuse to take the oath to support the constitution and laws of the State</P><P>Information has been received of your continued residence within that territory, without complying with the requisites of the law, and of your claim to be exempted from its operation, on an account of your holding the office of postmaster of <NAME TYPE="place">New Echota</NAME>.</P><P>You have no doubt been informed of your dismissal from that office.  That you may be under no mistake as to this matter, you are also informed the government of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> does not <ORIG REG="recognize">recognise</ORIG> as its agents the missionaries acting under the direction of the American Board of Foreign Missions.  Whatever may have been your conduct in opposing the humane policy of the general government, or exciting the Indians to oppose the jurisdiction of the State,<PB N="[2]">I am still desirous of giving you and all others similarly situated, an opportunity of avoiding the punishment which will certainly follow your further residence within the state contrary to its laws.  You are therefore, advised to remove from the territory of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, occupied by the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME>.</P><P><NAME TYPE="person">Col. Sanford</NAME>, the commander of the Guard, will be requested to have this letter delivered to you, and to delay your arrest until you shall have had an opportunity of leaving the State.</P><CLOSER><SALUTE>Very respectfully, yours, <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera">&amp;c.</ABBR></SALUTE> <ADD PLACE="left" CERT="appears to be different ink">(Signed)</ADD><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person">George R. Gilmer</NAME>.</SIGNED><ADD PLACE="bottom" CERT="appears to be different ink"><ABBR EXPAN="Nota Bene">N.B.</ABBR> Letters similar in <UNCLEAR>purport</UNCLEAR>, except so far as the fact that <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Worcester</NAME> held the office of postmaster occasioned a difference were sent and on the same date to <ABBR EXPAN="Messieurs">Messrs.</ABBR> <NAME REG="Mr." TYPE="person">Butrick</NAME> &amp; <NAME REG="Mr." TYPE="person">Proctor</NAME>, at <NAME TYPE="place">Carmel</NAME>; <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Thompson</NAME> at <NAME TYPE="place">Hightower</NAME>, &amp; <NAME TYPE="person">Dr. Butler</NAME>, at <NAME TYPE="place">Haweis</NAME>.</ADD></CLOSER></DIV1></BODY></TEXT></TEI.2>
