<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD">
<TEI.2 ID="ch047"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>[Extract from a] letter, 1831 June 23, Hightower Mission, [Cherokee Nation] to Mr. [Samuel] Worcester : a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>ch047</IDNO><IDNO>oclc: 44844893</IDNO><AVAILABILITY STATUS="FREE"><P>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>[Extract from a] letter, 1831 June 23, Hightower Mission, [Cherokee Nation] to Mr. [Samuel] Worcester</TITLE><DATE VALUE="1831-06-23">June 23, 1831</DATE><EXTENT>3p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">Extract from a letter dated June 23, 1831 from Miss Fuller, a teacher at the Hightower Mission in the Cherokee Nation, to Samuel Worcester, a Christian missionary living in the Nation. Fuller describes how the Georgia guard led by Colonel Charles H. Nelson came to occupy the mission house and arrest John Thompson, another missionary, for the second time. The copy of a letter from Thompson to Nelson concerning the guards' occupancy of the mission house is included in Fuller's correspondence.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box">1</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder">29</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">ch047</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Missions</ITEM><ITEM>Georgia--Politics and government--1775-1865</ITEM></LIST> </KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="letter military"><PB N="[1]"><HEAD><ADD PLACE="top" CERT="appears to be different ink and hand">L.<LB>Letter of <NAME TYPE="person">Miss Fuller</NAME>, teacher at <NAME TYPE="place">Hightower</NAME>, To <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Worcester</NAME>, detailing the circumstances of the visit of the <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> guard  to that station, &amp; the second arrest of <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Thompson</NAME>, June 22: dated June 23, 1831</ADD></HEAD><OPENER><SALUTE>Rev. and Dear Sir&mdash;</SALUTE></OPENER><P>It falls to my lot to communicate to you notice of <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Thompson</NAME>'s second arrest, together with the circumstances which led to it, so far as they have come under my observation.</P><P>Last evening, about 6 O'clock, <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Nelson</NAME> called on me, inquired for <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Thompson</NAME>, and also respecting my situation, and made a single remark respecting the loneliness of it.  <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Thompson</NAME> was absent &mdash; of course I told him so.  He then told me that as he found me here situated as I am, he should not occupy this house the next night, but with much assurance added, "We shall occupy it tomorrow night,"  He further said, "You can go or stay as you please.  If you stay you shall be protected" My reply was, " I must stay," "Very well," said he, and again repeated his promise of protection.  He then remarked that they considered it their privilege to occupy these abandoned places; spoke of being somewhat troubled for forage for his horses, and intimated that what was growing on these places belonged to them; &mdash; that nothing of last year's growth would<PB N="[2]">be required, but only the present; "for," said he, "we consider them as intrusions upon our state." &mdash; However much I might have felt disposed to remonstrate, I had not sufficient command of my feelings to permit me to do it.</P><P>Supposing that it must be so, if <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Thompson</NAME> did not return before the appointed time, and not being certain that he would, I asked <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Nelson</NAME> what part of the house he should occupy, "One room will be sufficient for us, there are only ten of us," was his answer.  Providentially, however, <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Thompson</NAME> arrived about an hour after <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Nelson</NAME>'s call.  He felt it his plain duty, not passively to yield the possession of his house into <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Nelson</NAME>'s hands, and accordingly dispatched a messenger to him, early this morning, with a letter, of which the following is a copy.</P><P><Q><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="letter military"><OPENER><DATELINE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE><NAME TYPE="place">Hightower</NAME> Mission,</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS> <DATE VALUE="1831-06-23">June 23. 1831</DATE></DATELINE><SALUTE><NAME TYPE="person">Col. Charles H. Nelson</NAME>,<LB>Sir, &mdash;</SALUTE></OPENER><P>I have been informed that you design to occupy the mission-house this evening, with a detachment of the <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> guard.  In regard to this subject, we can only say, that we have not the accommodations desirable to entertain yourself and company, and for this, and other reasons, you will excuse me in saying, that if your design is effected, it will be without my consent. </P><P>Permit me to add, that if an interview with me on this or any other subject is desired, it may be obtained at this place, at any time during the course<PB N="[3]">of this day.</P><CLOSER><SALUTE>I am, sir, very respectfully, Your obedient servant, </SALUTE><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person">John Thompson</NAME></SIGNED></CLOSER></DIV1></BODY></TEXT></Q></P><P>Both <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Thompson</NAME> and myself expected that it would result in his arrest; and therefore we were prepared to see armed men, which we did, and to hear one of them say,  "You may consider yourself a prisoner, Sir."  <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Thompson</NAME> was all ready, and did not detain them five minutes  They told him he would have no use for his horse, so, of course, he walked.  They spent the day at <NAME TYPE="person">Major Dawson</NAME>'s about two miles distant.  The company are to leave for head quarters tomorrow.</P><P>Since <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Thompson</NAME> is a prisoner, I suppose I may stay here without molestation as heretofore.  Do you think, Sir, that it is improper for me to stay as I do?  I know that in common cases it would not be proper, but I trust that in the present instance it is right.  I am desirous to stay, for I think that as soon as it is known that the people have left the house, some base intruder, if not the <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> guard, will take possession of it.  As yet I have no fears which would prevent my staying, though thus unprotected.  My heavenly Protector is ever near for my defence.  I trust that whatever may come, I may not be greatly moved.</P></DIV1></BODY></TEXT></TEI.2>
