<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD">
<TEI.2 ID="ch065"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>Cherokee Council's decision of the conflicting claims of Mrs. E. Pack [and] Jno. [i.e., John] H. Jeffrey, 1820 Apr. 22, Council House near Hicks' Mill / [signed by] John Ross : a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>ch065</IDNO><IDNO>oclc: 44854118</IDNO><AVAILABILITY STATUS="FREE"><P>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>Cherokee Council's decision of the conflicting claims of Mrs. E. Pack [and] Jno. [i.e., John] H. Jeffrey, 1820 Apr. 22, Council House near Hicks' Mill / [signed by] John Ross</TITLE><DATE VALUE="1820-04-22">April 22, 1820</DATE><EXTENT>2p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">Copy of a legal decision of the Cherokee Council dated April 22, 1820 concerning a property dispute between Mrs. E. Pack, who purchased property from Charles Hicks, and John H. Jeffrey, who claims right due to his marriage to a Cherokee woman. The council decides in favor of Pack. Elijah Hicks created this copy.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box">3</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder">4</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">ch065</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Claims</ITEM><ITEM>Southern States</ITEM></LIST> </KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><FRONT><DIV1 TYPE="legal decision claim"><PB N="[1]"><P><NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> Council's decision of the <UNCLEAR>conflicting</UNCLEAR> claims of <NAME TYPE="person">Mrs. E. <UNCLEAR>Pack</UNCLEAR></NAME> &amp; <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="John">Jno.</ABBR> H. Jeffrey</NAME><LB><DATE VALUE="1820-04-22">22nd April 1820</DATE>.</P></DIV1></FRONT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="legal decision claim">
<PB N="[2]"><OPENER><DATELINE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Council House near <NAME REG="Elijah?" TYPE="person">Hicks</NAME> mill</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS> <DATE VALUE="1820-04-22">April 22. 1820</DATE></DATELINE></OPENER><HEAD>In Council assembled.</HEAD><P>The national Committee and chiefs assembled for the purpose of deliberating and deciding on the following Subjects Viz.</P><P>1st. The sale of <NAME TYPE="place">neecoojack</NAME> improvement by <NAME TYPE="person">Charles Hicks</NAME> <ORIG REG="through">thro.</ORIG> the approbation of Sundry Chiefs to <NAME TYPE="person">Mrs. E Pack</NAME> and the forcible possession taken of said place by a certain <NAME TYPE="person">John H. Jeffrey</NAME> under pretext of having married a <NAME TYPE="person">Cherok<GAP DESC="ee" REASON="document edge"></NAME> wife the daughter of <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Thomas" TYPE="contraction">Thos.</ABBR> Wilson</NAME> a <UNCLEAR>reservee</UNCLEAR> citizen of the state of <NAME TYPE="place">Alabama</NAME> named <NAME TYPE="person">Alcey</NAME>, which circumstance has produced much confusion between the said <NAME TYPE="person">Mrs. E. Pack</NAME> and <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="John" TYPE="contraction">Jno.</ABBR> H. Jeffrey</NAME> and having a tendency of <ORIG REG="debarring">debaring</ORIG> the said <NAME TYPE="person">Mrs. Pack</NAME> from a peaceable possession of said improvements  Therefore Resolved that it is expedient that the said <NAME TYPE="person">John H. Jeffrey</NAME> be <ORIG REG="dispossessed">disspossed</ORIG> of the said place and put into the peaceable possession of the said <NAME TYPE="person">Mrs. E. Pack</NAME> by the legal authority of the nation.</P><CLOSER>True Copy <SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person">Elijah Hicks</NAME></SIGNED> <ABBR EXPAN="Clerk" TYPE="contraction">Clk</ABBR><LB>By order of Committee and chiefs assembled this day &amp; year above written signed, <SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person">John Ross</NAME></SIGNED></CLOSER></DIV1></BODY></TEXT></TEI.2>
