<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD">
<TEI.2 ID="ch063"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>Form of [a] treaty [between the Cherokee Nation and the United States], 1835[?] : a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>ch063</IDNO><IDNO>oclc: 44853665</IDNO><AVAILABILITY STATUS="FREE"><P>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>Form of [a] treaty [between the Cherokee Nation and the United States], 1835[?]</TITLE><DATE VALUE="1835-00-00">1835</DATE><EXTENT>4p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">Copy of a treaty form for negotiations between the Cherokee Nation and the United States. The treaty pertains to the removal of the Cherokees east of the Mississippi River. The treaty articles listed detail payment for land, improvements, and loss of crops and release of Cherokees who have been seized, as well as the logistics of emigrating. The date 1838 which appears on the treaty form is dubious in light of historical record.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box">3</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder">4</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">ch063</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Treaties</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Relocation</ITEM><ITEM>Southern States</ITEM></LIST> </KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="legal treaty"><PB N="[1]"><P>Whereas it has become expedient, under existing circumstances, that the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> should be released from various treaty <ADD PLACE="supralinear">oaths </ADD> solemnly guaranteeing to the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee nation</NAME> of Indians protection forever in the lands of the said nation, east of the <NAME REG="River" TYPE="place">Mississippi</NAME>,&mdash; provided, <DEL TYPE="overstrike">that we</DEL> in effecting this release, such conditions can be secured as will bring about the transfer of the aforesaid <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> lands to the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, <Q>peaceably and on reasonable terms,</Q>&mdash;</P><P>Now, Therefore, <GAP REASON="blank on page"> duly <ORIG REG="authorized">authorised</ORIG> and empowered to treat with the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> east of the <NAME REG="River" TYPE="place">Mississippi</NAME>, and <NAME TYPE="person">John Ross</NAME>, <GAP REASON="blank on page"> duly <ORIG REG="authorized">authorised</ORIG> and empowered by the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee nation</NAME>, in general council assembled, have entered into, agreed upon, and concluded, the following articles of a Treaty of cession and removal, this <GAP REASON="blank on page">  day of <GAP REASON="blank on page"> , <DATE VALUE="1838-00-00">1838</DATE>.</P><P>Article 1. - The <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee nation</NAME> of Indians, upon the conditions hereinafter expressed, do hereby cede, relinquish and convey to the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> of <NAME TYPE="place">North America</NAME>, all their right and title to all the lands owned, claimed and possessed by them, including the unsold lands reserved by them for a school fund, east of the <NAME TYPE="place">Mississippi river</NAME>.</P><P>Article <DEL TYPE="overstrike"><UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR></DEL>  2. - The sum of <GAP REASON="blank on page"> is to be paid by the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, in full for the cession <ADD PLACE="supralinear">forever</ADD> to the Said <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> country east of the <NAME REG="River" TYPE="place">Mississippi</NAME>:</P><P>Article 3. - The said sum of <GAP REASON="blank on page"> and all other sums, arising under this Treaty, are to be paid to the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee nation</NAME>, and to be subject to the <ORIG REG="control">controul</ORIG> and disposition of its regularly constituted authorities:</P><P>Article 4. - a sum of <GAP REASON="blank on page"> shall be <ORIG REG="separately">seperately</ORIG> allowed on the part of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, to indemnify the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> for all property destroyed and for all other claims of any and every description against the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, for which the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> is already liable under<PB N="[2]">former Treaties.</P><P><HI>Article 5.</HI>&mdash; A Sum of <GAP REASON="blank on page"> shall be further allowed by the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, to cover all the <ORIG REG="expenses">expences</ORIG> of removal from the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> country, which removal is to be effected under the management of the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee nation</NAME>:</P><P><HI>Article 6.</HI>  A patent in fee simple shall be given by the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> to the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee nation</NAME>, for all the land wh<GAP REASON="edge of document"> has been previously assigned and exchanged for, under former Treaties:</P><P><HI>Article 7.</HI>  All improvements belonging to <DEL TYPE="overstrike"> the</DEL> <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> east of the <NAME REG="River" TYPE="place">Mississippi</NAME> shall be assessed by agents nominated by the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> delegation and approved by the Secretary of War, and shall be paid for by the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> out of the sum paid by the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> for the cession of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> country:</P><P><HI>Article 8.</HI>  The <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee nation</NAME> will complete their entire withdrawal from the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> country, on or before the expiration of two years from the ratification of the present Treaty:</P><P><HI>Article 9. </HI>  The <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> will protect the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee nation</NAME>, according to the stipulations under former Treaties, until the removal of the whole nation,  <ADD PLACE="supralinear">as here agreed upon</ADD> shall be <ORIG REG="completed">compleated</ORIG>:</P><P><HI>Article 10. </HI>  To prevent, as far as may come within their power, any difficulties with the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, the <NAME TYPE="person">Cheroke</NAME><GAP REASON="edge of document"> will undertake entirely to quit that state, on or before the expiration of <GAP REASON="blank on page"> from the ratification of this Treaty; &mdash; with the full understanding <DEL TYPE="overstrike">that</DEL> and engagement <DEL TYPE="overstrike">that</DEL> <ADD PLACE="supralinear">on the part of</ADD> the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, that an allowance <DEL TYPE="overstrike"><UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR></DEL> <ADD PLACE="supralinear">shall be made to such </ADD> <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> as <DEL TYPE="overstrike"><UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR></DEL> <ADD PLACE="supralinear">I will</ADD> within  the limits claimed by <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, <DEL TYPE="overstrike">of</DEL> for the loss of their present crops, according to the value of each respective crop, and a sum of per head, for subsistence elsewhere, upon the vacant<PB N="[3]">the vacant lands of their country, until they can finally remove, according to their stipulation; or, provided <DEL TYPE="overstrike"><UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR></DEL> claimants to the lands in <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, shall prefer to allow them, or any of them, to remain in their present abodes, till they can finally remove from the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> Country, the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> will allow the <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> claimants to the respective residence, thus occupied, the sum of <GAP REASON="blank on page"> per acre as rental, for the remainder of the term during which the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> shall retain the occupancy, under the conditions of the treaty:</P><P><HI>Article 12. </HI>  All <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> who have been seized and imprisoned under the laws of the adjoining States, are to be released by the respective state, and allowed to remove with the rest of the nation and upon the same conditions.</P><PB N="[4]"></DIV1></BODY><BACK><DIV1 TYPE="legal treaty"><P>Form of Treaty <DATE VALUE="1835-00-00">1835</DATE>.</P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="legal treaty"><P>from <NAME REG="John?" TYPE="person">Ross</NAME> Papers <DATE VALUE="1930-03-08">March 8, 1930</DATE>.</P></DIV1></BACK></TEXT></TEI.2>
