<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD"[
<!ENTITY pg1 PUBLIC "pg1" "WCH067a.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg10 PUBLIC "pg10" "WCH067j.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg11 PUBLIC "pg11" "WCH067k.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg12 PUBLIC "pg12" "WCH067l.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg2 PUBLIC "pg2" "WCH067b.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg3 PUBLIC "pg3" "WCH067c.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg4 PUBLIC "pg4" "WCH067d.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg5 PUBLIC "pg5" "WCH067e.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg6 PUBLIC "pg6" "WCH067f.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg7 PUBLIC "pg7" "WCH067g.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg8 PUBLIC "pg8" "WCH067h.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg9 PUBLIC "pg9" "WCH067i.djv" NDATA TIFF>
]>
<TEI.2 ID="ch067"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>[Letter], 1823 Apr. 25, near Fortville, Cherokee Nation : a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>ch067</IDNO><IDNO>oclc: 44861132</IDNO><AVAILABILITY STATUS="FREE"><P>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>[Letter], 1823 Apr. 25, near Fortville, Cherokee Nation</TITLE><DATE VALUE="1823-04-25">April 25, 1823</DATE><EXTENT>12p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">Letter dated April 25, 1823 from the Cherokee Council to (U.S. Commissioners Duncan G. Campbell and James Meriwether ?) in response to a communication from these commissioners. The Council considers the commissioners' plea to repeal a resolution which disallows further land cession so that the commissioners can meet with the Council in Taloney and proceed with further negotiations. The Council responds in the negative, stating that the resolution was made to promote the interest and happiness of the Cherokee people and that no meeting will take place in Taloney because the seat of government is in New Town. A lengthy extract from the commissioners' letter follows which sets out arguments for the Cherokees to agree to further land cessions and remove west.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box">3</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder">5</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">ch067</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Land tenure</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Relocation</ITEM><ITEM>Southern States</ITEM></LIST> </KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><PB N="[1]"><OPENER><DATELINE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Near <NAME TYPE="place">Fortville</NAME>, <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME></ADDRLINE></ADDRESS> <DATE VALUE="1823-04-25">April 25th. 1823</DATE></DATELINE><SALUTE>2nd Council Convened<LB>Friends &amp; Brothers,</SALUTE></OPENER><P>The undersigned chiefs in behalf of the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> convened in council for the purpose of taking into consideration your communication of the <DATE VALUE="0000-02-10">10th February last</DATE> urging the repeal of the Resolutions of <DATE VALUE="1822-10-00">October 1822</DATE>.  So that a convention may take place at <NAME TYPE="place">Taloney</NAME> on the <DATE VALUE="0000-08-09">9th <ADD PLACE="supralinear">day </ADD> August next</DATE> for the purpose of entering into various topics of negotiation with you as <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> commissioners. &mdash; We have therefore maturely considered the subject contained in your several communications to our Head Chief, Mr. <NAME TYPE="person">Charles R. Hicks</NAME> and to the nation. &mdash; Brothers, It is with deep regret we have noticed the feeling with which you have expressed your sentiments towards the Resolutions of <DATE VALUE="1822-10-00">October 1822</DATE>. and the course which have been pursued by the nation in not meeting you at the Agency in <DATE VALUE="0000-01-00">January last</DATE>; and this strict <ORIG REG="adherence">adhereance</ORIG> to those Resolutions &mdash; you have thought proper to denounce those resolutions as being <HI>premature</HI>, <HI>disrespectful</HI> and of <HI>dangerous tendency</HI>.  Brothers; Surely you could not have read those resolutions with attention, or otherwise you could<PB N="[2]">not with due reflection have asserted what has been declared by the committee and council as emanating from <DEL TYPE="overstrike">mature</DEL> <HI>mature deliberation</HI>, to be premature.  Brothers, We declare in behalf of the nation and ourselves, that those Resolutions were adopted from just and proper motives, being actuated from an impulse of preserving and promoting the true interest and happiness of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> People, and that no disrespect or contempt to the general Government or to her commissioners are offered or intended.  So far is it from any such intention, that the concluding part of the general Resolution observes <Q>but on any other business not relating to making a Treaty of cession we will at all times during the Session of the National Council at <NAME TYPE="place">New Town</NAME> receive the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> Commissioners or agents with friendship and cordiality, and will even keep <HI>bright</HI> the <HI>chain</HI> of <HI>peace</HI> and <HI>friendship</HI> which <HI>links</HI> the <HI><NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME></HI> and the <HI>Government</HI> of the <HI><NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME></HI>,</Q> Such are the sentiments which you have so strongly protested against, as being <HI>premature</HI>, <HI>disrespectful</HI>, and of <HI>dangerous tendency</HI>, and so desirous that the chiefs should repeal so that a convention may take place on the <DATE VALUE="0000-08-09">9th August next</DATE> at <NAME TYPE="place">Taloney</NAME>, and the difficulties and breach which has taken place, between the President and his favorite Indian children may be healed."</P><PB N="[3]"><P>If these your expressions, flow from deliberate reflections and be your <HI>real</HI> construction of the Sentiments which we have quoted from the aforesaid Resolution &mdash; We are really at a loss how you could suppose that we could ever agree with your ideas, how to promote the <HI>welfare</HI> and <HI>happiness</HI> of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME>, when your object is to obtain their lands, and to seek compensation for things which have long since been solemnly adjusted by a Treaty and forgotten. &mdash;  Brothers, in adhering to our Resolutions we neither offer <HI>disrespect, contempt</HI> or refused to receive Ministers or commissioners of the <NAME TYPE="place">U. States</NAME> &mdash; during the sitting of the council which adopted this general Resolution, a communication, accompanying a copy of the Resolution was forwarded by the Chiefs in Council, to the Honorable Secretary of War and a letter was also written to the then agent <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Colonel">Colo.</ABBR> Meigs</NAME>, informing him of the course adopted by the council and requesting him to communicate the same to the <NAME TYPE="place">U States</NAME> commissioners in his correspondence with them, So that they may not be <ORIG REG="disappointed">dissappointed</ORIG> in coming forward to call a Treaty, and that the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> may  be saved the useless <ORIG REG="expenses">expences</ORIG> of making necessary preparations and of procuring supplies for a Treaty <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera">&amp;c.</ABBR> All this was done in <DATE VALUE="1822-10-00">October 1822</DATE> a considerable time previous to your fixing the time for a meeting and to entering into a contract <DEL TYPE="overstrike">with</DEL> for supplies <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera">&amp;c</ABBR> under these circumstances <PB N="[4]">you came forward and the <Q><HI>failure</HI>, <HI>exposure</HI> <HI>expense</HI> and <HI>trouble</HI></Q> which you complain of, <ORIG REG="occurred">occured</ORIG> &mdash; all these <ORIG REG="occurrences">occurences</ORIG> may be attributed, as we suppose, to the very little confidence and respect you had for the proceedings of our council &mdash; Brothers, To avoid similar <ORIG REG="occurrences">occurences</ORIG>, we now declare to you that the Resolution of Council emanated from due regard to the interest, happiness, and prosperity, of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> People and that its adoption <SIC CORR="was founded">was founded was founded</SIC> upon <HI>mature deliberation</HI> and that it will be strictly <DEL TYPE="overstrike"> adhered to</DEL> observed and cannot be repealed &mdash; and further &mdash; that we do hereby solemnly protest before God &amp; man against the nation meeting you at <NAME TYPE="place">Taloney</NAME> on the <DATE VALUE="0000-08-09">9th August next</DATE> as you <ADD PLACE="supralinear">have</ADD> suggested &mdash;  We have but one seat for our General Council, which is at <NAME TYPE="place">New Town</NAME>, and should you come forward during our next General Council at that place, the Committee &amp; Council will take you by the hand as Friends &amp; Brothers and hear what you have to say on the subject of your mission.  We know of no instance of Ministers or Commissioners to a foreign court persisting in selecting a spot remote from the Seat of Government to which their embassy were directed for negotiation; and of taking it entirely upon themselves to fix the time for a convention.  We make these remarks, because you have intimated that "a refusal to receive <PB N="[5]">Government by which you have been preserved and fostered.  Other Governments would have triumphed in your downfall, and held you down by cruelty, and oppression.  Such has not been the conduct of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>.  She has set an example which the whole civilized world ought to feel proud, to follow. It has been your unhappy lot to be shut out  from the advantage which many others enjoy;  It has been the constant study and exertion, of the government to relieve, you from, your unfortunate condition.  The struggle has been long but not in vain.  What was promised you by your first father <NAME REG="George" TYPE="person">Washington</NAME>, has been fully performed by those great friends of mankind who have followed him.  Under the kind protection of these earthly fathers you have been taught that you have a father above to whom you are accountable.  It should be your pride to act up to the <ADD PLACE="supralinear">near</ADD> relationship which exists between you and the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> &mdash;  If the President practices towards you the kind treatment of father, it becomes your duty, to return the obedience and gratitude of children.  You have received this kindness from government from the close of the Revolutionary war up to the present time.</P><P>The President acknowledges that you deserve it by the steadiness of your fidelity.  Your conduct as a Nation has been peaceable and harmless, although some of your <PB N="[6]">citizens, have been at times restless and troublesome.</P><P>We doubt not but that some of our citizens are liable to the same charges.  You have embraced the only, opportunity which has <ORIG REG="occurred">occured</ORIG>, of showing, that you are <ORIG REG="Warriors">Warriours</ORIG>, and that you are faithful to the country.</P><P>In the last War you were found bravely fighting by the side of the white man, your brother; against the enemies of liberty.  These enemies would have seduced you if they could, and after making you traitors to your father the President, they would have become traitors to you.   There would have followed a scene of desolation, at which every good man and Christian would weep;  It was your fidelity which prevented it, and the hand of the red man &amp; the whiteman were not raised against each other.  The redman and the whiteman now are brothers, and long may they so continue&mdash;</P><P>Brothers, these remarks have grown out of feelings which have been inspired by our acquaintance with you.  Coming as we do clothed in the high authority of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, we are left to speak the undisguised sentiments of sincerity,  We have done so and hope and expect to be met in the same spirit of conciliation and friendship.</P><PB N="[7]"><P>Having made these remarks, we now proceed to lay before you the subject of our mission.  We know that it is one which you have anticipated and upon which you have already expressed <DEL TYPE="overstrike">an opinion</DEL> yourselves with some earnestness <DEL TYPE="overstrike"><UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR></DEL>.  We must ask you to suspend any conclusion <ORIG REG="until">untill</ORIG> we have <ADD PLACE="supralinear">carried</ADD> the matter through a calm and deliberate discussion.  The whole of the authorities of the nation are now around their great council fire, with power to do any act they may think proper.  The authority of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> is also present.  Any contract which may be now concluded will be binding on both parties.</P><P>We propose to purchase of the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> the <HI>whole</HI> or a <HI>part of the territory</HI> now occupied by them and lying within the chartered limits of the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>.  We do not confine ourselves to <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> limits, because we are <NAME TYPE="person">Georgians</NAME>, but because the President has appointed us at the instance of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> and instructed us accordingly.  We will give you the reasons why a purchase is pressed by the general government for the use of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>.  Previous to the <DATE VALUE="1802-04-24">24th day of April 1802</DATE>, <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> held the right of Sovereignty over an immense space of <DEL TYPE="overstrike">territory</DEL> country extending even out to the<PB N="[8]"><NAME TYPE="place">Mississippi River</NAME>.  The general government seeing <DEL TYPE="overstrike">that</DEL> that the territory was too large to be contained within the limits of one State, made application to <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> for the purchase of a part of it.  This was for the purpose of organizing new States, and having them settled and populated for the better defence of the country in case of war.  <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> listened to the application of her father the President, and sold all the land which now lies in the States of <NAME TYPE="place">Mississippi</NAME> and <NAME TYPE="place">Alabama</NAME>.  This happened on the day above Stated.  At the same time, in consideration of this sale, the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> bound herself "at her own expense to extinguish for the use of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> as early as the same could be peaceably <DEL TYPE="overstrike">and reasonably</DEL> obtained <DEL TYPE="overstrike">and</DEL> on reasonable terms, the Indian title "to all lands within the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>.  The limits of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> are known to you, and the amount of territory occupied by you within those limits is also known to you.  For greater certainty , however concerning those limits, and the obligations of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> to the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, we refer you to the articles of agreement and cession entered into on the day and year aforesaid, between, <NAME TYPE="person">James Jackson</NAME>, &mdash;<PB N="[9]"><NAME TYPE="person">Abraham Baldwin</NAME>, and <NAME TYPE="person">John Milledge</NAME> on the part of the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, and <NAME TYPE="person">James Madison</NAME>, &amp; <NAME TYPE="person">Albert Gallatin</NAME> &amp; <NAME TYPE="person">Levi Lincoln</NAME> on the part of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>.   See laws of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> <ABBR EXPAN="Volume" TYPE="suspension">Vol.</ABBR> 1st  Page 488-</P><P>By these articles you discover the rights of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> and the obligations of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>.  That these rights may be fulfilled and these obligations discharged, is the important object of the present mission.  The sovereignty of the country which you occupy, is in the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> alone.  No State or foreign power can enter into a treaty or compact with you.  These privileges have passed away, and your intercourse is restricted, exclusively to the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>.  In matters of cession of territory, you are recognized as a contracting party.</P><P>The <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> possessing the <HI><ORIG REG="sovereignty">soverignty</ORIG></HI>, and the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> being in <HI>possession</HI>, your consent is asked for the extinction of your title to the void within the <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> lines.  We concede that the terms must be "peaceable" and "reasonable".  Our offer to purchase, establishes the first, and the consideration which may be agreed on, we trust, will be satisfactory as to the second.</P><PB N="[10]"><P>Beyond the <NAME REG="River" TYPE="place">Mississippi</NAME> the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> possess large domains of unsettled territory, embracing great variety of soil and climate.  A portion of this Nation is already there.  If those with whom we are now treating are disposed to emigrate, then we offer territory in exchange of such extent, and accompanied by such other advantages, as may be agreed on.  If this offer is not acceptable then we submit another, equally "peaceable" and <DEL TYPE="overstrike"><UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR></DEL> equally  "reasonable".  It is that you cede to the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, for the use of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, such part of the territory within her limits as can be easily spared.  Many reasons might be given which have induced <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> to urge her claim for land upon the general government.</P><P>The reasons have appeared satisfactory to the Legislature and Governor of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, and to the President &amp; Congress of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>.  Some of these reasons grow out of <ADD PLACE="supralinear">the</ADD> political connection of the <NAME TYPE="place"><DEL TYPE="overstrike">United</DEL> States</NAME>, and others out of the crowded Settlements of the people.</P><P>It is not necessary to detail the first, they are <HI>urgent</HI> and must at some time have their weight.  The last are plain to the view of every one who travels through that part of the Presidents dominion, &mdash;  </P><P>His White <PB N="[11]">people are becoming so much crowded, that they are driven from friends and <ORIG REG="connections">connexions</ORIG> to foreign lands.  Others are confined to a scanty piece of soil without timber for fencing or fuel.  To prove these statements, we need only  refer to the amount of our population and the rapidity of its increase.  In the county in which one of us resides there are <ORIG REG="Eighteen">Eighten</ORIG> Thousand inhabitants.&mdash;</P><P>The State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> in <DATE VALUE="1810-00-00">1810</DATE> contained 252433 inhabitants.  In <DATE VALUE="1820-00-00">1820</DATE>, -344,773,- showing an increase in ten years of 92,340, and yet the present settlements of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> do not <ADD PLACE="supralinear">very</ADD> greatly exceed the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> in extent, which contains about 12,000 inhabitants.  This difference is too great over to <ADD PLACE="supralinear">have</ADD> been intended by the great father of the Universe, who must have given the Earth, <HI>equally</HI>, to be the inheritance of his white and red children.&mdash;</P><P>Whether you dispose of all we ask for by exchange, or of a part by Sale, still you have enough, and to spare.  For each man, woman, and child of the nation, a large allowance will be left, even enough for thousands yet unborn.  Surely under this view of the Subject, when so much good is to result on our side, and so little, in fact, no evil, to the other, you will yield to our application.</P><P><PB N="[12]">Brothers, we have thus made known to you the subject of our mission and some of the reasons we support of it.  In a matter of so much consequence to the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, it certainly becomes you to deliberate, to look well to this matter in all its bearings.  To do unto us, as you would have us do unto you under like circumstances.</P><P>In such time as will best suit your convenience we shall expect an answer.  We believe that we shall receive one which shall comport with the calmness and friendly disposition of the council.  It is not to be supposed that an affair which involves so much might and importance is easily to be disposed of.  We shall therefore beg leave to reserve to ourselves the <ORIG REG="privilege">privelege</ORIG> of reply as often <DEL TYPE="overstrike">as often</DEL> as we may consider it necessary</P><CLOSER><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person">Duncan G. Campbell</NAME></SIGNED><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person">James Meriwether</NAME></SIGNED> <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> Commissioners</CLOSER></DIV1></BODY></TEXT></TEI.2>
