<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD"[
<!ENTITY pg1 PUBLIC "pg1" "WCH070a.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg10 PUBLIC "pg10" "WCH070j.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg11 PUBLIC "pg101" "WCH070k.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg2 PUBLIC "pg2" "WCH070b.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg3 PUBLIC "pg3" "WCH070c.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg4 PUBLIC "pg4" "WCH070d.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg5 PUBLIC "pg5" "WCH070e.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg6 PUBLIC "pg6" "WCH070f.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg7 PUBLIC "pg7" "WCH070g.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg8 PUBLIC "pg8" "WCH070h.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg9 PUBLIC "pg9" "WCH070i.djv" NDATA TIFF>
]>
<TEI.2 ID="ch070"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>[Letter] 1823 Oct. 21. Newtown, to the council of the Cherokee Nation / Duncan G. Campbell [and] James Meriwether: a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><AUTHOR>Campbell, Duncan Green, 1787-1828</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Meriwether, James</AUTHOR><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>ch070</IDNO><IDNO>oclc: 44862620</IDNO><AVAILABILITY STATUS="FREE"><P>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>[Letter] 1823 Oct. 21. Newtown, to the council of the Cherokee Nation / Duncan G. Campbell [and] James Meriwether</TITLE><AUTHOR>Campbell, Duncan Green, 1787-1828</AUTHOR><AUTHOR>Meriwether, James</AUTHOR><DATE VALUE="1823-10-21">October 21, 1823</DATE><EXTENT>11p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">This document is a letter or talk delivered to the General Council of the Cherokee Nation, by U.S. treaty commissioners Duncan G. Campbell and James Meriwether, and dated October 21, 1823.  The commissioners patronizingly explain the relationship between the United States government and the Cherokee people and attempt to rationalize the continued efforts to acquire Cherokee lands.  They insist that it is unfair that the Cherokees possess more land than they can physically occupy and thereby attempt to justify the intrusions of overzealous frontier settlers.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box">3</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder">5</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">ch070</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Land tenure</ITEM><ITEM>Southern States</ITEM></LIST> </KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><PB N="[1]"><OPENER>The following is a reply from the Commissioners to the Council<DATELINE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE><NAME TYPE="place">Newtown</NAME></ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE VALUE="1823-10-21">Oct. 21st. 1823</DATE></DATELINE><SALUTE>To the council of the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME><LB> Friends &amp; Brothers</SALUTE></OPENER><P>Your communication of yesterday was handed us by your messenger.  We feel constrained by duty and instruction to reply, and to reserve to ourselves the <HI>privilege</HI> of reply, as often as we may consider it necessary.  In doing this we violate no sentiment which we have heretofore expressed with regard to this Nation.  Nothing would give us a deeper regret than to find that our <DEL TYPE="overstrike">compliance</DEL> <ADD PLACE="supralinear">confidence</ADD> has been misplaced, and our encomiums improperly bestowed.  Of this we have no apprehension at present, and shall pursue the negotiation under the hope that it will yet be closed in a manner which shall comport with the just expectations of the General Government.</P><PB N="[2]"><P>Brothers, <LB>The relation in which this Nations stands to the Government of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, is somewhat peculiar.  The original title of this soil is acknowledged to have been in you.  There was a time when most of the <ORIG REG="territory">teritory</ORIG> now composing the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, belonged to various tribes of Indians.  The people of <NAME TYPE="place">Europe</NAME> were the first <ORIG REG="white men">whitemen</ORIG> who landed upon these shores.  As soon as they established Colonies they claimed the sovereignty of the soil by the <HI>right of discovery</HI>.</P><P>For a long period of time, this sovereignty was exercised without resistance.  At length, the colonies grew to a size which enabled them to take the management of their own affairs.  A war ensued which lasted Seven years and then ended in the complete success of the colonies.  What <NAME TYPE="place">Europe</NAME> claimed by discovery, was then vested in the people of the colonies by conquest.</P><PB N="[3]"><P>All the country which was conquered belonged to the conquerors.  The <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME>, the <NAME TYPE="person">Creek</NAME>, &amp; almost every other Indian tribe, powerful and numerous as they were, took sides against us.  All shared the same fate.&mdash;  All became subject to the government afterwards established under the title of the <Q><NAME TYPE="place">United States of America</NAME></Q></P><P>This subordination and loss of power would have followed conquest as a matter of course.  But in order that it might be reduced to a <ORIG REG="certainty">certanity</ORIG> and made plans and recorded, treaties were entered into in every instance with the Indian tribes who were parties to the war.</P><P>The <NAME TYPE="person">Delawares</NAME> surrendered their sovereignty at the treaty of <NAME TYPE="place">Fort Pitt</NAME>- The <NAME TYPE="person">six nations</NAME> at <NAME TYPE="place">Fort <UNCLEAR>Stanwix</UNCLEAR></NAME>. <ADD PLACE="supralinear">The <NAME TYPE="person">Creeks</NAME> at <NAME TYPE="place">New York</NAME></ADD> The <NAME TYPE="person">Chckasaws</NAME> at <NAME TYPE="place">Hopewell</NAME> <ADD PLACE="supralinear">&amp; the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> at <NAME TYPE="place">Hopewell</NAME></ADD> in <DATE VALUE="1785-00-00">1785</DATE>, and so on.  By these, and by a great many other Nations a complete surrender is made, and <HI><Q>protection</Q></HI> claimed.  The language of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> in the treaty of <NAME TYPE="place">Hopewell</NAME> 
<Q>gives peace to the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> and receives them<PB N="[4]">into <ORIG REG="favor">favour</ORIG> and protection.</Q>  The language of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME>, is submissive and accepts the offer.</P><P>So complete was the authority acquired by these memorable operations, that the territory of all those tribes was made the subject of <Q><HI>allotment</HI></Q>  All the lands which they now hold has been <Q>allotted</Q> to them.  Their original title is forever gone.&mdash;  First by discovery &mdash; Secondly by conquest and thirdly by treaty.  But the Surrenders which have been made from time to time <ADD PLACE="supralinear">by</ADD> the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> go still further, and <ORIG REG="authorize">authorise</ORIG> the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> to <Q>manage the trade of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> as they may think proper.</Q></P><P>Brothers, <LB>we have reference to these matters of history and compact, not to show your humility, but to shew your <HI>dependance.</HI> <ADD PLACE="supralinear">It does not degrade you to give you the evidence of your dependance,</ADD> on the con<DEL TYPE="overstrike">ntay</DEL> <ADD PLACE="supralinear">trary</ADD>, it is matter of distinction, to be connected <HI>with</HI>, and dependant <HI>upon</HI>, the Government of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>.  There are twenty four States and those territories, which are found to acknowledge this connection &amp; dependence.</P><PB N="[5]"><P>The advantage is mutual.  The <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> give laws, give stability &amp; protection to the States; and the States give <ORIG REG="obedience">obidience</ORIG>, support &amp; taxes to the government.  By this union, the government becomes powerful&mdash; by a division it would be feeble.  As relating to the different tribes of Indians who have settlements within the States, the government is prepared to speak with <ORIG REG="candor">candour</ORIG> and <ORIG REG="decision">decission</ORIG>.</P><P>If they cherish the idea of <ORIG REG="independence">independance</ORIG> &amp; self government, the sooner they are corrected, the better.  The <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> will not permit the existence of a separate, distinct, and independent government within her limits.  All the people on her soil must be hers, and her laws must sooner or later pervade the whole.  To qualify you for citizenship, the government has within the last twenty years expended upon you upwards of half a million of dollars.  You have been told that you are the president's favorite children.</P><PB N="[6]"><P>You are indeed so.  He seeks not to <ORIG REG="destroy">distroy</ORIG>, but to preserve you.  There is nothing annihilating in his scheme.  When he qualifies you as citizens you must become so.  The process of qualification will follow you where ever you go, and as fast as you become citizens you become subject to our laws.  Whether this subjection to our laws is to be individually or collectively, depends in a great degree upon yourselves.  As long ago as at the treaty of <NAME TYPE="place">Hopewell</NAME> in <DATE VALUE="1785-00-00">1785</DATE>, the idea is suggested of your becoming a territory of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, with the right of representation in Congress.  If this Nation would preserve a compact form, not within the limits of the states, no obstacle would remain to the organization of a territorial government composed of themselves.  While they are within the limits of States, the state <ORIG REG="sovereignty">sovreignty</ORIG> must prevail, and <ADD PLACE="supralinear">they</ADD> must become merged in the white population and take the standing of individual Citizens.</P><PB N="[7]"><P>Brothers, let your choice be as it may; your condition will be bettered. The Government which you have lately formed for yourselves, although it is greatly to your credit, yet it is objectionable in many of its important features.  A territorial organization under the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> would be greatly preferable.</P><P>Such changes are common among Nations, and often to the advantage of both parties.  But if this scheme is not yet sufficiently matured to meet your acceptance, then a cession of a part will quiet the solicitude of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> and of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, for the pre<DEL TYPE="overstrike">s</DEL>sent and give time for further deliberation.</P><P>The cession of a part need not <ADD PLACE="supralinear">affect</ADD> the wishes or interest of any individual with respect to citizenship.  If those who live upon the part ceded are not disposed to become  citizens they can be indemnified for their losses in removing and retire within your lines.</P><PB N="[8]"><P>If they are disposed to become members of the States, they can be secured <ADD PLACE="supralinear">in</ADD> a residence and let into all the privileges of ordinary citizens.</P><P>Brothers, <LB>We have thus laid before you some new topics for discussion.  These involve considerations of vast importance to yourselves and to posterity.  Listen to them and answer with calmness and deliberation.</P><P>You are not engaged in light disputes or trifling considerations&mdash;  Nations are parties to this correspondence.  If we know our government and our selves we design you no harm.  Our object is the good of the whole <NAME TYPE="person">American</NAME> family.</P><P>We shall now proceed to notice some of the remarks in your communication of yesterday and closed for the present.</P><P>The picture which you have drawn of the separation of friends and relatives as the <DEL TYPE="overstrike">relatives</DEL> emigration to <NAME TYPE="place">Arkansas</NAME> is honorable to <PB N="[9]">the sympathies of your hearts.  But the heart often bleeds at what the judgment approves.  Among ourselves, these separations occur almost daily.  You advert with some emphasis to the <Q>circumstances and means which caused the separation.</Q></P><P>Brothers, <LB>We understand that it was <HI><ORIG REG="wholly">wholy</ORIG> voluntary,</HI>and that your citizens projected the <ORIG REG="scheme">sheme</ORIG> themselves, as long ago as <DATE VALUE="1808-00-00">1808</DATE>.  At that time the President was aware that the season was unpropitious for so serious an operation.  His land beyond the <NAME REG="River" TYPE="place">Mississippi</NAME> had not been explored.  The distresses of the people and government, were great, &amp; the prospect of a War was in view.  The President acted as a great and good father to you and advised you not to go.  Since that, it has been ascertained that the country admits of eligible Settlement and organization and the most advantageous <PB N="[10]">terms have been allowed you for removal.  In all this, we discover nothing but the characteristic magnanimity of the <NAME TYPE="person">American</NAME> government.</P><P>Brothers,<LB>You state that you <Q>once possessed an extensive Country, but that you have made cession after cession until your limits have become circumscribed</Q>  would you if you could, repossess yourselves of all the soil which <ADD PLACE="supralinear">you</ADD> once held and allow it to be peopled only by yourselves.  Would you demolish temples raised to science and dedicated to god, that beasts might have a wider range, or game a broader play?  World you lay waste a city, that a wigwam might rise upon its ruins?  No Brothers, you are now drinking of the streams of civilization, and leaving far behind you the title and vulgar prejudices of untutored barbarism.</P><PB N="[11]"><P>These are giving place to just and liberal conceptions of the rights of man and the bounty of mans creator.</P><P>You suggest that the eagerness of your <ORIG REG="neighboring">neighbouring</ORIG> brethren to obtain land is so strong that a small cession would not satisfy them.  It <ADD PLACE="supralinear">is</ADD> true that self interest is a strong principle of action, and in its operations often requires restraint.  In this case however this Eagerness is considered reasonable and your father the President gives it his sanction.</P><P>We assure you that a small cession will have a much <ADD PLACE="supralinear">greater</ADD> quieting influence, than no cession at all&mdash; It is not altogether fair to set bounds to eagerness when it is founded upon right.</P><P>Your allusion to the subject of the line ran under the treaty of <DATE VALUE="1819-00-00">1819</DATE> will receive due attention before we close our correspondence.</P><CLOSER><SALUTE>With great respect for the Council and regard for its members, we again subscribe ourselves<LB>Your Friends &amp; Brothers</SALUTE><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person">Duncan G. Campbell</NAME></SIGNED><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person">James Meriwether</NAME></SIGNED></CLOSER></DIV1></BODY></TEXT></TEI.2>
