<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD">
<TEI.2 ID="ch073"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>Private remarks on the testimony given between the state of Georgia [and] the Cherokee Nation, 1829 Dec. 30 : a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><AUTHOR>Coffee, John, 1772-1833</AUTHOR><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>ch073</IDNO><IDNO>oclc: 44863387</IDNO><AVAILABILITY STATUS="FREE"><P>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>Private remarks on the testimony given between the state of Georgia [and] the Cherokee Nation, 1829 Dec. 30</TITLE><AUTHOR>Coffee, John, 1772-1833</AUTHOR><DATE VALUE="1829-12-30">December 30, 1829</DATE><EXTENT>17p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">Remarks compiled by John Coffee and dated December 30, 1829 upon the character and credibility of individuals who gave testimony in a land dispute between the Cherokee Nation and Georgia (claiming under the title of the Creek Nation.) Coffee relates his difficulty in receiving information from Colonels Wales and Montgomery about the collection of testimony related to the case and presents the names of those who made statements about the boundary line along with his own comments about their character. The original enclosures are no longer attached.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box">3</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder">6</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">ch073</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Boundaries</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Land tenure</ITEM><ITEM>Georgia</ITEM></LIST> </KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><FRONT><DIV1 TYPE="claim misc remarks"><PB N="[1]"><P>Private Remarks on the testimony given, between the state of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> &amp; the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME>&mdash;</P></DIV1></FRONT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="document"><PB N="[2]"><OPENER><DATE VALUE="1829-12-30">30th Dec. 1829</DATE></OPENER><P>Remarks on the testimony taken of the disputed country between the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> claiming under the title of the <NAME TYPE="place person">Creek Nation</NAME>, and the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> claiming under their own title,</P><LIST><HEAD>The names of persons who gave evidence, and furnished by the Govr. of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME></HEAD><ITEM><NAME TYPE="person">James Gilbert</NAME></ITEM><ITEM><NAME TYPE="person">Robert Venable</NAME></ITEM><ITEM><NAME TYPE="person">Isham Williams</NAME></ITEM><ITEM><NAME TYPE="person">Elisha Winn</NAME></ITEM><ITEM><NAME TYPE="person">Jas. M.C. Montgomery</NAME></ITEM><ITEM><NAME TYPE="person">George M. Grisham</NAME></ITEM><ITEM><NAME TYPE="person">Jacob. R. Brooks</NAME></ITEM></LIST><P>I have no information on the subject of the credibility of those Witnesses &mdash; The Govr. is silent on the subject</P><P><NAME TYPE="person">William B Wofford</NAME>, was a member of the Legislature of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, &amp; I understand he is the person who informed the Legislature that he could establish the <ADD PLACE="supralinear">claim</ADD> if they would institute an enquiry for testimony, the Govr. refers <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Wales</NAME> to him, he is from a frontier<PB N="[3]">country of the state, and is said to be <ORIG REG="clamorous">clamourous</ORIG> against the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME>, his letter shows his feelings</P><P><NAME TYPE="person">Hezekiah Luckie</NAME> &mdash; no information of Character</P><P><NAME TYPE="person">Col. Samuel A. Wales</NAME>. The <ABBR EXPAN="commissioner" TYPE="contraction">commr.</ABBR> appointed by the Govr. of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> to collect evidence of the claim of the state to the land in dispute <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera" TYPE="contraction">&amp;c</ABBR></P><P>When I arrived first at the Agency on the <DATE VALUE="0000-11-25">25th <ABBR EXPAN="November">Novr.</ABBR></DATE> I called on <NAME REG="Hugh" TYPE="person">Col. Montgomery</NAME> for information on the Subject of my mission &mdash; he informed me that there was a Gentleman there from <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Wales</NAME> who he supposed was sent there by the Govr. of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> on that business, but observed he was in an adjoining house, and he would send for him, he accordingly sent, and in a few minutes <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Wales</NAME> entered the office &amp; was introduced to me by <NAME REG="Hugh" TYPE="person">Col Montgomery</NAME>.  I asked <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Wales</NAME> if he was instructed by the Govr. of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> to attend to the business on his part &amp; to communicate with me on the subject. he answered me that he had no instructions what ever from the Govr. of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> on the subject of the business.  I then asked <NAME REG="Hugh" TYPE="person">Col. Montgomery</NAME> in his presence if he could procure some person who was acquainted <PB N="[4]">in the country to hire a confidential person to go express to <NAME TYPE="place">Millegeville</NAME> with a letter to the Govr. <SIC CORR="he">he he</SIC> immediately directed his Interpreter <NAME TYPE="person">Miller</NAME>, who was present to go out and get some suitable person <NAME TYPE="person">Miller</NAME> went out and in a few <ORIG REG="minutes">minuits</ORIG> returned into the office with a young man by the name of <NAME TYPE="person">James Walker</NAME> who the Agent said was a confidential man and one that would answer my purpose.  I immediately &amp; in the presence of <NAME REG="Hugh" TYPE="person">Col. Montgomery</NAME> &amp; <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Wales</NAME> employed <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Walker</NAME> to start next morning early.  The distance was said to be upwards of two hundred miles, he agreed to go and return to me in ten days or sooner if possible, for which I was to pay him twenty five dollars as his full compensation for his services &amp; <ORIG REG="expenses">expences</ORIG> <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera" TYPE="contraction">&amp;c</ABBR> This was late in the evening &mdash; I returned to my lodgings at Mr. <NAME TYPE="person">Lewis Ross</NAME>s.  distant  from the Agency office about two hundred yards, and addressed a letter to his Excellency <NAME REG="Gilmer" TYPE="person">Govr. Gilmore</NAME> informing him of my arrival, and asking from him an answer <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera">&amp;c.</ABBR> when I came down from my room, or about this time I <ABBR EXPAN="received">recvd. </ABBR> a note<PB N="[5]">from <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Wales</NAME>  in which he an<ADD PLACE="supralinear">n</ADD>ounced himself <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>s Representative, asking me for certain information, and requesting me to detain my express &mdash; you may readily imagine my surprise on the <ABBR EXPAN="receipt" TYPE="contraction">rect.</ABBR> of such an avowal, and that too so soon after his express declaration to me that he had no instructions whatever on the subject from the Govr. of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, I answered his note, and he replied by way of explanation &amp; apology.  all of which correspondence I here with send you that you may see the course pursued by the Agents of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> in collecting their evidence &mdash; when I first <ABBR EXPAN="received" TYPE="contraction">recvd</ABBR> his explanation for his singular conduct I thought it possible he felt timid among the Indians &amp; which was the reason of his not avowing himself when I first spoke to him, but that opinion was entirely removed when I applied to several of the emigrants for statements, and they positively refused to give them, saying they also were afraid of making enemies by so doing; when I afterwards learned, that these same persons had actually given written statements to <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Wales</NAME> under<PB N="[6]">the greatest injunctions of secrecy &mdash; I then went to <NAME REG="Hugh" TYPE="person">Col. Montgomery</NAME> and informed him what I had heard, and asked him if he knew any thing about it. he replied he did that I had been truly <ABBR EXPAN="informed">informd</ABBR> that the persons alluded to and <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Wales</NAME> come to him with the statement, already made out &amp; signed and he Witnessed them as Agent, but said <ADD PLACE="supralinear">that</ADD> he did not know their contents&mdash; thus by accident I <ABBR EXPAN="learned">learnd</ABBR> what I ought to have been informed of both by <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Wales</NAME> &amp; <NAME REG="Hugh" TYPE="person">Col. Montgomery</NAME>, by the former, that I might have been present at the taking down the evidence and see that nothing was unfair, and by the latter as the Agent of the <NAME TYPE="place">U. States</NAME>, who had been instructed to give me all the aid in his power to obtain <HI>correct</HI> information of the <HI>true</HI> line, presuming he would <ADD PLACE="supralinear">be </ADD> disposed to do equal justice to the one party, as to the other &mdash; thus finding I had no hopes of getting information at the agency from either source, and the Chiefs not meeting me as early as they ought to have done, I at once determined to leave there and travel through<PB N="[7]">the nation, and get what information I could find amongst the people.  I accordingly addressed a letter to <NAME REG="Hugh" TYPE="person">Col. Montgomery</NAME>, informing him of my determination and my intended route <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera">&amp;c.</ABBR> a copy of which letter is here with enclosed. <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Wales</NAME> in his last letter informed me that himself and <NAME TYPE="person">Charles Gates</NAME> <ABBR EXPAN="Esquire">Esqui.</ABBR> had been sent by the Govt. of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> to procure information <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera">&amp;c.</ABBR> that he had testimony in his possession of much importance and that more would be procured on the frontier of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> that if my express went on to <NAME TYPE="place">Milledgeville</NAME> he should feel it his duty to furnish me with the testimony then in his possession <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera">&amp;c.</ABBR> my express did go on, but I did not receive the testimony promised and <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Wales</NAME> wrote a letter by him to <NAME REG="Gilmer" TYPE="person">Govr. Gilmore</NAME>, and the Govr. answered his letter by my express <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Walker</NAME>, the express <ABBR EXPAN="showed">shewd.</ABBR> me the letter and proposed for me to take it. thinking I might possibly see <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Wales</NAME> before he would receive the letter, but I declined taking charge of it, notwithstanding the probability that <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Wales</NAME> informed the Govr. of what had taken <PB N="[8]">place between him, and myself, in their correspondence by my express.  yet the Govr. has never intimated to me that he had an Agent out in search of testimony nor that he had any further evidence to offer than that which he sent me. <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Wales</NAME> left the Agency before I did, and I heard of his arrival at <NAME TYPE="place">Milledgeville</NAME> and report said he had collected much testimony in <ORIG REG="favor">favour</ORIG> of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>s Claim, but I was not so fortunate as to <DEL TYPE="overstrike">receive</DEL> <ADD PLACE="supralinear"> see</ADD> it, or hear from him again after he left the Agency, but on seeing a man who was going direct to the residence of <NAME TYPE="person">Charles Gates</NAME>.  I addressed him a line and invited him to furnish me with any information in his possession a copy of which letter is also annexed hereto&mdash;</P><P><NAME TYPE="person">Hugh W. Ector</NAME> &mdash;  I have no information of &mdash;</P><P><NAME TYPE="person">D.B. Mitchell</NAME> &mdash; agent for <ABBR EXPAN="Indian Affairs">I,A,</ABBR> I understand is the person of <NAME TYPE="person">Govr. Mitchell</NAME> late <NAME TYPE="place">U States</NAME> agent in the <NAME TYPE="place person">Creek Nation</NAME></P><P>The foregoing includes all the testimony furnished by the state of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> with an account of the conduct of her representative on that business</P><PB N="[9]"><P>The following persons gave evidence to my self in the absence of both parties interested &mdash; to wit &mdash;</P><P>1 <NAME TYPE="person">George Sanders</NAME>, a half breed <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> &mdash; this man has a good character for honesty &amp; truth, but the interest of his nation may have biased his mind &amp; recollection, but it is not believed he would state willfully wrong</P><P>2 <NAME TYPE="person">James Daniel</NAME> a half breed <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME>, late one of the Judges of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> Courts, a man of good character in <ADD PLACE="supralinear">the</ADD> nation</P><P>3 <NAME TYPE="person">James H. Kidd</NAME>, a white man, citizen of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> found traveling in the nation &amp; having been informed he had been a trader with the Indians I called on him for a  statement &mdash; he is poor &amp; seems to have no interest to serve, by serving his statement his Character is not very fair as I was told</P><P>4 <NAME TYPE="person">John Rogers</NAME> &mdash; a white man married to a <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> wife, he is a man of excellent character for truth, honesty &amp; piety, and I have great confidence in his statement</P><P>5 <NAME TYPE="person">Daniel Clower</NAME> &mdash; an old citizen of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, and a pious good old man, such is his character</P><P>6 <NAME TYPE="person">William Mathews</NAME> &mdash; a white man with a white family but living in the Nation as a Millwright, is said to be an honest man of good character&mdash;<PB N="[10]3">7 <NAME TYPE="person">George G. Weatherspoon</NAME> &mdash; a methodist preacher lives in <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> &mdash; called a pious good man</P><P>8 <NAME TYPE="person">John Wright</NAME> &mdash; this is the man that the Govr. of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> <ORIG REG="referred">refered</ORIG> me to, by the name of <NAME TYPE="person">Jack Right</NAME> &mdash; he is a white man married to a <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> wife, and I think the oldest resident on the disputed land <DEL TYPE="overstrike">he is an</DEL> who can give any account of the Country, he is an illiterate man, but has a good name for truth and honesty, several of his children have emigrated for <NAME TYPE="place">Arkansas</NAME>.  I have much confidence in his statements, and I think they go further in support of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> Claim than any one Witness I examined&mdash;</P><P>9 <NAME TYPE="person">George Still</NAME> a half breed <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> of honest name.  I think his statement may be relied on, he seems to have a good memory which is not uncommon with Indians who have no other record than memory&mdash; <ADD PLACE="left"><UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR></ADD></P><PB N="[11]"><P>10 The <NAME TYPE="person">Rising Fawn</NAME> &mdash; a full blood <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME>, very old, and very simple, no doubt he spoke what he thought right&mdash;</P><P>11 <NAME TYPE="person">Tarcheche</NAME> &mdash; a full blood Indian</P><P>12 <NAME TYPE="person">Charley Moore</NAME> a half breed <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME></P><P>13 <NAME TYPE="person">John Garvick</NAME> a half breed <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME></P><P>All Indians of no particular character</P><P>14 <NAME TYPE="person">Wallen Eata</NAME> &mdash; a full blood <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME>, a very <ORIG REG="intelligent">inteligent</ORIG> Indian, but he seemed to be governed too much from feelings &amp; interest he overrated the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> claims more than any one I examined.</P><P>15 <NAME TYPE="person">James Buchanon</NAME> &mdash; a citizen of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>. I found him traveling in the nation &amp; seeing he was a very old man. I enquired if he knew any thing of the old line between the two nations, when he made the statement, I dont know his character, but he has the appearance of a decent old man&mdash;</P><P>16 <NAME TYPE="person">James Petite</NAME> a half breed <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> an <ORIG REG="intelligent">inteligent</ORIG> man of good character, seemed to be candid in his statement, &amp; I think <ORIG REG="endeavored">endeavoured</ORIG> to make it fairly &amp; agreeable to his information &amp; recollection but all hear say evidence is liable to differ an err&mdash;</P><PB N="[12]"><P>17 <NAME TYPE="person">Walter Adair</NAME> &mdash; about one fourth <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> &mdash; one of the Judges of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> Courts has an education an <ORIG REG="intelligent">inteligent</ORIG> man of good name in his country</P><P>18 <NAME TYPE="person">Thomas Cawdray</NAME> &mdash; a white man married to a <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> wife.  he has not been a steady man, rather dissipated but I did not hear of any other charge against him but that of drinking too freely, I believe his statement was fairly made. agreeable to his information and recollection&mdash; <ADD PLACE="left" CERT="appears to be different ink and hand"><DEL TYPE="erasure"><UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR> Shoals</DEL> <NAME TYPE="place">Shallow Ford</NAME> <UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR></ADD></P><P>19 <NAME TYPE="person">Dick Rowe</NAME> &mdash; about one fourth <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> who made me a verbal statement, has heretofore been a man of good Character, but of late he has been embarrassed in his circumstances and may have been induced to deviate from the truth, but I find his statement and <NAME TYPE="person">Cawdray</NAME>s agree &mdash; <ADD PLACE="left" CERT="appears to be different ink and hand">L. Ford <UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR></ADD></P><P>20 The Statement of <NAME TYPE="person">Nat Casey</NAME> made to me in the year <DATE VALUE="1816-00-00">1816</DATE> of information he <ABBR EXPAN="received" TYPE="contraction">recvd.</ABBR> from <NAME TYPE="person">Dick Rowe</NAME> <ADD PLACE="supralinear">in <DATE VALUE="1809-00-00">1809 </DATE></ADD> corresponds with <NAME REG="Dick" TYPE="person">Rowe</NAME>s statement to me at this day, there being 20 years between the dates, and the first statement was made under circumstances different from the present, when there was no inducement to err. <ADD PLACE="left" CERT="appears to be different ink and hand"><ABBR EXPAN="Ditto">Do</ABBR></ADD></P><PB N="[13]"><P>21 The statement of 29 <NAME TYPE="person">Creeks</NAME> made to me in <DATE VALUE="1816-00-00">1816</DATE> in the absence of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME>.  I think old <NAME TYPE="person">Chinuby</NAME> told the truth as far as he knew, but I have thought the line he made for them to <NAME TYPE="place">Wills Creek</NAME>, was intended by the <NAME TYPE="place person">Creek nation</NAME> as the true line &mdash;</P><P>This ends all the testimony taken by myself in the absence of both parties in interest &mdash;</P><P>The following names are persons presented to me by the Chiefs, as old men of <ORIG REG="intelligence">inteligence</ORIG> possessing some knowledge of their ancient lines and examined by me in the presence of each other and of the Chiefs, their statements written down by myself  &mdash;</P><P>22 <NAME TYPE="person">Daniel Ross</NAME> &mdash; a white man, this is the old <NAME REG="Daniel" TYPE="person">Mr. Ross</NAME> who lived many years at the upper end of the <NAME TYPE="place">lookout mountain</NAME> married a <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> wife, an <ORIG REG="intelligent">inteligent</ORIG> man come early to the country, and traded many years with the Indians, he is well known to travelers&mdash;</P><P>23 <NAME TYPE="person">David McNair</NAME> &mdash; a white man married to a <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> wife (the daughter of <NAME TYPE="person">James Vann</NAME>) he is the best farmer I saw in the country, and a very decent man, has a good character, he went to the Nation about the year <DATE VALUE="1800-00-00">1800</DATE> as a carpenter&mdash;</P><PB N="[14]"><P>24 <NAME TYPE="person">Clem Vann</NAME> &mdash; a white man married to a <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> wife, his character has not been very good he was under the influence of <NAME TYPE="person">James Vann</NAME>, and I have no doubt but <NAME REG="James" TYPE="person">Vann</NAME> did propose the line he mentions &amp; possibly  the <NAME TYPE="person">Creeks</NAME> may not have opposed it, but there is great doubts if it was agreed on in Council, the line he speaks of crosses the line they finally made&mdash;</P><P>25 <NAME TYPE="person">Chuliowah</NAME> &mdash; a full blood <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME>, an old chief of good standing in his nation, an <ORIG REG="intelligent">inteligent</ORIG> Indian, he is the principal <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> Chief who attended the <NAME TYPE="person">Creek</NAME> treaty in <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> at <NAME TYPE="place">Fort Wilkinson</NAME> in <DATE VALUE="1802-00-00">1802</DATE> at the time the <ABBR EXPAN="Commissioners">Commrs.</ABBR> wrote to the <ABBR EXPAN="Secretary">Secty.</ABBR> of War about the <NAME TYPE="person">Creek</NAME> Chiefs refusing to accompany the surveyors further than the <NAME TYPE="place">Currahee Mountain</NAME> <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera">&amp;c.</ABBR> his statement now does not correspond with the report that himself &amp; his other companions made to his people on their return to the nation at the time, see the statement of <NAME TYPE="person">Thomas Petite</NAME>, <NAME TYPE="person">Dick Rowe</NAME>, &amp; others who heard that subject spoken of at that day &mdash; <NAME TYPE="place">Scotts store</NAME> is 20 miles below the high shoals of <NAME REG="River" TYPE="place">Apalachy</NAME></P><PB N="[15]"><P>26 <NAME TYPE="person">Major Ridge</NAME> a full blood <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME>, one of the present principal chiefs of the nation is well known at <NAME TYPE="place">Washington City</NAME>, his statement goes to show the foresight of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> at the close of the late <NAME TYPE="person">Creek</NAME> war that the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> met &amp; appointed himself &amp; <NAME TYPE="person">Dick Brown</NAME> (perhaps two of the most <ORIG REG="intelligent">inteligent</ORIG> men of their nation at that day) to say how far they should set up their claim, they done so, and from his statement we see that they claimed a large portion of the country which has always been known to be <NAME TYPE="person">Creek</NAME> lands &amp; inhabited by them  but by claiming thus far and afterwards (conceding as they say) yielding a part they then got all they were entitled to and perhaps more</P><P>27 <NAME TYPE="person">Flute or Old Turkey</NAME> &mdash; one of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> delegation who went to the <NAME TYPE="person">Creek</NAME> treaty in <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> in <DATE VALUE="1802-00-00">1802</DATE> he differs from <NAME TYPE="person">Chuliowah</NAME>, in the point on <NAME TYPE="place">Chattahoohy</NAME>.  <NAME TYPE="person">Turkey</NAME> says the line was to cross the river at the mouth of <NAME TYPE="place">sweetwater creek</NAME> which is two miles below <NAME TYPE="place">Sandtown</NAME>, where the other said it was to cross &mdash; I fear these old men have been influenced by popular opinion of the present day in the nation, for all the information I could get the impression was<PB N="[16]">made at the time, that the high shoals of <NAME TYPE="place">Appalachy</NAME> was to be the point of <ORIG REG="Beginning">Begining</ORIG>, and to run from there with the old <NAME TYPE="place">Hightown path</NAME> by the <NAME TYPE="place">stone mountain</NAME> to <NAME TYPE="place">Chattahoochy</NAME>&mdash;</P><P>28 <NAME TYPE="person">Chickasawtue</NAME> &mdash; a full blood <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME>, the oldest looking man I saw &amp; examined in the nation he seems to have retained his mind &amp; intellect very well, and on cross examining him I found him to understand his story correctly but seeing that all the old men who were brought forward at the same time by the Chiefs and examined in presence of all tell the same story about their beginning at the lower big falls of <NAME TYPE="place">Appalachy</NAME>, 20 miles or more below the high Shoals induced a belief that their minds had become warped by hearing the story told over, often in their presence</P><P>29  <NAME TYPE="person">Thomas Woodard</NAME></P><P>30 <NAME TYPE="person">Walking Stick</NAME></P><P>31 <NAME TYPE="person">Going Snake</NAME> &amp; others</P><P>Those men are all <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> of good standing in the nation most of them are Chiefs but I did not learn any <PB N="[17]">particular circumstances, or character &mdash; their statements are generally reports and  impressions without any particular stress to be placed on them <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera">&amp;c</ABBR></P><CLOSER>The foregoing remarks contain the best information I could get, of the character of the individuals who gave evidence of the boundary line <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera">&amp;c</ABBR> <SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="John">Jno.</ABBR> Coffee</NAME></SIGNED></CLOSER></DIV1></BODY></TEXT></TEI.2>
