<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD"[
<!ENTITY pg1 PUBLIC "pg1" "wch076a.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg10 PUBLIC "pg10" "wch076j.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg11 PUBLIC "pg11" "wch076k.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg12 PUBLIC "pg12" "wch076l.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg2 PUBLIC "pg2" "wch076b.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg3 PUBLIC "pg3" "wch076c.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg4 PUBLIC "pg4" "wch076d.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg5 PUBLIC "pg5" "wch076e.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg6 PUBLIC "pg6" "wch076f.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg7 PUBLIC "pg7" "wch076g.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg8 PUBLIC "pg8" "wch076h.djv" NDATA TIFF>
<!ENTITY pg9 PUBLIC "pg9" "wch076i.djv" NDATA TIFF>
]>
<TEI.2 ID="ch076"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>Opinion of the Supreme Court of the United States, 1831 Jan. / delivered by Chief Justice [John] Marshall on a motion of the Cherokee Nation for a writ of injunction and subpoena against the State of Georgia: a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><AUTHOR>Marshall, John, 1755-1835</AUTHOR><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>ch076</IDNO><IDNO>oclc: 44864069</IDNO><AVAILABILITY STATUS="FREE"><P>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>Opinion of the Supreme Court of the United States, 1831 Jan. / delivered by Chief Justice [John] Marshall on a motion of the Cherokee Nation for a writ of injunction and subpoena against the State of Georgia</TITLE><AUTHOR>Marshall, John, 1755-1835</AUTHOR><DATE VALUE="1831-01-00">January 1831</DATE><EXTENT>12p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">This is a copy of the official opinion of the Supreme Court of the U.S., delivered by Chief Justice John Marshall, on the motion filed by the Cherokee Nation for an injunction against the state of Georgia.  The Cherokees sought the opinion of the court on the issue of Georgia's right to extend its jurisdiction over the Cherokee Nation, effectively depriving them of their sovereignty.  Marshall's decision here indicates that the Cherokees cannot be strictly considered foreign nations, as they had argued, and are instead considered "wards of the state," or "domestic dependents."  This decision was delivered in the January term of 1831 and is of extreme significance in the development of Indian Removal issues.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">State Library Cherokee Collection</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box">3</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder">7</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">ch076</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Government relations</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Claims</ITEM><ITEM>Georgia</ITEM></LIST> </KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="legal opinion"><PB N="[1]"><HEAD>The <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> VS The State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> <DATE VALUE="1831-01-00">January Term 1831</DATE><LB>Opinion of the Supreme Court of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, delivered by Mr. <NAME TYPE="person">Chief Justice Marshall</NAME> on a motion of the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> for a writ of injunction &amp; subpoena against the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME></HEAD><P>&horbar;<LB>This bill is brought by the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> praying an injunction to restrain the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, from the execution of certain laws of that state which as <UNCLEAR>this</UNCLEAR> alleged go directly to annihilate the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> as a political society, and to seize for the use of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, the lands of the nation which have been assured to them by the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> in Solemn treaties repeatedly made and still in force.</P><P>If Courts were permitted to indulge their sympathies, a case better calculated to excite them can scarcely be imagined.  A people once numerous, powerful, and truly independent found by our ancestors in the quiet and uncontrolled possession of an ample domain gradually sinking beneath our superior policy, our arts and our arms, have yielded their lands by successive treaties, each of which contains a solemn guarantee of the residue, until<PB N="[2]">they retain no more of their formerly extensive territory than is deemed necessary to their comfortable subsistence.  To preserve this remnant the present application is made.</P><P>Before we can look into the merits of the case, a preliminary enquiry presents itself.  Has this Court jurisdiction of the cause?</P><P>The third article of the <ORIG REG="constitution">constition</ORIG> describes the extent of the judicial power, The second section closes an enumeration of the cases to which it is extended, with <Q>controversies</Q> <Q>between a state or the citizens thereof, and foreign states citizens or subjects.</Q> A subsequent clause of the same section gives the Supreme court original jurisdiction in all cases in which a state shall be a party.  The party defendant may then unquestionably by sued in this court.  May the plaintiff sue <ADD PLACE="supralinear">in</ADD> it?  Is the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee nation</NAME> a foreign state in the sense in which that term is used in the Constitution?</P><P>The counsel for the plaintiffs have maintained the affirmative of this proposition with great earnestness and ability.  So much of the argument as was intended to prove the character of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> as a state, as a <ADD PLACE="supralinear">distinct</ADD> political society, separated from others, capable of managing its own affairs and govern-<PB N="[3]2">
ing itself, has in the opinion of a majority, of the judges been completely successful.  They have <ADD PLACE="left">been</ADD> uniformly treated as a state from the settlement of our country.  The numerous treaties made with them by the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> recognize them as a people capable of maintaining the relations of peace and war, of being responsible in their political character for any violation of their engagements, or for any aggression committed on the citizens of the <NAME TYPE="place">Unites States</NAME> by any individual of their community.  Laws have been enacted in the spirit of these treaties.  The acts of our government plainly recognize the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee nation</NAME> as a state, and the courts are bound by those acts.</P><P>A question of <ADD PLACE="supralinear">much</ADD> more difficulty remains?  Do the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> constitute a foreign state in the sense of the constitution?</P><P>Their counsel have shown conclusively that they are not a state of the Union, and have insisted that individually they are aliens, not owing allegiance to the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>.  An aggregate of aliens composing a state, must they say be a foreign state, Each individual being foreign the whole must be foreign.</P><P>This argument is imposing, but we must examine it more closely before we yield to it.  The condition of the Indians in relation<PB N="[4]">to the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> is perhaps unlike that of any other two people in existence.  In the general, nations not owing a common allegiance, are foreign to each other.  The term foreign nation is with strict propriety applicable by either to the other.  But the relation of the Indians to the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> is marked by peculiar and cardinal distinctions which exist no where else.</P><P>The Indian territory is admitted to compose a part of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>.  In all our maps, geographical treatises, histories, and laws, it is so considered.  In all our intercourse with foreign nations, in our commercial regulation in any attempt at intercourse between Indians and foreign nations, they are considered as within the jurisdictional limits of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, subject to many of those restraints which are imposed upon our own citizens.  They acknowledge themselves in their treaties to be under the protection of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, they admit that the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> shall have the sole and exclusive right of of regulating the trade with them, and managing all their affairs, as they think proper, and the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> in particular were allowed by the treaty of <NAME TYPE="place">Hopewell</NAME>, which preceded the constitution,<Q>to send a deputy of their choice when ever they think fit to congress.</Q>  Treaties were made with some tribes<PB N="[5]3">by the state of <NAME TYPE="place">New York</NAME> under a then unsettled construction of the  confederation by which they ceded all their lands to that state,  taking back a limited grant to themselves, in which they admit their  dependence.</P><P>Though the Indians are acknowledged to have an unquestionable and heretofore unquestioned right to the lands they occupy until that right shall be extinguished by <ADD PLACE="supralinear">a</ADD> voluntary cession to our government.  Yet it may well be doubted whether those tribes who reside within the acknowledged boundaries of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> can with strict accuracy be denominated for foreign nations.  They may <DEL TYPE="overstrike">now</DEL> <ADD PLACE="supralinear">more</ADD> correctly perhaps be denominated domestic dependent nations.  They occupy a territory to which we assert a title independent of their will, which must take effect in point of possession when their right of possession ceases.  Meanwhile, they are in a state of pupilage.  Their relation to the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> resembles that of a ward to his guardian.  They look to our government for protection, rely upon its kindness and its power, appeal to it for relief to their wants, and address the President as their Great Father.  They and their country are considered by foreign nations as well as by ourselves, as being so completely under the sovereignty and dominion of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME><PB N="[6]">that any attempt to acquire their lands, or to form a political <ORIG REG="connection">connexion</ORIG> with them would be considered by all as an invasion of our territory and an act of hostility.</P><P>These considerations go far to support the opinion that the framers of our Constitution had not the Indian tribes in view when they opened the Courts of the Union to controversies between a state or the citizens thereof and foreign states.</P><P>In considering this subject, the habits and usages of the Indians, in their intercourse with their white <ORIG REG="neighbors">neighbours</ORIG> ought not to be entirely disregarded.  At the time the constitution was framed, the idea of appealing to an <NAME TYPE="person">American</NAME> court of Justice for an assertion of right or a redress of wrongs had perhaps never entered the mind of an Indian or of his tribe.</P><P>Their appeal was to the tomahawk or to the government.  This was well understood by the Statesmen who framed the <ORIG REG="constitution">constition</ORIG> of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>.  And might furnish some reason for omitting to enumerate them among the parties who might sue in the <DEL TYPE="overstrike">state</DEL> Courts of the union.  Be this as it may, the peculiar relations between the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> and the Indians occupying one territory are such that we should feel much difficulty in considering them<PB N="[7]4">as designated by the term foreign state, were there no other part <DEL TYPE="overstrike">s</DEL> of the constitution which might shed light on the meaning of these words.</P><P>But we think that in construing them considerable aid is furnished by that clause in the eighth section of the third article which empowers Congress to regulate commerce with foreign nations, and among the several states, and the Indian tribes."</P><P>In this clause they are clearly contradistinguished by a name appropriate to themselves, from foreign nations, as from the several states composing the union.  They are designated by a distinct appellation and as this appellation can be applied to neither of the others, neither can the appellation distinguishing either of the other be in fair construction applied to them.  The objects to which the power of regulating commerce might be directed, are divided into three distinct classes- foreign nations; the several states, and Indian tribes. When framing this article the convention considered them as entirely distinct.  We cannot assume that the distinction was lost in framing a subsequent article unless there be something in its language to authorize the assumption</P><P>The counsel for the plaintiffs contends<PB N="[8]">that the words <Q>Indian tribes</Q> were introduced into the article empowering Congress to regulate Commerce for the purpose of removing those doubts in which the management of Indian affairs, was <ORIG REG="involved">envolved</ORIG> by the language of the ninth article of the confederation.  Intending to give the whole power of managing those affairs to the government about to be instituted, the convention confined it explicitly, and omitted those qualifications which embarrassed the exercise of it as granted in the confederation.  This may be admitted without weakening the construction which has been intimated.  Had the Indian tribes been foreign nations in the view of the convention this exclusive power of regulating intercourse with them might have been and most probably would have been specifically given in language indicating that idea, not in language contradistinguishing them from foreign nations.  Congress might have been empowered <Q>to regulate commerce with foreign nations including the Indian tribes, and among the several states.</Q> This language would have suggested itself to statesmen who considered the Indian tribes as<PB N="[9]5">foreign nations, and <DEL TYPE="overstrike">yet</DEL> were yet desirous of mentioning them particularly.</P><P>It has been also said that the same words have not necessarily the same meaning attached to them when found in different parts of the same instrument.  Their meaning is controlled by the Context.  This is undoubtedly true.  In common language the same word has various meanings and the peculiar sense in which it is used in any sentence is to be determined by the context.  This may not be equally true with respect to prop <GAP REASON="document damaged"> Foreign nations is a general term the application of which to Indian tribes when used in the <NAME TYPE="person">American</NAME> Constitution is at best extremely questionable.  In one article in which a power is given to be exercised in regard to foreign nations generally, and to the Indian tribes particularly, they are mentioned as <ORIG REG="separate">seperate</ORIG> in terms clearly <ADD PLACE="supralinear">Contra</ADD>distinguishing them from each other.  We perceive plainly that the constitution in this article does not comprehend  Indian tribes in the general term foreign nations, not we presume because a tribe may not be a nation, but because it<PB N="[10]">is not foreign to the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>.  When afterwards the term foreign state is introduced we cannot impute to the convention the intention to desert <ADD PLACE="supralinear">its former</ADD> <DEL TYPE="overstrike">from</DEL> meaning and to comprehend Indian tribes within it, unless the context forced that construction on us.  We find nothing in the context, and nothing in the subject of the article which leads to it.</P><P>The court has bestowed its best attention on this question, and after mature deliberation the majority is of opinion that an Indian  tribe or nation within the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> is not a foreign <DEL TYPE="overstrike">nation</DEL> <ADD PLACE="supralinear">State</ADD> in the sense of the Constitution <GAP REASON="document damaged"> not <DEL TYPE="overstrike">sustain</DEL> <ADD PLACE="supralinear">maintain</ADD> an action in the Courts of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>.</P><P>A serious additional objection exists to the jurisdiction of the court.  Is the matter of the bill the proper subject for judicial enquiry and decision?  It seeks to restrain a state from the forcible exercise of legislative power over a <ORIG REG="neighboring">neighbouring</ORIG> people asserting their independence, their right to which the state denies.  On several of the matters alleged in the bill, for example on the laws making it criminal to exercise<PB N="[11]6">the usual powers of self government in their own country by the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee nation</NAME>, this court cannot interpose, at least in the form in which those matters are presented. That part of the bill which respects the land occupied by the Indians, and prays the aid of the Court to protect their possessions may be more doubtful. The <DEL TYPE="overstrike">new</DEL> <ADD PLACE="supralinear">mere</ADD> question of right might perhaps be decided by this court in a proper case with proper parties.  But the court is asked to do more that decide on the title.  The bill requires us to control the legislation of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, <GAP REASON="document damaged"> exertion of its physical force.  The propriety of such an interposition by the court may well be questioned.  It <ORIG REG="savors">savours</ORIG> too much of the exercise of political power to be within the proper province of the judicial department. But the opinion on the point respecting parties makes it unnecessary to decide this question.</P><P>If it be true that the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee nation</NAME> have rights this is not the tribunal in which those rights are to be asserted.  If it be true that wrongs have been inflicted, and that still greater are to be apprehended, this is not the tribunal which<PB N="[12]">can redress the past or prevent the future</P><P>The motion for an injunction is denied</P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="legal opinion"><P><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE><NAME TYPE="place">Washington</NAME></ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE VALUE="1831-03-19">March 19th, 1831</DATE>I  <NAME TYPE="person">Richard Peters</NAME> reporter of the decisions of the Supreme Court of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> do hereby certify that the foregoing is a true copy of the opinion of said Supreme Court delivered by Mr. <NAME TYPE="person">Chief Justice Marshall</NAME> on the motion of the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee nation</NAME> for writs of injunction &amp; <GAP REASON="document damaged"> of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, at <DATE VALUE="1831-01-00">January term 1831</DATE>.<LB>Given under my hand and seal the day and year above written</P><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person">Rick Peters</NAME></SIGNED></DIV1></BODY></TEXT></TEI.2>
