<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um037">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1845 Mar. 21, Paradise LaGrange, Ala[bama] [to] Brother &amp; Sister / Bob [Taylor]  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Taylor, Bob</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um037</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50280883</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1845 Mar. 21, Paradise LaGrange, Ala[bama] [to] Brother &amp; Sister / Bob [Taylor]</title>
               <author>Taylor, Bob</author>
               <date when="1845-03-21">March 21, 1845</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by Bob Taylor to his brother and sister, Susan, on March 21, 1845. Bob writes about events happening to him while at school in Alabama.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Taylor Family of Fayette Co. TN Letters MS 384 (corr. 1836-1847)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">4</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um037</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>College students</term>
               <term>Alabama</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Taylor, Bob</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um037a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Paradise Lagrange <choice>
                           <abbr>Ala.</abbr>
                           <expan>Alabama</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1845-03-21">March 21, 1845</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Brother &amp; Sister — :</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letter was received by the last mails. Is is needless to add the recitals of home were perused with interest. You intimated an apology for writing on fools cap paper, this was unnecessary, for I would that all the communications that I receive <choice>
                  <sic>were were</sic>
                  <corr>were</corr>
               </choice> spread out on these lengthy sheets, containing every variety of news calculated to call up fond <choice>
                  <orig>apreciation</orig>
                  <reg>appreciation</reg>
               </choice>, for it is nearly a luxury to <add place="supralinear">the</add> student's mind wearied down by <choice>
                  <orig>clasic</orig>
                  <reg>classic</reg>
               </choice> studies on <choice>
                  <orig>metaphisical</orig>
                  <reg>metaphysical</reg>
               </choice> sciences to have his attention diverted from these continuous themes, and indulge his thoughts in contemplating the happy scenes about his <choice>
                  <orig>indeared</orig>
                  <reg>endeared</reg>
               </choice> home. You perceive that I have followed your example in my selection of <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>lecter</orig>
                     <reg>lecture</reg>
                  </choice>
               </unclear>
               <del type="overstrike">pa</del> paper, not that I have so much to write but for another reason that will manifest itself in the sequel, For, for the life of me I dont know what to write that would interest or amuse you. Shall I give you a history of my present condition, this you know, I am at Lagrange acting in the capacity of a student, with eight different studies to engage my attention weekly, besides numerous other subjects that are not less burdensome, hence it cannot be expected that all will receive their due <choice>
                  <orig>shair</orig>
                  <reg>share</reg>
               </choice> of attention, but I trust that I may be enabled so to dispose of them, at that critical time with the senior on which his destiny hangs, and ⁁ <add place="supralinear">which</add> will soon be wafted to our presence <del type="overstrike">by</del>
               <add place="supralinear">on</add> time's rapid moving streams, as to reflect no discredit to myself of friends &amp; kindred. I feel highly grateful to the author of my being for the remarkable health &amp; strength he grants me to prosecute my labors I <gap agent="damage"/>
               <pb n="2" facs="um037b.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top left corner, sideways">Both of you be sure to write soon R —</add>
            </p>
            <p>Late last night, I spread a few unpremeditated thoughts on another page of this sheet. The blazing rays of the sun has lit up another day &amp; <del type="overstrike">with it</del> aided by its <choice>
                  <orig>cherful</orig>
                  <reg>cheerful</reg>
               </choice> light I attempted to drag the slow length of my letter along — For several days the atmosphere has been chilled as in the depth of winter, the piercing winds of March has truly penetrated our system, the premature foliage of  the <choice>
                  <orig>vegatable</orig>
                  <reg>vegetable</reg>
               </choice> kingdom is withered by the pinching cold.</p>
            <p>Though heavy frost this morning has whitened our mountain tops. The <choice>
                  <orig>resplendant</orig>
                  <reg>resplendent</reg>
               </choice> sun has shone forth in all her <choice>
                  <orig>grandieur</orig>
                  <reg>grandeur</reg>
               </choice>, as if, bespeaking her warmth wont no more be extinguished by the northern blast, the cherful birds have resumed their musical notes that have been hushed by the recent colds; as hailing the happy morn of spring. So the planter to his fields — The ladies to their gardens, and the student with renewed energy to his studies, so gone by —</p>
            <p>Sister <name type="person">Susan</name> my imagination was scarce <choice>
                  <orig>suficiently</orig>
                  <reg>sufficiently</reg>
               </choice> vivid to paint that beautiful &amp; amicable <choice>
                  <orig>creture</orig>
                  <reg>creature</reg>
               </choice> seen in the person of your lovely babe. &amp; more especially as you would not grant the privilege of contrast with the <figure>
                  <figDesc>unindentified drawing</figDesc>
               </figure> but as she is so fond of <unclear>Memphis</unclear> I shall cease to number her on my list of fairy beauties. her <choice>
                  <orig>silph</orig>
                  <reg>sylph</reg>
               </choice> like form &amp; siren voice shall &amp; ever will delight the fancy of others, while Bob pursues his destined course.</p>
            <p>You mentioned something about <name type="person">Mary</name> &amp; <name type="person">Julia</name>. Tell pa: he has a son that has experienced the inconvenience &amp; increased expense of changing <choice>
                  <orig>shools</orig>
                  <reg>schools</reg>
               </choice>. I love my church, It is my pleasure to see her institutions prosper, But consider either circumstances. With your <choice>
                  <orig>permishion</orig>
                  <reg>permission</reg>
               </choice> I will write to brother <unclear>Kent</unclear> on the next page as he requested a <choice>
                  <orig>corispondence</orig>
                  <reg>correspondence</reg>
               </choice> of this sort. You can bet him <unclear>was</unclear> that without showing him this my respects to inquiring friends <gap agent="damage"/>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Bob</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
