<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl736">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1796 Apr. 2, Knoxville [Tennessee, to] Warriors and Chiefs of the Cherokee Nation / John Sevier : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Sevier, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl736</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1796 Apr. 2, Knoxville [Tennessee, to] Warriors and Chiefs of the Cherokee Nation / John Sevier</title>
               <author> Sevier, John</author>
               <date when="1796-04-02">April 2, 1796</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Governor John Sevier dated April 2, 1796. The letter is to the warriors and chiefs of the Cherokee Nation. Sevier writes to advise the Cherokee to maintain peaceful relations with the U.S. He writes that peace is in the Cherokee's best interest, and if there is war again, it will not be the fault of the U.S.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor John Sevier Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">B</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl736</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Sevier, John, 1745-1815 Correspondence.</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr89016779"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Sevier, John, 1745-1815</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl736a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Knoxville</name>
                     <date>2d April 1796</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Friends and Brothers</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>It is some time since I talked to you upon paper and living so great a distance from each other, we can seldom speak face to face</p>
            <p>I am lately come to this place, and us yet not acquainted with all the things that have happened for some time past.</p>
            <p>I am sorry to hear that some of my red <choice>
                  <orig>Breathen</orig>
                  <reg>Brethren</reg>
               </choice> are missing or lost if it is the case we cannot as yet find out who it is that have done so wrong and black a deed but when it is known our laws will then punish him with death</p>
            <p>It is very wrong to punish the innocent for the fault of rogues and bad men neither will it bring back our friends that sleep in the dust; it is enough for one to be lost by bad people, and not a great many perhaps on both sides was either of us, to begin to take satisfaction, for you know every person have their friends</p>
            <p>you that are men and warriors must listen well to my talks and not let foolish and inconsiderate people <choice>
                  <orig>brake</orig>
                  <reg>break</reg>
               </choice> the white belt of <pb n="2" facs="sl736b.small.jpg"/> Peace, that now so happily extends from our hearts to those of our red brothers.</p>
            <p>Dont think harm when I say you are <del type="overstrike">all</del> only a <choice>
                  <orig>handfull</orig>
                  <reg>handful</reg>
               </choice> of people, and that war will ruin you if ever you enter into it again. look back thirty years ago, you was then a great people, more then ten times the number you have now, and if you had never went to war you would have been ten times stronger now, then you was at that time.</p>
            <p>Brothers you know I have always advised you to live in peace, I pitied your women and children and warriors ought always to take care of them, for they are harmless and innocent, and depend upon men for their safety and protection.</p>
            <p>I shall always endeavour to keep the path of peace wide and straight between us, and if ever war is again known in your land, it will not be our fault.</p>
            <p>Your Good and great friend <name>Governor Blount</name> is going to <name>Philadelphia</name> to set in the great and beloved Council of America your beloved Father <name>Washington</name> the President is there, and so long as your Nation keeps bright the chain of peace, they will both be your friends.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your friend and Brother</salute>
               <add>signed</add>
               <signed>
                  <name>John Sevier</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl736c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>The Warriors &amp; Chiefs of the <name>Cherokee nation</name>
               </add>
               <add>2d <choice>
                     <abbr>Apl</abbr>
                     <expan>April</expan>
                  </choice> 1796 <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>No</abbr>
                     <expan>Number</expan>
                  </choice> 3</add>
               <add>Recorded</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
