<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um083">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1842 Dec. 14, Columbia, Tennessee [to] Col[onel] Robert J. Chester, Jackson, Tenn[essee] /   M[ary] J[ane] Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um083</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50316954</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1842 Dec. 14, Columbia, Tennessee [to] Col[onel] Robert J. Chester, Jackson, Tenn[essee] /   M[ary] J[ane] Chester </title>
               <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
               <date when="1842-12-14">December 14, 1842</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">  The following document is a letter, dated December 14, 1842, from Mary Jane Chester to her father Robert J. Chester.  Mary Jane writes urging her father to visit her, and she talks about her upcoming public examination and other issues related to her schooling and finances.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers MS-25 (Jan-Dec 1842)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">10</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um083</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Mary Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um083a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1842-12-14">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Decbr</abbr>
                           <expan>December</expan>
                        </choice>
                        <add place="infralinear" rend="different hand, ink">[14th]</add> 42</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Papa,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I answer your kind letter now, which I received last Sunday by <name type="person">Uncle Walker</name>, he was detained at the Iron Works in which <name type="person">Cousin Sam</name>  has some share, or is engaged in some way I <choice>
                  <abbr>dont</abbr>
                  <expan>do not</expan>
               </choice>
               <emph>precisely know</emph> and therefore did not get home so soon as he expected; he gave me a great deal of news, said that he saw all the children, and that you were all enjoying good health; but he was unable to tell me when you will be up to see me.  Indeed dear Papa you have remained so long silent, in your letters, upon that subject, that I'm uncertain, whether I must look for you or not. If you <emph>only</emph> knew how <emph>very</emph>   anxious I am to see you, I feel certain that if it were possible you would come. I am aware that your business prevented you from coming at the time appointed, but hope that you will have leisure to come before Christmas, which you must remember is very near — and then the Examination.  I can assure you <pb n="2" facs="um083b.small.jpg"/> that it is looked forward to, with dread, by us all.  You, I expect know from experience how very trying, and <choice>
                  <orig>embarassing</orig>
                  <reg>embarrassing</reg>
               </choice> it is to any one to stand a <emph>Public Examination</emph>.  We have commenced <choice>
                  <orig>reveiwing</orig>
                  <reg>reviewing</reg>
               </choice> in all our studies, to day, and it is the <emph>rule</emph> in our class that we are not to go over a <choice>
                  <orig>sentance</orig>
                  <reg>sentence</reg>
               </choice> without understanding precisely its meaning.  A French Tutoress arrived at the Institute the other day, She is a French lady; and we are not permitted to speak to her in any language but that. I think that we will improve more by that Means.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Cousin Sam</name>  has made a new arrangement in his family.  his Father in law and family [<name type="person">Mr Wormely</name>]  and himself all live together, quite a large family ⁁ <add place="supralinear">of us</add> I assure you.  It reminds me of last winter when there were fifteen of the Children staying at <name type="person">Aunt Butler's</name>.</p>
            <p>Papa you said that I have not acknowledged the receipt of the $5 that you sent me <date when="--10-28">28th <choice>
                     <abbr>Oct.</abbr>
                     <expan>October</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date>  indeed I was under the impression that I did in the letter after I received it. I had also the pleasure of receiving the $10 that you sent by Uncle Walker, for which I thank you very much, as I was in need of it then.  I bought me a very handsome <choice>
                  <orig>Mouslin</orig>
                  <reg>Muslin</reg>
               </choice> with it.  it was 87 ½ <choice>
                  <abbr>cts</abbr>
                  <expan>cents</expan>
               </choice> a <choice>
                  <abbr>yd.</abbr>
                  <expan>yard</expan>
               </choice> which including the trimmings took the whole of the $10 — This will <choice>
                  <orig>superede</orig>
                  <reg>supersede</reg>
               </choice> the necessity of your bringing me one.  But <name type="person">Cousin Ellen</name> thinks that I need a Calico.  I must say that I think so too. I am making my dress myself with Cousin Ellen's kind assistance.  she thinks that I sew very well. I keep an account of all the articles that I get, you will I expect <pb n="3" facs="um083c.small.jpg"/>  think me very particular, but I merely wish to show you that your daughter is not so extravagant as She has always had the character of being.</p>
            <p>As Cousin Sam leaves home in a day or two, he handed me my School Bills to <choice>
                  <orig>inclose</orig>
                  <reg>enclose</reg>
               </choice> in this letter.  he said that he is very much engaged or he would write himself.  I want see <emph>Dear</emph> little Sam, my Sister, Brothers and all my little Cousins <emph>very very</emph> much. Tell <name type="person">Aunt Narcissa</name> I hope that she will not let my letter remain long unanswered.  We have a considerable Revival of Religion here, both in the Methodist and Presbyterian Churches.  The meeting is still going on.  they have Mourners <emph>every</emph> night.  It is now bed time and I must bid you good night Give my love to all.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your <choice>
                     <abbr>afft.</abbr>
                     <expan>affectionate</expan>
                  </choice> Daughter</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>M. J.</abbr>
                        <expan>Mary Jane</expan>
                     </choice> Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="bottom">
                  <name type="person">Alice Bennis</name> has entirely recovered from the <choice>
                     <orig>Moumps</orig>
                     <reg>Mumps</reg>
                  </choice> sends her love to sister, and says that she would be very glad to receive a letter from her.</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="um083d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="left of address">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>postmark for Dec. 14</figDesc>
                  </figure> 18</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel</expan>
                        </choice> Robert J. Chester</name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson</name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn.</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left of address">Mail }</add>
               <add place="below address" rend="different hand, ink">My Dear Mary Jane <lb/>
                  <date when="1842-12-14">14 <choice>
                        <abbr>Dec.</abbr>
                        <expan>December</expan>
                     </choice> 1842</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
