<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl430">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1848 Nov. 23, Nashville, Tennessee [to] Daniel D. Claibourne, Lafayette, Tennessee / Adam Fergusson   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Fergusson, A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl430</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1848 Nov. 23, Nashville, Tennessee [to] Daniel D. Claibourne, Lafayette, Tennessee / Adam Fergusson</title>
               <author>Fergusson, A.</author>
               <date when="1848-11-23">November 23, 1848</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Adam Fergusson to his nephew Daniel D. Claibourne, dated November 23, 1848. Fergusson mentions the recent presidential election in which his candidate Cass lost, despite winning the popular vote. Fergusson  informs Claibourne that his name is not allowed to be a  on a bank note that Claibourne is trying to obtain. Fergusson writes that Claibourne needs a different person to sign.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">IV-G-1, B6</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl430</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Banks and banking</term>
               <term>Elections</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Fergusson, Adam</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl430a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name>
                     <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>23d November 1848</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Nephew</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I find on trial today that the note will not take owing to my name being on it and as a rule that they will not Suffer any persons name to be on paper either as drawer or endorser for more than a  certain amount no matter how Solvent he may be. It is therefore not on account of any fears of me or dislike towards me on the contrary they have manifested a degree of kind partiality for me. They Say they will with pleasure discount a note for you if you get another name instead of mine It will show on their Books they Say that the <choice>
                  <orig>accomodation</orig>
                  <reg>accommodation</reg>
               </choice> is not for me. This course they are compelled to take to Save themselves from censure of partiality or <choice>
                  <orig>favouritsm</orig>
                  <reg>favoritism</reg>
               </choice> Should an investigation take place hereafter I want you to come down to <name>Carthage</name> on or before monday next, even Saturday night if you get this in time as next Saturday is Lodge night I shall have to Stay as court is and will be in Session. I do not expect my bill will take owing to the above objections and as misrepresentations have no doubt been made at the other Banks I shall leave here on tomorrow unless I get matters arranged at the Planters Bank of which I have no expectations. I will <pb n="2" facs="sl430b.small.jpg"/> have to rely upon other resources beside Bank accomodations I could Say a great now but do not wish to place it upon paper This is the result of friends forsaking another in time of need. not that I mean you on the contrary I know you would do whatever lay in your power Be sure to come down if you can and file this letter away where no person can see it but yourself I got here last night almost broke down with fatigue I feel better today. <name>Cass</name> has got a greater number of votes than <name>Taylor</name> yet Taylor is the President I mean a larger popular vote throughout the Union. Nashville is dull to day as it is thanksgiving day. I hope to extricate myself out of my difficulties yet</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Respectfully</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>A.</abbr>
                        <expan>Adam</expan>
                     </choice> Fergusson</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Daniel D Claibourne</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Lafayette</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl430c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Confidential</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Daniel D. Claibourne Esqr</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Lafayette <name>Macon <choice>
                           <abbr>Cty</abbr>
                           <expan>County</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Your note <lb/> ___ pay me <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>amt</abbr>
                     <expan>amount</expan>
                  </choice> Bank note <lb/> My note____</add>
               <add>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>math calculations</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
