<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="pa0051"> 
  <teiHeader> 
	 <fileDesc> 
		<titleStmt> 
		  <title>[Spoliation Claim] 1838 Sep. 18, The United States to Ratting
			 Gourd / Collins McDonald : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
		  
		  <author> McDonald, Collins</author> 
		  <respStmt> 
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 <name>Debra Roney</name> 
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name> 
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name> 
		  </respStmt> 
		</titleStmt> 
		<publicationStmt> 
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace> 
		  <address> 
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine> 
		  </address> 
		  <date>2003 
		  </date> 
		  <idno type="SPCID">pa0051</idno> 
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno> 
		  <availability> 
			 <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p> 
		  </availability> 
		</publicationStmt> 
		<sourceDesc> 
		  <bibl> 
			 <title> [Spoliation Claim] 1838 Sep. 18, The United States to Ratting
				Gourd / Collins McDonald </title> 
			 <author> McDonald, Collins</author> 
			 <date value="1838-09-18">September 18, 1838 
			 </date> 
			 <extent> 3p</extent> 
			 <note type="summary">This document is a Spoliation claim made September 18,1838, and signed by Collins McDonald, agent to the Cherokee Indians. This particular claim was for Ratting Gourd, who wanted reimbursement from the United States for the improvements that he had made to his property prior to Cherokee removal. </note> 
			 <note type="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note> 
			 <note type="box">MS-2033</note> 
			 <note type="folder">n/a</note> 
			 <note type="document"> n/a</note> 
		  </bibl> 
		</sourceDesc> 
	 </fileDesc> 
	 <encodingDesc> 
		<projectDesc> 
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		</projectDesc> 
		<editorialDecl n="4"> 
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p> 
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		</editorialDecl> 
		<refsDecl> 
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		</refsDecl> 
		<classDecl> 
		  <taxonomy> 
			 <bibl> 
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
			 </bibl> 
		  </taxonomy> 
		</classDecl> 
	 </encodingDesc> 
	 <profileDesc> 
		<textClass> 
		  <keywords> 
			 <list> 
				<item>Legal documents</item>
				<item>Cherokee Indians -- Claims</item>
				<item>Relocation</item>
				<item>Trail of Tears, 1838</item>
				<item>Southern States</item> 
			 </list> 
		  </keywords> 
		</textClass> 
	 </profileDesc> 
  </teiHeader> 
  <text> 
	 <body> 
		<div1 type="Legal document"><pb n="1"/> 
		  <opener>
		  The<name>United States</name> for Spoliation <abbr expan="Debtor">Dr</abbr> Improvements before 23rd of May 1836 <lb/> To <name>Ratting Gourd</name> of <name> <orig reg="Coosawattee">Coosoowattie</orig> District</name></opener>
		  <p>One field containing four acres good fence <lb/> One dwelling House 16 feet by 18 puncheon <lb/> floor loft of boards the wall hewd down good <lb/> wooden chimney rock back board roof weight poles_ One kitchen house 12 feet by 9_ round logs Dirt floor no loft. board roof weight poles tolerable <lb/> Chimney small rock back 1/2 an acre in Turnip patch one other house at an other place in <name>turnip mountain</name> fifteen by twelve puncheon floor board loft. Board roof weighted wooden chimney rock back <lb/> One small <unclear>Truck</unclear> patch containing two acres &amp; a half <lb/>  One corn field containing eight acres good fencing <lb/> Three peach trees all bearing. An Improvement in racoon Town one <orig reg="cabin">cabbin</orig> House 18. by 20 feet logs <abbr expan="scalped">scalpd</abbr> down, dirt floor board roof weighted with poles good wooden chimney rock, Turnip patch containing half an acre good fence another Improvement in <unclear>Amutchee</unclear> one cabin house 18 feet by 20 round logs puncheon floor, board loft <orig reg="clapboard">clabboard</orig> roof weight poles, good wooden chimney rock back, Two corn cribs 10 feet square One Field containing sixteen acres good fencing_ <lb/> Twelve small apple trees and ten small peach trees <lb/> Personally came <orig reg="before">beffore</orig> me Ratting Goard and affirms that the above <orig reg="Improvements">Improvents</orig> were his Improvements and that only apart of them have <add>ever</add> been valued by the assessing agents and that he has not received any valuation for said Improvements. Affirmed to before me this 18th of Sept. 1838</p> 
		<closer><signed><name>Collins McDonald</name></signed><lb/><add><abbr expan="Agent">Agnt.</abbr> C.C. East</add><add><name>Ratting <add>his x mark</add> Gourd</name></add><pb n="2"/><add>Personally came before <name>Collins McDonald</name> agent for collecting claims Cherokee Nation East. Tobacco Plant and <name>Cah.soo.tau.tee</name> and solemnly affirms that the above named Improvements did belong to the <orig reg="applicant">applican</orig> and that there has been only part valued affirmed to me this 18th of Sept. 1838.</add><signed>Collins McDonald</signed><abbr expan="Agent">Agnt</abbr> C.C. East <add><name>Tobacco <add>his x mark</add> Plant</name><name>Cah.soo.toty <add>his x mark</add></name></add><pb n="3"/><add>Spoliation <lb/> Ratting Gourd <lb/> Before the 23rd May 1836 <lb/> Coosoowatee <abbr expan="District">Dist</abbr><lb/> <abbr expan="Referred">Referd</abbr> through <name><abbr expan="John">Jno</abbr> Ross</name> <lb/><unclear><abbr expan="Principle">Pr</abbr></unclear> Chief to <abbr expan="Major General">Maj Genl </abbr> <lb/> Scott commanding US <lb/> Army for Settlement <lb/><abbr expan="Richard">Richd</abbr> Taylor <abbr expan="present">pres</abbr> <lb/> Committee<name> J Jones</name> <abbr expan="Clerk">Clk</abbr> <abbr expan="protempore">protem</abbr> <lb/> Committee</add></closer></div1> 
	 </body> 
  </text>
</TEI.2>
