<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="pa0274"> 
  <teiHeader> 
	 <fileDesc> 
		<titleStmt> 
		  <title>  [Claim] 1838 Sep. 5, Fort Armstrong, Alabama : a machine readable transcription of an image</title> 
		   
		  <respStmt> 
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 <name>Debra Roney</name> 
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name> 
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name> 
		  </respStmt> 
		</titleStmt> 
		<publicationStmt> 
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace> 
		  <address> 
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine> 
		  </address> 
		  <date>2003 
		  </date> 
		  <idno type="SPCID">pa0274</idno> 
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 45963731</idno> 
		  <availability> 
			 <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p> 
		  </availability> 
		</publicationStmt> 
		<sourceDesc> 
		  <bibl> 
			 <title>[Claim] 1838 Sep. 5, Fort Armstrong, Alabama </title> 
			  
			 <date value="1838-09-05">September 5, 1838</date> 
			 <extent> 4p</extent> 
			  
			 <note type="summary">This document is a claim dated September 5, 1838 made by Nawatta (also called Grits) to the United States to recover the value of six horses that were stolen by a white man in 1830.</note><note type="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note> 
			 <note type="box">MS-2033, b 1</note> 
			 <note type="folder">167</note> 
			 <note type="document"> pa0274</note> 
		  </bibl> 
		</sourceDesc> 
	 </fileDesc> 
	 <encodingDesc> 
		<projectDesc> 
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		</projectDesc> 
		<editorialDecl n="4"> 
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p> 
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		</editorialDecl> 
		<refsDecl> 
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		</refsDecl> 
		<classDecl> 
		  <taxonomy> 
			 <bibl> 
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
			 </bibl> 
		  </taxonomy> 
		</classDecl> 
	 </encodingDesc> 
	 <profileDesc> 
		<textClass> 
		  <keywords> 
			 <list> 
				<item>Claims</item><item>Cherokee Indians -- Crimes against</item><item>Cherokee Indians -- Claims</item><item>Fort Armstrong (Ala.)</item> 
			 </list> 
		  </keywords> 
		</textClass> 
	 </profileDesc> 
  </teiHeader> 
  <text> 
	 <body> 
		<div1 type="Claim"><pb n="1"/> 
		  <head>The <name>United States</name> To <name>Nawatta</name>, or <name>Grits</name> <name>(Fort Armstrong <abbr expan="Alabama">Ala.</abbr>)</name><abbr expan="Debtor">Dr</abbr>. To 6 head of horses stolen from him by &rcub; white men citizens of the United States in &rcub; the fall 8 years ago at Fort Arm &rcub;-strong Ala, To wit</head><p><table><row><cell>1 Gray mare 8 <abbr expan="years">yrs</abbr> old large</cell><cell>Worth</cell><cell>$60.00</cell></row><row><cell>1 Black mare 4 yrs. old, large</cell><cell>Worth</cell><cell>80.00</cell></row><row><cell>1 Black horse 3 yrs. old</cell><cell><abbr expan="Ditto">Do.</abbr></cell><cell>73.00</cell></row><row><cell>1 Bay horse 5 yrs. old</cell><cell>Do_</cell><cell>80.00</cell></row><row><cell>1 Iron Gray 4 yrs. old</cell><cell>Do_</cell><cell>50.00</cell></row><row><cell>1 Bay mare 3 yrs. old</cell><cell>Do_</cell><cell>45.00</cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell> </cell><cell>&horbar;</cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell> </cell><cell>$385.00</cell></row></table><lb/> Grits makes Oath, that he had Stolen from him the 6 horses charged in his <unclear>a/c</unclear>, in the fall of 1830 at Fort Armstrong in the state of Alabama_ Affiant at the time the horses were stolen, was the owner thereof_ That the horses were of the description and he believes of the value charged_ Affiant never saw the horses after they were stolen, but understood the horses were seen shortly afterwards in the possession of white men citizens of the United States,_ affiant never recovered any of said horses or any <pb n="2"/> thing for them, and prays the value thereof may be allowed him by the <abbr expan="Honorable">Hon</abbr> Committee in Spoliations</p><p>Sworn to and subscribed before me &rcub;this 5th day of September 1838 &rcub; <name>Jay Hicks</name> one of the Committee &rcub;</p></div1> 
	 <signed><name> Grits </name><add>his x mark</add></signed><closer><name>Eli Scott</name> and <name>Con, noo, ta, yah</name> make oath that they were acquainted with the claimant Grits and his property_ they know, that he owned the horses charged in his a/c,_ and believed the horses were worth the prices charged for them_ affiants knew that 8 yrs ago in the fall the horses were stolen from Grits at Fort Armstrong in the State of Alabama_ Affiants had been out Turkey hunting about 6 miles from where the horses were stolen, and were on our way back when we met 3 white men citizens of the United States, two of them called <name>Craddock</name>, the name of the other unknown, having claimants horses in possession_ riding bare backed, with paupau bark <orig reg="tied">tyed</orig> in the horses mouths in lieu of bridles, and running the horses off a pathway towards <name>Cedar Town</name>_ when they discovered <pb n="3"/> affiants, they turned off the path through the woods &amp; <orig reg="galloped">gallopped</orig> around affiants_ They had approached within a short distance of affiants before we were discovered_ Affiants saw the horses distinctly &amp; were well acquainted with them, and know them to belong to the claimant Grits_ affiants never heard of Grits recovering any of said horses or any thing for them_ Sworn to and subscribed before me 5th <abbr expan="September">Sept</abbr>. 1838 &rcub; Jay Hicks one of the Committee <signed>Eli <add>his x mark</add> Scott</signed><signed>Con, noo, ta, ya, <add>his x mark</add></signed>Examined by the Committee allowed &amp; reduced to $300. Sept. 7th, 1838. <signed><name>A. Fields</name> <abbr expan="Present">Prest.</abbr> Protem Committee</signed><pb n="4"/> No. 1169 Grits of Fort Armstrong <abbr expan="Alabama">Ala</abbr>. Spoliation Claim 6 horses $383.00 Reduced to $300.<add>admitted examined and allowed by the Commissioners</add></closer>    </body> 
  </text>
</TEI.2>
