<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="pa0292"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter]  1808 March 6, Federal Bottoms, [to] Return J. Meigs, Highwassee  / William P. Anderson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Anderson, William P.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harden</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">pa0292</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter]  1808 March 6, Federal Bottoms, [to] Return J. Meigs, Highwassee  / William P. Anderson</title><author>Anderson, William P.</author><date value="1808-03-06">March 6, 1808</date><extent> 4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter to Return J. Meigs, agent of the War department from William P. Anderson. Anderson asks that Meigs help a Mr. Barclay with a business enterprise in Cherokee territory.</note><note type="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note><note type="box">MS-2033</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">pa0292</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Business enterprises</item><item>Cherokee Indians</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine>Federal Bottoms</addrLine></address><salute>My much respected friend,</salute></opener><p>As this will be handed to you by an old &amp; intimate acquaintance of mine, who visits <abbr expan="your">yr.</abbr> country for the purpose of making an establishment in it &amp; that too through yr. knowledge &amp; better understanding of <unclear>their cliuny</unclear> I hope <abbr expan="you will">y'll</abbr> pardon the <abbr expan="liberty">libty</abbr> I have taken, and will <abbr expan="recommend">recdm</abbr> <name>Mr. Barclay</name> (the gentleman alluded to &amp; who hands you this) all the <unclear>praue</unclear> you may consistently &amp; without trouble to <abbr expan="yourself">yrself</abbr> find convenient.</p><p>He is I can assure you a plain honest gentleman &amp; on whom the greatest confidence &amp; trust may be placed_</p><p>He wishes to rent the ferry at the <name>Nickajack</name> &amp; to make an establishment there in the line of <pb n="2"/> a ferryman &amp; farmer that shall do credit to the Nation_ He is a man of sufficient property to do so and as I know not whether yrself has the  renting of it as how it is, I have recommended him to first see you &amp; know how to act on the occasion_</p><p>This <abbr expan="he will">h'll</abbr> do.</p><p>I have also <orig reg="got to">goto</orig> haul my little son Rufus to <name>Mrs. Gambold</name>, who lives near <orig reg="Vann's">Vans</orig> to be <abbr expan="learned">learn'd</abbr> by her the English &amp; German language, provided she will receive him_</p><p>I am altogether disposed  to teach my children from <unclear>leome</unclear> &amp; having the highest opinion of Mrs Gambold have put him there by way of experiment_  Be pleased Sir to signify whether this meets yr. approbation &amp; whether you think it will have the tendency of exciting their jealousies ( I mean the indians)__ Should you think well of it &amp; they nor none of them <unclear>ever</unclear> <pb n="3"/> <unclear>sneer</unclear> about it, I shall rest contented that my little son will have yr. protection &amp; good wishes so long as he shall remain in their land.</p><p>Your kind letters to<name> <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Strother</name> &amp; myself with the manuscript copies of the treaties, have been <abbr expan="received">recd.</abbr> &amp; for which we most humbly thank you__ The elucidation <orig reg="really">realy</orig> gave us great relief. I hope you will not hesitate to command either of us at all times__We would with pleasure <unclear>free</unclear> you in anyway that may be within the <orig reg="Compass">Cumpass</orig> or our power.</p><closer><salute>In haste I am yr. friend</salute><signed><name><abbr expan="William">W.</abbr> P. Anderson</name></signed><date>6th March 1808</date><pb n="4"/> <address><addrLine><name><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Return J. Meigs</name> <name>Highwassee</name><name>Mr Barclay</name></addrLine></address><add><abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr> P. Andersons Letter in favor of Mr. Barclay no date <abbr expan="received">receivd</abbr> <date>24 March 1808</date></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
