<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="pa0221"> 
  <teiHeader> 
	 <fileDesc> 
		<titleStmt> 
		  <title>[Letter] 1817 Jan. 29, Highawassee Garrison [Tenn. to] Col[onel] Return J. Meigs, Cherokee Agency / David Parkhill  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title> 
		   
		  <author> Parkhill, David</author><respStmt> 
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 <name>Debra Roney</name> 
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name> 
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name> 
		  </respStmt> 
		</titleStmt> 
		<publicationStmt> 
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace> 
		  <address> 
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine> 
		  </address> 
		  <date>2003 
		  </date> 
		  <idno type="SPCID">pa0221</idno> 
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 45870019</idno> 
		  <availability> 
			 <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p> 
		  </availability> 
		</publicationStmt> 
		<sourceDesc> 
		  <bibl> 
			 <title>[Letter] 1817 Jan. 29, Highawassee Garrison [Tenn. to] Col[onel] Return J. Meigs, Cherokee Agency / David Parkhill</title><author>Parkhill, David</author> 
			  
			 <date value="1817-01-29">January 29, 1817</date> 
			 <extent>2p</extent> 
			  
			 <note type="summary">This is a letter, dated January 29, 1817 to Colonel Return J. Meigs, Cherokee Agent, from David Parkhill concerning accusations of injustice leveled against him by a group of Cherokee. The letter also discussed Parkhill's concerns that a Mr. Gambill was trying to take his place.</note><note type="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note> 
			 <note type="box">MS-2033, b1</note> 
			 <note type="folder">89</note> 
			 <note type="document"> pa0221</note> 
		  </bibl> 
		</sourceDesc> 
	 </fileDesc> 
	 <encodingDesc> 
		<projectDesc> 
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		</projectDesc> 
		<editorialDecl n="4"> 
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p> 
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		</editorialDecl> 
		<refsDecl> 
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		</refsDecl> 
		<classDecl> 
		  <taxonomy> 
			 <bibl> 
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
			 </bibl> 
		  </taxonomy> 
		</classDecl> 
	 </encodingDesc> 
	 <profileDesc> 
		<textClass> 
		  <keywords> 
			 <list> 
				<item>Cherokee Indians -- Crimes against</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>Letters</item> 
			 </list> 
		  </keywords> 
		</textClass> 
	 </profileDesc> 
  </teiHeader> 
  <text> 
	 <body> 
		<div1 type="Lettters"><pb n="1"/> 
		  <opener><address><addrLine>Highawassee Garrison<date><abbr expan="January">Jany</abbr>. 29th 1817</date></addrLine></address><name><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Return J. Meigs</name><salute>Dear Sir,</salute></opener><p>I feel <orig reg="very">verry</orig> much embarrassed on account of the probability of my being disappointed in my contract with <name>Vann</name>, I have made every arrangement which was necessary on my part to <del type="overstrike">fullfill</del> meet my engagement with him, a failure at this time would I will assure you injure me verry considerably I have understood that <add>it</add> has been alleged by some of the Indians that I done them injustice in <unclear>issuing</unclear> whilst acting as contractor, This I presume can be no solid objection it can be nothing more than a protest, because the whole of my conduct was well known to them previous to my contract with <name>McNair &amp; Brown</name>, nothing can have transpired since that time to lessen their confidence in me. I am strongly inclined to believe that this tale is not on foot for the purpose of <unclear>susstanting</unclear> me in this business, Indeed I have just learned that Mr. <name><abbr expan="Robert">Robt</abbr>. Gambell</name> is using every exertion to obtain the place over my head, contrary to every principle of Justice &amp; common honesty. You Sir are the only person I have to look up to in this trying situation. I hope and trust that you will not fail to befriend me_</p><closer>Accept the assurances of my esteem<signed>David Parkhill</signed><pb n="2"/><add><name><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo</abbr>. Return J. Meigs</name><address><addrLine>Cherokee Agency</addrLine></address></add><add>David Parkhills letter</add></closer><closer><add></add></closer></div1> 
	 </body> 
  </text>
</TEI.2>
