<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="pa0271"> 
  <teiHeader> 
	 <fileDesc> 
		<titleStmt> 
		  <title>[Claim] 1838 May 23, United States to Black Fox : a machine readable transcription of an image</title> 
		   
		  <respStmt> 
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 <name>Debra Roney</name> 
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name> 
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name> 
		  </respStmt> 
		</titleStmt> 
		<publicationStmt> 
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace> 
		  <address> 
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine> 
		  </address> 
		  <date>2003 
		  </date> 
		  <idno type="SPCID">pa0271</idno> 
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 45963719</idno> 
		  <availability> 
			 <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p> 
		  </availability> 
		</publicationStmt> 
		<sourceDesc> 
		  <bibl> 
			 <title>[Claim] 1838 May 23, United States to Black Fox</title> 
			  
			 <date value="1838-05-23">May 23, 1838</date> 
			 <extent>4 p</extent> 
			  
			 <note type="summary">This document is a spoliation claim dated May 23, 1838, by the United States to Black Fox for improvements made to the land he owned before he was removed by the US authorities. The case was referred to Major General Scott for settlement. </note><note type="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note> 
			 <note type="box">MS-2033, b1</note> 
			 <note type="folder">162</note> 
			 <note type="document"> pa0271</note> 
		  </bibl> 
		</sourceDesc> 
	 </fileDesc> 
	 <encodingDesc> 
		<projectDesc> 
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		</projectDesc> 
		<editorialDecl n="4"> 
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p> 
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		</editorialDecl> 
		<refsDecl> 
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		</refsDecl> 
		<classDecl> 
		  <taxonomy> 
			 <bibl> 
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
			 </bibl> 
		  </taxonomy> 
		</classDecl> 
	 </encodingDesc> 
	 <profileDesc> 
		<textClass> 
		  <keywords> 
			 <list> 
				<item>Claims</item> 
			 <item>Cherokee Indians -- Claims</item><item>Betterments</item><item>Cherokee Indians -- Land tenure</item><item>Southern States</item></list> 
		  </keywords> 
		</textClass> 
	 </profileDesc> 
  </teiHeader> 
  <text> 
	 <body> 
		<div1 type="claim"><pb n="1"/> 
		  <p><table><head>The <name>United States</name> for Spoliation <abbr expan="Debtor">Dr</abbr> To <name>Black Fox</name> <name>Amuhee District</name></head><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell><orig reg="dollar sign">&cent;</orig> <abbr expan="cents">cts</abbr></cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>Dwelling house hewed inside &amp; out <lb/> 23 by 19 feet <del type="overstrike">Sys</del> short board roof <lb/> nailed on puncheon floor 1 doon <lb/> plank shutter stick &amp;  dirt <lb/> chimny Rock Back</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell> 1</cell><cell><orig reg="cabin">cabbin</orig>  18 feet <abbr expan="square">sqr</abbr> hewed Log common board roof puncheon floor</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>cabbin 18 feet sqr round log no floor board roof</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>milk house hewed log board roof</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell> small lot for garden about one acre</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>15 acres of cleared ridge <add>or up</add> land under <lb/> good fence</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>acres of up land in <add>one</add> other field under <lb/> good fence</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>800</cell><cell>Rails___</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>yoke of Steers</cell><cell>50 00</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>Brown mare 2 <abbr expan="years">yrs</abbr> old</cell><cell>60 00</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>Bay mare 2 yrs old</cell><cell>70 00</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>Stock hogs</cell><cell>7 00</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>shoats one year old _ 3.00</cell><cell>18 00</cell></row><row><cell>5 apple trees bearing fruit</cell><cell>$205 00</cell></row><row><cell>25 peach trees bearing fruit</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>15 young peach trees</cell><cell></cell></row></table></p><p>The petitioner states that he made the improvements above stated and resided there until he was removed by the authorities of  the United States &amp; that he cultivated the cleared land above named until the present year that the dwelling house &amp; other small houses were of the description above described and that there was the number of  acres of cleared land as stated &amp; under good fences <pb n="[2]"/> And <del type="overstrike">that</del> there was the number &amp; Kind of fruit as above stated <sic>as above stated</sic> and that <add>he</add> left eight hundred good rails on the premises when he left This petitioner further states that about four years ago he loaned the yoke of work steers described in the foregoing account to a white man citizen of the United States Known to the cherokees by the name of <del type="overstrike">Sol</del> <add><name>Davis</name></add> and that during the time the said <del type="overstrike"><name>Solomon</name></del><add><name>Davis</name></add> had the steers in possession he ran away &amp; took the steers with <add>him</add> &amp; that this petitioner has never been able to procure them and that the steers were well worth the prices stated in the foregoing account. This petitioner further states that about four years a white man citizen of the United States by the name of <del type="overstrike">Davis</del><add>Solomon</add> held a claim against a Cherokee by the name of  <name>Elic Sutesefen</name>  said that the said <add>Solomon</add> <del type="overstrike">Davis</del> without any lawful process took the brown mare first described in the foregoing account to satisfy his claim against Sutestefen and that he never received from any person any compensation whatever for said mare &amp; that he believes that she was well worth the price charged._</p><p>This petitioner further states that about the year 1834, he was in possession &amp; owned the bay mare last described in the foregoing account and that he loaned said mare to a white man citizen of the United States known to the Cherokees by the name of <name>John</name> and that during the time he had the mare in possession under a loan he sold the mare, and stated to this petitioner <pb n="3"/> that he would pay him for the mare but never at any time paid him one cent by way of compensation for his mare and that he believes that the mare was worth the price set forth. And this petitioner further saith that the hogs set forth in the foregoing account were worth the prices charged and that he purchased the hogs from a Cherokee who resided in the State of <name>Georgia</name> and that the hogs ran away &amp; they were sold under the stray laws of Georgia and that he never received any money arising from the sale of the hogs. All of the foregoing statement the said Black Fox affirms to be just and true to the best of his knowledge &amp; belief.</p><p>Affirmed before me this 15th day of Sept. 1838</p><signed><name>Collins McDonald</name><add>Agent for Collecting Claims</add><name>Black Fox <add>his x mark</add></name></signed></div1> 
	 <div1><p>Personally came before me <del>Black Fox </del> <name>Catchen</name> of the Cherokee Nation and solemnly affirmed that he was well acquainted with the applicant Black Fox and knows that he knows that he made and occupied the improvements above stated and that owned the property described in his account and that he lost it under the circumstances he had set forth to the best of his recollection and that it was worth the prices charged all of which he lost before the 23rd of May 1838 to the best of his knowledge and belief</p><p>Affirmed to before me the 15th <abbr expan="September">Sept</abbr>. 1838</p><signed>Collins McDonald <add>Agent for Collecting Claims</add><name>Catchen</name><add>his x mark</add></signed></div1></body> 
  <pb n="4"/><back><head>Amuhee District <lb/> The United States <lb/> To <lb/> Black Fox <lb/> Up to 23rd May 1838 <lb/> Referred through <abbr expan="John">Jno</abbr> Ross <lb/> <abbr expan="Principle">Pr</abbr>. Chief to <abbr expan="Major General">Maj. Genl</abbr> <lb/>Scott Commanding US <lb/> Army for Settlement <lb/> <abbr expan="Richard">Richd</abbr> Taylor <abbr expan="president">pres</abbr> <lb/> N. Committee <lb/> J. Jones <abbr expan="clerk ">clk</abbr> protem <lb/> N. Committee <add><unclear>ABLs</unclear></add></head></back></text>
</TEI.2>
