<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl709">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter]  1808 Jul. 7, Talassee [Alabama, to] Benjamin Hawkins / Hopohuilthlu Miceo : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Miceo, Hopohuilthlu</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl709</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter]  1808 Jul. 7, Talassee [Alabama, to] Benjamin Hawkins / Hopohuilthlu Miceo</title>
               <author>Miceo, Hopohuilthlu</author>
               <date when="1808-07-07">July 7, 1808</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a copy of a  letter to Colonel Benjamin Hawkins from the Creek Chief Hopohuilthlu Miceo, dated July 7, 1808. Hawkins is the U.S.'s  Agent for Indian Affairs south of the Ohio River. Miceo is writing in regards to an attack by some Creeks on their American  neighbors. Miceo wants Hawkins to assure President Jefferson that the Creeks will find out and punish the guilty parties.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor John Sevier Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl709</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Alabama</term>
               <term>Creek Indians --  Government relations</term>
               <term>Hawkins, Benjamin, 1754-1816.</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Miceo, Hopohuilthlu</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl709a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <orig>Talassee</orig>
                           <reg>Tallassee</reg>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                     <date>7th July 1808</date>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>From Hopohoilthlu Miceo (<unclear>Tanee</unclear> King) to <choice>
                        <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                        <expan>Colonel</expan>
                     </choice> Hawkins</addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>we have this day received your letter and after duly considering the contents have sent you the following reply.</p>
            <p>I am happy you sent the president a message by <name>Hard</name> he is a great chief and one of our best Warriors, and able to report to you things in <choice>
                  <orig>there</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice> true light I have a full sense of the situation of our Country. I have a feeling for our Red people and our white <choice>
                  <orig>Neighbours</orig>
                  <reg>Neighbors</reg>
               </choice>, and should be very sorry to see innocent people murdered on account of the bad conduct of a few villains and do <choice>
                  <orig>asure</orig>
                  <reg>assure</reg>
               </choice> you that every thing shall be done to reestablish harmony and friendship between us and our white neighbours_ I well Know that mischief has been done by some of our people, I also know that the Law of nations always require satisfaction for crimes of this nature, we therefore feel ourselves under obligation to give Satisfaction demanded by the President which I promise shall be done immediately. I am an old man but find I must once more step forward to save our land from ruin, by my Exertions. I hope you will shortly see that I can find warriors of firmness enough which will when <choice>
                  <abbr>call;d</abbr>
                  <expan>called</expan>
               </choice> on come forward to detect and punish <choice>
                  <orig>villany</orig>
                  <reg>villainy</reg>
               </choice>, I shall send them out immediately with orders to punish those perpetrators without discrimination as fast as they may be found.</p>
            <p>You may inform the president that our intentions are just that we only want time to find and chastise the Guilty and if  we after this neglect to perform and fulfill this promise we cannot think hard if the white people should take satisfaction which they now require from our hands, but <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> that time I hope that our innocent people may not be injured for the conduct of a few wicked men___</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am Your friend a friend to the white people</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Hopohoilthlu &amp; Miceo</name>
                  <add>Talesee x Miceo</add>
               </signed>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl709b.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Fooseehatche n Tustunnugge</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Colo <choice>
                           <abbr>B.</abbr>
                           <expan>Benjamin</expan>
                        </choice> Hawkins</addrLine>
                  </address> Written as interpreted by <lb/>
                  <name>Alexander Cornell</name>s <choice>
                     <abbr>asst</abbr>
                     <expan>assistant</expan>
                  </choice> agent &amp; public Interpreter <lb/> By <name>Samuel F. Bloomfield</name>
               </add>
               <add>A True Copy from the Original <lb/>
                  <name>Christian Luisbaugh</name> Asst agent</add>
               <add>The above Hopohoilthle Miceo was known during the war of the revolution as the Talesee King always friendly to the <name>United States</name> He is now at the head of affairs <choice>
                     <orig>amoung</orig>
                     <reg>among</reg>
                  </choice> the <unclear>Upper Creeks</unclear> one of the three Great Medal Chiefs</add>
               <add>
                  <name>Benjamin   Hawkins</name>
               </add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl709c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Hopohoilthle Miceo <lb/> to <lb/> Colo Hawkins <lb/> promise of satisfac <lb/> tion on the part of the <name>Creek <lb/> nation</name> for <choice>
                     <abbr>autrosses</abbr>
                     <expan>atrocities</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>commited</orig>
                     <reg>committed</reg>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/> on the position of <name>Tennessee</name>
                  <lb/> 7 July 1808 <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Recd.</abbr>
                     <expan>Received</expan>
                  </choice> 13.</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
