<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl475">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1796 Oct. 29, Knox[ville, Tennessee, to] John Chisholm / D[avid] Henley: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Henley, D.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl475</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1796 Oct. 29, Knox[ville, Tennessee, to] John Chisholm / D[avid] Henley</title>
               <author>Henley, D.</author>
               <date when="1796-10-29">October 29, 1796</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to John Chisholm from David Henley, dated October 29, 1796. Henley, an agent for the War Department, is giving instructions on the transportation of several native peoples to Philadelphia. The natives are members of the Cherokee, Choctaw, Creek, and Chickasaw Nations. The purpose of the trip may be to gain U. S. citizenship for them. Chisholm is instructed to take great care with them, keep them fed and healthy, and to limit their drinking.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">David Henley Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">29</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl475</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Indians of North America -- Government policy</term>
               <term>Travel</term>
               <term>Military</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n85198931"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Henley, David, 1749-1823</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl475a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir)</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>As you are the conductor of the ten <name>Cherokee</name>s, namely <name>Watts</name> and his Son_ <name>Willioe</name> and his mother- <name>Big airon</name>- <name>George Lowry</name>- <name>John Langley</name>- <name>Middle Stricken</name>- <name>Thigh</name>- and <name>Charles Beaman</name>, and nine <name>Creek</name> namely <name>Dog Warrior</name>
               <name>Chinabe</name>- <name>Factor</name>- <name>Long Warrior</name>- <name>Kern off</name>- <name>Little Morgan</name>- <name>Coosey</name>- <name>Holowing Blue</name>- and <name>Cusatee King</name>- my orders are that you proceed with all <del type="overstrike">immediate displd</del> the expedition that the circumstances of such a charge will admit, delaying no more time on the Road than may be necessary for the saving of your Horses <add>or unavoidable called to</add> and proceed through the Great Road to <name>Winchester</name>- <name>Lancaster</name> and <name>Philadelphia</name>, and deliver my letter to the honorable Secretary of War who will direct where and how the indians are to be provided for at <add>that city</add>
               <del type="overstrike">Philadelphia</del>
            </p>
            <p>
               <del type="overstrike">Should any of them be taken sick you must provide for them in some good family as the <choice>
                     <orig>expence</orig>
                     <reg>expense</reg>
                  </choice> of the United States</del> - You must provide for them <add>all things necessary</add> on their journey so that <pb n="2" facs="sl475b.small.jpg"/> that they may be comfortable and with as much prudence as the <add>town and care of the indians</add>
               <del type="overstrike">charge</del> in which You are engaged in will allow_ <add>and prevent as much as possible their having drink to excess__ </add> You must also provide for them in case of sickness or accident at the expence of the United States in some good <choice>
                  <orig>familys</orig>
                  <reg>families</reg>
               </choice> and do what is in your power to save them from any injury, and to make their journey agreeable to them- </p>
            <p>The two interpreters, <del type="overstrike">must</del>
               <add>and</add>
               <name>Sandy</name>&amp;<name>Walter Grayson</name> two half breeds <add>may</add>
               <del type="overstrike">way</del> also be furnished on their journey with Provisions and forage at the expence of the public, and you pay will be what <name>Governor Blount</name> has formerly allowed till you get to <choice>
                  <abbr>Phila</abbr>
                  <expan>Philadelphia</expan>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <p>Five <name>Choctaw</name>s <add>and a <name>Chickasaw</name>
               </add>
               <name>Pawnshenaumtalk</name>_ <name>Yestossia</name>_ <name>Shosshawhomach</name>__ <name>Alstanabay</name>_  <del type="overstrike">Jate manstaba</del>
               <name>Colbert</name>_ and <name>Nowawtobay</name> a boy__ having just arrived You have been detained to take them also under your care, and they <add>and their interpreters</add> must he considered as included in the above <add>orders</add> respecting their care, expence and providing for them in the same manner as the others___</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>D</abbr>
                     <expan>David</expan>
                  </choice> Henley</signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Knox</abbr>
                           <expan>Knoxville</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <unclear>th</unclear>
                     <date> 29 October 1796</date>-</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Capt</abbr>
                        <expan>Captain</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name>John Chisholm</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl475c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Knox <lb/> th 29 October 1796 <lb/> orders to John Chisholm</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
