<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl464">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1795 May 20, Cedar Hall [to] David Henley, Knoxville [Territory South of the Ohio River] / Robert Hays : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Hays, Robert</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl464</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1795 May 20, Cedar Hall [to] David Henley, Knoxville [Territory South of the Ohio River] / Robert Hays</title>
               <author>Hays, Robert</author>
               <date when="1795-05-20">May 20, 1795</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Robert Hays to David Henley, dated May 20, 1795. Hays wants to know if Henley will be coming to his district to pay the soldiers. Hays writes that he will have the Muster Rolls ready in a month. He also writes that he can come to Knoxville if necessary.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">David Henley Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl464</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Territory of the United States South of the River Ohio</term>
               <term>Henley, David, 1749-1823</term>
               <term>Military</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Hays, Robert</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl464a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Cedar Hall</name>
                     <date>20th May 1795</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir/</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>yours of the <date>25th April</date> came safe to hand in which you mentioned the Secretary of the Treasury opinion respecting the Militia finding Their own Rations. I have shown them your Letter for their Better government, you mentioned the arrival of the money for the Service of the Militia for 1794, But heard no mention in your Letter to me about your <unclear>coming</unclear> to this place to make payment to the Troops in this District as you Told me you would when I parted with you &amp; I informed the men They would Receive their pay in this Country, I hope you have not give over that thought for many of the men keeps up their <unclear>Certificate</unclear> with are Expectation of their certainly getting it here _ _ _ _ </p>
            <p>Should you come to the Country I could go to <name>Knoxville</name> in June and assist you in <unclear>recieving</unclear> the money here If you think you will not I will thank you to <choice>
                  <orig>Informe</orig>
                  <reg>Inform</reg>
               </choice> me of it as I may let the Soldiers know it as Disagreeable as it may be, you mentioned to me there would be money for me by the first arrival of money from <name>Philadelphia</name> upon the strength of that I fell in Debt to <name>Mr Saunderson</name>. Hundred dollars and give him an order on you to that <choice>
                  <orig>ammount</orig>
                  <reg>amount</reg>
               </choice> I will be much Obliged to you <add>to</add> Pay him that sum. If there should be no money in your Hands for me, you will Oblige me in a Singular manner If you will advance that sum for me, I have Some money but when money gets to the Country we ought to try to keep it as there  are a risk in getting money to this place_</p>
            <p>I have not got in all my Muster Rolls as yet but Shall have them Ready by the <date>20th</date> next month when a Large Company will Start for Knoxville from this Place <pb n="2" facs="sl464b.small.jpg"/> your good Bottle of Brandy was a just friend to me Through the wilderness &amp; we <del type="overstrike">made</del> made it hold out to the Bank of Cumberland where it was Finished <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Smith</name> &amp; myself Drank <choice>
                  <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Henlys Health</p>
            <p>Pray make my Compliments to <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Capt</abbr>
                     <expan>Captain</expan>
                  </choice> Record</name>-</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have the <choice>
                     <orig>Honour</orig>
                     <reg>Honor</reg>
                  </choice> Sir to be your <lb/> Sincere Friends &amp; <choice>
                     <abbr>Huml Servt</abbr>
                     <expan>Humble Servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Robert Hays</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Colo <name>David Henley</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>NB</abbr>
                     <expan>Nota Bene</expan>
                  </choice> the Blank Rolls I got from you when at Knoxville were pay Rolls therefore I have no <choice>
                     <orig>Blanke</orig>
                     <reg>Blank</reg>
                  </choice> Muster Rolls would be glad of Some If you can Send me any- </add>
               <signed>Robert Hays</signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl464c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Colo David Henley</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Knoxville</addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Cedar Hall 20 May 1795</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>from <choice>
                        <abbr>Robt</abbr>
                        <expan>Robert</expan>
                     </choice> Hays</addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Cedar Hall 20 May 7</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
