<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl365">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1836 Jun. 5 [to] Maj[or] A[ndrew] J[ackson] Donelson, Washington City / Stockly Donelson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Donelson, Stockly</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl365</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1836 Jun. 5 [to] Maj[or] A[ndrew] J[ackson] Donelson, Washington City / Stockly Donelson</title>
               <author>Donelson, Stockly</author>
               <date when="1836-06-05">June 5, 1836</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated June 5, 1836, to Andrew Jackson Donelson, nephew and personal secretary to President Andrew Jackson,  from his brother-in-law Stockly Donelson.  Stockly writes about a recent horse race that his horse, which he named Martin Van Buren, won.  He also provides an update on the condition of Andrew's home, which is in the process of being built.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bettie M. Donelson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> III-E-2-3 b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">4</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl365</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Middle Tennessee</term>
               <term>Donelson, Andrew Jackson 1799-1871</term>
               <term>Recreation-horse racing</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr91014733"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Donelson, Stockley, -approximately 1804</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl365a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>June the 5th 1836</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Andrew</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The races are now over and I have <choice>
                  <orig>liesure</orig>
                  <reg>leisure</reg>
               </choice> to write you a few lines- I won both my races- The Crusader distanced the <choice>
                  <orig>feild</orig>
                  <reg>field</reg>
               </choice> the 2nd heat in 2.<add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>m</abbr>
                     <expan>minutes</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add> 1. <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>s</abbr>
                     <expan>second</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add> and could have run 4 miles and repeat at the same tick track  heavy I run the Pacific against <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Gen</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Mabry</name>  celebrated Leviathan filly a dash of a mile and carried 10 pounds the most weight and a raw inexperienced rider- I got a bad start and ran locked from the first turn until within a hundred yards of the Judges stand.  The filly had the track &amp; was good a rider as ever mounted.  I beat him about 2 lengths-time 2. <add>m</add> 2. <add>s</add> It was the handsomest and best contested race I ever saw and the time was good- with the same weight that the <add>filly</add> carried and as good a rider my colt could have run it in 1. <add>m</add> 57. <add>s</add> track heavy and several bad mud holes.  There was not  a man that saw my colt But pronounced <add>him</add> the best Pacific they ever saw and able with equal advantage to beat the <add>Leviathan</add> 50 yards.  I have <add>named</add> him Martin Van Buren- The bets were 2 to 1 on the Leviathan until mine made his appearance on the track and then the bets were even-</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="sl365b.small.jpg"/>
            <p> In relation to your affairs here all is going well at your farm- You have a good crop &amp; it is in good order- Your stock all look well- Your house will now be soon finished- The paper has arrived and the painters are finishing off and papering as fast as they can- But I am sorry to say to you nothing as yet has been done towards the yard. But that can yet be done this summer</p>
            <p>By reference to the last Union you will see that Carter has been advertised by me I am very uneasy about him I fear you will never get him again if he gets on the <name>Ohio</name> .  I am going to town tomorrow and will endeavor <del type="overstrike">
                  <unclear/>
               </del> to get a man to pursue him.</p>
            <p>I wish you to write me if you wish <unclear>Stockly</unclear> to remain the year out- He is a <choice>
                  <orig>disagreable</orig>
                  <reg>disagreeable</reg>
               </choice> man- but will have more work done than any one else- He will agree to quit at any time you wish him-</p>
            <p>Cousin Daniel and Lady and family has arrived and will remain here the summer out.</p>
            <p>When shall we expect you and sister Emily &amp; family.</p>
            <p>Give our love to all and believe me</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>sincerely yours</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Stockly Donelson</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl365c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Maj A J</abbr>
                           <expan>Major Andrew Jackson</expan>
                        </choice> Donelson</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Washington City</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Capt</abbr>
                     <expan>Captain</expan>
                  </choice> Stockly Donelson <lb/>
                  <date>June 5 1836</date>
               </add>
               <add>Bettie M. Donelson papers.</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
