<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl623">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Financial report] 1842 Sep. 19, Memphis, Tennessee [to] James Jones, Nashville, Tennessee / Lewis C. Hezwurst : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Hezwurst,  Lewis C.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl623</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Financial report] 1842 Sep. 19, Memphis, Tennessee [to] James Jones, Nashville, Tennessee / Lewis C. Hezwurst</title>
               <author>  Hezwurst,  Lewis C.</author>
               <date when="1842-09-19"> 
			 September 19, 1842</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a financial report, dated September 19, 1842, from the Memphis state Hospital in Tennessee to the governor of the state, James Jones.  The report contains information that the hospital's funds are insufficient for the term of the regular cession of the state legislature.    </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor James Jones Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">4</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl623</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor (1841-1845 : Jones)</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Hospitals Accounting</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Associated name http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/asn">Hezwurst, Lewis C.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl623a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <add>His Excellency <name>James C. Jones</name> Governor of the State of <name>Tennessee</name>
               </add>
            </opener>
            <p>The president and board of Commissioners of the <name>Memphis</name> Hospital, would respectfully call your attention to the state of the affairs of that institution, with a view that you would be pleased to call the attention of the Legislature about to assemble on the 1st monday in October next to it.</p>
            <p>We would respectfully refer you to the statement and report made to the general <choice>
                  <orig>Asembly</orig>
                  <reg>Assembly</reg>
               </choice> on the 10th day of November last which showed a balance in the Treasurers hands of 6615.88 <lb/>  Amount in suit against former treasurer 1236.00  <lb/> Cash received the property of deceased patients 9.37 <lb/> $7861.25</p>
            <p>The <choice>
                  <orig>expendatures</orig>
                  <reg>expenditures</reg>
               </choice> for the completion of the building and improving the grounds have been $1852.60</p>
            <p>The expendatures for the benefit of the sick in Hospital up to the present time is 2970.06 <lb/> Still uncollected from former Treasurer 811.00 <lb/> Cash in Treasurers hands deposited in the Farmers and Merchants Bank of this place 2227[.] 59 $7861.25</p>
            <p>The balance remaining in the Treasurers hands will be insufficient to carry on the establishment until the regular cession of the Legislature.</p>
            <p>The number of sick admitted into the Hospital since its commencement in <choice>
                  <abbr>Novemr</abbr>
                  <expan>November</expan>
               </choice>. last have been eighty six the number of deaths have been sixteen, and the number still under treatment are seventeen__<pb n="2" facs="sl623b.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>We would further state, that owing to the low state of the finances, numbers of applicants have been refused admittance, and none but those persons who are in utter destitution, and who have no house to shelter or friends to protect have been admitted; we therefore trust that the great utility and importance of the continuance of this institution will induce you to call the attention of the Legislature to the <choice>
                  <orig>necesity</orig>
                  <reg>necessity</reg>
               </choice> of making an appropriation of the merchants <choice>
                  <orig>Lisences</orig>
                  <reg>Licenses</reg>
               </choice> of <date>shelby county</date> from the 1st day of <date>January 1842</date> the time at which the last act for the benefit of the institution <choice>
                  <orig>expresed</orig>
                  <reg>expressed</reg>
               </choice>; this sum as shown in the former report would be <choice>
                  <orig>insufficent</orig>
                  <reg>insufficient</reg>
               </choice> for the carrying on of the Hospital in extended usefulness, but it would enable the institution to be carried on in its present limited state until the regular cession of the Legislature when a more full report will be laid before that body</p>
            <p>All of which is most respectfully submitted for your consideration and <choice>
                  <orig>favourable</orig>
                  <reg>favorable</reg>
               </choice> action </p>
            <closer>
               <add>Signed on behalf of the Hospital Commissioner</add>
               <signed>
                  <name>Lewis C hezwurst</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Prest</abbr>
                     <expan>President</expan>
                  </choice> of the Board of Hospital <choice>
                     <orig>Commissur</orig>
                     <reg>Commissioner</reg>
                  </choice>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                     <expan>William</expan>
                  </choice> G. Adams <choice>
                     <abbr>Secry</abbr>
                     <expan>Secretary</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <name>Memphis</name>
                  <date>19th <choice>
                        <abbr>Sept</abbr>
                        <expan>September</expan>
                     </choice> 1842</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
