<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc234">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter]  1850 Aug. 3, Memphis, Tennessee [to] Miss Sarah J. Armstrong,  Jerusalem, Virginia / Daniel Douglass : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Douglass, Daniel</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc234</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter]  1850 Aug. 3, Memphis, Tennessee [to] Miss Sarah J. Armstrong,  Jerusalem, Virginia / Daniel Douglass</title>
               <author> Douglass, Daniel</author>
               <date when="1850-08-03"> 
			 August 3, 1850</date>
               <extent> 4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated August 3, 1850 from Daniel Douglass to Sarah Armstrong. Douglass writes of his travels from Lancaster, Pennsylvania to various other cities along the Mississippi River.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Daniel Douglass Letter</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">New Accessions</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc234</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Travel</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Virginia</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Douglass, Daniel</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc234a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Memphis Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>August 3rd 1850</date>
               <salute>Dear Miss Armstrong</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your favour of the first ultimo was received just as I was about to leave <name>Lancaster</name> on the sixth; Since that time I  have been so constantly engaged that have not had an opportunity to reply to it. I am extremely sorry to hear such bad news of <name>Mrs. Tyler's</name> health. I hoped that the warm weather would restore her to at least her usual health and strength. The thought of leaving this world even by that lingering and painful disease, Consumption, I am sure would not have any <unclear>remorse</unclear> for her, but <name>Mrs. Rochelle</name> must feel it deeply. I can hardly conceive a severer trial than to see the daily, hourly inroads of that horrible disease on one we love, I trust that Mrs. Rochelle may be spared this trial. You ask me to teach you my mode of pressing flowers, it is extremely simple; most that preserve I press in my diary as it is always convenient, those that I preserved in <name>Charleston</name> I placed between course paper and placed under a weight sufficiently heavy to bring every part of <sic>of</sic> the flower in contrast with the paper, but heavy enough to crush it, I frequently took them out to look at them, this was an advantage to them as I have since learned, the great secret, an old friend of mine in <name>Wheeling </name>
               <pb n="2" facs="sc234b.small.jpg"/> is to change the paper frequently. My curiosity caused me to move those which I preserved from one part of the paper to another and I thus obtained some better specimens than I expected. A florist in Charleston told me that the coarsest paper (straw paper) was the best. You are wrong in your notions with regard to Lancaster county <choice>
                  <abbr>Pa</abbr>
                  <expan>Pennsylvania</expan>
               </choice>; the surface of that county is generally undulating, in some places rising by easy slopes so the height of four or five hundred feet. There are some spurs of the <note anchored="true">Blue <choice>
                     <orig>Ridg </orig>
                     <reg>Ridge</reg>
                  </choice>
               </note>which the natives dignify with the name of mountains but the  <sic>the</sic>
               <choice>
                  <orig>higest</orig>
                  <reg>highest</reg>
               </choice> of them will not much excuse that above mentioned. Altogether Lancaster is one of the most beautiful portions of our beautiful country that I have seen it is justly called the garden of America. The population is very dense, the county alone constitutes a congressional district, and after the census if the apportionment was not changed would have to spare about one third of its number to another district. It is also <choice>
                  <orig>wealthies</orig>
                  <reg>wealthiest</reg>
               </choice> agricultural district in the <name>United States</name> with all <sic>all</sic> these advantages, however the people are the most illiteral that it has been my lot to meet with. I was <choice>
                  <orig>verry </orig>
                  <reg>very</reg>
               </choice> soon disgusted with them and on the sixth of July left there with the sincere hope that if I ever see it again, it may be on my way to some other place. From Lancaster I went to <choice>
                  <abbr>Balt</abbr>
                  <expan>Baltimore</expan>
               </choice>. where I spent the Sabbath, and the next day went on to <name>Washington</name> after attending to some business <pb n="3" facs="sc234c.small.jpg"/> I left there on the ninth and the same evening after an absence of nearly eleven months I reached home. I staid from the ninth to the twenty second with my parents and sisters and at that time started for this place. You will no doubt be surprised to hear that I am still in the service of the <unclear>monument</unclear>, as you heard me express myself so strongly against the service last fall. The Board being anxious to retain me however, I have taken the tenth district of this state, and shall probably, for the purpose of spending the winter in the south take the <name>Savannah</name> district in <name>Georgia</name>.  If I should do so, and I think there is not much doubt that I shall, I promise myself the pleasure of a visit to Jerusalem in the spring. My trip to Wheeling, and down the <name>Ohio </name>on <name>Mississippi </name>was verry <choice>
                  <orig>fatigueing</orig>
                  <reg>fatiguing</reg>
               </choice>. At Wheeling I saw some of my old friends and spent the short time I staid there quite pleasantly. Once on the river my toil began, the river was so low that it was impossible to see over the banks, and before we got to <name>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Cincinnatti</orig>
                     <reg>Cincinnati</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> I was quite sick, and continued so till we reached <name>cairo</name> at the mouth of the Ohio. In consequence of my sickness I had no chance to look about the cities of Cincinnatti and <name>Louisville</name> or any of the towns on the river. I have never been on any river the banks of which ever as devoid interest as the Mississippi that portion of it which I saw is remarkable for nothing but its verry muddy water. You may form some idea of it by looking into a pig sty (one that has no floor) after a rain of a weeks continuance; it will not be more muddy than the father of waters. <pb n="4" facs="sc234d.small.jpg"/> Please present my regards to Mrs. Rochelle Mrs. Tyler and <unclear>all hey ms.</unclear> Tell Mrs Tyler that I hope to make amends in the spring for not calling on my return last May and I hope to make due her and her little blossoms in the enjoyment of health and every other blessings which they so sickly deserve. My Mother and sisters were so glad to see that they forgot to scold me about the Charleston joke.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Verry Respectfully and Sincerely Your friend </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Daniel Douglass</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <name>Miss Sarah J. Armstrong</name>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name>Jerusalem </name>
                        <name>Virginia</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
