<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="gc011">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1829 May 13, Cropland [to] Issac Butler, Murfreesborough, Tennessee / John Butler: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Butler, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harding</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>gc011</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1829 May 13, Cropland [to] Issac Butler, Murfreesborough, Tennessee / John Butler</title>
               <author>Butler, John</author>
               <date when="1829-05-13">May 13, 1829</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated may 13, 1829 from John Butler to his father Issac Butler.  He expresses wishes of well-being for his father, and a desire to hear from him soon.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">James Moore King papers Correspondence 1829</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">gc011</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Butler, John</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="gc011a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <name type="place">Alexandria  <choice>
                     <abbr>La</abbr>
                     <expan>Louisiana</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>
               <date when="1829-05-11">may 11th</date>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Capt</abbr>
                        <expan>Captain</expan>
                     </choice> Issac Butler Murfreesborough Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>  From <name type="person">John W. Butler</name> — 1829  <add place="top right of center ">25</add>
               <add place="Bottom of center envelope">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>mal</orig>
                     <reg>mail</reg>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="gc011b.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Cropland</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date when="1829-05-11">May 13th 1829</date>
            </opener>
            <salute>Dear Father</salute>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Whar</orig>
                  <reg>What</reg>
               </choice> an <choice>
                  <orig>unuterable</orig>
                  <reg>unutterable</reg>
               </choice> pleasure <choice>
                  <orig>whould</orig>
                  <reg>would</reg>
               </choice> it be to me, if I could say that my pen was now grasped to answer a fond letter from you assuring a far <choice>
                  <orig>aistant</orig>
                  <reg>assistant</reg>
               </choice> but affectionate son that all were well, or that fortune had not blessed you with good health; for it is better to learn within than remain for months in a state of entire <choice>
                  <orig>suspence</orig>
                  <reg>suspense</reg>
               </choice>; of ace the evils to which the mind of man is addicted there are <unclear>more</unclear> so tormenting, so insupportable as that of deep and <choice>
                  <orig>unatterable</orig>
                  <reg>unutterable</reg>
               </choice> suspence; and that too which could be mentioned by the recitation of thee words all are well</p>
            <p>I returned to this place from <name type="place">New Orleans</name> on yesterday a few days before my departure for that place I added you a letter to sister, from <choice>
                  <orig>whome</orig>
                  <reg>whom</reg>
               </choice> I fondly hoped on my return to have receive an answer to some of my previous letters in this and <choice>
                  <orig>excitment</orig>
                  <reg>excitement</reg>
               </choice> has <choice>
                  <orig>succeded</orig>
                  <reg>succeeded</reg>
               </choice>. </p>
            <p>Not knowing at that time what regular course would be adopted as to my future movements; nothing was said </p>
            <p>Lover I have abandoned steam boating, because it is a pursuit or occupation entirely too precarious and unskilled for a young man to make any calculations as to the profits of less <choice>
                  <orig>labour</orig>
                  <reg>labor</reg>
               </choice>; for he is at all times subject to lapes which perhaps would in one day <choice>
                  <orig>occurance</orig>
                  <reg>occurrence</reg>
               </choice>  that he had <choice>
                  <orig>occumulated</orig>
                  <reg>accumulated</reg>
               </choice> in a month.</p>
            <p>I have formed a resolution to <choice>
                  <orig>commense</orig>
                  <reg>commence</reg>
               </choice> at the sunday of neudi-cine which I can do with  every possible advantage, and with but <pb n="3" facs="gc011c.small.jpg"/> a small expense.   I think that with my capital I will enabled to attend a regular course of Lectures; though economy must be observed, I will need about 18 months there and then go on to  <name>Lexington</name> or <name>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Cincinate</orig>
                     <reg>Cincinatti</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name>
            </p>
            <p>Uncle W will leave this for the north in the course of ten or fifteen days, we continue plates on spending this Summer at the <name>White Sulpher Springs</name> in <name>Virginia</name>; which he thinks will be of material advantages to his complaint, he has written the last three months  been at the point of what  service times with the Rheumatism combined with the gout, his family will company service.</p>
            <p>Thomas is still at <name>Hynsons</name> his health is good, he is getting along  I think very well; and there is but little doubt but that he will with his present economy accumulate a handsome property in a few years, he had been badly treated with respect to his Legacy, has not as yet received it in full, he has judge Overtons note for 200  dollars, has <choice>
                  <orig>recived</orig>
                  <reg>received</reg>
               </choice> a share from Hydor and drew a draft on <name>Henry Overton</name> a few days ago for the valance, He has become much attached to this country and with it Avanier incolales.</p>
            <p>Cousin Thomas is still on <name>Cropland</name>, his health at the is not very good at this time, he complains of a pain in his side &amp; the back ache, the fore runners of old age</p>
            <p>It was with much astonishment that shares the condice of your ex governor, who I think had vilified and disgraced himself in the eyes of the whole humane race, I am all most ashamed to hail from a state, whose <choice>
                  <orig>Govenor</orig>
                  <reg>Governor</reg>
               </choice> has thus <unclear>bereaved </unclear> himself and the State <pb n="4" facs="gc011d.small.jpg"/> Rupieve is getting quite sickly on account of the unusually cold weather, Spring is later this season than it has been known for many years, Planters have generally a poor stave of cotton.</p>
            <p>I have nothing more worth your attention except it is that you will give me an answer to this as soon as possible, I had the promise of letter from <name>W.O. Moore</name> on his return to <name>Tennessee</name>, but have not as yet been <choice>
                  <orig>favoured</orig>
                  <reg>favored</reg>
               </choice> with it.</p>
            <p>Present me respectfully to Mother, sister <choice>
                  <abbr>Capt</abbr>
                  <expan>Captain</expan>
               </choice> King, Lady, Children and to all my enquiring friends and accept for yourself the <unclear>filiae</unclear> affection of a dutiful son</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Butler</signed>
               <add>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Capt</abbr>
                        <expan>Captain</expan>
                     </choice> Isacc Butler </name>PS. direct yours to <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Alexd</abbr>
                        <expan>Alexandria</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>
                  <name>J.W. Butler</name>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
