<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl195">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1829 Mar. 17, Columbia, Tennessee [to] John Overton, Nashville, Tennessee / T. H. Cahal    : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Cahal, T. H.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl195</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51196495</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1829 Mar. 17, Columbia, Tennessee [to] John Overton, Nashville, Tennessee / T. H. Cahal    </title>
               <author>Cahal, T. H. </author>
               <date when="1829-03-17">March 17, 1829</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated March 17, 1829 to John Overton from T. H. Cahal regarding the purchase of mules.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">4</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl195</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Mules</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Cahal, T. H.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl195a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia</name>
                     <date when="1829-03-17">March 17. 29.</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your kind <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice> of the 26th ultimo came to hand on the 4th instant. Since its reception, I have been assiduous in my endeavors to procure for you such mules as you described. I have found its a matter of no small difficulty to get such as would answer your purpose. Your information of a considerable number being raised in this county, I believe, is correct; but the number, at this time, in market, is small &amp; great many have, in the course of the past <del type="overstrike">fall</del> autumn ⁁ <add place="supralinear">and winter</add>  been driven off, to supply the demand in the south. On saturday last, I made a condition⁁ <add place="supralinear">al</add> purchase <pb n="2" facs="sl195b.small.jpg"/> of the only two yet found to suit your description. I think it would be well for <name type="person">Mr. Woods</name> , if he can be spared from your farm, to come out, and see if they will answer. One of them is a horse two years old in May; the other a mare two years old in August. They have last winter been worked some little in a cotton gin, and appear to disadvantage, as they are rather lean. You can get them ⁁ <add place="supralinear">both</add> for sixty five dollars in cash. You are aware, I can't know much about the value of mules, or I would say, I think them a good bargain. I got competent judges to examine them, who corroborated my opinion. <name type="person">Mr Booker</name>, whom you know to be one of the closest and hardest dealers in the world, and who is, at this time, buying himself, says <pb n="3" facs="sl195c.small.jpg"/> they are worth the money. <name type="person">Mr. Badget</name>, (the owner) who is but a youth and knows too little of the world to commence lying for <del type="overstrike">the</del> mere speculation, tells me they came out of pretty good mares, and that <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Capt.</abbr>
                     <expan>Captain</expan>
                  </choice> Peters</name> has offered him $80. for them on a credit till christmas.</p>
            <p>He has agreed to keep them till I could hear from you. His residence ⁁ <add place="supralinear">is</add> seven miles below town, on the north side of the river. You can send immediately to his house, or to Columbia and I will go down.</p>
            <p>It will always afford me great pleasure to render you assistance, in any business I am capable of performing.</p>
            <p>Present ⁁ <add place="supralinear">me</add> to Mrs. O. — and accept for yourself assurances of the highest respect from</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your most <choice>
                     <abbr>obt servt</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">T. H. Cahal</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Hon.</abbr>
                           <expan>Honorable</expan>
                        </choice> John Overton.</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl195d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Columbia <choice>
                        <abbr>T</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Mch</abbr>
                     <expan>March</expan>
                  </choice> 17</date>
               <add place="right of address">10</add>
               <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Hon</abbr>
                     <expan>Honorable</expan>
                  </choice> John Overton</name>
               <address>
                  <addrLine> mail }<name type="place">Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>T.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="side of address">T. H. Cahal <lb/> Mar 17 1829 <lb/>  Respecting purchase of mules</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
