<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl407">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1849 Oct. 19, Trenton, Tennessee [to] Isaac B Williams / James M Moore   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Moore, James M</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl407</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1849 Oct. 19, Trenton, Tennessee [to] Isaac B Williams / James M Moore</title>
               <author>Moore, James M</author>
               <date when="1849-10-19">October 19, 1849</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated October 19, 1849 from James M. Moore to Isaac B. Williams.  In the letter, Moore consoles Williams over his defeat in an election while verbally chastising the political system that facilitated his demise.  Moore denounces the corrupt, and secretive methods of the power brokers who control elections, and favors giving power to the people through democracy.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fitzgerald - Williams - Greer Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">15</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl407</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Elections</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Moore, James M</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl407a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Trenton <choice>
                        <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Octr</abbr>
                     <expan>October</expan>
                  </choice> 19th 1849</date>Isaac B. Williams <choice>
                  <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                  <expan>Esquire</expan>
               </choice> . <salute> My Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have just travelled from the <choice>
                  <abbr>P.O</abbr>
                  <expan>Post</expan>
               </choice> office and taken my coffee (supper) and now sit down in my office -.  the <name>Nashville</name> mail came in on this morning, which informed us of your defeat. I dont know when I have been so much out of humor and so profoundly disgusted -. God forbid that you should let it effect your mind any more than the smallest storm would in comparison affect the physical system -.  Blot it out and go straight forward never Taking so much as a second thought about it -. The fellows, yes the fellows have done what they could to shake &amp; <unclear>jeopard</unclear> a great &amp; vital interest of this community, wherein, It is to be feared, they have but too well succeeded, and at the same time endeavored to prostrate you -. I congratulate you my friend, that, you stand beyond the reach of that Kennel when not even so much as their yelping &amp; whining may be heard by you, to remind you of their existence.  I am out of humor my friend -. how long yet, ah how long, before God will give to the children of men, pure hearts &amp; clean hands. well I am discouraged and disgusted at some parts of the workings of our Political machinery -.  I believe I feel  prepared now to take power from irresponsible &amp; filthy hands,  and give it directly to the people -. again I repeat, look not neither to the right or left, nor even behind you but go forward <pb n="2" facs="sl407b.small.jpg"/> If I am not mistaken this deed will be considered before another tribunal, that will give your interests and impetus, that will be beyond the power of our irresponsible and depraved legislative Body to control - sir, I am ashamed of this Political Party to which I belong, in this Thing.  If I knew where to go, I should run -.   But unfortunately for the Country both parties are too much given to this unholy vocation -.  I shall never cease, upon all suitable occasions, to denounce it &amp; the men concerned in it. with my power &amp; league, to all men -. now you remember, that, I was, once upon a time upon a similar mission - upon that occasion, I had such an insight into this accusive system of Bargain &amp; sale, in league and Corruption, as will last me through life -. well here we go my <choice>
                  <orig>frind</orig>
                  <reg>friend</reg>
               </choice>, on the voyage of <gap agent="damage"/> life Independent alike, of Combination &amp; <choice>
                  <orig>eliquence</orig>
                  <reg>eloquence</reg>
               </choice>. the world cant kill us - we are all to live in spite of This If God before us, It matters not who is against us - well; I shall always believe this, That, God is in <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice> of an honest man who shall in due time receive his reward - so cheer up; And let our motto be Onwards, Onwards Good night -</p>
            <closer>Your friend <signed>James M Moore</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
