<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um084">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1842 Dec. 29,    Columbia, Tennessee [to] Col[onel] Robert J. Chester, Jackson, Tennessee / M[ary] J[ane] Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um084</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50317016</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1842 Dec. 29,    Columbia, Tennessee [to] Col[onel] Robert J. Chester, Jackson, Tennessee / M[ary] J[ane] Chester</title>
               <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
               <date when="1842-12-29">December 29, 1842</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by Mary Jane Chester to her father, Robert J. Chester, on December 29, 1842. In the letter, Mary Jane discusses her examination in January and her hopes that some of her family will be there for it. She also mentions to her father that the rumors regarding her engagement to an unnamed man are unfounded. She concludes the letter by expressing love to her family and asking her father to burn the letter once he had read it, which he obviously did not do.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers MS 25 (January-December 1842)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">10</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um084</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Mary Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um084a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1842-12-29">December 29th 42</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Papa,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I am happy to hear from your kind letter that all the dear children were so much better.</p>
            <p>I suffered great uneasiness and anxiety about them   <choice>
                  <sic>until until</sic>
                  <corr>until</corr>
               </choice> I received your last, indeed you cannot imagine how sincerely I have wished to be at home so that I could assist you and <name type="person">Aunt Narcissa</name> in nursing them. I hope that <name type="person">King</name> &amp; <name type="person">Will</name> will not have a severe spell.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Mr Smith</name> was so kind as to give us this christmas, a weeks <choice>
                  <orig>holyday</orig>
                  <reg>holiday</reg>
               </choice>. I have employed my time in writing my Examination Composition. I <choice>
                  <orig>attented</orig>
                  <reg>attended</reg>
               </choice> a party at <name type="person">Aunt Walkers</name> on Monday evening, enjoyed myself very much. It does not seem to be a Merry Christmas with any one. <name type="person">Alice Bennis</name> has been at Aunt Walkers all week. she seem to be very well contented now.</p>
            <p>Dear Papa You dont know how much distressed I am to hear that you entertain any doubt concerning the subject which you mentioned in your letter. I had thought that I said <choice>
                  <orig>eneough</orig>
                  <reg>enough</reg>
               </choice> to convince you that it was <emph>not so</emph>, I am <pb n="2" facs="um084b.small.jpg"/>
               <choice>
                  <orig>greived</orig>
                  <reg>grieved</reg>
               </choice> to hear that my name should be mentioned in <choice>
                  <orig>connextion</orig>
                  <reg>connection</reg>
               </choice> with his. I tell you candidly that there is no foundation for such reports. he has never even mentioned the subject to me, and I cant imagine what it was taken from, but why waste words about it; as I hope that you are convinced now. I know that it was perfectly natural that you should ask me about it and also perfectly right; <choice>
                  <orig>Beleive</orig>
                  <reg>Believe</reg>
               </choice> me, you need never fear that I will make any engagements without your knowledge and consent or at least that is what I think now. I hope now that you will rest satisfied upon that head.</p>
            <p>I shall expect you up to the Examination in January, and will study very hard, to do justice both to myself and you. I should be delighted if you could bring Sister up with you, if you cannot come please let <name type="person">Brother John</name>, for I shall be much better satisfied if some one of you are here. Tell <name type="person">Aunt Narcissa</name> that I am anxious to receive an answer to my last letter. I should be pleased to receive a letter from Sister and my two Brothers. but I know it is useless to ask them.</p>
            <p>Give my <emph>Best</emph> love to Aunt <choice>
                  <abbr>N.</abbr>
                  <expan>Narcissa</expan>
               </choice> and all my relations. Kiss my dear little Brothers and sister, and all the children for me. Please Papa dont let any one see this letter. Burn it as soon as you get it.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Ever affectionately</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>M. J.</abbr>
                        <expan>Mary Jane</expan>
                     </choice> Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="um084c.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="above address">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>post mark seal</figDesc>
                  </figure> 18</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Col</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel</expan>
                        </choice> Robert J. Chester</name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson</name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address, upside down" rend="different hand, ink">My Dear Mary Jane <lb/>
                  <date when="1842-12-29">29 <choice>
                        <abbr>Decr</abbr>
                        <expan>December</expan>
                     </choice> 1842</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
