<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl381">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1836 Aug. 10, Head Quarters West Depart[ment], Camp Sabine, To Brig[adier] Gen[era]l Arbuckle, Fort Gibson, Ark[ansa]s /  E[dmund] P. Gaines: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Gaines, Edmund P.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl381</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1836 Aug. 10, Head Quarters West Depart[ment], Camp Sabine, To Brig[adier] Gen[era]l Arbuckle, Fort Gibson, Ark[ansa]s /  E[dmund] P. Gaines</title>
               <author>Gaines, Edmund P.</author>
               <date when="1836-08-10">August 10, 1836</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated August 10, 1836, written by Edmund Pendleton Gaines, commander of the US Army Western Division, to General Arbuckle at Fort Gibson, Arkansas.  Gaines reports of hostility perceived  and expected from Native American tribes in Texas, who were allying with the Mexican army during its war against Texas.  He talks specifically about the Cherokees, led by Chief Bowl, who had been pushed west into Texas, and the Caddoes.  Gaines also discusses the fate of Mexican leader Santa Anna, and he  commends Arbuckle on his ordering of troops from Missouri and Arkansas to protect frontier settlers from possible Native American attacks.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Gaines Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">I-C-3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl381</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Texas--History--Revolution, 1835-1836</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Wars</term>
               <term>Caddoan Indians--Wars</term>
               <term>Gaines, Edmund Pendleton, 1777-1849 Correspondence.</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n88277194"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Gaines, Edmund Pendleton, 1777-1849</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl381a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Head Quarters  <choice>
                        <abbr>West. Depart.</abbr>
                        <expan>Western Department</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Camp <name>Sabine</name>
                     <date>August 10th 1836</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>General</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have received your communication of the 21st of last month, with the enclosures <choice>
                  <orig>refered</orig>
                  <reg>referred</reg>
               </choice> to, and which <choice>
                  <orig>preceeded</orig>
                  <reg>preceded</reg>
               </choice> the mail.  They were handed to me last night by <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Lieut.</abbr>
                     <expan>Lieutenant</expan>
                  </choice> Paul</name>.</p>
            <p>A favorable change in the health of <name>Mrs Gaines</name>, added to new indications of hostility among the Indians in and West of the disputed Territory induced me to remain here, until your duties with the Indians of the West would allow you to visit this place of <name>Nacogdoches</name>.</p>
            <p>I have received information the truth of which I cannot doubt, that many tribes of the Indians of <name>Texas</name>, and of our side of the unmarked but supposed boundary, have been engaged by the authorities of <name>Mexico</name> to aid in the war extermination against Texas.</p>
            <p>I have proof that the <name>Cherokees</name> under <name>Bowl</name> with the <name>Caddoes</name> have been so engaged.  The Caddoes are reported to have 400 Warriors,- Bowl's  Cherokees are estimated at less than 150.  These tribes though not numerous are capable of being very formidable by their perfect knowledge of this country, by which they would have it in their power to lead the more westerly and northerly tribes into every settlement, and to every house on our side of the line, and as far as the <name>Red River</name>, from <name>Alexandria</name> to <name>Fort Towson</name>, and throughout the disputed Territory._</p>
            <p>I have had reason to calculate on hostilities being commenced as soon as the Corn got ripe enough to eat- or as soon as the Mexican Army shall approach the remaining settlements of Texas- which are principally on this side of the <name>Brazos</name>.-</p>
            <p>The Mexican Army was however still at <name>Matomoras</name> on the <pb n="2" facs="sl381b.small.jpg"/> 16th of last Month_ held in check probably by the supposed determination on the part of the Texans to hold the life of <name>Santa Anna</name> answerable for the movement of the Mexican forces operating against Texas.  But should this be the cause of the suspended movements of the Mexican Army, it is certainly a cause that cannot long be relied on.  Mexico may very soon order the new Commander to prosecute the War regardless of the fate of Santa Anna, as they have already reprimanded their <name>General Filasola</name> for <choice>
                  <orig>retireing</orig>
                  <reg>retiring</reg>
               </choice> from Texas at the request of Santa Anna, after the battle of <name>San Jacinto</name>; and they have decreed that any act of Santa Anna while a prisoner of war shall be null and void.  Besides the death of Santa Anna by sickness, accident, or otherwise, or his escape will be the signal for vigorous operations on the part of the Mexicans, and that the Indians will co-operate with them I have no doubt.</p>
            <p>Hence it is that I have deemed it necessary and proper to have the Dragoons, and the Six Companies of the 7th Infantry held in readiness for action upon the Nacogdoches frontier. Should the Indians or any other force attempt to disturb the inhabitants,- The disputed Territory here will be the principal theatre of War. The want of an effective force here will endanger the whole of the beautiful and immensely valuable cotton growing region of Red River,   from Alexandria to the great raft, and from thence to Fort Towson.- The first mentioned settlement is one  the destruction of which would involve in ruin hundreds of worthy and excellent families, with Millions of dollars worth of property._ The prospect of the plunder of which would tend powerfully to excite the cupidity of many men who have pretensions to <choice>
                  <orig>civillization</orig>
                  <reg>civilization</reg>
               </choice> , - and tempt them to assume the Garb and character of Savages, and accompany the real Indians on <pb n="3" facs="sl381c.small.jpg"/> such a crusade, under the <choice>
                  <orig>pretence</orig>
                  <reg>pretense</reg>
               </choice> of liberating the ______ as suggested by Santa Anna.- but in reality to kill and plunder their owners.-</p>
            <p>You ask me the very appropriate question whether the troops are to be called to the frontier before the commencement of hostilities?  I answer in the language of a letter which I some time past addressed to the Secretary of War.- "I think it is our duty to afford the frontier inhabitants that "sort of protection guaranteed by the Constitution of the United "States- the whole people including the Pioneer, his widow, "or orphan inhabitant of the frontier Camp, or Cabin, as well "as the Wealthy citizens of the great emporium of Politics and of "fashion_ the Protection the work of which should commence before the work of destruction upon the frontier has begun: Protection to the living citizens rather than the the ashes of the slain."</p>
            <p>You did right therefore to call for <name>Arkansas</name> troops, and the sooner you can have them ready for efficient service at <name>Gibson</name> the better.</p>
            <p>I shall immediately request the Governor of the State of <name>Missouri</name> to furnish One thousand men- one half mounted- and shall desire <name>General Atkinson</name> to place the half of this force at <name>Leavenworth</name> and you the other half Gibson,- or if they should not be needed there they will be ordered to Towson.- <choice>
                  <abbr>Viz</abbr>
                  <expan>videlicet</expan>
               </choice> 250 Mounted men and 250 Infantry at Leavenworth and a like number at Gibson.</p>
            <p>Without this force called out soon, added to all that you and I have recently called for, we cannot say truly that we are prepared to afford to this most important and very  <pb n="4" facs="sl381d.small.jpg"/> slender frontier that protection of which I have been speaking whilst 10,000 to 15,000 troops backed by 6 to 10,000 Indians are employed in a war of extermination near us.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>With great Respect <choice>
                     <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                     <expan>et cetera</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>(Signed) <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>E. P.</abbr>
                        <expan>Edmund Pendleton</expan>
                     </choice>  Gaines</name>
               </signed>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Maj. Genl.</abbr>
                     <expan>Major General</expan>
                  </choice> Commanding</signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Brigr. Genl.</abbr>
                           <expan>Brigadier General</expan>
                        </choice> Arbuckle</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Command. &amp;c</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Fort Gibson</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Arks.</abbr>
                        <expan>Arkansas</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>No.</abbr>
                     <expan>Number</expan>
                  </choice> 3. <lb/> Major General E. P. Gaines <lb/> to <lb/> Brg. Genl. M. Arbuckle <lb/> dated 10th August 1836</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
