<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl741">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1797 Jan. 7, Knoxville, Tennessee [to] Members of Congress / John Sevier : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Sevier, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl741</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1797 Jan. 7, Knoxville, Tennessee [to] Members of Congress / John Sevier</title>
               <author> Sevier, John</author>
               <date when="1797-01-07">January 7, 1797</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated the 7th of January, 1797 from governor  John Sevier of Tennessee to members of Congress.  In the Letter, Sevier informs the statesmen of supposed plundering of several wagons by Cherokee Indians while in route to the Cumberland plateau.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor John Sevier Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl741</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Sevier, John, 1745-1815 Correspondence.</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Claims against</term>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor (1796-1801 : Sevier)</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr89016779"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Sevier, John, 1745-1815</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl741a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Knoxville</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>7 January 1797</date>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Since my last nothing of material moments excepting that Several <choice>
                  <orig>waggons</orig>
                  <reg>wagons</reg>
               </choice> on the road through the wilderness to <name>Cumberland</name> have been plundered by the indians <del>supposed to be the cherokees</del> , and some of them left without a horse, Supposed to be done by the Cherokees.</p>
            <p>The agent to the cherokees has complained about Settlements being made as low down as the <name>tennessee</name>, on which Subject I to him replied, a copy of which is <del>here</del>    inclosed for your information, should any thing or that head be <del>brought</del>
               <add>sent</add>    forward   to the department of war.  It will elucidate in some measure the circumstances attending the matter, and you will take such measures in your wisdom will best promote the interest of this state  I wish the line could be extended to the Tennessee.</p>
            <p>It has for some time past been reported that one Indian was killed, and another wounded, on the waters of clinch; I hope the report is not true, and I am induced so to believe from this reason, that neither the indians nor agent have complained to me on the Occasion.</p>
            <p>Our port <add>was</add> has several times been disappointed in meeting with and receiving in order the mail at <name>abingdon</name>, which neglect may prove very injurious to us.  A letter from the department of <pb n="2" facs="sl741b.small.jpg"/>
               <sic>of</sic>     war to the executive of this state, Dated 13 august last only arrived here on the 11th instant, brought by <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice>. <name>John Deadrick</name> from Cumberland, Another from same department dated 29 September came by our port   a few days before.    How these irregularities happen I am at a loss to know.  It is not the first time my letters Directed to me at this place from <name>philadelphia</name>, has went round by the way of  Cumberland and some of them came forward with a broken seal.  </p>
            <p>I hope you will <add>please</add>   acquaint the port Master General of such Irregularities, in order <add>that</add>    the defect may be <choice>
                  <orig>remidied</orig>
                  <reg>remedied</reg>
               </choice>.     Captain Wade and Spark's companies have arrived <del>here</del>    neither of them <choice>
                  <orig>complet</orig>
                  <reg>complete</reg>
               </choice>,  I hope if no more is sent, these will be inadequate to the protection of our frontiers, and the defect ought to be Supplied by militia.  more companies of Infantry and a troop of    <unclear>horses went on west</unclear>    the purpose, on which I have wrote the Secretary of war</p>
            <closer>
               <add>I have the honor to be &amp; Signed</add>
               <signed>
                  <name>J. Sevier</name>
               </signed>
               <add>to each of <del>He</del>    our Members in Congress <lb/> Letter to the members in Congress <date>7th January 1797</date>
                  <lb/> Recorded</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
