<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc176">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Legal document] 1801 May 4, Tennessee, Affidavit of Samuel Barton / Andrew Jackson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Jackson, Andrew</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc176</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Legal document] 1801 May 4, Tennessee, Affidavit of Samuel Barton / Andrew Jackson</title>
               <author>Jackson, Andrew</author>
               <date when="1801-05-04"> 
			 May 4, 1801</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is the affidavit of Samuel Barton dated May 4, 1801. It is witnessed and signed by Andrew Jackson who also writes a petition for writs of Certiorari and Supersedeas on behalf of Barton. Barton accuses Andrew McCasland of wrongfully claiming some of his land while Barton was being held in a Mero prison, for which Barton also blames Moses Akels. Barton also accuses William Allen of impersonating a deputy sheriff.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Andrew Jackson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS 366</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc176</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</term>
               <term>Legal document</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79088888"
                        role="Autographer http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ato">Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc176a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <add>
                  <name>Moses Akels</name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>vs</abbr>
                     <expan>versus</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <name>Samuel Barton</name>
               </add>
            </opener>
            <p>Samuel Barton maketh Oath that some time in year seventeen hundred and ninety nine he was arrested under the authority of a Federal Court Writ at the instance of a certain <name>William Hay</name> of the State of <name>Virginia</name> and <name>Wythe County</name>, and for the want of bail was confined in the District Jail of <name>Mero</name> for a considerable length of time; during which time of confinement, the said Moses Akels sued out an Original Writ against the said Samuel which Writ was returned by the sheriff of <name>Sumner County</name> to the Court of said County not found at July term one thousand seven hundred and ninety nine, in <choice>
                  <orig>consiquence</orig>
                  <reg>consequence</reg>
               </choice> of which return a motion at the said term was made for a Judicial attachment to issue against the estate of the said Samuel which was granted and said attachment levied on a part of the goods of your <choice>
                  <orig>deponant</orig>
                  <reg>deponent</reg>
               </choice> whilst in Jail as above stated, by a certain <name>William Allen</name> who called himself Deputy Sheriff without ever having taken the oath of a deputy sheriff as the law directs, and in consequence of which levying a Judgement was obtained at January term Eighteen hundred for six hundred and eighty nine Dollars and from said January Term an order of sale issued commanding the sheriff of sumner County to expose to sale the property <pb n="2" facs="sc176b.small.jpg"/> property attached to say satisfy said Judgement and cost of suit which property as appears by the sheriff returns <add>sold</add> for the sum of one Dollar, Your deponant further states that he is informed and verily believes that the said Moses Akels has caused an alias fieri facias to issue against the property of your deponant and is at this time in the hands of the Sheriff of County; your deponant further states that the grounds of the above stated suit, is as followers, your deponant sold to the said Moses Akels six hundred and twenty acres of land known by the name of the Pond tract on <name>Bartons Creek</name> of which the said Moses Akels had possession, your deponant further states that a certain <name>Andrew McCasland</name> set up claim to part of the said Acres and caused a writ of Ejectment to be served on the tenant in possession and the said Moses Akels quit claim without ever trying titles with the said Andrew McCasland or ever giving your deponant notice of such a suit having been commenced against him whereas your deponant do humbly conceive that if notice had been given him and no <choice>
                  <orig>acquitance</orig>
                  <reg>acquittance</reg>
               </choice> of the claim to the said disputed land to the said Andrew McCasland he could have supported the title of said land</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Saml</abbr>
                     <expan>Samuel</expan>
                  </choice> Barton</signed>
               <add>State of Tennessee <lb/> on this <date>4th day of May 1801</date> personally</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sc176c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Personally came Samuel Barton before me <name>Andrew Jackson</name> one of the Judges of the superior Courts of law and Equity for the state aforesaid and made oath that the matters &amp; things set forth in the proceeding  affidavit as of his own Knowledge are true and those set forth as <unclear>that</unclear> of his own__ Knowledge he believers to be true Sworn to &amp; Subscribed the day &amp; date before mentioned before me</add>
               <signed>Saml Barton</signed>
               <signed>Andrew Jackson</signed>
               <add>To the Honourable the Judges of the superior Court of law and equity held for the District of Mero in the State of Tennessee; The petition of Samuel Barton Humbly pray that on an examination of the <choice>
                     <orig>anexed</orig>
                     <reg>annexed</reg>
                  </choice>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>affidavet</orig>
                     <reg>affidavit</reg>
                  </choice> your Honour will direct writs of certiorari and <choice>
                     <orig>Supercedias</orig>
                     <reg>Supersedeas</reg>
                  </choice> to issue  in such a manner as that the proceedings had in the County Court of Sumner as set forth in the anexed affidavet may come before this Honorable Court so that Justice may be done your petitioner according to the Justice of your petitioners case <gap/> agreeable to the law in such case made and provided and your petitioner in duty bound will ever pray <choice>
                     <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                     <expan>etcetera</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <signed>Saml Barton</signed>
               <add>Set writs of Certiorari and Superseadea issue <choice>
                     <orig>agreable</orig>
                     <reg>agreeable</reg>
                  </choice> to the prayer of the Petitioner</add>
               <signed>Andrew Jackson</signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sc176d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Saml Barton <lb/> } Moses Akels <lb/> Petition for <choice>
                     <abbr>Cer.</abbr>
                     <expan>Certiorari</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/> &amp; <choice>
                     <abbr>Sup.</abbr>
                     <expan>Supersedeas</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <add>Affidavet &amp; petition of Saml Barton</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
