<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl368">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1818 Sep. 20, Hendersonville, T[ennessee] [to] Andrew J[ackson] Donelson, West Point, New York / Daniel S. Donelson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Donelson, Daniel S.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl368</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1818 Sep. 20, Hendersonville, T[ennessee] [to] Andrew J[ackson] Donelson, West Point, New York / Daniel S. Donelson </title>
               <author>Donelson, Daniel S.</author>
               <date when="1818-09-20">September 20, 1818</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter, dated September 20, 1818, from Daniel Donelson to his brother Andrew Jackson Donelson at West Point academy.  Daniel writes about the death of their grandfather, and he discusses how proud the family is of Andrew's performance in school.  Daniel also updates his brother on other family news, included the illness of their uncle Severn Jackson, and an upcoming Indian treaty involving another uncle, Andrew Jackson.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bettie M. Donelson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> III-E-2-3 b1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">4</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl368</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee, Middle</term>
               <term>Stressful life events</term>
               <term>School and continuing education</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Donelson, Daniel S.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl368a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>September 20th <add>1818</add>
                     </date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have <choice>
                  <orig>recieved</orig>
                  <reg>received</reg>
               </choice> your affectionate letter dated <date>August 12th</date> and with a sense of thankfulness write you that you may welcome it as cordially as I did yours.  I have already informed you <add>of</add> Grandfathers death, and the pain he suffered before his departure.  He has gone from our sight but his memory lives, <choice>
                  <orig>lit</orig>
                  <reg>let</reg>
               </choice> us be mindful of him, and mark his steps as long as we may enjoy life this world.  Your advice to me concerning our Grandfathers rules and regularities are remarkably good and quite interes<add>ting</add> It is my sincere wish that we may never be so delighted with the follies and vices of the world as not to pursue Grandfathers instructions and advice The time is approaching brother we will have to  transact all the varieties and turns of life within ourselves and by our own assistance.  Our principal guide is gone; that is Grandfather he is no longer alive to aid and assist through the <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>amiguous</orig>
                     <reg>ambiguous</reg>
                  </choice>
               </unclear> courses of life. I was very much rejoiced <del type="overstrike">your</del> when I recieved your letter to hear of your <pb n="2" facs="sl368b.small.jpg"/> good health, and the progress that you have made in study since your departure is very considerable It is quite pleasing to me and all the rest of your friends.  I was extremely glad to hear also what an admirable examination you bore the last session, and the idea of your being second in your class which is <choice>
                  <orig>comosed</orig>
                  <reg>composed</reg>
               </choice> of 70 or 80 cadets is quite entertaining to me I still continue to go to school to Mr <unclear>Mc Wright</unclear> and am reading <name>homer</name> and <name>blair</name>s <choice>
                  <orig>lecturs</orig>
                  <reg>lectures</reg>
               </choice> . There is a probability that I will go some college next session.  Uncle <name>Severn Donelson</name> is very ill with the dropsy and it is the thought by the Doctor that he cannot recover.  Uncle Jackson starts to day to hold treaty with the indians he is not very well.  Aunt and all the rest are <add>in</add> tolerable good health.  Mother is well but very anxious that you would return home <add>a</add>gain <name>Mr Sanders</name> and the rest of the family is well.  Grandmother has been in a low state of health all summer but she is something better present.  <name>Mr Lafayette Sanders</name> and cousin Mary is staying with her mom but they design moving to <name>Gallatin</name> next month</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="sl368c.small.jpg"/>
            <p> Uncle <name>geare Smith</name> and Aunt are both very well.  I have generally enjoyed my health very well.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am your loving and affectionate brother</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Daniel S Donelson</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Mr Andrew <choice>
                           <abbr>J</abbr>
                           <expan>Jackson</expan>
                        </choice> Donelson</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl368d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <name>Hendersonville <choice>
                        <abbr>T</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Sep.</abbr>
                        <expan>September</expan>
                     </choice> 23</name>
               </add>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>D.</abbr>
                     <expan>Daniel</expan>
                  </choice> S. Donelson</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mr Andrew J Donelson</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>West Point</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>State of <name>New York</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>mail</add>
               <add>Received <date>13th october 1818</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
