<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl699">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1805 Feb. 21, Knoxville, Tennessee [to] E. Chism / John Sevier : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Sevier, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl699</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1805 Feb. 21, Knoxville, Tennessee [to] E. Chism / John Sevier</title>
               <author>  Sevier, John</author>
               <date when="1805-02-21"> 
			 February 21, 1805</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated February 21, 1805 from Tennessee Governor, John Sevier to Elijah Chism.  It is an answer to a letter from Chism regarding United States law relating to Indian affairs.  The specific subject of the letter is not clear, however, it is indicated that it concerns the dangers of expensive judicial proceedings.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor John Sevier Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl699</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Treaties</term>
               <term>Indians, treatment of</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Sevier, John, 1745-1815</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr89016779"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Sevier, John, 1745-1815</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl699a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Knoxville</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>21st February 1805</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have to acknowledge the receipt of your letter dated the 15th <choice>
                  <abbr>ult</abbr>
                  <expan>ultimo</expan>
               </choice> and have carefully examined the <del>same</del>  contents.  With respect to the laws of the <name>United States</name> touching indian affairs I make no doubt you are as well acquainted with them as myself and also the treaties that have been made with the cherokee indians.  If the persons have conducted in the manner you have been pleased to describe, I know of no law prohibiting such a conduct, nor do I believe that the General Government would ever notice or <unclear>disapprobate</unclear> such a measure, and as to my own part I am inclined to think it a <choice>
                  <orig>humain</orig>
                  <reg>humane</reg>
               </choice> and benevolent act, and such a one I make no doubt has rendered many poor and distressed individuals much comfort and relief; but my friend experience has taught you as well as myself, that few, and too few, pay any regard to the Sufferings of their fellow creatures.  Permit me to <pb n="2" facs="sl699b.small.jpg"/> to advise your friends how necessary it is to be cautious and not expose themselves to any liability of the law, for if they do you may be assured there is always persons to be found mean enough to distress them; In a country like yours the first adventures are not of the richest class of Citizens and if they should be dragged off to nashville before a tribunal that perhaps would not have much lenity for their conditions, they might suffer greatly were they evenly not found guilty of any <choice>
                  <orig>trespas</orig>
                  <reg>trespass</reg>
               </choice>.  You know lawyers and other court Officers will have their fees.  I throw out these <unclear>hints</unclear> , as it is my wish your <choice>
                  <orig>neighbours</orig>
                  <reg>neighbors</reg>
               </choice> may not involve themselves, but be cautiously guarded against the dangers of expensive law suits.  With respect to furnishing provisions on the road it is my opinion that all that could be carried would not be sufficient together with the supplies furnished by the keepers of the Stands, and I <choice>
                  <orig>dont</orig>
                  <reg>don't</reg>
               </choice> see why there should be any discontent on the Subject.  The indians attend the road constantly, is it  not as free for the passage of the whites?  or are the indians entitled to greater privileges? </p>
            <closer>
               <add>with great respect <choice>
                     <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                     <expan>and etcetera</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <signed>
                  <name>John Sevier</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <name>Elijah Chism</name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>esq</abbr>
                     <expan>esquire</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <name>Jackson County</name>
               </add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl699c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>copy Letter to <choice>
                     <abbr>E</abbr>
                     <expan>Elijah</expan>
                  </choice> Chism <date>21st <choice>
                        <abbr>Feby</abbr>
                        <expan>February</expan>
                     </choice> 1805</date>
                  <lb/> To be recorded__</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
