<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0033">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> [Letter] 1814 May 4, Highwassee Garrison [to] General [John] Armstrong, Secretary of War / [Return J. Meigs] : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Meigs, Return J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0033</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 44930372</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1814 May 4, Highwassee Garrison [to] General [John] Armstrong, Secretary of War / [Return J. Meigs]</title>
               <author>Meigs, Return J.</author>
               <date when="1814-05-04">May 4, 1814</date>
               <extent>4 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated May 4, 1814, from Cherokee agent Return J. Meigs to General John Armstrong, Secretary of War.  Meigs writes in regards to levies brought against the Cherokee and asks for reparations.  Meigs explains that many Cherokee warriors fought alongside the US against the Creek and thus deserve appreciation.   </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0033</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letter</term>
               <term>Meigs, Return Jonathan, 1764-1824</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Claims</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n92008354"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Meigs, Return Jonathan, 1740-1823</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0033a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Highwassee Garrison</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>5th May 1814</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I herewith transmit a statement of claims of <name>Cherokees</name>  who respectfully ask for indemnity for losses suffered by the wanton maraudings &amp; depredations of the Tennessee levies on their marches &amp; countermarches through the Cherokee County in the late expeditions against the <name>Creeks</name>: said to be all done by the left wing or division of those levies._ There has been no complaint of the conduct of the right wing of the army or the 39th Infantry Commanded by <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Colo.</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Williams</name>. In the large detailed statement now transmitted the kinds of property lost by each claimant is described opposite to his name &amp; <choice>
                  <abbr> no.</abbr>
                  <expan>number</expan>
               </choice>_ &amp; supported by his <choice>
                  <orig>narative</orig>
                  <reg>narrative</reg>
               </choice> as taken by a <choice>
                  <orig>faithfull</orig>
                  <reg>faithful</reg>
               </choice> intelligent <choice>
                  <orig>Interpretor</orig>
                  <reg>Interpreter</reg>
               </choice>: from the large statement I have made an abstract that the whole may be seen at one view.  These depredations may at first seem incredible: but I have no <choice>
                  <orig>dout</orig>
                  <reg>doubt</reg>
               </choice> of the justness of the statements: they are well known to thousands.  I received a letter from an officer of  high rank in that army in which he says, "The return of the  horse through their Country has been marked by the plunder and prodigal unnecessary and wanton destruction of property: their stock of cattle &amp; hogs have been shot and suffered to rot untouched_ their horses in some instances shared the same fate, their <choice>
                  <orig>cloathing intened</orig>
                  <reg>clothing intended</reg>
               </choice> to defend them from the wet &amp; cold in the present campaign has been stolen and in some instances where they remonstrated their lives have been threatened, <pb n="2" facs="pa0033b.small.jpg"/> this conduct is well calculated to dishearten &amp; may withhold their services which would be sincerely felt by us." I have been well informed that when in some instances applications were made by the Indians to officers they received for answer that their men felt themselves unfettered by the laws &amp; that they could not restrain them. The task of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl.</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Jackson</name>  to break down the spirit of licentiousness &amp; insubordination of such men &amp; turn the current of barbarity against the Creeks has been done by a kind of address and unconquerable resolution united rarely to be found &amp; the successful termination of the Creek war aught, perhaps, to spread a veil over every <unclear>vice</unclear> &amp; every expense in the prosecution of such a war since it is now impossible to place the <choice>
                  <orig>expence</orig>
                  <reg>expence</reg>
               </choice> on the individuals who committed those excesses.  some of the Cherokees have been deprived of all their Cattle &amp; hogs, others nearly all.  The Cherokees <choice>
                  <orig>chearfully supplyed</orig>
                  <reg>cheerfully supplied</reg>
               </choice>   the army with Beef &amp; pork and nearly all the corn they had.  General Jackson wrote me that on his route south of the mountains with the right wing or division of the army that the Indian let him have all their corn.</p>
            <p>The Cherokee warriors have <choice>
                  <orig>faught</orig>
                  <reg>fought</reg>
               </choice> and bled freely and according to their numbers have lost more men than any part of the army.  they know that they have rendered great services in this Creek war  and have no dout their services are properly appreciated by the Government.</p>
            <p>They are a little uneasy about the intrusion on their lands but believe the intruders will be removed as soon as troops can be spared for this part of the country: for they confide <pb n="3" facs="pa0033c.small.jpg"/>  in the Government they know their standing.  There are people who regret that the Cherokees have taken arms in our favor they would rejoice to have some pretext to drive them off their lands-</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have the honor to be with great respect your obedient <choice>
                     <abbr>servt.</abbr>
                     <expan>servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>General Armstrong</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Secretary of War.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="4" facs="pa0033d.small.jpg"/>  To the Secretary of war 5th May 1814.  letter on the subject of  Spoliations by the Tennessee Levies in the Creek war</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
