<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch059">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cherokee Council minutes, 1818 May 20 [to] 27, Cherokee Agency : a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch059</idno>
            <idno>oclc: 44846963</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Cherokee Council minutes, 1818 May 20 [to] 27, Cherokee Agency</title>
               <date when="1818-05-20">May 20, 1818</date>
               <date when="1818-05-27">May 27, 1818</date>
               <extent>12p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">Cherokee Council minutes from May 20 to May 27, 1818 wherein several issues related to a recent treaty (Treaty of the Cherokee Agency, July 8, 1817) are discussed. The Cherokees request provisions such as guns, blankets, and kettles that were promised to them in the treaty, and there is a discussion about the census that is planned for June. An address made by the president to General Talentisky (Talohtiske ?) and others of the Arkansas Delegation to Washington concerning Cherokee removal and land in Arkansas is read to the Council. Also, a question and answer session regarding the recent treaty and specifically concerning reservations is held, wherein Cherokee leaders Walter Adair and Thomas Foreman raise issues.</note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch059</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Treaties</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Census</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch059a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Cherokee Agency</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
                  <date when="1818-05-20">May 20th 1818</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>At a meeting of the Chiefs headmen and warriors of the <name>Cherokee Nation</name> of <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear/> by <name type="person">Col. Meigs</name> at the request of <gap agent="damage"/> Excellency <name type="person">Governor McMinn</name>
               <add place="supralinear">under instructions from the war Department</add> at the counsel <gap agent="damage"/> at this place.  By order of his Excellency <name type="person">James C. Mitchell</name> Esquire was appointed Secretary to the Governor during the Continuance of the ass<gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>em</unclear>bly.  Who proceeded to the duties of his office; and there not having convened a sufficient number of <unclear/> to proceed to Business Council Adjourned <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice>
               <choice>
                  <orig>to morrow</orig>
                  <reg>tomorrow</reg>
               </choice>.</p>
            <p>
               <date when="1818-05-21">May the 21st 1818</date> Met and adjourned until <choice>
                  <orig>to morrow</orig>
                  <reg>tomorrow</reg>
               </choice>.</p>
            <p>
               <date when="1818-05-22">Friday May the <choice>
                     <abbr>22d</abbr>
                     <expan>22nd</expan>
                  </choice> 1818 </date>
            </p>
            <p>The Chiefs <choice>
                  <abbr>c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> having Assembled in the Council House</p>
            <p>The Chiefs represented to his Excellency that they had brought with them a considerable <gap agent="damage"/>
               <pb n="2" facs="ch059b.small.jpg"/>of young men and Boys for the purpose of Obtaining arms agreeable to the promise made to the <name type="place">Arkansas</name> Delegation by their Father the President of <name type="place">Washington City</name> last winter and which is also contained in the Presidents Speech addressed to said Delegation.
                  </p>
            <p>They also stated that they wanted the terms of the treaty so varied that the women should draw the Kettles and Blankets Stipulated to be given to the poor warriors.</p>
            <p>To which his Excellency made the following reply</p>
            <q>
               <p>Friends and Brothers Your request relative to furnishing the young men and Boys with arms is founded upon the highest authority known to the <name type="person">American</name> Government and shall be attended to with cheerfulness and <choice>
                     <orig>promtitude</orig>
                     <reg>promptitude</reg>
                  </choice>  Notwithstanding the power and Authority with which I am invested on this point is <choice>
                     <orig>indeffinite</orig>
                     <reg>indefinate</reg>
                  </choice> as relates to age or size: You must permit me to exercise that Authority with an eye to the interest of my Government as well as that of yours and I do assure you that an unbiased discretion shall be my Guide.</p>
               <p>I will select one from a <gap agent="damage"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="ch059c.small.jpg"/>Those young men and Boys whose height shall be marked on the doorpost of the <name type="place">United States</name> Store House as a standard: and it must be distinctly understood that no guns will be furnished to any whose <choice>
                     <orig>hight</orig>
                     <reg>height</reg>
                  </choice> shall fall below the standard measure nor will any Blankets or Kettles be furnished to Boys under this arrangement but will be kept in reserve for the widows  children you have just now brought into view.  <choice>
                     <orig>Too</orig>
                     <reg>To</reg>
                  </choice> whose wants I am authorized by your Father the President to make adequate Provision.  But as to withholding the Kettles and Blankets from the poor warriors, it <choice>
                     <orig>can not</orig>
                     <reg>cannot</reg>
                  </choice> be granted they are secured to them by the 6th Article of the late Treaty which must be regarded in the most solemn manner and let it be remembered that the Guns given to the Boys and the Kettles and Blankets given to the widows and Children form no part of the Treaty, but are presents made to your people as a sure mark of your Fathers Goodness and friendship toward the red people
                     </p>
            </q>
            <p>With which reply of his Excellency the Council appeared to be much pleased</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="ch059d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>Saturday <date when="1818-05-23">May the <choice>
                     <abbr>23d</abbr>
                     <expan>23rd</expan>
                  </choice> 1818 </date>
            </p>
            <p>The council met and Adjourned</p>
            <p>Monday <date when="1818-05-25">May the 25th 1818 </date> The Chiefs headmen and warriors having met in the Council House and the meeting having been announced by <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>fireing</orig>
                     <reg>firing</reg>
                  </choice>
               </unclear> the <unclear>Cannon</unclear>
            </p>
            <p>His Excellency met them in the Open council and explained to them the cause of calling them together at this time in an   <unclear>apt</unclear> and an appropriate introductory address.  Among other things he stated: by the terms of the Treaty the <choice>
                  <orig>sensus</orig>
                  <reg>census</reg>
               </choice> of the whole Nation is to be taken in the month of <date when="--06">June</date> next as <add place="supralinear">well</add> those who reside on the <name type="place">Arkansas</name> as those who reside on the East of the <name type="place"> 
                  <reg>River</reg> Mississippi</name>; and that he wished to have this talk over in time for them to return to their respective houses before the Arrival of the Period at which the <choice>
                  <orig>sensus</orig>
                  <reg>census</reg>
               </choice> is to be taken, when you are at your houses My Brothers (he added) a correct account can be taken of your numbers, and the opportunity at least is not so great for the <choice>
                  <orig>comission</orig>
                  <reg>commission</reg>
               </choice> of Errors in taking the<pb n="5" facs="ch059e.small.jpg"/>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Sensus</orig>
                  <reg>Census</reg>
               </choice> and more accuracy can be Observed than in any other situation in which you can be placed, and I hope my Red Brothers (he added) that the course I have taken will be entirely satisfactory to you to which they all nodded assent
                  </p>
            <p>His Excellency then proceeded to read to the Council the Address of the President of the <name type="place">United States</name> to <name type="person">General <unclear>Talentisky</unclear>
               </name> and Others of the <name type="place">Arkansas</name> Delegation at <name type="place">Washington City</name>
               <date when="--03">last march</date> Viz</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div subtype="1" type="letter">
                        <opener>To <name type="person">General Talentisky</name> Chiefs and warriors of the <name>Cherokee Nation</name> of the <name type="place">Arkansas</name> Country</opener>
                        <p>My Friends and Children I am very glad to see you when we are face to face we can understand the wishes and intentions of each other without any danger of mistake I have long known your Friendship for the white people and it is my wish to make you and your Nation happy  The Country you gave us is a good Country and it is near and convenient to us and I <pb n="6" facs="ch059f.small.jpg"/>shall in return act generous towards you and <choice>
                              <orig>endeavour</orig>
                              <reg>endeavor</reg>
                           </choice> to make you happy in your new homes on  the <name type="place">Arkansas</name>.  I have not yet obtained the lands lying up that River to the west of your settlement I will give instructions to <name type="person">Governor Clark</name> to hold a Treaty with the <name type="person">Quapaws</name> this Summer in order to purchase them and when purchased I will direct them to be laid off for you.  It is my wish that you should have no limits to the west so that you may have good will <orig>seats plenty</orig> of <unclear>game</unclear>  and not be surrounded by the white people.
                              </p>
                        <p>It is better for you and us, that all of the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> should go to the <name type="place">Arkansas</name>.  We should be then kept more apart and bad people would not have the power to excite quarrels between us.  If  however any should choose to remain I will treat them with Justice.</p>
                        <p>I know you will not have food for the first year to feed yourselves and the emigrants who will join you.  I will <choice>
                              <orig>endeavour</orig>
                              <reg>endeavor</reg>
                           </choice> to supply you with as much corn as you may want and <pb n="7" facs="ch059g.small.jpg"/>as the Country abounds in game you must Obtain meat with your Rifles 
                              </p>
                        <p>
                           <name type="person">Governor McMinn</name> will <add place="supralinear">be</add> instructed to furnish Guns to such as may need them, and to give any aid to those who may chose to emigrate.</p>
                        <p>I will not forget my red Children because they are far off.  I will still remember you.  It is my wish to make you prosperous and happy in your new homes; and if you will at any time make known to me your wishes, I will attend to them. </p>
                        <closer>Signed by the President.</closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>His Excellency very satisfactorily explained to the Council, those parts of the above address which they did not understand; and among other things (he added) that this address was intended by their Father the President to apply to the whole Nation though delivered to the <name type="place">Arkansas</name> Delegation.  That the President of the <name type="place">United States</name> knew nor recognized no Division of the <name>Cherokee Nation</name>; nor will any division be noticed by your Father the President <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> the Enumeration is taken and the Annuities apportioned between the <pb n="8" facs="ch059h.small.jpg"/>Arkansas and those who may remain East of the <name type="place"> 
                  <reg>River</reg> Mississippi</name>.
                  </p>
            <p>His Excellency then proceeded to read the Treaty as ratified by the President and the Senate of the <name type="place">United States</name>; and explained to them such parts as he had been advised they did not understand requesting them to ask or propound any question growing out of the Treaty that might facilitate its <choice>
                  <orig>illucidation</orig>
                  <reg>elucidation</reg>
               </choice>, hoping (he added) that none would leave this place without an expression of their minds upon any clause or article of the Treaty they did not clearly understand; as it would give him the greatest pleasure to remove any <choice>
                  <orig>obsticles</orig>
                  <reg>obstacles</reg>
               </choice> that lay in the way of a plain and correct understanding of the Treaty.</p>
            <p>Amongst others of less importance <name type="person">Walter Adair</name> (one of the natives) propounded the follow questions (to wit) 1st are any persons or person entitled by the Treaty to reservation Except the head of an Indian Family. 2ndly  If a person who has taken a reservation removes to any other part of the Old Nation<pb n="9" facs="ch059i.small.jpg"/>will the land reserved revert to the <name type="place">United States</name> in the same manner as if he were to remove to the <name type="place">Arkansas</name>.  3rdly with whom will persons taking reservations be Enumerated with those who remain in the Old Nation or those who remove to the <name type="place">Arkansas</name>. (These questions grew out of the 3rd and eighth Articles of the Treaty)
                  </p>
            <p>To which <choice>
                  <orig>interogatories</orig>
                  <reg>interrogatories</reg>
               </choice> his Excellency made the following answers  To the 1st he ans<gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>wer</unclear>ed negatively, that none were entitled to take reservation under the treaty but the heads of Indian families.  The second question he answered in the affirmative that a removal from the land reserved would be by the terms of the Treaty an abandonment of <gap agent="damage"/> To the third question he answered, that he conceived those taking reservations ought not to be Enumera<gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>ted</unclear> with either, as it is upon the express condition <del type="overstrike">of becoming of</del> becoming Citizens that they are authorized to take reservations; and of course <choice>
                  <orig>can not</orig>
                  <reg>cannot</reg>
               </choice> belong to the <name type="place">Ark<gap agent="damage"/>
                  <unclear>an</unclear>sas</name> or the Old Nation; whence then the reason for Enumerating them with either.  And <choice>
                  <orig>supose</orig>
                  <reg>suppose</reg>
               </choice> there are of<pb n="10" facs="ch059j.small.jpg"/>the Old Nation 5000 who wish to remain East of the <name type="place"> 
                  <reg>River</reg> Mississippi</name> and 5000 of the <name type="place">Arkansas</name> and 440 persons who have taken reservations.  Place these reserves on part of the <name type="place">Arkansas</name>, and when the division of the land takes place you will be leasing the quantity of land allowed to those reserves more than is right out of the Old Nation.  On the other hand suppose them added to the Old Nation to be Enumerated: you  will be taking from the <name type="place">United States</name> a like quantity of Land, which in my opinion <add place="supralinear">(he added)</add> would be extremely unjust in either case and contrary to what ever was contemplated by the Treaty.  Therefore taking it upon every ground upon which it could be placed, he was of Opinion that they ought not to be Enumerated with either.
                           </p>
            <p>The treaty having been read and explained throughout the Council adjourned to meet <choice>
                  <orig>to morrow</orig>
                  <reg>tomorrow</reg>
               </choice> of the usual signal</p>
            <p>Tuesday <date when="1818-05-26">May the 26th 1818</date>
            </p>
            <p>His Excellency <add place="supralinear">met</add> the Chiefs and warriors in the <pb n="11" facs="ch059k.small.jpg"/>council House according to Adjournment.
                  </p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Thomas Foreman</name> a native stated that he did not believe that the <name type="person">Cherokees</name> had a right to take reservations until the Enumeration is taken   To which his Excellency Answered that it would give him great pleasure at any time to answer any question that might be asked upon any point growing out of the treaty that might appear ambiguous or difficult, But that he conceived the suggestion of <name type="person">Mr. Foreman</name> as <unclear> aimed</unclear> at the treaty essentially, and requiring no explanation</p>
            <p>The council then adjourned until <choice>
                  <orig>to morrow</orig>
                  <reg>tomorrow</reg>
               </choice> at the usual signal for meeting</p>
            <p>Wednesday <date when="1818-05-27">May the 27th 1818</date>
            </p>
            <p>His Excellency met the Chiefs and warriors in the Council House according to adjournment and stated to them that he would call their attention to a talk he had written to deliver to them <choice>
                  <orig>imbracing</orig>
                  <reg>embracing</reg>
               </choice> the most material points relative to the matter under investigation from the<pb n="12" facs="ch059l.small.jpg"/>commencement of the Treaty up to this time.  Which is as fallows in the succeeding  sheets 
                  </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
