<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch094">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Article on the Cherokees], 1844, [from the] Universal gazetteer / R. Brookes and John Marshall: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Brookes, (Richard), fl. 1721-1763</author>
            <author>Marshall, John, 1783-1841</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>ch094</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 44908693</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Article on the Cherokees], 1844, [from the] Universal gazetteer / R. Brookes and John Marshall</title>
               <author>Brookes, (Richard), fl. 1721-1763</author>
               <author>Marshall, John, 1783-1841</author>
               <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
               <publisher>Butler and Williams</publisher>
               <date when="1844">1844</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a typed excerpt from an article in the <hi rend="i">Universal Gazetteer</hi>, a geographic dictionary originally published in 1835, and reprinted in 1844.  The typed excerpt contains parts of the full article and describes the state of the Cherokee people in the mid-nineteenth century.  Cherokee leaders Charles Hicks and John Ross are mentioned.  The excerpt presented here contains several minor typographical variations from the original article.</note>
               <note type="repository" anchored="true">The Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">State Library Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">19</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">10</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch094</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Social conditions</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Population</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="https://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n88132740"
                        role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Marshall, John, 1783?-1841</name>
               </term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n83007776"
                        role="Contributor http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/ctb">Brookes, R. (Richard), active 1721-1763</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch094.small.jpg"/>
            <head>
               <bibl>
                  <title>Universal <choice>
                        <orig>Gazeteer</orig>
                        <reg>Gazetteer</reg>
                     </choice>
                  </title>, <date when="1844">1844</date>.<lb/>by <author>
                     <name type="person">R. Brookes</name>
                     <name type="person">John Marshall</name>
                  </author>.<lb/>p. 188.
                     
                  </bibl>
            </head>
            <p>The <name type="person">Cherokees</name> are among the bravest and noblest of the <name type="person">American</name> race.  This nation has long been distinguished for being in advance of the other Indian tribes in the arts of civilization. Some of their chieftains have been really great men, fully sensible of the disadvantages of their condition, and sagacious in devising a means to remedy them. Among these chieftains, the late <name type="person">Charles Hicks</name>, and <name type="person">John Ross</name>, now at the head of the nation, were preeminent. Under their directing councils, and aided by the policy of the general government, they have outstripped all the other tribes in the march of improvement.</p>
            <p>The natives carry on considerable trade with the adjoining states, and some of <choice>
                  <orig>they</orig>
                  <reg>them</reg>
               </choice> carry their cotton down the <name type="place">Tennessee</name>, and even down the <name type="place"> 
                  <reg>River</reg> Mississippi</name> to <name type="place">New Orleans</name>.  Apple and peach orchards are very common, and much attention is paid to gardens in the nation. There are many public roads in the nation and houses of entertainment kept by the natives.</p>
            <p>Numerous /<add place="superlinear"/> flourishing villages are to be seen in every section of the country. Cotton and woolen cloths and blankets are manufactured here. Almost every family raise<gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>s</unclear> cotton for its own consumption. Industry and commercial enterprise <del type="overstrike">have</del>
               <add place="supralinear">are</add> extending themselves throughout the nation.</p>
            <p>Different <choice>
                  <orig>machanical</orig>
                  <reg>mechanical</reg>
               </choice> trades are pursued. The population is rapidly increasing, and the female character is much respected.</p>
            <p>Their number is about 14000.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
