<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl763">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1820 Nov. 23,  Catawba [to] Joseph McMinn / William Terry : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Terry, William</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl763</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1820 Nov. 23,  Catawba [to] Joseph McMinn / William Terry </title>
               <author> Terry, William</author>
               <date when="1820-11-23">November 23, 1820</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated November 23, 1820 from William Terry to the governor of Tennessee, Joseph McMinn.  The subject of the letter is a survey of the Coral River conducted by Terry regarding its navigation.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Joseph McMinn Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl763</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>McMinn, Joseph, 1758-1824</term>
               <term>Tennessee. Governor, Office of the</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Terry, William</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl763a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Catawba</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Nov</abbr>
                     <expan>November</expan>
                  </choice>: 23, 1820</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>On the 23 of <choice>
                  <abbr>Sept</abbr>
                  <expan>September</expan>
               </choice> last I availed myself of the privilege granted me by your Excellency at our last <unclear>interview</unclear>  &amp; <choice>
                  <orig>addressd</orig>
                  <reg>addressed</reg>
               </choice> a letter to you on the subject of the navigation of the <unclear>Coral River</unclear>
            </p>
            <p>At the time I wrote that letter I had it in contemplation to proceed immediately to the survey of the <name>muscle shoals</name> of the <name>Tennessee</name>, from which however I was prevented for a time by an attack of the bilious fever;__ Since my recovery that river has been surveyed by me; and as I have no doubt but yourself, as well as most of the inhabitants of the state over which you preside, will feel a level interest in the navigation of that river, I have thought that a letter on that subject would not be altogether unacceptable to your Excellency.__</p>
            <p>The survey was commenced at the <add>Hurricane</add>
               <del type="overstrike">muscle</del> shoals which are three miles above <name>Meltons Bluff</name>.__  The obstructions to the navigation are caused by solid bed of limestone rock extending quite across the river, &amp; from one quarter to those and four miles down the same__ at these places the River spreads not very wide, and in consequence becomes very shallow, say from nine to twelve inches in depth at the longest season.__ I have submitted to the General assembly of this State (now in session) an estimate of the probable expense of opening a sluice two and a half foot deep and forty feet wide__ an abstract of which I will take the liberty of adding at the foot of this letter.__</p>
            <p>The <choice>
                  <orig>embbarrasments</orig>
                  <reg>embarrassments</reg>
               </choice> that have involved the <pb n="2" facs="sl763b.small.jpg"/> inhabitants of the other states have also reached this state, and from the want of funds to carry into effect any plans that might be formed for the internal improvement of the state they seem discouraged, and I expect the further surveys contemplated will for the present be discontinued.__</p>
            <p>As I have so arranged my private affairs so as to put it in my power to devote my time to the <choice>
                  <orig>labour</orig>
                  <reg>labor</reg>
               </choice> of civil engineering I shall have it in my power to serve your State in that capacity should your Legislature at their next session conclude to reserve their resolution to have their streams surveyed</p>
            <closer>
               <add>your <choice>
                     <abbr>most. obt. servt.</abbr>
                     <expan>most obedient servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                        <expan>William</expan>
                     </choice> Terry</name>
               </signed>
               <add>His <choice>
                     <abbr>Exy Gov</abbr>
                     <expan>Excellency Governor</expan>
                  </choice>: McMinn <lb/> Estimate of the expense of improving the Tennessee Roads from the head of the muscle shoals to the foot of the little shoals which is 36 1/2 miles <lb/> Total fall 96 feet 3 inches <lb/> Cost of sluicing the same as estimates in my report $221.300 <lb/> From the foot of the little shoals <lb/> to Bear Crash is 36 miles fall not taken; cost $16.875 <lb/> Total distance 68 1/2 miles__ Cost   $238.075 <lb/> from the foot of the shoals down the survey and estimate was for steam Boat navigation__</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl763c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>No</abbr>
                     <expan>Number</expan>
                  </choice> 3 <name>Wm Terry</name> To <choice>
                     <abbr>Gov</abbr>
                     <expan>Governor</expan>
                  </choice> McMinn <date>23 <choice>
                        <abbr>Nov</abbr>
                        <expan>November</expan>
                     </choice> 1820</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
