<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl425">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1844 Oct. 7, Carthage, Tennessee [to unknown recipient] / A[dam] Fergusson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Fergusson, A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl425</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1844 Oct. 7, Carthage, Tennessee [to unknown recipient] / A[dam] Fergusson</title>
               <author>Fergusson, A.</author>
               <date when="1844-10-07">October 7th, 1844</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Adam Fergusson dated October 7, 1844. The recipient is unknown, but may be James K. Polk. Fergusson writes the recipient that Smith county supports his bid for presidency. Fergusson believes that this candidate will follow in the steps of George Washington, Thomas Jefferson, and Andrew Jackson.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">IV-G-1, B6</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl425</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Politics.</term>
               <term>Presidential elections</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Fergusson, Adam</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl425a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Carthage</name>
                     <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>7th October 1844</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I  hope it will <add>not</add> be <add>un</add> acceptable to you to hear from <del type="overstrike">your well tried friends in Smith</del>
               <add>old <name>Smith</name>
               </add> I am Sure there can be <unclear>nonpareil</unclear> of <add>your friends therein more</add> Tennessee so devoted to your elevation to the office of President of this Great Nation than that <del type="overstrike">portion</del> comprising the Democracy of Smith They have been long and well tried we are here then <choice>
                  <orig>battleing</orig>
                  <reg>battling</reg>
               </choice> away like men not at <add>all</add> faulting or hesitating our position has been nobly maintained; and although opposed by greater numbers our confidence is growing stronger. we have made repeated charges on their whole line with the means in our power and I am happy to inform you  the result has told in our favour. I am convinced <choice>
                  <sic>the the</sic>
                  <corr>the</corr>
               </choice> excitement is now changed to this part of the State and is on the increase daily. We are still organizing military companies. No exertions <add>or sacrifices</add> are now spared on the part of our <del type="overstrike">Phalaxy</del> Democratic Phalanx; while <del type="overstrike">all the other</del> on the other side are opposed to us a most formidable enemy who Seeks every advantage that <choice>
                  <orig>fraude</orig>
                  <reg>fraud</reg>
               </choice> or falsehood can invent we have certainly arrived at a most powerful crises in the History of our country on the one hand we See in your elevation to the office of chief magistrate a <choice>
                  <orig>resteration</orig>
                  <reg>restoration</reg>
               </choice> of all those first Principles dear to freemen that we have enjoyed under the Patriots <name>washington</name>
               <name>Jefferson</name> and <name>Jackson</name> while on the other hand should defeat be our fate (which God forbid the long train of evils and measures to be fastened ere us and our children our childrens children are too <unclear>Horid to  mention</unclear>
               <del type="overstrike">I am Pleased to hear from various parts of the state the most</del> whatever other <choice>
                  <orig>pats</orig>
                  <reg>parts</reg>
               </choice> of <pb n="2" facs="sl425b.small.jpg"/> the state may do rest assured <del type="overstrike">Smith</del> the Democracy of Smith will do her duty but I feel I am trespassing on your time which is precious yet amid the weight of correspondence and the <unclear>virtues</unclear> of friends pray Snatch a moment on two and let us hear from you I am Sure from the indications every where you can afford us something both cheering and animating</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>with sentiments the most respectful <lb/> I am your truly</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>A</abbr>
                        <expan>Adam</expan>
                     </choice> Fergusson</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
