<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um088">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1843 Mar. 28, Columbia, Tennessee [to]    Col[onel] Robert J. Chester, Jackson, Tenn[essee] / Mary [Jane] Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um088</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50323470</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1843 Mar. 28, Columbia, Tennessee [to]    Col[onel] Robert J. Chester, Jackson, Tenn[essee] / Mary [Jane] Chester</title>
               <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
               <date when="1843-03-28">March 28, 1843</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by Mary Jane Chester to her father, Robert J. Chester, on March 28, 1843. Mary Jane discusses events going on at school, thanks her father for money that he sent her, and talks about a comet viewed by a telescope that is passing near Earth.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers MS 25 (January-June 1843)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um088</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Mary Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um088a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1843-03-28">March 28th 1843</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Father,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Indeed I scarcely know what excuse to plead, for my delay in answering your very kind letter, but the one which I have offered so often that I am really ashamed to mention it again, so trusting to you levity, I shall merely promise, that I will not be so negligent in future. I need not inform you with what delight yours was received, and with what pleasure I saw that my dear Brother had not forgotten me. I intend to answer his letter very soon. I feel much obliged  <choice>
                  <sic>to to</sic>
                  <corr>to</corr>
               </choice> for the  Money which you sent. I believe that I have not before acknowledged the receipt of it.</p>
            <p>There has been very great excitement in this place, concerning the Comet, Our <emph>little</emph> Rector has examined it with his Telescope, and has arrived at the conclusions that it  nearer the Earth, than any has been known, within a considerable length of time, I dont remember exactly the period. I think it truly a beautiful phenomenon. We have had a snow <pb n="2" facs="um088b.small.jpg"/> on the ground for the last two weeks, of the depth of several inches, which rendered the walking to School extremely unpleasant. One week we were all obliged to take holiday. I have taken some very fine sleigh rides. This is the first spring day that there has been this month, I really fear that we shall have no flowers  <choice>
                  <sic>or or</sic>
                  <corr>or</corr>
               </choice> which is more distressing no fruit. At least unless the weather greatly changes. There is an old weather <choice>
                  <orig>Wizzard</orig>
                  <reg>Wizard</reg>
               </choice> living here, who has predicted one more snow this Spring, which will be <emph>six feet deep</emph>, but I must confess that I have not much faith in his predictions. <name type="person">Cousin Sam</name> will be in <name type="place">Jackson</name> next week. Oh! you have no idea how sincerely I wish that I was in his <del type="overstrike">his</del> place for indeed it appears to me, that I should be perfectly, happy if I could see you all again, but I console with the idea that I have only three more months to be <choice>
                  <orig>sepperated</orig>
                  <reg>separated</reg>
               </choice> from you. Why does not  <name type="person">Aunts <choice>
                     <abbr>N</abbr>
                     <expan>Narcissa</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> and <name type="person">Patsey</name> write to me, Tell them they are both in debt to me for one letter. Ask Aunt <choice>
                  <abbr>P</abbr>
                  <expan>Patsey</expan>
               </choice> for me if Home does not feel very dear to her, as she has been away from it; I suppose she is capable of judging. Certainly There is no place like Home: but do not infer from this that I am not pleased with <name type="place">Columbia</name>, on the contrary I like it <emph>very much</emph> indeed; I greatly prefer boarding with <name type="person">Cousin Ellen</name> than at the Institute, for it is too confining. I want you to kiss Sam &amp; the Children as often as you can possibly spare time to do it in. Give my very best love to <emph>all</emph> my dear Relations.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Mary Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="um088c.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="above address">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>post mark seal</figDesc>
                  </figure> 18</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Col</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel</expan>
                        </choice> Robert J. Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address" rend="different hand, ink">My Dear Mary Jane <lb/>
                  <date when="1843-03-28">28 March 1843</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
