<TEI.2 id="sc015"> 
  
   <teiHeader> 
	 
      <fileDesc> 
		
         <titleStmt> 
		  
            <title> [Murder indictment for Jacob Gardenhire] 1795 Aug., Washington
			 District Superior Court of Law / W[illia]m Cocke: a machine-readable
			 transcription of an image</title> 
		  
            <author>Cocke, William</author> 
		  
            <respStmt> 
			 
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name> 
			 
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name> 
			 
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 
               <name>Amy Mays</name> 
		  
            </respStmt> 
		
         </titleStmt> 
		
         <publicationStmt> 
		  
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace> 
		  
            <address> 
			 
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine> 
		  
            </address> 
		  
            <date>2001</date> 
		  
            <idno>sc015</idno> 
		  
            <idno>OCLC: 50009283</idno> 
		  
            <availability> 
			 
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text.</p> 
		  
            </availability> 
		
         </publicationStmt> 
		
         <sourceDesc> 
		  
            <bibl> 
			 
               <title>[Murder indictment for Jacob Gardenhire] 1795 Aug., Washington
				District Superior Court of Law / W[illia]m Cocke</title> 
			 
               <author>Cocke, William</author> 
			 
               <date value="1795-08-00">August 1795</date> 
			 
               <extent>2p</extent> 
			 
               <note type="summary">This document is the murder indictment of Jacob
				Gardenhire passed in the August 1795 term by the Washington District Superior
				Court of Law. The trial was in regards to the murder of Joseph Hackley in
				Greene County on May 2, 1791. The jurors declared that Gardenhire had indeed
				killed Hackley with the willful intent to murder. The indictment further
				explained the nature of the crime and Hackley's death. It was signed by
				attorney William Cocke, and further instructions on the back of the indictment
				recommended that Gardenhire be taken into custody immediately.</note> 
			 
               <note type="Collection">Superior Court Indictment for Murder</note> 
			 
               <note type="Box">n/a</note> 
			 
               <note type="Folder"> MS-808</note> 
			 
               <note type="Document">sc015</note>
            </bibl> 
		
         </sourceDesc> 
	 
      </fileDesc> 
	 
      <encodingDesc> 
		
         <projectDesc> 
		  
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		
         </projectDesc> 
		
         <editorialDecl> 
		  
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p> 
		  
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		
         </editorialDecl> 
		
         <refsDecl> 
		  
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		
         </refsDecl> 
		
         <classDecl> 
		  
            <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
			 
               <bibl> 
				
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl> 
		  
            </taxonomy> 
		
         </classDecl> 
	 
      </encodingDesc> 
	 
      <profileDesc> 
		
         <textClass> 
		  
            <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
			 
               <list> 
				
                  <item>Legal document </item> 
				
                  <item>Tennessee </item> 
			 
               </list> 
		  
            </keywords> 
		
         </textClass> 
	 
      </profileDesc> 
  
   </teiHeader> 
  
   <text> 
	 
      <body> 
		
         <div1 type="legal document">
            <pb n="[1]"/> 
		  
               <opener> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine>Washington District</addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine>Superior Court of Law 
				  <date value="0000-08-00">August</date>
                     </addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine>Term A. D. 
				  <date value="1795-00-00">1795</date>
                     </addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine>Territory of the United States</addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine>South of the River Ohio</addrLine> 
			 
                  </address>
               </opener> 
		  
               <p>The Jurors for the Territory upon their Oaths Present that 
			 <name type="person">Jacob Gardenhire</name> labourer late of the
			 County of <orig reg="Greene">Green</orig> not having the fear of God before his
			 Eyes but being moved and Seduced by the Instigation of the Devil on 
			 <date value="1791-05-02">second Day of May in the year of our Lord
				one Thousand Seven Hundred and <orig reg="ninety">ninty</orig> one</date> with
			 force and arms at the County aforesaid within the District aforesaid
			 <orig reg="Feloneously">Felsoneously</orig>, Wilfully and of his malice
			 aforethought did make an assault on and upon the Body of one 
			 <name>Joseph Hackley</name> then and there being in the peace of God
			 and of the United States and then and there <orig reg="Feloneously">Felsoneously</orig> Wilfully and of his malice aforethought
			 and with Intent to murder the said Joseph Hackley did in the County aforesaid
			 within the District aforesaid and on the day aforesaid place and Fix on the
			 ground and on the Path whereon the said Joseph Hackley was Expected to ride a
			 Certain sharp pointed Stakes which he the said Jacob Gardenhire had prepared
			 and made out of a Small Tree which he had fallen for the purpose of making the
			 said sharp pointed Stake where with he <orig reg="Feloneously">Felsoneously</orig> and of his malice aforethought murdered
			 the aforesaid Joseph Hackley with the said sharp pointed Stakes by him the said
			 Jacob Gardenhire so <orig reg="Feloneously">Felsoneously</orig> sharp pointed
			 set up and fixed on the ground and on the path which said Stakes so fixed and
			 Set up he <orig n="pierced">pearced</orig> the Body of the said Joseph Hackley
			 and then and there did give the said Joseph Hackley one mortal wound on the
			 head of him the said Joseph Hackley of the depth of four Inches and of the
			 Breadth of two Inches of which mortal wound the said Joseph Hackley Instantly
			 died and so the Jurors aforesaid upon their Oath aforesaid do say that the said
			 Jacob Gardenhire <orig reg="Feloneously">Felsoneously</orig> Wilfully and of
			 his malice aforethought in manner and form aforesaid did kill and murder the
			 said Joseph Hackley against the peace and Dignity of the 
			 <name type="place">United States</name>
               </p> 
		  
               <closer> 
			 
                  <signed> 
				
                     <name type="name">
                        <abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr> Cocke
				  </name>
                     <abbr expan="Attorney">Att.</abbr>
                  </signed>
               </closer> 
		
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </body> 
	 
      <back> 
		
         <div type="legal document">
            <pb n="[2]"/> 
		  
               <p>
                  <unclear>
                     <orig reg="Territory">Teritory</orig> US</unclear> Jacob
			 Gardenhire Indictment for Murder 
			 <abbr expan="et cetera">c</abbr>.</p> 
		  
               <p> Prosecutor 
			 <name type="person">
                     <abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr>
				McCormick</name>
               </p> 
		  
               <p>Witnesses<abbr expan="et cetera">c</abbr>, 
			 <list> 
				
                     <item> 
				  
                        <name type="person">Robert McFarley</name>
                     </item> 
				
                     <item>
                        <abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr> McCormack</item> 
				
                     <item> 
				  
                        <name type="person">Nathaniel Day</name>
                     </item> 
				
                     <item> 
				  
                        <name type="person">Spencer Rainey</name>
                     </item> 
				
                     <item> 
				  
                        <name type="person">
                           <abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr>
					 Small</name>
                     </item> 
				
                     <item> 
				  
                        <name type="person">Charles Hodges</name>
                     </item> 
				
                     <item> 
				  
                        <name type="person">Alexander Outlan</name>
                     </item> 
			 
                  </list>Sworn and Sent <del type="overstrike">
                     <unclear>unk</unclear>
                  </del> 
                  <unclear> 
		  
                     <name type="person">H Gawsey</name>
                  </unclear> 
		  
                  <abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> Cocke 
		  <abbr expan="attorney">atto</abbr>
                  <add place="right">The Within a True
		  Bill and Recommend that the person charged be immediately taken into Custody
		   <lb/> 
                        <emph>L. <unclear>Carlorson</unclear>
                        </emph>
                     
                  </add>
               </p> 
		
            
         </div> 
	 
      </back> 
  
   </text>
</TEI.2>
