<TEI.2 id="sc028"> 
  
   <teiHeader> 
	 
      <fileDesc> 
		
         <titleStmt> 
		  
            <title>[Letter] to Andrew Jackson / S[ampson] Williams : a
			 machine-readable transcription of an image</title> 
		  
            <author>Williams, Sampson</author> 
		  
            <respStmt> 
			 
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name> 
			 
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name> 
			 
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 
               <name>Amy Mays</name> 
		  
            </respStmt> 
		
         </titleStmt> 
		
         <publicationStmt> 
		  
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace> 
		  
            <address> 
			 
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine> 
		  
            </address> 
		  
            <date>2001</date> 
		  
            <idno>sc028</idno> 
		  
            <idno>OCLC: 50037403</idno> 
		  
            <availability> 
			 
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text.</p> 
		  
            </availability> 
		
         </publicationStmt> 
		
         <sourceDesc> 
		  
            <bibl> 
			 
               <title>[Letter] to Andrew Jackson / S[ampson] Williams</title> 
			 
               <author>Williams, Sampson</author> 
                         
               <date value="1820-00-00">ca. 1820</date>
			 
               <extent>3p</extent> 
			 
               <note type="summary">This document is a letter whose date is unknown,
				written from Sampson Williams to Andrew Jackson when Jackson was a member of
				Congress. In the letter, Williams asked Jackson to support his proposal to
				establish a trading post at Fort Blount. Williams also discussed the conflicts
				between the Indians and Whites of the Cumberland area, and he stated that some
				500 families were currently residing on Indian lands. At the end of the letter,
				Williams also briefly mentioned the possibility of appointing a man by the name
				of Overton as Federal Judge.</note> 
			 
               <note type="Collection">Sampson Williams</note> 
			 
               <note type="Box">n/a</note> 
			 
               <note type="Folder"> MS-1959</note> 
			 
               <note type="Document">sc028</note>
            </bibl> 
		
         </sourceDesc> 
	 
      </fileDesc> 
	 
      <encodingDesc> 
		
         <projectDesc> 
		  
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		
         </projectDesc> 
		
         <editorialDecl> 
		  
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p> 
		  
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		
         </editorialDecl> 
		
         <refsDecl> 
		  
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		
         </refsDecl> 
		
         <classDecl> 
		  
            <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
			 
               <bibl> 
				
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl> 
		  
            </taxonomy> 
		
         </classDecl> 
	 
      </encodingDesc> 
	 
      <profileDesc> 
		
         <textClass> 
		  
            <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
			 
               <list> 
				
                  <item>Trading posts</item> 
				
                  <item>Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</item> 
				
                  <item>Cherokee Indians Claims against</item> 
				
                  <item>Cherokee Indians Land tenure</item> 
				
                  <item>Tennessee</item> 
			 
               </list> 
		  
            </keywords> 
		
         </textClass> 
	 
      </profileDesc> 
  
   </teiHeader> 
  
   <text> 
	 
      <body> 
		
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[1]"/> 
		  
               <opener> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine>
                        <gap reason="page is torn"> 
				  
                           <name type="person"> Jackson</name>
                        </gap>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                  </address>
               </opener> 
		  
               <p>My Exposed Situation will be a Sufficient apology for me to Solicit
			 your friendship in <orig reg="using">useing</orig> your influence in trying to
			 Keep up the post at 
			 <name type="place">Fort Blount</name>, the present mode of Keeping it
			 up by the Militia I Should prefer was it left to me, for reasons you can Judge
			 of. the Establishment of a trading post at Fort Blount I am of opinion will be
			 of great <orig reg="advantage">advantag</orig> 
                  <add place="supralinear">and
			 convenience</add> to the Indians as it is in the heart of the 
			 <name type="persons">Cherokees </name>
                  <orig reg="Hunting ground">Huntinground</orig> and they themselves have
			 <orig reg="Solicited">Solicitted</orig> me to bring goods there for them
			 However I know that cannot be done under the present establishment, The Indians
			  white people are both Violating the Treaty the result of which is hard to
			 conjecture. but I hope the present Session of Congress will take measures to
			 prevent any <orig reg="future or further">futer</orig> Violation on either side
			  many white people have Settled upon the Indian Lands I am told to the
			 amount of 500 families one Indian has been killed and one other wounded
			 supposed by the <orig reg="Kentuckians">Kentuckyans</orig> and a report of four
			 others missing, in return the Indians have Stolen many Horses on the Cumberland
			 road and robbed one <orig reg="wagon">waggon</orig> this was done previous to
			 the killing and wounding the Indians, there are three companies of Troops at 
			 <name type="place">Knoxville</name> their destination
			 <orig reg="unknown">un known</orig> but supposed for the purpose of removing
			 those people from off the Indian Lands, nothing new has
			 <add place="supralinear">transpired</add> 
                  <del type="overstrike">traspired</del> at Cumberland since you left there Except the
		  loss of our friend 
		  <name type="person"> Bennet </name>out of the old <orig reg="Bachelors">Batchelors</orig> Society who I always thought <pb n="[2]"/> in
		  that way, but to return to my <gap reason="page is torn"> and quit
		  <orig reg="plaguing">plagueing</orig> you with <orig reg="nonsense">nonsence</orig>, I hope you will not think that I wish to
		  dictate to you, but Should you be of opinion that the Keeping up the post and
		  the establishment if a trading post also at Fort Blount <del type="overstrike">I know</del> would be of <orig reg="public">publick</orig>
		  utility, I Know it would be to my advantage, but I hope my private Interest
		  will have no weight with you, I also hope you will not <orig reg="forget">foget</orig> our friend 
		  <name type="person">Overton </name>when the appointment of Federal
		  Judge comes upon the carpet I am sir with Sincere Esteem  regard</gap>
                  
               </p> 
		  
               <closer> 
			 
                  <salute> your most obedient 
				<abbr expan="Servant">Servt</abbr>
                  </salute> 
			 
                  <signed> 
				
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Sampson">S.
					 </abbr>Williams</name>
                  </signed> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine>Andrew Jackson 
				  <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr</abbr>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                  </address>
               </closer> 
		
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </body> 
	 
      <back> 
		
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[3]"/> 
		  
               <p> 
		  
                  <address> 
			 
                     <addrLine> 
				
                        <name type="person">Andrew Jackson</name> 
				
                        <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr</abbr>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                     <addrLine> Member of Congress </addrLine> 
		  
                  </address> 
                  <add place="below, left">Mr Anthony</add>
               </p> 
		
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </back> 
  
   </text>
</TEI.2>
