<TEI.2 id="sc020"> 
  
   <teiHeader> 
	 
      <fileDesc> 
		
         <titleStmt> 
		  
            <title>[Letter] 1822 Mar. 25, Hermitage [to] Captain Richard K. Call,
			 Pensacola, West Florida / Andrew Jackson : a machine-readable transcription of
			 an image</title> 
		  
            <author>Jackson, Andrew</author> 
		  
            <respStmt> 
			 
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name> 
			 
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name> 
			 
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 
               <name>Amy Mays</name> 
		  
            </respStmt> 
		
         </titleStmt> 
		
         <publicationStmt> 
		  
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace> 
		  
            <address> 
			 
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine> 
		  
            </address> 
		  
            <date>2001</date> 
		  
            <idno>sc020</idno> 
		  
            <idno>OCLC: 50031109</idno> 
		  
            <availability> 
			 
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text.</p> 
		  
            </availability> 
		
         </publicationStmt> 
		
         <sourceDesc> 
		  
            <bibl> 
			 
               <title>[Letter] 1822 Mar. 25, Hermitage [to] Captain Richard K. Call,
				Pensacola, West Florida / Andrew Jackson</title> 
			 
               <author>Jackson, Andrew</author> 
			 
               <date value="1822-03-25">March 25, 1822</date> 
			 
               <extent>4p</extent> 
			 
               <note type="summary">This document is a letter dated March 25, 1822
				from Andrew Jackson to Captain Richard K. Call. Jackson writes of his
				resignation from the army and rumors of his possible impeachment.</note> 
			 
               <note type="Collection"> Andrew Jackson</note> 
			 
               <note type="Box">n/a</note> 
			 
               <note type="Folder">MS-1038</note> 
			 
               <note type="Document">sc020</note>
            </bibl> 
		
         </sourceDesc> 
	 
      </fileDesc> 
	 
      <encodingDesc> 
		
         <projectDesc> 
		  
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		
         </projectDesc> 
		
         <editorialDecl> 
		  
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p> 
		  
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		
         </editorialDecl> 
		
         <refsDecl> 
		  
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		
         </refsDecl> 
		
         <classDecl> 
		  
            <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
			 
               <bibl> 
				
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl> 
		  
            </taxonomy> 
		
         </classDecl> 
	 
      </encodingDesc> 
	 
      <profileDesc> 
		
         <textClass> 
		  
            <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
			 
               <list> 
				
                  <item>United States Politics and government 1817-1825</item> 
				
                  <item>Tennessee</item> 
				
                  <item>Hermitage (Hermitage,Tenn.)</item> 
			 
               </list> 
		  
            </keywords> 
		
         </textClass> 
	 
      </profileDesc> 
  
   </teiHeader> 
  
   <text> 
	 
      <body> 
		
         <div1 type="Letter">
            <pb n="[1]"/> 
		  
               <opener> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <name type="place">Hermitage</name> 
				  
                        <date value="1822-03-25">March 25th 1822</date>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                  </address> 
			 
                  <salute>Dear Call</salute>
               </opener> 
		  
               <p>By last mail I had the pleasure to receive your letter of the 
			 <date value="0000-00-24">24th</date> 
			 
                  <abbr expan="ultimo">ult.</abbr> and am pleased to learn that 
			 <name type="person">Mr. Brakenridge</name> had <orig reg="shown">shewn</orig> you my letter upon great consideration, on the 
			 <abbr expan="receipt">recpt</abbr> of the documents, and a sight of 
			 <name type="person">Fromentines</name> letters to the 
			 <abbr expan="Secretary">Sec.</abbr> of State (for baseness,
			 <orig reg="Falsehood">Falshood</orig>  impudence has not their
			 <orig reg="parallel">parralel</orig>, and which the Judge never expected to be
			 before the public) I <orig reg="addressed">adressed</orig> a letter to 
			 <name type="person">Mr Monroe</name>, calling on him for an
			 explanation in a friendly way, of the <emph>"good cause he had to
			 believe"</emph> that Fromentine  myself thought we were both acting
			 <orig reg="agreeable">agreable</orig> to our respective powers; as he has
			 expressed in his communication to Congress on the 
			 <date value="0000-12-05">5th of 
				<abbr expan="DEcember">Decbr</abbr>
                  </date> last. and to be
			 consistent, and not to depart from my friend <orig reg="until">untill</orig> I
			 had a full explanation with him, or <orig reg="until">untill</orig> I had
			 satisfactory proof that he had departed from me, I enclosed him a copy of the
			 <orig reg="anonymous">enonimous</orig> letter, dated at 
			 <name type="place">Augusta Georgia</name> the 
			 <date value="0000-10-29">29th of 
				<abbr expan="October">Ocbt</abbr>
                  </date> last a copy of this
			 letter I will send you by 
			 <name type="person">Doctor Bronough</name> let it have been wrote by
			 whom it may, what he has informed me was in contemplation, has thus far taken
			 place, and the time  manner of my resignation being 
			 <pb n="[2] "/> is well calculated to confirm a belief that Mr Monroe is, 
			 has been acting the double part by me, my resignation is excepted the 
			 <date value="0000-12-31">31st of 
				<abbr expan="December">Decbr</abbr>
                     </date> and 
			 <name type="person">Mr Whitmans</name> resolutions the 
			 <date value="0000-01-02">2nd of January</date>  it is postmarked
			 the 
			 <date value="0000-01-09">9th of January</date>, seven days after Mr
			 Whitmans resolutions, and in which debate it was intimated that I resigned to
			 prevent an impeachment, however I was fortunate; for before I 
			 <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr> Mr Monroes letter of
			 <orig reg="acceptance">acceptence</orig>, I had seen the resolutions in the
			 National Intelligencer, and wrote by the next mail, both to the president 
			 the speaker of the house of Representatives to the first to withhold the
			 acceptance of my resignation, and to the latter to assure congress, if my
			 Resignation was accepted of before my letter reached the president, that I
			 stood ready to meet any charge that might be brought against me
			 <add place="supralinear">and would plead personally as tho I had not
			 resigned.</add>  The speaker has not laid my letter before
			 congress nor has Mr Monroe made any communication to the house I
			 will await his answer to my late letter if he chooses to explain, 
			 that explanation is satisfactory, I will be silent, but should he not answer my
			 my letter, or if he answers  that should not be satisfactory, I have
			 determined on my course and when I state the facts to the nation
			 If I mistake not the public, will Judge rightly and Mr Monroe will go
			 out of office with less <pb n="[3]"/> popularity than any President that has
			 preceded him I have been perfectly silent, and mean to maintain that
			 course <orig reg="until">untill</orig> congress, disposes of the Florida
			 business I have not ever wrote to one member of Congress, nor do I mean
			 to do so but I trust when it is over I shall speak, and that with
			 effect. When my friends at Pensacola reads Mr Fromentines letters to the
			 Secretary of State, I expect find <orig reg="hot weather">hotweather</orig>
			 there and I think when my friend 
			 <name type="person">Duncan</name> gets a sight of them, he will have
			 a warm  hot bed in 
			 <name type="place">
                           <orig reg="New Orleans">Neworleans</orig>
                        </name>,
			 his language as it respects Mr Duncan is of such a kind, (if 
			 <abbr expan="Fromentine">F</abbr> was worth notice <unclear>then his
			 ears</unclear> might be in danger. I have no <unclear>doubt</unclear>
			 but he dreams of horsewhips  cowskins every night of his life 
			 when you read these <add place="supralinear">letters</add> you will be still
			 more surprised how Mr Monroe could consistent with Justice to me, introduce the
			 thing to congress in the manner he has done Mr 
			 <abbr expan="Fromentine">F.</abbr> has introduced Mr Brakenridge as a
			 channel through which he has 
			 <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr> some information he details
			 Where is the Judge, present me to him if with you Mrs 
			 <abbr expan="Jackson">J.</abbr> desires to be presented to you
			 affectionately 
			 <name type="person">
                           <abbr expan="Lieutenent"> Lt.</abbr>
				Donelson</name> is at 
			 <name type="place">Lexington</name> studying law,  the two
			 Andrews request to be remembered to you. Present me affectionately to the
			 officers of the army, and all friends, and believe me to be as usual your
			 sincere friend
                  
               </p> 
		  
               <closer> 
			 
                  <signed>
                     <emph> 
				
                        <name type="person">Andrew Jackson</name>
                     </emph>
                  </signed>
                  <add place="bottom, left">
                     <abbr expan="Post Script">P.S.</abbr> My health is slowly
			 improving</add> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine>
                        <abbr expan="Captain Richard K">Capt. R. </abbr>
				  K.Call</addrLine> 
			 
                  </address>
               </closer> 
		
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </body> 
	 
      <back> 
		
         <div1 type="letter"> 
            <pb n="[4]"/> 
		  
               <p>
                  <unclear>25</unclear>
               </p> 
		  
               <p> 
		  
                  <address> 
			 
                     <addrLine> 
				
                        <name type="person">Captain Richard K. Call</name>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                     <addrLine> 
				
                        <name type="place">West Florida</name>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                     <addrLine> 
				
                        <name type="place">Pensacola</name>
                     </addrLine> 
		  
                  </address> 
                  <add place="upper left"> 
		  
                     <figure> 
			 
                        <figDesc>Postmark March 27</figDesc> 
		  
                     </figure>
                  </add>
               </p> 
		  
               <p>mail  <add place="bottom"> 
			 
                     <date value="1822-00-00">1822</date>
                  </add>
               </p> 
		
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </back> 
  
   </text>
</TEI.2>
