<TEI.2 id="sc024"> 
  
   <teiHeader> 
	 
      <fileDesc> 
		
         <titleStmt> 
		  
            <title>[Petition to abolish slavery] Tennessee, General Assembly : a
			 machine-readable transcription of an image</title> 
		  
            <respStmt> 
			 
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name> 
			 
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name> 
			 
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 
               <name>Amy Mays</name> 
		  
            </respStmt> 
		
         </titleStmt> 
		
         <publicationStmt> 
		  
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace> 
		  
            <address> 
			 
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine> 
		  
            </address> 
		  
            <date>2001</date> 
		  
            <idno>sc024</idno> 
		  
            <idno>OCLC: 50031542</idno> 
		  
            <availability> 
			 
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text.</p> 
		  
            </availability> 
		
         </publicationStmt> 
		
         <sourceDesc> 
		  
            <bibl> 
			 
               <title>[Petition to abolish slavery] Tennessee, General
				Assembly</title> 
			 
               <date value="1800-00-00">ca. 1800</date> 
			 
               <extent>4p</extent> 
			 
               <note type="summary">This document is an undated petition to abolish
				slavery in the State of Tennessee and is signed by seventy five people.</note> 
			 
               <note type="Collection">Petition to Abolish Slavery</note> 
			 
               <note type="Box">n/a</note> 
			 
               <note type="Folder"> MS-1204</note> 
			 
               <note type="Document">sc024</note>
            </bibl> 
		
         </sourceDesc> 
	 
      </fileDesc> 
	 
      <encodingDesc> 
		
         <projectDesc> 
		  
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		
         </projectDesc> 
		
         <editorialDecl> 
		  
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p> 
		  
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		
         </editorialDecl> 
		
         <refsDecl> 
		  
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		
         </refsDecl> 
		
         <classDecl> 
		  
            <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
			 
               <bibl> 
				
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl> 
		  
            </taxonomy> 
		
         </classDecl> 
	 
      </encodingDesc> 
	 
      <profileDesc> 
		
         <textClass> 
		  
            <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
			 
               <list> 
				
                  <item>Legal documents</item> 
				
                  <item>Tennessee Politics and government To 1865</item> 
				
                  <item>Antislavery movements</item> 
			 
               </list> 
		  
            </keywords> 
		
         </textClass> 
	 
      </profileDesc> 
  
   </teiHeader> 
  
   <text> 
	 
      <body> 
		
         <div1 type="petition">
            <pb n="[1]"/> 
		  
               <opener> 
			 
                  <salute>To the Honorable Senate and house of Representatives of the
				State of 
				<name type="place">Tennessee</name> Assembled.
				</salute>
               </opener> 
		  
               <p> We your humble petitioners hereunto Subscribed feeling
			 <orig reg="solicitous">solitcitious</orig> to promote the rights of man, as
			 acknowledged and held forth in the Constitution of the United States of
			 America; and <add place="supralinear">the</add> Declaration of Independence;
			 are Induced to petition your <orig reg="Honorable">Honourable</orig> Body, to
			 take into Consideration the deplorable Situation of the
			 <add place="supralinear">people</add> of <orig reg="color">colour</orig>, who
			 are held in Slavery in this our highly <orig reg="favored">favoured</orig> and
			 high professing Country; and in your wisdom derive Some plan and pass it into a
			 law for the relief, <del type="overstrike">of</del> such, at
		  <del type="overstrike">
                     <unclear/>
                  </del> least, as allowing of Masters
		  who are convinced of the Impropriety of holding Slaves; to Emancipate them on
		  terms which would not involve them nor their Estates, for their
		  <orig reg="maintenance">maintainance</orig> 
		  
                  <abbr expan="et cetera">c</abbr>  provided that the Court
		  Should be of opinion that the Slaves to be Emancipated are in all probability
		  capable of maintaining themselves.</p> 
		  
               <p> And further we would Suggest to you the propriety, the
			 Justice, the good policy, 
			 <abbr expan="et cetera">c</abbr> of your honorable body passing
			 a law Declaring, agreeable to the purport of our Federal Constitution our bill
			 of rights, and the laws of nature; that all men are, and Should be free, and
			 that, notwithstanding the laws, which have heretofore, Involved so considerable
			 a part of our population in Slavery; That all the descendents of Slaves which
			 may be born after <del type="overstrike">some</del> 
                  <add place="supralinear">the</add> passing of the law, Shall be free, at Some age,
		  which your <orig reg="honorable">honourable</orig> body, Doing as you would be
		  done by, may fix upon; Meanwhile Enjoining on those who may have the raising of
		  such, to teach them Some occupation by which they may get an honest living, And
		  teach them (<emph>at least</emph>) to read the holy Scripture, and give them
		  reasonable <orig reg="privilege">previlege</orig> of attending meetings for
		  divine worship, and further we  would not Intrude upon your
		  understanding, knowing your Entire Capability of digesting this our petition,
		  and and passing it into a law; For which we humbly pray the author of Justice
		  and willer of right, to Influence your minds thereunto, </p> 
		  
               <p> 
		  
                  <table> 
			 
                     <row> 
				
                        <cell>Names</cell> 
				
                        <cell>Names</cell> 
			 
                     </row> 
			 
                     <row> 
				
                        <cell> 
				  
                           <name type="person">Thomas Lymons</name>
                        </cell> 
				
                        <cell> 
				  
                           <name type="person">James Britton</name> 
                        </cell> 
			 
                     </row> 
			 
                     <row> 
				
                        <cell> 
				  
                           <name type="person">Hugh <unclear>Leenes</unclear>
					 Olaseh</name>
                        </cell> 
				
                        <cell> 
				  
                           <name type="person">Joseph Beals</name>
                        </cell> 
			 
                     </row> 
			 
                     <row> 
				
                        <cell> 
				  
                           <name type="person">godfray Salar</name>
                        </cell> 
				
                        <cell> 
				  
                           <name type="person">William Mchaney</name>
                        </cell> 
			 
                     </row> 
			 
                     <row> 
				
                        <cell> 
				  
                           <name type="person">Adam Lowry</name>
                        </cell> 
				
                        <cell> 
				  
                           <name type="person">Isaac Beals</name>
                        </cell> 
			 
                     </row> 
			 
                     <row> 
				
                        <cell> 
				  
                           <name type="person">Obediah Givens</name>
                        </cell> 
				
                        <cell> 
				  
                           <name type="person">John Jones</name>
                        </cell> 
			 
                     </row> 
			 
                     <row> 
				
                        <cell> 
				  
                           <name type="person">Gideon Marr</name> slave</cell> 
				
                        <cell> 
				  
                           <name type="person">Eli Richey</name>
                        </cell> 
			 
                     </row> 
			 
                     <row> 
				
                        <cell> 
				  
                           <name type="person">John McCraken 
					 <abbr type="Junior">Jr</abbr>
                           </name>
                        </cell> 
				
                        <cell> 
				  
                           <name type="person">Samuel Jones</name>
                        </cell> 
			 
                     </row> 
			 
                     <row> 
				
                        <cell/> 
				
                        <cell> 
				  
                           <name type="person">William Nickel</name>
                        </cell> 
			 
                     </row> 
		  
                  </table>
                  <pb n="[2]"/> 
		  
                     <table> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell>Names</cell> 
				
                           <cell>Names</cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">
                                 <abbr expan="Thomas">Thos</abbr>
					 Ferguson</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">James Robinson</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Henry Martain</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">
                                 <unclear>SJm Rooss</unclear>
                              </name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Richard Martain</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">James B. Rodgers</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Isaac Slaire</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Elias Owens</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Andrew Duncan</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Jonas Marsh</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">John Brown</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Samuel Grubs</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">John <unclear>Richard</unclear>
                              </name>
                           </cell>
				
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">John <unclear>Kanedy</unclear>
                              </name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Jacob Closon</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Hugh Kanedy</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Isaac Smith</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">John Martain</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Ezra Devine</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">John Neloose</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Henry Marsh</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">William Smith</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">John Tucker</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Joseph Duncan 
					 <abbr expan="Junior">Junr</abbr>
                              </name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Joseph Tucker</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Caleb Martain</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Jacob Taylor</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">John Steam</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Jesse Murphey</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">George jinken</name> slave
				  <unclear>h</unclear>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">
                                 <abbr expan="Samuel">Sam.l</abbr>
					 
                                 <unclear>Greves</unclear>
                              </name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">John
					 <unclear>Dupreeve</unclear>
                              </name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">John Greve</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">
                                 <abbr expan="Joseph">Jos</abbr> Duncan 
					 <abbr expan="Senior">Snr</abbr>
                              </name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">
                                 <abbr expan="Nathaniel">Nathel</abbr>
					 Jones</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Isaac Mulkey</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">George Pursell</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Jonathan Mulkey</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">John Squibb</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Philemon Lacey</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Isaac Keas</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Henry Haire</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">George bell</name>, slave h</cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">
                                 <unclear>John</unclear> Haire</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Francis Alexander</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Abraham Haire</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Francis Duncan</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell/> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Andrew Duncan</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Samuel Lewis</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Nicholas Tucker</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell/> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Mathew Stephenson</name> slave h</cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">John Keas</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">John B, Estes</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Jacob Ellis</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Jacob Haire</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">Ezekiel Lyon</name>
                           </cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
			 
                        <row> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">George Squibb</name>
                           </cell> 
				
                           <cell> 
				  
                              <name type="person">
                                 <unclear>lark Olly</unclear>
                              </name> slave
				  L</cell> 
			 
                        </row> 
		  
                     </table>
                     <pb n="[3]"/> 
		  
                        <table> 
			 
                           <row> 
				
                              <cell>Names</cell> 
			 
                           </row> 
			 
                           <row> 
				
                              <cell> 
				  
                                 <name type="person">Andrew Duncan</name>
                              </cell> 
				
                              <cell> 
				  
                                 <name type="person">
                                    <unclear>Mosses van
					 sayoc</unclear>
                                 </name>
                              </cell> 
				
                              <cell>Names 75</cell> 
			 
                           </row> 
		  
                        </table>
                        <add place="Middle of page">petition 
		  <abbr expan="et cetera">c </abbr>
                        </add> 
                        <pb n="[4]"/>
                     
                  
               </p> 
		
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </body> 
	 
      <back> 
		
         <div1 type="petition"> 
		  
            <p>
               <add place="top of back matter" cert="different hand and ink">Petition to abolish slavery</add>
               <add place="Top of back matter" cert="different hand and ink"> no date</add>
            </p> 
		  
            <p>James <unclear>Cotton</unclear>
            </p> 
		  
            <p>75</p> 
		
         </div1> 
	 
      </back> 
  
   </text>
</TEI.2>
