<TEI.2 id="sc038"> 
  
   <teiHeader> 
	 
      <fileDesc> 
		
         <titleStmt> 
		  
            <title>Biographical Album of Tennessee Governors [Sam
			 Houston--1827-1829] / J. S. Jones : a machine-readable transcription of an
			 image</title> 
		  
            <author>Jones, J. S.</author> 
		  
            <respStmt> 
			 
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name> 
			 
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name> 
			 
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 
               <name>Amy Mays</name> 
		  
            </respStmt> 
		
         </titleStmt> 
		
         <publicationStmt> 
		  
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace> 
		  
            <address> 
			 
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine> 
		  
            </address> 
		  
            <date>2001</date> 
		  
            <idno>sc038</idno> 
		  
            <idno>OCLC: 50395969</idno> 
		  
            <availability> 
			 
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text.</p> 
		  
            </availability> 
		
         </publicationStmt> 
		
         <sourceDesc> 
		  
            <bibl> 
			 
               <title>Biographical Album of Tennessee Governors [Sam
				Houston--1827-1829] / J. S. Jones</title> 
			 
               <author>Jones, J. S.</author> 
			 
               <date value="1904-00-00">1904</date> 
			 
               <extent>2p</extent> 
			 
               <note type="summary">The Biographical Album of Tennessee Governors,
				dated 1904, contains 31 plates, each featuring a Tennessee Governor's photo on
				the front and biographical information on the back. This plate features Sam
				Houston, Governor of Tennessee from 1827 to 1829.</note> 
			 
               <note type="Collection">Biographical Album of Tennessee
				Governors</note> 
			 
               <note type="Box">n/a</note> 
			 
               <note type="Folder">F435.J65</note> 
			 
               <note type="Document">sc038</note>
            </bibl> 
		
         </sourceDesc> 
	 
      </fileDesc> 
	 
      <encodingDesc> 
		
         <projectDesc> 
		  
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		
         </projectDesc> 
		
         <editorialDecl> 
		  
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p> 
		  
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		
         </editorialDecl> 
		
         <refsDecl> 
		  
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		
         </refsDecl> 
		
         <classDecl> 
		  
            <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
			 
               <bibl> 
				
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl> 
		  
            </taxonomy> 
		
         </classDecl> 
	 
      </encodingDesc> 
	 
      <profileDesc> 
		
         <textClass> 
		  
            <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
			 
               <list> 
				
                  <item>Houston, Sam, 1793-1863</item> 
				
                  <item>Tennessee</item> 
			 
               </list> 
		  
            </keywords> 
		
         </textClass> 
	 
      </profileDesc> 
  
   </teiHeader> 
  
   <text> 
	 
      <body> 
		
         <div1 type="Book">
            <pb n="[1]"/> 
		  
               <p> 
			 
                  <figure> 
				
                     <head>Sam Houst<gap desc="on.--1827" reason="document torn">-1829.
				  [Photo]</gap>
                     </head> 
			 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
		
            
         </div1> 
         <pb n="[2]"/> 
		
            <div1 type="book"> 
		  
               <p> 
			 
                  <name type="person">Sam Houston</name>, Governor of 
			 <name type="place">Tennessee</name>, 
			 <date value="1827-00-00">1827</date>- 
			 <date value="1829-00-00">1829</date>, was descended from the 
			 <name type="person">Scottish Convenanteers</name> and was born in 
			 <name type="place">Rockbridge County, 
				<abbr expan="Virginia">Va.</abbr>
                  </name>, 
			 <date value="1793-03-02">March 2, 1793</date>. Moved to 
			 <name type="place">Blount County</name>, Tennessee, with his widowed
			 mother about 
			 <date value="1806-00-00">1806</date>, where they had relatives
			 living. He attended 
			 <name type="place">Maryville</name> Academy, now Maryville College,
			 for a short while, but soon left home to live with the 
			 <name type="person">Cherokee Indians</name>. He returned to
			 civilization after two years and went to 
			 <name type="place">Kingston</name> to clerk in a store. Here, 
			 <date value="1813-00-00">1813</date>, he enlisted as a private in the
			 39th 
			 <abbr expan="United States">U. S.</abbr> Regulars, Infantry; soon
			 advanced to Ensign, and for bravery at the battle of Horseshoe was promoted to
			 Lieutenant. He was severely wounded in this battle and did only post duty
			 afterwards. Moved to 
			 <name type="place">Nashville</name> 
			 
                  <date value="1818-00-00">1818</date> and studied law; 
			 <date value="1819-00-00">1819</date> was elected Major-General of
			 Tennessee; 
			 <date value="1823-00-00">1823</date>- 
			 <date value="1825-00-00">1825</date> was a member of Congress. 
			 <date value="1827-00-00">1827</date> was elected Governor, defeating 
			 <name type="person">Newton Cannon</name> and 
			 <name type="person">Willie Blount</name>. 
			 <date value="1829-04-00">April, 1829</date>, he resigned the
			 Governorship and went to West to live with the Cherokee Indians again. 
			 <date value="1832-00-00">1832</date> went to 
			 <name type="place">Texas</name>, won the battle of 
			 <name type="place">San Jacinto</name> 
			 
                  <date value="1836-04-21">April 21, 1836</date>, which gave Texas her
			 independence; Houston was elected the first President of Texas Republic and led
			 the State into the Union, and was her first Senator in Congress, where he
			 served 
			 <date value="1846-00-00">1846</date>- 
			 <date value="1859-00-00">1859</date>. Was Governor of State of Texas,
			 
			 <date value="1859-00-00">1859</date>- 
			 <date value="1861-00-00">1861</date>; opposed secession and resigned
			 when Texas seceded. Died at 
			 <name type="place">Huntsville</name>, 
			 <date value="1863-07-25">July 25, 1863</date>. His first wife was 
			 <name type="person">Eliza Allen</name>, of 
			 <name type="place">Gallatin, 
				<abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn.</abbr>
                  </name>; his second wife was 
			 <name type="person">Margaret Lea</name>, of 
			 <name type="place">Marion, 
				<abbr expan="Alabama">Ala.</abbr>
                  </name>
               </p> 
		
            </div1> 
	 
         
      </body> 
  
   </text>
</TEI.2>
