<TEI.2 id="sc043"> 
  
   <teiHeader> 
	 
      <fileDesc> 
		
         <titleStmt> 
		  
            <title>Biographical Album of Tennessee Governors [Neil Smith
			 Brown--1847-1849] / J. S. Jones : a machine-readable transcription of an
			 image</title> 
		  
            <author>Jones, J. S.</author> 
		  
            <respStmt> 
			 
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name> 
			 
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name> 
			 
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 
               <name>Amy Mays</name> 
		  
            </respStmt> 
		
         </titleStmt> 
		
         <publicationStmt> 
		  
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace> 
		  
            <address> 
			 
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine> 
		  
            </address> 
		  
            <date>2001</date> 
		  
            <idno>sc043</idno> 
		  
            <idno>OCLC: 50406855</idno> 
		  
            <availability> 
			 
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text.</p> 
		  
            </availability> 
		
         </publicationStmt> 
		
         <sourceDesc> 
		  
            <bibl> 
			 
               <title>Biographical Album of Tennessee Governors [Neil Smith
				Brown--1847-1849] / J. S. Jones</title> 
			 
               <author>Jones, J. S.</author> 
			 
               <date value="1904-00-00">1904</date> 
			 
               <extent>2p</extent> 
			 
               <note type="summary">The Biographical Album of Tennessee Governors,
				dated 1904, contains 31 plates, each featuring a Tennessee Governor's photo on
				the front and biographical information on the back. This plate features Neil
				Smith Brown, Tennessee governor from 1847 to 1849.</note> 
			 
               <note type="Collection">Biographical Album of Tennessee
				Governors</note> 
			 
               <note type="Box">n/a</note> 
			 
               <note type="Folder">F435.J65</note> 
			 
               <note type="Document">sc043</note>
            </bibl> 
		
         </sourceDesc> 
	 
      </fileDesc> 
	 
      <encodingDesc> 
		
         <projectDesc> 
		  
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		
         </projectDesc> 
		
         <editorialDecl> 
		  
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p> 
		  
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		
         </editorialDecl> 
		
         <refsDecl> 
		  
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		
         </refsDecl> 
		
         <classDecl> 
		  
            <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
			 
               <bibl> 
				
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl> 
		  
            </taxonomy> 
		
         </classDecl> 
	 
      </encodingDesc> 
	 
      <profileDesc> 
		
         <textClass> 
		  
            <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
			 
               <list> 
				
                  <item>Brown, Neill Smith, 1810-1886</item> 
				
                  <item>Tennessee</item> 
			 
               </list> 
		  
            </keywords> 
		
         </textClass> 
	 
      </profileDesc> 
  
   </teiHeader> 
  
   <text> 
	 
      <body> 
		
         <div1 type="Book">
            <pb n="[1]"/> 
		  
               <p> 
			 
                  <figure> 
				
                     <head>Neil Smith Brown.--1847-1849. [Photo]</head> 
			 
                  </figure>
               </p> 
		
            
         </div1> 
         <pb n="[2]"/> 
		
            <div1 type="book"> 
		  
               <p> 
			 
                  <name type="person">Neil Smith Brown</name>, Governor of 
			 <name type="place">Tennessee</name>, 
			 <date value="1847-00-00">1847</date>- 
			 <date value="1849-00-00">1849</date>, was born in 
			 <name type="place">Giles County</name>, 
			 <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn.</abbr>, 
			 <date value="1810-04-18">April 18, 1810</date>. He was well educated
			 and began his career as a school teacher. 
			 <date value="1833-00-00">1833</date> he began to study law; was
			 admitted to the bar 
			 <date value="1834-00-00">1834</date> and began his practice at 
			 <name type="place">Pulaski</name>. 
			 <date value="1836-00-00">1836</date> he enlisted as a private in the 
			 <name type="person">Seminole</name> war and was soon promoted to
			 Sergeant-Major, First 
			 <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn.</abbr> Regulars, Armstrong's brigade. 
			 <date TEIform="1836-00-00">1836</date> he was district elector on the
			 
			 <name type="person">Hugh Lawson White</name> ticket, and the next
			 year was elected on the Whig ticket to the Legislature. He was on 
			 <name type="person">Harrison</name>- 
			 <name type="person">Tyler</name> ticket as elector 
			 <date value="1840-00-00">1840</date>, and four years later on the
			 ticket for 
			 <name type="person">Henry Clay</name>. 
			 <date value="1847-00-00">1847</date> he defeated the democratic
			 candidate, 
			 <name type="person">Aaron V. Brown,</name> and was elected Governor
			 by a vote of 61,372 to 60,004. During his administration, 
			 <date value="1847-00-00">1847</date>, "the 
			 <name type="place">New Orleans</name> and 
			 <name type="place">Ohio</name> Telegraph Company" was incorporated,
			 being the first in the State. 
			 <date value="1848-00-00">1848</date> Legislature passed an act
			 requiring the Governor to endorse bonds of the 
			 <name type="place">East 
				<abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn.</abbr>
                  </name>  
			 
                  <name type="place">Georgia</name> Railroad. This was the first State
			 aid to railroads in Tennessee. 
			 <date value="1849-00-00">1849</date> Neil S. Brown was defeated by 
			 <name type="person">William Trousdale</name>, Democratic candidate
			 for Governor. 
			 <date value="1850-00-00">1850</date> he was appointed Minister to the
			 Court of 
			 <name type="place">Russia</name>. Returned to America and was elected
			 to State Legislature 
			 <date value="1855-00-00">1855</date> and was Speaker of the House.
			 Retired to private life and practiced law. Died at 
			 <name type="place">Nashville</name> 
			 
                  <date value="1886-01-20">January 20, 1886</date>, and his buried in
			 Mount Olivet Cemetery.</p> 
		
            </div1> 
	 
         
      </body> 
  
   </text>
</TEI.2>
