<TEI.2 id="sc045"> 
  
   <teiHeader> 
	 
      <fileDesc> 
		
         <titleStmt> 
		  
            <title>[Letter] 1845 Feb. 28, Hermitage [to] Major W[illia]m B Lewis /
			 Andrew Jackson : a machine-readable transcription of an image</title> 
		  
            <author>Jackson, Andrew</author> 
		  
            <respStmt> 
			 
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name> 
			 
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name> 
			 
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 
               <name>Amy Mays</name> 
		  
            </respStmt> 
		
         </titleStmt> 
		
         <publicationStmt> 
		  
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace> 
		  
            <address> 
			 
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine> 
		  
            </address> 
		  
            <date>2001</date> 
		  
            <idno>sc045</idno> 
		  
            <idno>OCLC: 50407027</idno> 
		  
            <availability> 
			 
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text.</p> 
		  
            </availability> 
		
         </publicationStmt> 
		
         <sourceDesc> 
		  
            <bibl> 
			 
               <title>[Letter] 1845 Feb. 28, Hermitage [to] Major W[illia]m B Lewis
				/ Andrew Jackson</title> 
			 
               <author>Jackson, Andrew</author> 
			 
               <date value="1845-02-28">February 28, 1845</date> 
			 
               <extent>2p</extent> 
			 
               <note type="summary">This document is letter from Andrew Jackson (US
				president, 1829-1837) to Major William B. Lewis dated February 28, 1845. In the
				letter, Andrew Jackson states to Major Lewis his opinions about who he believes
				to be the best men for the Tennessee State Department administration. Jackson
				approves Mr. Clay for the Secretary of State position and Mr. Buchanan into the
				Department of State. He approves of Colonel Polk obtaining a position in the
				administration, but says that Mr. Tyler's succession to the administration
				would split the democracy apart and damage Polk's administration. Jackson
				concludes this letter by informing Major Lewis of his failing health. He
				consequently dies several months later.</note> 
			 
               <note type="Collection"> Andrew Jackson</note> 
			 
               <note type="Box">n/a</note> 
			 
               <note type="Folder">MS-219</note> 
			 
               <note type="Document">sc045</note>
            </bibl> 
		
         </sourceDesc> 
	 
      </fileDesc> 
	 
      <encodingDesc> 
		
         <projectDesc> 
		  
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		
         </projectDesc> 
		
         <editorialDecl> 
		  
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p> 
		  
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		
         </editorialDecl> 
		
         <refsDecl> 
		  
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		
         </refsDecl> 
		
         <classDecl> 
		  
            <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
			 
               <bibl> 
				
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl> 
		  
            </taxonomy> 
		
         </classDecl> 
	 
      </encodingDesc> 
	 
      <profileDesc> 
		
         <textClass> 
		  
            <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
			 
               <list> 
				
                  <item>Jackson, Andrew 1767-1845</item> 
				
                  <item>Tennessee</item> 
				
                  <item>Clay, Henry 1811-1847</item> 
				
                  <item>Tennessee Politics and government To 1865</item> 
			 
               </list> 
		  
            </keywords> 
		
         </textClass> 
	 
      </profileDesc> 
  
   </teiHeader> 
  
   <text> 
	 
      <body> 
		
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[1]"/> 
		  
               <opener> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <name type="place">Hermitage</name>
                     </addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <date value="1845-02-28">
                           <abbr expan="February">Feby</abbr> 28th
					 1845</date> 
                     </addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine>
                        <add place="top left corner">
                           <emph>private</emph>
				  
                        </add> 
				  
                        <name type="person">Major 
					 <abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> B Lewis</name>,</addrLine> 
			 
                  </address> 
			 
                  <salute>My dear Major,</salute>
               </opener> 
		  
               <p>Your interesting letter of the 
			 <date value="0000-00-17">17th</date>, instant is <orig reg="received">recieved</orig>, advising that mine of the 
			 <date value="0000-00-04">4th</date>  
			 
                  <date value="0000-00-05">5th</date> had reached you  Before
			 this reaches you 
			 <name type="person">
                     <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Polks</name>
			 
                  <orig reg="Cabinet">Cabinett</orig> will be known, and I am <gap> there will no
			 one compose it unless under the terms I named to you should there be, then 
			 <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Polk must have changed his mind
			 after he left me. Your observations with regard to 
			 <name type="person">Mr. <orig reg="Buchanan">Buchannan</orig>
                     </name>,
			 are correct  He <orig reg="showed">shwd</orig> a want of moral courage
			 in the affair of the intrigue of 
			 <name type="person">Adams  Clay</name>  did not do me
			 justice in the expose he then made  and I am sure about that time did
			 believe there was a perfect understanding between Adams  Clay about the
			 presidency  the <orig reg="Secretary">Secratary</orig> of State 
			 This I am sure of  But whether 
			 <abbr expan="I have">Ive</abbr> ceded that there was any corruption
			 in the case or not I know not, but one thing I do know, that he wished me to
			 combat <add place="supralinear">them</add> with <orig reg="their">thier</orig>
			 own weapons  that was to let my friends say if I was elected I would
			 make Mr. Clay Secretary of State  This to <emph>me</emph> appeared deep
			 corruption,  I repelled at  with that honest indignation, as I
			 thought such corruption deserved!! Mr. Buchanan is a man of fine talents 
			 if he comes into the Department of State will execute the duties with ability
			 </gap>
               </p> 
               <pb n="[2]"/> 
		  
                  <p>I was truly astonished at some information brought by 
			 <name type="person">Mr A. Jackson jr</name>  from 
			 <name type="place">Nashville</name> the other day. It was this, that 
			 <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Laughlin</name>
			 had went on to 
			 <name type="place">Washington</name> had bought an interest in the
			 Madisonian, and expected to make it the organ of the administration This if
			 true would be one of the most fatal steps for 
			 <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Polk that could be taken it would be
			 placing him in the Shoes of 
			 <name type="person">Mr. Tyler</name>, and Laughlin travelling on with
			 the 
			 <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> to Washington would place 
			 <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Polk under the implication of taking
			 him on there for the purpose which I am sure was not the case. Common sense
			 will at once shed the evil consequences that had ensue to 
			 <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Polk, to put himself in the attitude
			 of <orig reg="favoring">favouring</orig> Mr. Tyler for the succession 
			 It would split the democracy to pieces, and redound to the great injury of
			 Polks administration  I have from the moment I heard it put my face
			 against it,  hope I have checked this inconsiderate movement  I
			 hope there is no truth in the rumor  if there is, there is less common
			 sense in the movers than I calculated upon, let me hear from you.</p> 
		  
                  <p>your sister 
			 <name type="person">Mrs. Leister</name>,  one of her daughters
			 spent day before yesterday with us  They all enjoy good health</p> 
		  
                  <p>All my <orig reg="Household">Houshold</orig> join me in the kindest
			 salutations,</p> 
		  
                  <closer> 
			 
                     <salute>
                        <abbr expan="your">yr</abbr> friend.</salute> 
			 
                     <signed> 
				
                        <name type="person">
                           <emph>Andrew Jackson</emph>
                        </name>
                     </signed>
                     <add place="bottom of page">
                        <abbr expan="Post Script">P. S.</abbr> My shortness of
			 breath increases  I am greatly afflicted  
			 <abbr expan="Andrew Jackson">A J.</abbr>
                     </add>
                  </closer> 
		
               
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </body> 
  
   </text>
</TEI.2>
