<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sc058">		<teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1844 Apr. 20, Nashville, Tenn[essee] [to] Maj[or] W. J. Whitthorne, Shelbyville, Tenn[essee] /  S[amuel] H. Laughlin : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Laughlin, Samuel H.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sc058</idno><idno>OCLC: 51302043</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1844 Apr. 20, Nashville, Tenn[essee] [to] Maj[or] W. J. Whitthorne, Shelbyville, Tenn[essee] /  S[amuel] H. Laughlin</title><author>Laughlin, Samuel H.</author><date value="1844-04-20">April 20, 1844</date><extent>4 p</extent><note type="summary">The following document is a letter, dated April 20, 1844, from Samuel Laughlin to Major W. J. Whitthorne in Shelbyville, Tennessee.  In the letter, Laughlin discusses both national and state politics.  He updates Whitthorne on election results from around the country, and he warns that a fierce battle must be fought to prevail  against the Whigs in upcoming elections.  Laughlin, an ardent supporter of James K. Polk, was also one of the "Immortal Thirteen" who, fearing the election of a Whig, refused to meet with the Tennessee House to elect a representative to the U.S. Senate, leaving Tennessee unrepresented in the Senate for 1841-1843. </note><note type="collection">Samuel H. Laughlin</note><note type="box">MS-1205</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">sc058</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</item><item>United States -- Politics and government -- 1841-1845</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Nashville, <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn.</abbr></name> <date value="1844-04-20">April 20, 1844</date></addrLine></address><add place="top, left">(Private)</add> <salute>My dear sir,</salute></opener><p> For the posture of political affairs here, and abroad, I must refer you to the current newspapers.  The <abbr expan="Honorable">Hon.</abbr> <name type="person">Cave Johnson</name> writes me, that our <orig reg="friends">frinds</orig> are determined, in the House of Representatives, to adjourn by the 27th or 28th of May unless something grows out of the <orig reg="negotiations">negociations</orig> in regard to <name type="place">Oregon</name> or <name type="place">Texas</name> which may make a postponement for a short time beyond those dates necessary and proper. &mdash; In <name type="place">New York</name>, in the town elections, we have gained, judging from the <name type="place">Albany</name> Atlas and other sober, calculating points.  In the city, the Native American Democratic ticket has prevailed; but the Whigs are beaten badly, and knowing they would be beaten, many of them abandoned their own regular ticket, and voted for the Native ticket (a branch of the democracy mostly friendly to <name type="person">Tyler</name> and <name type="person">Calhoun</name>) in order to beat the regular locossco ticket.  Of three, our ticket was much the strongest, but the natives and Whigs united, beat us.  The Whigs do not exult in the result&mdash;it has shown their weakness.  <name type="person">Harper</name>  the Mayor elect, called a Whig is a Calhoun man&mdash;and has been a Tylerite.&mdash; In <name type="place">Kentucky</name> , our friends are <add place="left margin"><abbr expan="Post Script">P.S.</abbr> Being in haste to save the mail, I have no time to look over and correct errors or omissions. With a friend, it makes no difference&mdash;as errors will be excused.</add> <pb n="[2]"/> making a rush, and I verily believe will elect <name type="person">Butler</name> Governor and <name type="person">Pilcher</name> Lieutenant Governor next August, however the main election may afterwards go in the fall.  Four or five good democratic papers have been started lately in that state at proper points &mdash; one of them a German paper at <name type="place">Louisville</name> &mdash; and the best talents of the state are in the field for us on the electoral ticket and for the legislature.</p><p>In this state the Whigs intend, as we learn here, and one purpose of my writing is to inform you of it, to have a universal, simultaneous rising as soon as they hear from their nominations at <name type="place">Baltimore</name>. Old <unclear>Taul</unclear>, old <name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> Martin</name> of <name type="place">Smith</name>, and a full  representation of Whig Delegates have passed here many of them and gone on.  When they hear from the convention and know the result, the Whig candidates for Elector, old <name type="person">Barringer</name>, <name type="person">John Bell</name>, and all, will take the field.  We must be prepared to breast the shock and meet them.  Our candidates, and all others who can speak, or strike a stroke, must be on the alert.  I have written to <name type="person">Mr. Rogers</name> of <name type="place">Fayetteville</name>, who will probably be your candidate for Elector, that he must be in readiness to fight; and I have written to the candidate in my own district, and to <name type="person">Mr. H. L. Turney</name> for <pb n="[3]"/> the state at large to be ready&mdash;to fight.</p><p>Here, with the papers, the old Union, and Star Spangled Banner, I will do the best I can, and up at home, from <name type="place">Fentress</name> to <name type="place">Coffee</name>, I will address the people in the course of the canvass.</p><p>I find with all my private collections and stores of books, documents, journals, debates <abbr expan="et cetera, et cetera">&amp;c. &amp;c.</abbr> and with all I can procure by begging, buying and borrowing here, that there are many documents,  papers, journals, debates <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;c.</abbr> which it is necessary to have here for the use of the press to fight the battle as it ought to be fought.  I have no personal interest in it but my love of the cause, and wish to sustain my credit as a <emph>pro tempore</emph> editor for the party.  This being the case I feel free to call for help on friends who are willing if it is ever so little.  I have already bought and ordered at my own charge $50 worth of <emph><orig reg="ammunition">amunition</orig></emph> of this sort since I have been at my port.  Our folks here have heavy <unclear>drafey</unclear> and taxes on them, but will all help <del type="overstrike"><unclear></unclear></del> as they can.  Any sum from $1 to $200 can be well laid out.  I therefore request you, <name type="person">Mr. Matthews</name>, <name type="person">Mr. <unclear>Frierson</unclear></name>, and any friends who may be willing to throw a mite into the common democratic treasury, to do so through you, and that you remit it to me to aid in buying documents&mdash;as I have a chance of ordering them &mdash; in the course of next week&mdash; by Thursday or Friday if you can.  Every little will help. <pb n="[4]"/> Also write me the prospects of things in General in your County.  Write to my individual address, and freely and fully as you can. &mdash; I hope you all approve of my dealing with <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Gen.</abbr> Caruthers</name>, and of the 1st. No of the Banner.  I hope our friends will hasten and send subscriptions to <name type="person">Hogan</name> and <name type="person">Heifs</name>' address for it&mdash;as it will not quit cost unless pretty numerously subscribed for.  Our friend <name type="person">Davis</name>  will remit subscriptions for that as postmaster.  I had to make some of our people here <emph>know</emph>, a few days since, that Mr. <abbr expan="Davis">D.</abbr> is an old and true democrat. &mdash; Write as requested, while I am, very truly,</p><closer><salute><abbr expan="your">yr.</abbr> friend</salute><signed><emph><name type="person"><abbr expan="Samuel">S.</abbr> H. Laughlin</name></emph> <add place="left"><name type="person"><abbr expan="Major">Maj.</abbr> W. J. Whitthorne</name></add>. &rcub;</signed><address><addrLine>Major. W. J. Whitthorne</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Shelbyville</name>,</addrLine><addrLine><name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn.</abbr></name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
