<TEI.2 id="sc051"> 
  
   <teiHeader> 
	 
      <fileDesc> 
		
         <titleStmt> 
		  
            <title>[Letter] 1821 May 6, [to] R.E.W. Earl, New Orleans / A.J.
			 Donalson: a machine-readable transcription of an image</title> 
		  
            <author>Donalson, A.J.</author> 
		  
            <respStmt> 
			 
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name> 
			 
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name> 
			 
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 
               <name>Amy Mays</name> 
		  
            </respStmt> 
		
         </titleStmt> 
		
         <publicationStmt> 
		  
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace> 
		  
            <address> 
			 
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine> 
		  
            </address> 
		  
            <date>2001</date> 
		  
            <idno>sc051</idno> 
		  
            <idno>OCLC: 50449365</idno> 
		  
            <availability> 
			 
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text.</p> 
		  
            </availability> 
		
         </publicationStmt> 
		
         <sourceDesc> 
		  
            <bibl> 
			 
               <title> [Letter] 1821 May 6, [to] R.E.W. Earl, New Orleans / A.J.
				Donalson</title> 
			 
               <author>Donalson, A.J.</author> 
			 
               <date value="1821-05-06">May 6, 1821</date> 
			 
               <extent>4p</extent> 
			 
               <note type="summary">This document is a letter from A.J. Donalson to
				R.E.W. Earl dated May 6, 1821. In the letter, Donalson speaks of the
				hospitality of the citizens of New Orleans toward himself and his troops while
				they have been there. Donalson awaits information from Colonel Forbes on
				whether or not he has reached Pensacola, carrying orders to Cuba for the
				surrender of Florida to the United States. He states that after the information
				is attained, he will march to Pensacola as well and that troops will soon take
				possession of St. Augustine. Donalson states that people are moving from all
				parts of the country to Pensacola and that it has the potential to become a
				great commercial city. He concludes by asking R.E.W. Earl to finish the
				portrait of Donalson that he started and present it to his mother when it is
				completed.</note> 
			 
               <note type="Collection"> Ralph E. W. Earle</note> 
			 
               <note type="Box">n/a</note> 
			 
               <note type="Folder">MS-856</note> 
			 
               <note type="Document">sc051</note>
            </bibl> 
		
         </sourceDesc> 
	 
      </fileDesc> 
	 
      <encodingDesc> 
		
         <projectDesc> 
		  
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		
         </projectDesc> 
		
         <editorialDecl> 
		  
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p> 
		  
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		
         </editorialDecl> 
		
         <refsDecl> 
		  
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		
         </refsDecl> 
		
         <classDecl> 
		  
            <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
			 
               <bibl> 
				
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl> 
		  
            </taxonomy> 
		
         </classDecl> 
	 
      </encodingDesc> 
	 
      <profileDesc> 
		
         <textClass> 
		  
            <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
			 
               <list> 
				
                  <item>Southern States</item> 
				
                  <item>Donalson, A.J.</item> 
				
                  <item>Florida</item> 
				
                  <item>Florida History Cession to the United States, 1819</item> 
				
                  <item>Cuba</item> 
			 
               </list> 
		  
            </keywords> 
		
         </textClass> 
	 
      </profileDesc> 
  
   </teiHeader> 
  
   <text> 
	 
      <body> 
		
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[1]"/> 
		  
               <opener> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <name type="place">Blakely</name> 
				  
                        <date value="1821-05-06">May 6th 1821</date>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                  </address> 
			 
                  <salute>Dear 
				<name type="person">Earl</name>
                  </salute>
               </opener> 
		  
               <p> I avail myself of this, the first opportunity of conveying a letter
			 to you;  We arrived at this place on the 
			 <date value="0000-00-29">29th</date> 
			 
                  <unclear>ultimo</unclear> ; after a quiet and pleasant passage from
			 <orig reg="New Orleans"> 
			 
                     <name type="place">New  Orleans</name>
                  </orig>, The ladies
			 <add place="supralinear">only</add> accepting the little sickness, which
			 <hi>old ocean</hi> always tributes, as a passport through his dominions
			 </p> 
		  
               <p>The 
			 <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> is in waiting for information from 
			 <name type="person">
                     <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Forbes</name>,
			 who was appointed by the President, Agent and Commissary to carry the royal
			 order to 
			 <name type="place">Cuba</name> for the surrender of the 
			 <name type="place">Florida's</name> : whether he has reached 
			 <name type="place">Pensacola</name>, or not, we are as yet
			 uninformed. 
			 <name type="person">Bronough</name> and 
			 <name type="person">Breckenridge</name> have been sent to Pensacola,
			 with a view of Reporting to the Governor of Pensacola, and ascertaining how far
			 things are in progress towards the ceremonies of exchange, we expect their
			 return <orig reg="today">to day</orig>. Our movements depend entirely upon
			 their report, or at least so much of it, as regards the <orig reg="preparatory">perparatory</orig> state of the Spanish authority to carry
			 the treaty into effect  no delay will take place as the part of our
			 Government. The 
			 <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> is always prepared, and will be
			 prompt and quick. The <orig reg="Regiment">Regimant</orig> at 
			 <name type="place">Montpelier</name>, and the company of Artillery at
			 
			 <name type="place">Mobile</name> will <orig reg="constitute">con
			 <pb n="[2]"/> stitute
                  </orig> his military force, and <unclear>in</unclear> held
			 in readiness to march when ordered; We will proceed, <orig reg="probably">brobably</orig>, tomorrow for <orig reg="Montpelier">MontPelier</orig>, <orig reg="Whenever">Whener</orig> we will
			 march to Pensacola.</p> 
		  
               <p>We are extremely anxious to leave this place, notwithstanding the
			 efforts of the citizens to make us as comfortable as possible  they have
			 served us with, dinners, suppers, <hi>sermons</hi> and all that such of
			 <add place="supralinear">thing called</add> civility, which a sickly town a bad
			 market and a poor country can hardly make agreeable, and can at most but prove
			 the good wishes of the people  <unclear> 
			 
                     <name type="person">Call</name>
                  </unclear> arrived here on the 
			 <date value="0000-00-01">1st</date> 
			 
                  <abbr expan="instant">inst.</abbr> in good health. He brings no news
			 from 
			 <name type="place">Tennessee</name> later than what you have 
			 All friends were well : 
			 <name type="person">
                     <abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> Butler</name>
			 is a provisional Commissioner to take possession of 
			 <name type="place">
                     <abbr expan="Saint">St</abbr> Augustine</name>,
			 and is on his way to that place. This provision in the 
			 <abbr expan="Colonels">Colns</abbr> commission, arrives from 
			 <name type="person"> 
				
                     <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> Gaines</name> being ordered to 
			 <name type="place">Washington</name> whom you know was the first
			 appointed to execute that business </p> 
		  
               <p>The people, I understand, are running from all parts of our country
			 to Pensacola, like Sandhill cranes from snow storms; I am afraid our western
			 boys will miss their aim, and will soon back again with hard times to their
			 brush heaps, for of all countries I have ever seen, I think this promises
			 least, to that <pb n="[3]"/> plain sailing, forming character which attaches to
			 our Western countrymen generally. Pensacola if healthy, may attain some
			 eminence in a commercial point of view  The character which our nation
			 may give it, the safety of its Port, and the certainty of its market may induce
			 <orig reg="capitalism">capotalism</orig> to remove there; but this granted, and
			 all the fashionable report which is promised it, I think its greatness much
			 overrated, and this trumpeting <hi>mania</hi> of many of our people, will and
			 in <hi>feverish hard times.</hi> This is no business of ours, I shall therefore
			 say no more on the subject.
               </p> 
		  
               <p>I am sorry that I was compelled to leave 
			 <name type="place">
                     <orig reg="New Orleans">New 
				Orleans</orig>
                  </name>, before you had finished my portrait. I will
			 <gap reason="document damaged"> you again shortly, and will tell you then,
			 whether I will have an opportunity of seeing you again soon. if I shall not see
			 you and <add place="supralinear">you</add> can make a
			 <unclear>tolerable</unclear> likeness without farther sitting, I shall thank
			 you to do so, and present it to my mother, 
			 <name type="person">Mr Sanders</name> will be instructed to
			 compensate you for the favor you will confer on my mother and myself 
			 The 
			 <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Aunz</name>,
			 and all their family sent themselves to you, give my respects to 
			 <name type="person">Mr Vanderlynn</name>. 
			 <abbr expan="Doctor">Doctr</abbr> 
			 
                     <name type="person">Bell  Smith</name>, and accept for yourself
			 assurances of the <unclear>esteem</unclear> and regard of your friend and
			 servant.</gap>
               </p> 
		  
               <closer> 
			 
                  <signed> 
				
                     <name type="person">AJ Donalson</name>
                  </signed> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine>R.E.W. Earl</addrLine> 
			 
                  </address>
               </closer> 
		
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </body> 
	 
      <back> 
		
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="[4]"/> 
		  
               <p> 
		  
                  <address> 
			 
                     <addrLine> 
				
                        <name type="person">
                           <hi>R.E.W. Earl</hi>
                        </name>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                     <addrLine> 
				
                        <name type="place">
                           <orig reg="New Orleans">New 
				  Orleans</orig>
                        </name>
                     </addrLine> 
		  
                  </address>
                  <add place="left of text"> 
		  
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> Gadsden</name>
		  
                  </add>
               </p> 
		
            
         </div> 
	 
      </back> 
  
   </text>
</TEI.2>
