<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sc065"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1844 Jan. 7 Clarksville, Tenn [essee], [to] Annie Haven / Charles E. Haven :a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Haven, Charles E.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sc065</idno><idno>OCLC: 51317182</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1844 Jan. 7 Clarksville, Tenn [essee], [to] Annie Haven / Charles E. Haven</title><author>Haven, Charles E.</author><date value="1844-01-07">January 7, 1844</date><extent>4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter written by Charles E. Haven to his wife Annie on January 7, 1844. In the letter, Charles discusses his travels and the conditions under which he is travelling on his way through Tennessee back to Pennsylvania. Charles mentions in his letter that he witnessed an auction in which black slaves and freemen were being sold or bought in the marketplace, and he expresses the opinion that this is one of the worst features about slavery.</note><note type="collection">Charles E. Haven</note><note type="box">MS-1864</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">sc065</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Slavery</item><item>Tennessee -- Description and travel</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Clarksville, <abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn.</abbr></name> <date value="1844-01-07"><abbr expan="January">Jany</abbr> 7, 1844</date></addrLine></address><salute>My Dearest <name type="person">Annie</name></salute></opener><p>Another week has passed since I had the pleasure of writing to you. &amp; I am only 45 miles from where I was then. so you see I am not getting home very fast but I have had a busy week of it &amp; a more fatiguing one than any I have previously had, but thank God I have arrived here in safety without meeting with any accident &amp; in good health. On <orig reg="Monday">monday</orig> I remained in Nashville. called upon my acquaintances there, &amp; was introduced to most of the largest <orig reg="operators">opperators</orig> in Produce by <name type="person"><abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> McEwen</name>. it rained nearly all day, but still I was on the go from morning <abbr expan="until">til</abbr> night. I received some encouragement from several houses, but as but very few will say that they will <orig reg="positively">possitively</orig> ship to us. I cannot tell what to depend upon. I wish there was more certainty in it. I want to know what we can depend upon, but that cannot be, &amp; we must trust to Providence that we shall have enough after having &caret; <add place="supralinear">done</add> all we can do to succeed, &amp; me conscience bears me witness that I have exerted my &caret; <add place="supralinear">self</add> to the utmost to promote the success of our undertaking, &amp; I trust in <name type="person">God</name> it will not be altogether thrown away. I wish to succeed in business so that my family may live comfortably, &amp; not be at all dependant upon your relatives, &amp; I am anxious to pay what I am owing to <name type="person">Uncle John</name>, I cannot say that I have any great desire to &caret; <add place="supralinear">be</add> very rich, but I wish to be <orig reg="independent">independant</orig>. you know my feelings on this subject, &amp; you can readily <pb n="[2]"/> imagine my anxiety to succeed in this business, aside from the unpleasant idea of being unsuccessful in what I undertake &mdash; on Monday evening I took tea with <name type="person">Mr Yeatman</name>. they live in handsome <orig reg="style">stile</orig>. &amp; are very pleasant people, although I was there but a short time, as I had letters to write in the evening &mdash; on <orig reg="Tuesday">tuesday</orig> morning at 4 O'Clock I left <name type="place">Nashville</name> in the stage for <name type="place">Bowling Green <abbr expan="Kentucky">Ky.</abbr></name>&amp; reached there "between sundown &amp; daylight down" just as the driver said we should &mdash; I got along very comfortably that day. the next day I remained in <unclear>B</unclear> &amp; attended to my business there, but the next morning I left there in a common cart drawn by 4 horses. it had no springs nor top &amp; very low sides, so that I had to sit on a mail bag &amp; hold on the best way I could, &amp; then was danger of my being jolted out continually, going over the terrible bad road, very rocky &amp; muddy. the weather too was quite cold. I continued in it for 12 hours until I reached <name type="place">Elkton</name>, where I found I could save considerable travel in it by taking a horse there the next day &amp; going this <name type="place">Trenton</name> to <name type="place">Hopkinsville</name>, &amp; as a friend said he would lend me one, &amp; the driver of the cart promised to bring him back. I sent my valise on &amp; remained there until the next day. &amp; as I was sore all over I was glad to get out, the next day I left on horseback I rode 25 miles to <abbr expan="Hopkinsville">H.</abbr> the first part was very pleasant, but after a little which I became quite sore from that as I had not been in the habit of riding for so long, &amp; when I dismounted about dark, I was very stiff, felt worse if any thing than I did the previous night, but after a good nights sleep I felt better. I remained there the next day (yesterday) attended to my business, &amp; this mor &caret; <add place="supralinear">n</add> ing before 3 O'Clock I left in a buggy without a top, but had springs, it rained &amp; I was obliged to carry an umbrella, but it <orig reg="stopped">stoped</orig> after we had been out an hour or two &mdash; the road was excessively bad. we <pb n="[3]"/> would go first down one side then the other in the ruts, &amp; <del type="overstrike">often</del> the mud was up to the axles. I arrived here about 10 O'Clock &amp; then got my breakfast, not having had anything until then but an apple I had in my pocket. So you can form some idea how delightful it is to travel in this country at this season of the year. the cart &amp; the buggy were run instead of stages &mdash;  How do you think you would have borne it if you had come along as you wished to. you could not have lived through it, but thank God I have a strong constitution &amp; can bear a great deal of fatigue, but I congratulate myself that I am over the worst part of my journey if the <name type="place">Ohio</name> <orig reg="don't">dont</orig> freeze up before I can get up but that little word is in the way &amp; may trouble me considerably, but I have but little to do off from the rivers provided I can get along them. I have to stop at a considerable number of places, but if I h <gap reason="document damaged"/> very <emph>good luck</emph> I hope to see you about the <date value="0000-02-01">first of <abbr expan="February">Feby.</abbr></date> how glad I shall be when I get there. I want to see you so much. it will indeed be lovely when we once more get settled down in our own house again. I shall not wish to leave it again unless my dear <name type="person">Annie</name> &amp; my little <name type="person">Rebecca</name> goes with me. I look forward with a great deal of pleasure to our meeting again &mdash; I am very anxious to hear from  you as the last letter I <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr> from you was dated <date value="0000-12-02"><abbr expan="December">Dec.</abbr> 2</date>. I hope to get 2 letters when I reach <name type="place">Smithland</name> which will probably be by next Sunday. I hope &amp; trust you are all well. do take good care of yourself. be careful of your eyes. I wonder if I should know you if I should meet you in &caret; <add place="supralinear">the</add> street with you new bonnet &amp; coat on &mdash; I expect you <del type="overstrike">you</del> look very fine. have you engaged your girls yet? I think I would not take <name type="person">Wilhelmina</name> if you can get any other good girl. she stutters so bad. it is very unpleasant for me to hear her talk, but do as you think best about it &mdash; I was at the Episcopal Church this afternoon. it was rather a pretty church but a small congregation, a tolerably good minister. I expect to remain here tomorrow, then shall take the first boat down the Cumberland, <orig reg="stopping">stoping</orig> at <name type="place">Dover</name> &amp; <name type="place">Eddyville</name>, &amp; from that place shall go horseback 12 miles to <name type="place">Princeton</name>, back again <pb n="[4]"/> then to <name type="place">Smithland</name>, from there I shall go up the Ohio, stopping at several places, at some places I <orig reg="don't">dont</orig> stop as long as I ought to, but I am so anxious to get along. I hurry off. I have no doubt it would have been better for me to have remained longer in <name type="place">Nashville</name>. The day I was there (New Years) was a busy day &amp; a very anxious one for many of the poor blacks. there were 3 or 4 auctioneers in the Market house all the forenoon either selling or hiring &caret; <add place="supralinear">them</add> to the highest bidder. that is one of the worst features of the system of slavery &mdash;</p><p><add place="left of address"><date value="1844-01-09"><abbr expan="January">Jany</abbr> 9, 1844</date> I have kept this until now as the mail does not leave <abbr expan="until">till</abbr> this evening. I am now on a boat &amp; expect to leave for Dover in a few minutes. I am well. Good bye my dear one. give my love to all the members of the family &amp; a kiss to little <abbr expan="sister">sis</abbr> &mdash;</add></p><closer><salute>Yours affectionately</salute><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Charles">Chas</abbr> E. Haven</name></signed><add place="above address">25</add><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mrs. <abbr expan="Charles">Chas.</abbr> E. Haven</name></addrLine><addrLine>Care of <abbr expan="Messieurs">Mess</abbr> <name type="person"><unclear>Earps</unclear> Haven</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Philadelphia</name></addrLine><addrLine><abbr expan="Pennsylvania"><name type="place">Penn.</name></abbr></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
