<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sc062"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1835 Jun. 19, New Tazewell  [to] David Hunt, Franklin County / John Hunt: a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Hunt, John</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sc062</idno><idno>OCLC: 51314703</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1835 Jun. 19, New Tazewell [to] David Hunt, Franklin County / John Hunt</title><author>Hunt, John</author><date value="1835-06-19">June 19, 1835</date><extent>2 p</extent><note type="summary">The following document is a letter written by John Hunt in New Tazewell to his brother David in Franklin County and dated June 19, 1835.  In the letter, John explains that he plans to retire from his 18 years as sheriff and move to the  rich lands of the Missouri River.</note><note type="collection">John Hunt</note><note type="box">MS-1410</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">sc062</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/> <opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Near tazewell </name><date value="1835-06-19">June 19th 1835</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Sir</salute></opener><p>having an <orig reg="opportunity">opertunity</orig> at this time to drop you a line by <name reg="person">Mr Martin</name>  I can inform you that the family are all well at <orig reg="present">presant</orig> only <name type="person">Rhody</name> the pain in <orig reg="her">hir</orig> breast gets <orig reg="worse">wors</orig> constantly I am looking constantly for <orig reg="her">hir</orig> to take <orig reg="her">hir</orig> <unclear>bead</unclear> She Still keeps <orig reg="about">a bout</orig> the greater part of <orig reg="her">hir</orig> time I am Very much <orig reg="troubled">trobeled</orig> with pains in my Joints I have no means thats is worth communicating to you, I have had 2 letters from my children that has <orig reg="gone">gon</orig> to the <name type="place"><orig reg="missouri">mosoriee</orig></name>  the <orig reg="right">rite</orig> the have got in a <orig reg="country">contry</orig> of Rich land and is very productive fine range gain in great quality Honey plenty I intend going out there in April next to See the <orig reg="country">contry</orig> I cannot go any Sooner on the account of my business as <abbr expan="Sheriff">Shff</abbr> I will try to wind up this fall and winter I have served as Sheriff 18 years come march next and I think it is time for me to quit as I am <orig reg="getting">geting</orig> old and tired of the business <name type="person">F.S. Hunt</name> is Running for the legislator and will be Elected very Easy <name type="person">James Overton</name>  is his <orig reg="opponent">a ponant</orig> who you know has no <orig reg="talents">tallents</orig> for nothing in the world he tells the people he is a farmer and he goes for the farmers <orig reg="interests">intrusts</orig>, <unclear>ourt</unclear> crops of small grain is very much <orig reg="inferred">infered</orig> by the wet it has rained in this county Every day for 3 or 4 weeks more or less I believe <name type="person">Fidilo</name> was at <name reg="place"><orig reg="Talladega">taledego</orig></name> a <orig reg="few">fiew</orig> days Since at his <orig reg="uncle">unkle</orig> <name type="person">georges</name> the was all well he likes that <orig reg="country">contry</orig> very well please <orig reg="write">rite</orig> to me as I would be glad to hear from you give my Respects to <name type="person">John &amp; Henry Lurkins</name> all the friends it is likely I will pass <orig reg="through">throug</orig> your <orig reg="country">contry</orig> one time <orig reg="more">mor</orig> if I Ever Should get any thing of <name type="person">Mayfield</name> and if not I do not Expect Ever to See you again So I am most respectfully your brother till death</p><closer><signed><name type="person">John Hunt</name></signed><address><addrLine><name type="person">David Hunt</name></addrLine></address></closer></div1></body><back><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[2]"/><p><address><addrLine>David Hunt <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr</abbr></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Franklin county</name> near <unclear>Solemn bears</unclear> creek</addrLine></address></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
