<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sc135"> 
  <teiHeader> 
	 <fileDesc> 
		<titleStmt> 
		  <title>[Letter] 1831 Sept. 22, Warrenton, Virginia [to]  David Burford, Nashville, Tennessee / J[ourdan] M. Saunders  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title> 
		  <author> Saunders, Jourdan M.</author> 
		  <respStmt> 
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 <name>Debra Roney</name> 
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name> 
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name> 
		  </respStmt> 
		</titleStmt> 
		<publicationStmt> 
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace> 
		  <address> 
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine> 
		  </address> 
		  <date>2003 
		  </date> 
		  <idno type="SPCID">sc135</idno> 
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno> 
		  <availability> 
			 <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p> 
		  </availability> 
		</publicationStmt> 
		<sourceDesc> 
		  <bibl> 
			 <title> [Letter] 1831 Sept. 22, Warrenton, Virginia [to]  David Burford, Nashville, Tennessee / J[ourdan] M. Saunders</title> 
			 <author> Saunders, Jourdan M.</author> 
			 <date value="1831-09-22"> 
			 September 22, 1831</date> 
			 <extent> 4p</extent> 
			 <note type="summary">This document is a letter from Jourdan M. Saunders to David Burford regarding their slave-trading business. Saunders reports on their profits for the 1st quarter of 1831.</note> 
			 <note type="collection">David Burford Papers</note> 
			 <note type="box">MS-935</note> 
			 <note type="folder">n/a</note> 
			 <note type="document"> sc135</note> 
		  </bibl> 
		</sourceDesc> 
	 </fileDesc> 
	 <encodingDesc> 
		<projectDesc> 
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		</projectDesc> 
		<editorialDecl n="4"> 
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p> 
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		</editorialDecl> 
		<refsDecl> 
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		</refsDecl> 
		<classDecl> 
		  <taxonomy> 
			 <bibl> 
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
			 </bibl> 
		  </taxonomy> 
		</classDecl> 
	 </encodingDesc> 
	 <profileDesc> 
		<textClass> 
		  <keywords> 
			 <list> 
				<item>Letters</item><item>Slave trading -- American history</item><item>Virginia</item><item>Tennessee</item> 
			 </list> 
		  </keywords> 
		</textClass> 
	 </profileDesc> 
  </teiHeader> 
  <text> 
	 <body> 
		<div1 type="Letter"><pb n="1"/> 
		  <opener><address><addrLine>Warrenton <date><abbr expan="September">Sepr</abbr>. 22nd 1831</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear Burford</salute></opener><p>Having closed the business of last year with <abbr expan="Messieurs">Messr</abbr>_ <name>Franklin</name> &amp; <name>Armfreto</name>_ I have it in power to furnish you a specific account of our matter up to the 1st of April. last_ The concern of <name><abbr expan="Jourdan">J</abbr> M Saunders</name> &amp; Co made $4258.84 the half of which being $2129.42 is our part of the profits, this sum added to our former capital makes $12389_ I have delivered 17<orig> negroes</orig> to my friends in the district which will be <abbr expan="shipped">shipd</abbr> about the 1st of <abbr expan="October">Octr</abbr>. <pb n="2"/> Times are dull and slaves difficult to procure, I think however my prospect is sufficient to warrant the belief that I shall be able to do as well as I did last season which is about a fair specimen of the trade in this quarter_</p><p>I must call your attention over now to the suit in the Federal court I have been informed that you are reelected to the Legislature, and during the session it will be convenient for you <add>to</add> see that cause is put in a proper situation for trial, which I hope may take place at the next term_ The Branch of the old state Bank of <name><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name>. at <name>Clarksville</name>, owes me $123 with several years interest, I will thank you to apply to the cashier <name>Joel C Pier</name> <abbr expan="Esquire">Eqr</abbr>. for the money, you will be certain to see <pb n="3"/> him at <name>Nashville</name>, let me hear from you on your receipt of this and let me know whether or not you will be disposed to continue your funds in trade longer than this year my engagement with Franklin &amp; Co. being at the will of the parties, the firm of <abbr expan="Franklin &amp; Armfreto">F. &amp; A </abbr> will expire in the Spring of 1833 and I think it <unclear>likely</unclear> they will calculate upon my continuance until that time which as concerns myself I shall certainly do, if nothing turns up to change my present notion_</p> 
		<closer><salute><abbr expan="Your">Yr</abbr> friend</salute><signed><name>JM Saunders</name></signed><add>my capital this year is 25,000</add><pb n="4"/><add><address><addrLine>Warrenton <abbr expan="Virginia">Va </abbr><lb/> Sept 23rd <add>25</add><lb/></addrLine><addrLine><name><abbr expan="Major">Maj</abbr>. David Burford</name> <name>Nashville Tennessee</name></addrLine></address></add><add>From J. M. Saunders <lb/> <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr>. 5 October 1831 <lb/> Statement to 1st <lb/> April 1831</add></closer></div1> 
	 </body> 
  </text>
</TEI.2>
