<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sc140"> 
  <teiHeader> 
	 <fileDesc> 
		<titleStmt> 
		  <title>[Letter] 1832 Oct. 2, Warrenton, Virginia [to] D. Burford, Dixons Springs, Tennessee / J. Saunders : a machine readable transcription of an image</title> 
		  <author> Saunders, Jourdan M.</author> 
		  <respStmt> 
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 <name>Debra Roney</name> 
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name> 
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name> 
		  </respStmt> 
		</titleStmt> 
		<publicationStmt> 
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace> 
		  <address> 
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine> 
		  </address> 
		  <date>2003 
		  </date> 
		  <idno type="SPCID">sc140</idno> 
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno> 
		  <availability> 
			 <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p> 
		  </availability> 
		</publicationStmt> 
		<sourceDesc> 
		  <bibl> 
			 <title>[Letter] 1832 Oct. 2, Warrenton, Virginia [to] D. Burford, Dixons Springs, Tennessee / J. Saunders</title> 
			 <author>  Saunders, Jourdan M.</author> 
			 <date value="1832-10-02"> 
			 October 2, 1832</date> 
			 <extent>3p</extent> 
			 <note type="summary">This document is a letter dated October 2, 1832 from J. Saunders in Warrenton, Virginia  to David Burford in Dixons Spring, Tennessee.  The subject of the letter is business, specifically slave labor speculation  involving the purchase of slaves.</note> 
			 <note type="collection">David Burford Papers</note> 
			 <note type="box">MS-935</note> 
			 <note type="folder">n/a</note> 
			 <note type="document"> sc140</note> 
		  </bibl> 
		</sourceDesc> 
	 </fileDesc> 
	 <encodingDesc> 
		<projectDesc> 
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		</projectDesc> 
		<editorialDecl n="4"> 
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p> 
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		</editorialDecl> 
		<refsDecl> 
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		</refsDecl> 
		<classDecl> 
		  <taxonomy> 
			 <bibl> 
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
			 </bibl> 
		  </taxonomy> 
		</classDecl> 
	 </encodingDesc> 
	 <profileDesc> 
		<textClass> 
		  <keywords> 
			 <list> 
				<item>Tennessee -- History</item><item>Business transactions.</item><item>Slave trade</item> 
			 </list> 
		  </keywords> 
		</textClass> 
	 </profileDesc> 
  </teiHeader> 
  <text> 
	 <body> 
		<div1 type="Letter"><pb n="1"/> 
		  <opener><address><addrLine>Warrenton</addrLine></address> <date value="1832-10-02"><abbr expan="October">Octr</abbr>: 2nd 1832</date><salute>Dear Burford</salute></opener><p>Your letter of the 22nd <abbr expan="September">Sept</abbr>. countermanding your order of the 19th Same month was <abbr expan="received">red</abbr> this morning, and agreeable to your instruction, I return you the check for $1200__ having made it payable to your order__ It is impossible at this time to purchase such negroes as you want at the funds you <orig reg="authorized">authorised</orig> me in your last letter to pay__ I will however keep you advised of the state of the market whenever a charge worthy of notice occurs__ <pb n="[2]"/> I have resumed business in the small way, and will not undertake to enlarge it to any great extent until there is a change for the better in the market__ Negroes are generally lower in this country, in the latter part of the winter, than at any other season of the year, and if you should determine to try the market at any future period, my services will at all times be at your command and I would now retain your friends in anticipation of a <orig reg="favorably">favourable</orig> change in the price of slaves, but for fear of putting you to some inconvenience in the event of such a contingency not coming to pass in a reasonable time__</p> 
		<closer><add>your friend</add>  <signed><name>JM Saunders</name></signed> <pb n="[3]"/> <add>From J.M. Saunders <lb/> <date><abbr expan="October">Octr</abbr> 2__1832</date> <lb/> Warrenton <abbr expan="Virginia">Va</abbr> <date><abbr expan="October">Oct</abbr> 3rd</date> <address><addrLine><abbr expan="Major">Majr</abbr>. David Burford Dixon Spring Tennessee</addrLine></address></add></closer></div1> 
	 </body> 
  </text>
</TEI.2>
