<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sc168"> 
  <teiHeader> 
	 <fileDesc> 
		<titleStmt> 
		  <title>[Letter] 1818 Nov. 2, Fairfield [to] Ralph Earle / W. B. Lewis : a machine readable transcription of an image</title> 
		  <author> Lewis, W. B.</author> 
		  <respStmt> 
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 <name>Debra Roney</name> 
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name> 
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name> 
		  </respStmt> 
		</titleStmt> 
		<publicationStmt> 
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace> 
		  <address> 
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine> 
		  </address> 
		  <date>2003</date> 
		  <idno type="SPCID">sc168</idno> 
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno> 
		  <availability> 
			 <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p> 
		  </availability> 
		</publicationStmt> 
		<sourceDesc> 
		  <bibl> 
			 <title>[Letter] 1818 Nov. 2, Fairfield [to] Ralph Earle / W. B. Lewis</title> 
			 <author>Lewis, W. B.</author> 
			 <date value="1818-11-02">November 2, 1818</date> 
			 <extent> 2p</extent> 
			 <note type="summary">This document is a letter written by W. B. Lewis regarding orders from the Secretary of War to General Gaines. Lewis received the wrong orders and wanted the correct orders sent immediately.</note> 
			 <note type="collection">W. B. Lewis Letter</note> 
			 <note type="box">MS-856</note> 
			 <note type="folder">n/a</note> 
			 <note type="document"> sc168</note> 
		  </bibl> 
		</sourceDesc> 
	 </fileDesc> 
	 <encodingDesc> 
		<projectDesc> 
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		</projectDesc> 
		<editorialDecl n="4"> 
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p> 
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		</editorialDecl> 
		<refsDecl> 
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		</refsDecl> 
		<classDecl> 
		  <taxonomy> 
			 <bibl> 
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
			 </bibl> 
		  </taxonomy> 
		</classDecl> 
	 </encodingDesc> 
	 <profileDesc> 
		<textClass> 
		  <keywords> 
			 <list> 
				<item>Jackson, Andrew</item>
                                <item>1767-1845</item>
                                <item>Tennessee -- History</item> 
			 </list> 
		  </keywords> 
		</textClass> 
	 </profileDesc> 
  </teiHeader> 
  <text> 
	 <body> 
		<div1 type="Letter"><pb n="1"/> 
		  <opener><address><addrLine>Fairfield</addrLine></address><date><abbr expan="November">Nov</abbr>. 2nd 1818</date><salute><abbr expan="Dear">D</abbr>.Sir</salute></opener><p>The order which you sent me by Sam is not the order or orders that I wanted. Those that I wrote for, or those that I thought I wrote for, were from the Secretary of War to <name><abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr><orig reg="Gaines"> Gains</orig></name> and referred to by the Secretary of War in his order to <name><abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr>. Jackson</name>. I had the order you sent me; but I want those from the Secretary to Genl Gains, which I think are 4 or 5 in number.</p><p>I am anxious to get them in time to take copies before <name><abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr>. Butler </name>and <name>Doctor Brunaugh</name> <orig reg="leaves">leavs</orig> <name>Nashville</name> for the city, as I wish to send them to <name>Major Eaton</name> by them. Do not mistake me; the orders I want are from the Secretary of War to Genl. Gains, and perhaps, 4 or 5 in number_ Send me all of that discerption <pb n="2"/> you can find among the Genl's papers. The packages addressed to Col. Butler and the Doctor shall be attended to as by you requested.</p> 
		    <closer><salute>I have the honor to be very respectfully Sir, your<abbr expan="obedient servant"> Obt. Servt</abbr>.</salute><signed><name>W. B. Lewis</name></signed></closer></div1> 
	 </body> 
  </text>
</TEI.2>
