<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sc193"> 
  <teiHeader> 
	 <fileDesc> 
		<titleStmt> 
		  <title>[Deposition]  1795 Jun. 2, Knox County Court / [witnessed by] G. Roulstone : a machine readable transcription of an image</title> 
		  <author>Roulstone, G. </author> 
		  <respStmt> 
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 <name>Debra Roney</name> 
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name> 
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name> 
		  </respStmt> 
		</titleStmt> 
		<publicationStmt> 
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace> 
		  <address> 
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine> 
		  </address> 
		  <date>2003 
		  </date> 
		  <idno type="SPCID">sc193</idno> 
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno> 
		  <availability> 
			 <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p> 
		  </availability> 
		</publicationStmt> 
		<sourceDesc> 
		  <bibl> 
			 <title>[Deposition]  1795 Jun. 2, Knox County Court / [witnessed by] G. Roulstone </title> 
			 <author> Roulstone, G. </author><date value="1795-06-02">June 2, 1795</date> 
			 <extent>1p</extent> 
			 <note type="summary">This document is a deposition in a case where John Allen Smith Carrington assaulted George Martins after a verbal dispute.</note> 
			 <note type="collection">Carrington Deposition</note> 
			 <note type="box">MS-1826</note> 
			 <note type="folder">n/a</note> 
			 <note type="document"> sc193</note> 
		  </bibl> 
		</sourceDesc> 
	 </fileDesc> 
	 <encodingDesc> 
		<projectDesc> 
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		</projectDesc> 
		<editorialDecl n="4"> 
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p> 
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		</editorialDecl> 
		<refsDecl> 
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		</refsDecl> 
		<classDecl> 
		  <taxonomy> 
			 <bibl> 
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
			 </bibl> 
		  </taxonomy> 
		</classDecl> 
	 </encodingDesc> 
	 <profileDesc> 
		<textClass> 
		  <keywords> 
			 <list> 
				<item>Tennessee -- History</item><item>Assault and battery</item><item>Depositions</item> 
			 </list> 
		  </keywords> 
		</textClass> 
	 </profileDesc> 
  </teiHeader> 
  <text> 
	 <body> 
		<div1 type="Legal document"><pb n="1"/> 
		  <p>The Deponant <name><abbr expan="John Allen Smith">J.A.S</abbr>. Carrington</name> Happening to Beat <name>George Martins</name> on the Evening of the <date>Seventh of may 95</date> Where, <add place="supralinear">there</add> was <name>Samuel Hammons</name>, and Samuel and William McEvine Dworting Themselves for some time, in the water, then Coming in to the house and Beginning with Some Rough Language, Which Consisted of Profaine <orig reg="swearing">Swairing</orig> for which Said Martin <abbr expan="Reprimanded">Reprid</abbr> them for, which <orig reg="enraged">inraged</orig>, <name>William McEvine</name> that he flung out of the House. then Calling Said Martin a <orig reg="damned">Damnd</orig> Weavel Eater of Haskel. and if he had him out of the House he Would Drown him in the River. then <abbr expan="Misses">Mrs</abbr> martin Coming to the Door Said too William McEvine it would be as good for him to give another Button too a <orig reg="Negro">Neagro</orig> than Come there to quarrel with the old Man.  Which was all that Passed </p> 
		<closer><signed>J.A. Harrington</signed> <add>This day personally appeared before me <name>John Allen Smith Carrington</name>, who being duly sworn deposed that the testimony above received is just &amp; true subscribed before me, <name>G Roulstone</name>, Commissioner of affidavits__</add></closer></div1> 
	 </body> 
  </text>
</TEI.2>
