<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sc238"> 
  <teiHeader> 
	 <fileDesc> 
		<titleStmt> 
		  <title>[Legal document] 1788 Nov. 17, Washington District, North Carolina  [Warrant for man accused of stealing slaves] : a machine readable transcription of an image</title> 
		   
		  <respStmt> 
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 <name>Debra Roney</name> 
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name> 
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name> 
		  </respStmt> 
		</titleStmt> 
		<publicationStmt> 
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace> 
		  <address> 
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine> 
		  </address> 
		  <date>2003 
		  </date> 
		  <idno type="SPCID">sc238</idno> 
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno> 
		  <availability> 
			 <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p> 
		  </availability> 
		</publicationStmt> 
		<sourceDesc> 
		  <bibl> 
			 <title>[Legal document] 1788 Nov. 17, Washington District, North Carolina  [Warrant for man accused of stealing slaves]</title> 
			  
			 <date value="1788-11-17"> 
			 November 17, 1788</date> 
			 <extent>5p</extent> 
			 <note type="summary">This document is a warrant dated November 17, 1788 for the arrest of Micager Crews and an unknown woman who are accused of stealing slaves from an unknown person.</note> 
			 <note type="collection">Washington District Warrant</note> 
			 <note type="box">New Accessions</note> 
			 <note type="folder">n/a</note> 
			 <note type="document"> sc238</note> 
		  </bibl> 
		</sourceDesc> 
	 </fileDesc> 
	 <encodingDesc> 
		<projectDesc> 
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		</projectDesc> 
		<editorialDecl n="4"> 
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p> 
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		</editorialDecl> 
		<refsDecl> 
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		</refsDecl> 
		<classDecl> 
		  <taxonomy> 
			 <bibl> 
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
			 </bibl> 
		  </taxonomy> 
		</classDecl> 
	 </encodingDesc> 
	 <profileDesc> 
		<textClass> 
		  <keywords> 
			 <list> 
				<item>Legal documents</item><item>Slaves</item><item>Slave trade</item><item>North Carolina</item> 
			 </list> 
		  </keywords> 
		</textClass> 
	 </profileDesc> 
  </teiHeader> 
  <text> 
	 <body> 
		<div1 type="Legal document"><pb n="1"/> 
		  <opener><address><addrLine>North Carolina <lb/> Washington County &rcub;</addrLine></address></opener><p>Ninion Hoskins complains To me on Oath that from Information from <unclear>in a <orig reg="clandestined">clendentant</orig></unclear> Manner that there Is a Certain Micager Crews in this  Neighborhood with Two Negroes fellows &amp; a wench that  are Stolen From some Where the Owner yet__ unknown <add>when</add> &amp; that the <unclear><name>Alea Frasier</name></unclear> <name>Elisha Hoskins</name> &amp; <unclear><name>William Kanady</name></unclear>  are concerned with <unclear>him in sd</unclear> matter  These are therefore in the name of The state to <abbr expan="command">commd</abbr>. you &amp; every of you to__ Take the Bodies of the said <name>Micager Crews</name>   Alea Frasier <name>Elisha Hoskins</name> &amp; <name>William Kanady</name> if to be found in <abbr expan="Your">Yr</abbr>. Bailiwick &amp; in case they are escaping that you <unclear>pursue</unclear> from county to county from state to state as well by <unclear>Footmen</unclear> or Horse the also the <abbr expan="said">sd</abbr> Negroes &amp; them safely keep <pb n="[2]"/> so that you have them Before some justices or justices of our said county of  Washington <add><unclear>such other Equity of</unclear></add> that they may be <orig reg="Dealt">Delt</orig> with as the Law Directs &amp; this shall be Your Wards for the same given under my Hand this Thirtieth Day of June 1788</p> 
		<closer>To all <orig reg="Lawful">Lawfull</orig> sheriffs &amp; constables the &amp; Capt.__ Rowland Jenkins Deputed officer__ <signed>Richard White</signed><pb n="[3]"/><add>The State vs <lb/> Crews Frasier <lb/> Hoskins &amp; Kanady <lb/> Executed on Crews <lb/> &amp; two Negroes the <lb/> fellow escaped Crews <lb/> &amp; <unclear>wench bro</unclear> Before <lb/><abbr expan="Richard">Ricd</abbr> White <lb/> first <lb/> Day of July 1788 <lb/> Rowland Jenkins <lb/> Deputy Constable</add><pb n="4"/><add>The State of North Carolina Washington County Whereas Micager Crews Hath this day Having been Brought Before me on <orig reg="Suspicion">Suspition</orig> of  Stealing Two Negroes a fellow &amp; wench they named Jack &amp; Nanei and on examination He appears guilty of said charge These are therefore in the name of sd. <unclear>day</unclear> to <abbr expan="commission">comm</abbr>. all Sheriffs &amp;c Has this <abbr expan="Monday">Mondy</abbr> of the said Micager Crew Together With the Wench Nanei Now in Custody <orig reg="Until">Untill</orig> you shall deliver them into the <orig reg="Jail">Goal</orig> of Washington District the <orig reg="Jailer">Goaler</orig> of the said Goal are <unclear>kurese</unclear> commd. to Receive them into your said Goal &amp; Safely keep as so to provide that you Have them Before the Judge or Judges of our District of Washington <add>on the next court that shall be held for sd District</add> &amp; this shall be your <unclear>Dist.</unclear> for the same Given under my hand this first day of July one thousand seven hundred &amp; eighty eight </add> <add>To all Sheriffs Constables &amp;c <lb/>&amp; Captain Rowland Jenkins <lb/> Deputed Officer <lb/> Belonging to said District </add><signed>Richard White</signed><pb n="5"/><add>The State vs Crews</add><add>July 4 Day 1788 <lb/> then came to prison</add></closer></div1> 
	 </body> 
  </text>
</TEI.2>
