<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/dtds/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sc251"> 
  <teiHeader> 
	 <fileDesc> 
		<titleStmt> 
		  <title> [Letter] 1848 Jul. 17, Independence, Texas [to] Louiza G. Flemming, Mount Pleasant, Murry County, Tennessee / N.A. Gee : a machine readable transcription of an image</title> 
		  <author> Gee, N.A.</author> 
		  <respStmt> 
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 <name>Debra Roney</name> 
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name> 
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name> 
		  </respStmt> 
		</titleStmt> 
		<publicationStmt> 
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace> 
		  <address> 
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine> 
		  </address> 
		  <date>2003</date> 
		  <idno type="SPCID">sc251</idno> 
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno> 
		  <availability> 
			 <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p> 
		  </availability> 
		</publicationStmt> 
		<sourceDesc> 
		  <bibl> 
			 <title> [Letter] 1848 Jul. 17, Independence, Texas [to] Louiza G. Flemming, Mount Pleasant, Murry County, Tennessee / N.A. Gee</title> 
			 <author> Gee, N.A.</author> 
			 <date value="1848-07-17"> 
			 July 17, 1848</date> 
			 <extent>4p</extent> 
			 <note type="summary">This is a letter from N.A. Gee to his sister Louiza, dated July 17, 1848. He writes about several deaths in his family and his remarriage. Most of the letter regards the division of their family estate, including that of two female slaves.</note> 
			 <note type="collection">N.A. Gee Papers</note> 
			 <note type="box">New Accessions</note> 
			 <note type="folder">n/a</note> 
			 <note type="document"> sc251</note> 
		  </bibl> 
		</sourceDesc> 
	 </fileDesc> 
	 <encodingDesc> 
		<projectDesc> 
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		</projectDesc> 
		<editorialDecl n="4"> 
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p> 
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		</editorialDecl> 
		<refsDecl> 
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		</refsDecl> 
		<classDecl> 
		  <taxonomy> 
			 <bibl> 
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
			 </bibl> 
		  </taxonomy> 
		</classDecl> 
	 </encodingDesc> 
	 <profileDesc> 
		<textClass> 
		  <keywords> 
			 <list> 
				<item>Southern States</item> 
			 <item>Family communication</item><item>Estate planning</item></list> 
		  </keywords> 
		</textClass> 
	 </profileDesc> 
  </teiHeader> 
  <text> 
	 <body> 
		<div1 type="letter"><pb n="1"/> 
		  <opener><address><addrLine><name>Caldwell</name> <date>July 17th 1848</date></addrLine></address><salute>Dear sister</salute></opener><p>I take my pen in hand to <orig reg="write">Rite</orig> to you to Inform you that my self and family are all well at present hoping that those lines may find you and family <orig reg="Enjoying">Injoying</orig> the same I have had some misfortunes in my family I lost my wife last December Henry Died last January John died Last wednesday <orig reg="night">knight</orig> ) <del type="overstrike">the</del> <unclear>Mr</unclear> and <name><abbr expan="Squire">Sqr</abbr> Lewis</name> has divided the land you get six hundred and forty I get three hundred and sixty seven Lewis and my self Left it to five good men agreeable to the Ritings between Brother and my self and the Estate fell in my Debt fifteen hundred dollars besides the money I paid <name>Brother Claburn</name> for them negroes when he was out here which was twelve hundred dollars and I have Receipts in his own hand Rite to show that I paid it I dont want any thing of you and the children only what is <orig reg="right">Rite</orig> between us If you are a mind to keep that negro <orig reg="girl">gurl</orig> Martha <pb n="[2]"/> and give me this one <orig reg="here">heare</orig> you can <orig reg="do">doo</orig> so this one heare has two children and they can go in for the negro man that Brother was to <orig reg="buy">bye</orig> for me if we have to go to law about the property it will cost us more than the property is worth sister I think its hard for you to try to keep me out of my money and give it to Lewis <name>Mr McClinchy</name> Gives Lewis ten per cent which will amount to about fifteen hundred dollars Crops is fine here I will make about fifty Bales of cotton and a great <orig reg="deal">deel</orig> of Corn I am <orig reg="married">maried</orig> to a <name>Miss Oldham</name> from the western <orig reg="district">destrict</orig> <name>Tennessee</name> Rite to me on the Reception of this letter Rite to me <orig reg="where">whor</orig> sister Nancy lives and how they are all <orig reg="getting">gitting</orig> along the county she lives in and the post office so that I can Rite to <orig reg="her">hur</orig> Give my leave to the children all and</p> 
		<closer><salute>Receive my Best wishes your self</salute><signed>N.A. Gee</signed><address><addrLine><name>Louiza G Flemming</name></addrLine></address><add><abbr expan="nota bene">NB</abbr> Direct your letter to <name>Burlesson county</name> Caldwell post office sister I <orig reg="don't">dount</orig> want to go to low if we <gap/> and if we do I <sic>dount dount</sic> <orig reg="want">wount</orig> you to get mad with me because I always <pb n="[3]"/> <unclear><orig reg="thought">thaut</orig> a hope</unclear> of you I paid Brother every <orig reg="cent">sent</orig> I <orig reg="owed">ood</orig> him when he <orig reg="was">wous</orig> out <orig reg="here">her</orig> for god <orig reg="knows">knoys</orig> I paid him <add>evry</add> and <unclear>cant</unclear> <add>and I</add> prove it by Mr  Irons <add>and</add> others I dount think but what you <orig reg="believe">beleave</orig> that I did <add>Caldwell</add></add>  <pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine><name>Independence</name> <name>Texas</name></addrLine><addrLine><date>21 July 1848</date></addrLine></address><address><addrLine>Mrs Louiza G Fleming</addrLine><addrLine><name>Mount <orig reg="Pleasant">Plesant</orig> <abbr expan="Post Office">Po</abbr></name></addrLine><addrLine><name>Murry County</name></addrLine><addrLine>Tennessee</addrLine></address></closer></div1> 
	 </body> 
  </text>
</TEI.2>
