<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl123">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1838 Nov 17, Clover Dale, TN [to] Mrs. Ann Jane Bell, Cornplanter, PA / Sarah Bell   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Bell, Sarah</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl123</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50591323</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1838 Nov 17, Clover Dale, TN [to] Mrs. Ann Jane Bell, Cornplanter, PA / Sarah Bell</title>
               <author>Bell, Sarah</author>
               <date when="1838-11-17">November 17, 1838</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Sarah Bell to her sister Ann Jane Bell dated Nov. 17, 1838. Sarah writes of her recent illness, and the death of woman from consumption. She hopes that Jane is better from her illness. She regrets not being able to visit Jane and nurse her back to health every time she is sick. Sarah writes of the repairs and improvements that are being done to the house in preparation for winter. She writes of what they have been producing on the farm. She mentions the efforts to build a church in Charlotte and of a recent camp meeting. Her favorite preacher, Mr. Marshal will be the permanent preacher now, and this pleases her very much. She includes some briefs about the neighbors, and inquiries from their parents.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl123</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Religious gatherings</term>
               <term>Religious facilities</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Bell, Sarah</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl123a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Clover Dale</name> . <date when="1838-11-17">November 17.th 1838</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sister</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have wished to write you before this, yet I  put it off from day to day, thinking I  had nothing to say that would interest you, but as William speaks of going to preaching in <name type="place">Charlotte</name>
               <choice>
                  <orig>to morrow</orig>
                  <reg>tomorrow</reg>
               </choice> I thought I would take the <choice>
                  <orig>oppertunity</orig>
                  <reg>opportunity</reg>
               </choice> offered, and write you a few lines believing that a letter from us would afford you pleasure, if there was not much in it. When <name type="person">Margaret</name> wrote you last I was very sick, it was the first time I ever wished to see <name type="person">Dr. Carter</name> when I was sick; I was so very sick in two hours after I was first taken, that I was very willing he should be sent for, you know his manner of laughing and saying he expects you are only playing <choice>
                  <orig>possom</orig>
                  <reg>possum</reg>
               </choice>, but when he felt my pulse, he was candid and said I was very sick, the next time he came back I was much better he asked me if I had thought I was going to die, I said no for I did not think I should die then. But I have great cause to be thankful that I recovered so soon, for many that was taken sick about the same time, lingered much longer and some are since dead. Your friend <unclear>
                  <name type="person">Mrs. Ingrum (Cathrin Clemmens</name>
               </unclear> that was) died last Month at <name type="person">Mr. Robert West</name> on her way to Charlotte, like most persons that have <del type="overstrike">the</del> the consumption, think ⁁ <add place="supralinear">a</add> change of place will benefit them, she thought if she could only get <choice>
                  <orig>too</orig>
                  <reg>to</reg>
               </choice> her sisters <pb n="2" facs="sl123b.small.jpg"/> she would ⁁ <add place="supralinear">be</add> well, I have not heard the particulars of her death I have not seen <name type="person">Mrs. Collier</name> since, but understood she was much distressed. I hope you are <unclear>gronewell</unclear>,  I often think of you since I heard you were sick and wish I was near enough to go and nurse you which I would wish to do whenever you are sick, yet that is almost out of the question, The house and yard has been all out of fix for two weeks past, <choice>
                  <orig>puting</orig>
                  <reg>putting</reg>
               </choice> sills under the back and front part of the house, puting a new floor and <choice>
                  <orig>raleings</orig>
                  <reg>railings</reg>
               </choice> in  the porch, and <choice>
                  <orig>wetherbording</orig>
                  <reg>weatherboarding</reg>
               </choice> a part of the house, which adds both to looks and comfort. William is now <choice>
                  <orig>haueling</orig>
                  <reg>hauling</reg>
               </choice> logs to the saw mill to make planks to floor the garret over, he is much in the spirit of <choice>
                  <orig>improveing</orig>
                  <reg>improving</reg>
               </choice> the place, when you come you will hardly know the place. <choice>
                  <abbr>Mag</abbr>
                  <expan>Margaret</expan>
               </choice> says she is now ready for the flower seeds and roots you promised to send her  she wants the tulip and wallflower to bloom in <name type="place">Dickson</name>before she leaves it, the drouth killed all our flowers that we have no seed though it is so cold I have to write by the fire, we have a beautiful box of white <choice>
                  <orig>Chrissantheum</orig>
                  <reg>Chrysanthemum</reg>
               </choice> in full bloom. Mother says she <choice>
                  <orig>pitties</orig>
                  <reg>pities</reg>
               </choice> you if it is colder there than it is here. We have our new carpet on the floor, which is the admiration of the <choice>
                  <orig>neighbourhood</orig>
                  <reg>neighborhood</reg>
               </choice>, it is very pretty for a rag carpet. Caroline wove 16  yards of girting last week, which is as good as store girting. And William had some leather tan<add place="supralinear">n</add>ed of which he has made each of us fine double <add place="supralinear">reign</add> bridles so you see we have become quite <choice>
                  <orig>econnomical</orig>
                  <reg>economical</reg>
               </choice>. <pb n="3" facs="sl123c.small.jpg"/> They are trying to build a church in Charlotte, but I am afraid they will not succeed, there is but $500 subscribed yet. <name type="person">Mr. Mar<del type="overstrike">tial</del>
                  <add place="supralinear">shal</add>
               </name> our favorite preacher moves to this County next month, so we will have the pleasure of hearing him preach oftener, I would rather hear him converse with mourners than  hear any other person p<add place="supralinear">r</add>each. On Monday night of our campmeeting, there were two young ladies very much affected and went in to the <choice>
                  <orig>alter</orig>
                  <reg>altar</reg>
               </choice>, their Mother took them out and was opposed to their getting religion she let them come back under <add place="supralinear">the</add> stand, Mr. <choice>
                  <orig>Martial</orig>
                  <reg>Marshal</reg>
               </choice> knelt by them, and exacted and prayed more fervently than I ever heard any person, I was <choice>
                  <orig>siting</orig>
                  <reg>sitting</reg>
               </choice> by  them and became deeply interested in them and prayed that they might be converted. that night I received a stronger <choice>
                  <orig>manisfitation</orig>
                  <reg>manefestation</reg>
               </choice> of my being <choice>
                  <orig>forgivin</orig>
                  <reg>forgiven</reg>
               </choice>
               <unclear>me</unclear> than I ever had before <name type="person">Mrs. Caldwell</name> has a pain in her nose which is very severe some times, she is very much alarmed and fears it is a cancer <name type="person">Mr. Mill's</name> Sister <choice>
                  <orig>inlaw</orig>
                  <reg>in-law</reg>
               </choice> moved near here last month she has three daughters two of them are grown and quite intel<add place="supralinear">l</add>igent My Father wishes <choice>
                  <orig>too</orig>
                  <reg>to</reg>
               </choice> know how many tons of iron you have made this year his health is very good this summer and fall and looks much better than he did last year. Mother wishes to know  how many comforts you have made Wm. wrote to brother Sam last week. It is <choice>
                  <orig>geting</orig>
                  <reg>getting</reg>
               </choice> late so I must bid you good night. They all join me in love to you all</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>'Ever your affectionate sister</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Sarah Bell</name>.</signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl123d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="top, right of address">25</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Charlotte <choice>
                        <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1838-11-20">Nov 20. 1838 </date>
                     <add>}</add>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mrs. Ann Jane Bell</name>.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Cornplanter</name>.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Venango County</name>.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Pa.</abbr>
                           <expan>Pennsylvania</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
