<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="gc054">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1849 Nov. 30, Alexandria, Louisiana [to] James King / Thomas Moore : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Moore, Thomas</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harding</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>gc054</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1849 Nov. 30, Alexandria, Louisiana [to] James King / Thomas Moore</title>
               <author>Moore, Thomas</author>
               <date when="1849-11-30">November 30, 1849</date>
               <extent> 4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated November 30, 1849 from Thomas Moore to his cousin James King.  In the letter Moore criticizes King for his political views associated with the Whig party and urges him to repudiate them before God and his fellow countrymen.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">James Moore King Papers Correspondence, 1849</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">7</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">gc054</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Slavery</term>
               <term>Comunication in the family</term>
               <term>Louisiana</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n93014550"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Moore, Thomas Overton, 1804-1876</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="gc054a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>near Alexandria</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>30th <choice>
                     <abbr>Nov</abbr>
                     <expan>November</expan>
                  </choice>. 1849</date>
               <salute>Dear <choice>
                     <abbr>Col</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <add>Answered 25th January 1850</add>
            </opener>
            <p> I <choice>
                  <abbr>red</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice> a letter from Sarah under date of 10th <choice>
                  <abbr>inst</abbr>
                  <expan>instant</expan>
               </choice>. informing me of the decision of the suit for those negroes that went against her, which I exceedingly regret, poor Sarah! the case is nolly a hard one.</p>
            <p>She wishes me to aid her in purchasing them at the sale which she writes takes place on the 10th April next, I am at this moment in the worst possible condition to assist her, having undergone this year an enormous expense of building my larger house, &amp; purchasing mill &amp; engine &amp; other fixtures which will cost me at least Fifteen Thousand dollars, and my crop a small one for want of a <choice>
                  <orig>sufficent</orig>
                  <reg>sufficient</reg>
               </choice> quantity of seed came last spring to plant, I shall grind only 130 acres which is very grim in <choice>
                  <orig>consequince</orig>
                  <reg>consequence</reg>
               </choice> of the warm winter &amp; shall make about 200 hogsheads &amp; 400 barrels of molasses, my cane would have been perfectly good for 300 hogsheads with an ordinary winter, it looks now as grim &amp; fresh as it did in July.</p>
            <p>Relative to the negroes, are they valuable? and could not others be bought for the same <choice>
                  <abbr>amt</abbr>
                  <expan>amount</expan>
               </choice> of money that would be more valuable, and yield a better revenue than they would?  Sarah's Condition will not advert  of his purchasing negroes mainly because they are family negoes, without regard to this efficiency as hands, if she purchases at all, the advantages resulting from that purchase  should be the main consideration, and <add>it</add> should be such a one as would <pb n="2" facs="gc054b.small.jpg"/> be profitable.  If I am correct  in my views among this family, Fanny and children, there are several that is of no service at this time and will not be for some time to come, why then purchase negroes from which no revenue can be derived, I suppose one negro would do Brothers probably as well as another, as I presume he is too indolent for any use.</p>
            <p>Please write me the age &amp;  size &amp; appearance of all the family and what you consider the fair value of each one (please get Butler's aid in doing so) and whether you believe they would be worth as much to Sarah the the same <choice>
                  <abbr>amt</abbr>
                  <expan>amount</expan>
               </choice>. of money invested in other negroes.  My situation is not easy at this moment in consequence of what I stated above, but I can always command money <add>if </add> I should want it, but it worse than useless for Sarah to want property that can not support itself. Write me fully on the subject.</p>
            <p>I have  been <choice>
                  <orig>corupted</orig>
                  <reg>corrupted</reg>
               </choice> to do a heavy years labor, I have made 680,000 brick and put up a <choice>
                  <orig>sury</orig>
                  <reg>surrey</reg>
               </choice> as  house 45 feet wide &amp; 250 long &amp; cane shed 70 by 100 feet, split out 75,000 boards &amp; made my crop, and raining all the years if you can beat that, Come down &amp; be my neighbor &amp; I believe I could let out one more <unclear>brick</unclear>.  I have the satisfaction of having a <choice>
                  <abbr>d-m</abbr>
                  <expan>damn</expan>
               </choice> fine establishment if it breaks me, besides all this, I have worked hard in assisting to elect my old friend &amp; neighbor <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice>.<pb n="3" facs="gc054c.small.jpg"/> Walker <choice>
                  <abbr>Govn</abbr>
                  <expan>Governor</expan>
               </choice>. of our state, a victory that tells "old Zack" he should never make a promise that his ministry will not permit him to fulfil, &amp; tells the whigs never again to run a man for that high station that had not two political ideas in <add>his</add> head, and indeed thought so little about such things as to never cast but one vote, poor "Old Zach." the our <choice>
                  <orig>eigth</orig>
                  <reg>eighth</reg>
               </choice> of a pish, as I know you are ashamed of him I will say no more, as I feel as if you were now are the stout of repentance, &amp; would soon pray to your god &amp; your countrymen to forgive your for all your political sins, I for one will say Amen, to that prayer &amp; forgive you, on conditions that you so solemnly pledge yourself to <unclear>abjour</unclear> coonery &amp; <unclear>Coundorm</unclear> and become a good servant, as I have not had it in my power to enjoy your company long at a time in this world, let me hope that you will hence forward so conduct yourself politically that you will be able to meet me in that Land of promise of which we have heard so much, &amp; if my religion is right I fear I shall not but few of my whig friends there, then Col. repent &amp; stand up to the divine rack fodders or not fodder, &amp; write me &amp; let me know your feelings &amp; what you saw at the time of your conversion, in short, give me your experience in full, as I should like to know the feelings of a sinful old coon where he changes his political sins, for that of the True Faith- enough.  I expect Four Butler &amp; family down this winter-Come you &amp; yours.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="gc054d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>I cant say when I shall be able to visit <choice>
                  <abbr/>
                  <expan>Tennessee</expan>
               </choice>. again but I fear not soon, as I have a great deal more trouble with the <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>est</abbr>
                     <expan>establishment</expan>
                  </choice>
               </unclear> of  others those my <unclear>own</unclear>.</p>
            <p>Pen Sarah &amp; state the contents of my letter to her, &amp; write me, I will then conclude what to do.  My love to cousin O. &amp; family Tom &amp; family &amp; all my relations &amp; friends and <unclear>remember</unclear> me to he as ever.</p>
            <closer>Your Friend &amp; relative <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Tho</abbr>
                     <expan>Thomas</expan>
                  </choice>, O, Moore</signed>
               <add>Tell Tom the Doctor has been elected to the senate whether <gap agent="damage"/> good or not I dont know his family will spend the winter with me</add>
               <add>mis-she-gander Mis. she-gander</add>
               <add>25th <choice>
                     <abbr>Jany</abbr>
                     <expan>January</expan>
                  </choice> 1850 Names of Sarah Brothers Negro Woman &amp; Children Fanny-Years 36-Worth $350 &amp; 1 Mariah [years] 18- [worth] 650 2 Easles [years] 14- [worth] 450 3 Eady- [years] 11- [worth] 400 4 Henry- [years] 7- [worth] 350 5 Harrott- [years] - [worth] 250 6 Boy- [years] 6m [worth] 100 </add>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Thos</abbr>
                     <expan>Thomas</expan>
                  </choice>. O. Moore (Sarah Brother's negroe)</add>
               <add>1849</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
