<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl602">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1829 Sep. 1, Winchester, Tennessee [to] William Hall / Micah Tane : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Tane, Micah </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl602</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1829 Sep. 1, Winchester, Tennessee [to] William Hall / Micah Tane</title>
               <author> Tane, Micah</author>
               <date when="1829-09-01"> 
			 September 1, 1829</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated September 1, 1829 from Micah Tane, writing from Winchester, Tennessee, to the acting governor of the state, William Hall.  In the letter he tells the governor of the brutal murder of his son Thomas P. Tane by Rufuss K. Anderson.  He asks the governor to use his position and influence to assist in the apprehension of Anderson, believed to be in Alabama.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor William Hall Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl602</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Murder victims</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Tane, Micah</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl602a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Winchester, <choice>
                        <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Sept</abbr>
                     <expan>September</expan>
                  </choice>. 1st 1829</date>
               <salute>His Excellency <name>William Hall</name>
                  <lb/> acting Governor of the State of Tennessee</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>My son <name>Thomas P. Tane</name>, was most cruelly murdered, in this place on the 24th instant by <name>Rufuss K. Anderson</name> of <name>Alabama</name>
            </p>
            <p>The Murderer and the deceased, were personally strangers to each other__</p>
            <p>My son was confident from the first that the wound was mortal; &amp; solemnly stated on his dying bed, that when he saw the Murderer approaching him he supposed he was a madman, and that he went into the house, at the door of which he was standing toward him that he did not see the Pistol <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> it was within two or three feet of his body__ He then threw forward his hand to get hold of it__ &amp; at the same moment  <del>his right</del> the Murderer fired__ His right arm was burned between the hand &amp; wrist, by the fire from the pistol.  The Murderer has fled, &amp; I pray your Excellency, to address the Governors of the several States, particularly <name>Alabama</name> to cause harm to be apprehended &amp; brought to justice      <name>Micah Tane</name>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl602b.small.jpg"/> I further state from the information of others, which I believe to be true, that there is no doubt of the part, that the Murderer came from <name>Perkins County</name>
               <name>Alabama</name>, to this place for the express purpose of committing the murder.   His father &amp; other relations reside in this place &amp; its neighborhood The night before his arrival home, I am informed &amp; believe, he stayed at the home of <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Tho</abbr>
                     <expan>Thomas</expan>
                  </choice> Miller</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Eqr</abbr>
                  <expan>Esquire</expan>
               </choice> in Alabama, distant about 25 miles from this place__ At which time &amp; place, he had no <unclear>portman team</unclear>, in saddle bags or baggage of any description He was travelling on Horseback. <lb/>
               <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>M</abbr>
                     <expan>Micah</expan>
                  </choice>. Tane</name>.  </p>
            <p>Micah Tane, this day personally appeared before the undersigned justice of the peace of said county &amp; made oath that the within &amp; above statements are true  <unclear>
                  <name>Saml norwood JP</name>
               </unclear>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl602c.small.jpg"/> His Excellency <name>William Hall</name> acting <choice>
                  <abbr>Govr</abbr>
                  <expan>Governor</expan>
               </choice> of the State of <name>Tennessee</name>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
