<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0041">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> [Letter] 1824 Apr. 20, Washington City [to] Jno. [i.e., John] C. Calhoun, Secretary of War / Jno [i.e., John] Ross : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Ross, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harden</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0041</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1824 Apr. 20, Washington City [to] Jno. [i.e., John] C. Calhoun, Secretary of War / Jno [i.e., John] Ross</title>
               <author>Ross, John</author>
               <date when="1824-04-20">April 20, 1824</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated April 20, 1824, written by John Ross to John C. Calhoun, US Secretary of War.  Ross writes in complaint of a reservation given to John Spears which encroaches upon  the land of Lewis Ross, given to him under the terms of the Treaty of 1819.  Ross asks for further investigation into the matter.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">pa0041</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letter</term>
               <term>Ross, John, 1790-1866</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Claims</term>
               <term>Washington (D.C.)</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n82214557"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Ross, John, 1790-1866</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0041a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Washington City</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1824-04-20">April 20th 1824</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Honble Jno.</abbr>
                           <expan>Honorable John</expan>
                        </choice> C. Calhoun</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Secretary of War.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>When I last had the honor of an interview with you <choice>
                  <orig>accompanyed</orig>
                  <reg>accompanied</reg>
               </choice>  by <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl.</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Houston</name>,  you will recollect that I laid before you a plat of <name>Lewis Ross</name>' reservation as run out agreeably to its location by the treaty of 1819.  And also exhibiting the survey as made by the United States Surveyor Agreeably to your Order, in Consequence of <name>John Spears</name> setting up a claim for a life <add>estate</add> reservation.  And also the surveys made under the authority of the State of <name>Tennessee</name>  ,  by which you will discover the survey as made for John Spears <add>under your order</add> came in contact with a part of Lewis Ross' claim as seemed to him by Treaty. <pb n="2" facs="pa0041b.small.jpg"/>   and that the reservation laid off for John Spears was sectioned off &amp; sold by State of Tennessee, in consequence of these circumstances, a part of Lewis Ross'  claim is involved by litigation with Spears and the State of Tennessee.  in addition  to the verbal statements made to you by Genl. Houston on the subject of Spears' claim for a reservation, I beg leave to lay before you <add>a copy of</add> his letter  to me on the subject_ And I am requested by Lewis Ross to say that when these facts are made known, that you will at once see that  he has been unjustly led into <add>useless</add> difficulties and expense by the representations made to the Department in favor of Spears' claim, and as it cannot be the intention of the Government to make the reservations of less value than contemplated by the parties under the provision of the Treaty stipulation, nor to subject them to unnecessary litigation in law,  it is confidently expected that you will reinvestigate the <pb n="3" facs="pa0041c.small.jpg"/> subject in the end that the land reserved to him under the Treaty of 1819.  may be secured to him without further Trouble &amp; expense, or otherwise should the Government insist that Spears ought to have a reservation he would be willing to surrender his claim altogether provided the  Government would pay him a reasonable price for it; or else pay him the value of the difference of the land as secured to him by Treaty and as laid off for him by your Order in consequence of Spear's claim- these propositions I am directed to state, are made solely with the view and a desire to be freed from an unjust and an unnecessary law suit, produced by the Contravening claim allowed to Spears by the Government_ I therefore beg your early attention and decision of the subject.  I beg leave further to add that on my arrival in this City, I handed you a letter from <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jas.</abbr>
                     <expan>James</expan>
                  </choice> Brown</name> in relation to <name>Charles McClung</name> instituting a suit against him for the land granted to him by reservation, <pb n="4" facs="pa0041d.small.jpg"/> you will please to inform me whether the subject of that letter has been acted On, And the result_.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have the honor to be Sir, <choice>
                     <abbr>yr. Vry. Obt. Hble Servt.</abbr>
                     <expan>Your Very Obedient and Humble Servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Jno</abbr>
                        <expan>John</expan>
                     </choice> Ross</name>
               </signed>
               <add>information as to <del type="overstrike">the</del> intruders on the Cherokees has <choice>
                     <abbr>recd</abbr>
                     <expan>received</expan>
                  </choice>- the <unclear>delegation the they</unclear> are <unclear>more numerous</unclear> than ever, <unclear>and</unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Capt</abbr>
                     <expan>Captain</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <unclear>Frank  burn their horses</unclear>
               </add>
               <add>Washington Apl. 20. 1824. <lb/> Cherokee delegation, East of the <name>Mississippi-</name>
                  <lb/> Relative to the Reservation of Lewis Ross, and the difficulty occasioned by the interference of the reservation selected by Spears with it_</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
