<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm023">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Drawing of posthole pattern of Overhill Cherokee townhouse,
			 summer pavilion, and large pit-features at Chota] / [by Marion Drescher] : a
			 machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Drescher, Marion</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Catherine Michelle Love</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Tara Hottenstein</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. 3k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>mm023</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 45081735</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Museum, University of
				Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Drawing of posthole pattern of Overhill Cherokee townhouse,
				summer pavilion, and large pit-features at Chota] / [by Marion
				Drescher]</title>
               <author>Drescher, Marion</author>
               <date/>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This photograph of a drawing shows the posthole
				patterns of a Cherokee townhouse, summer pavilion, and large pit-features at
				Chota. Townhouses, or council houses, were large circular dome structures that
				served as an arena for all political and social events. The summer pavilion,
				which was open and rectangular in shape was used for the same purpose during
				warmer weather. Pits were dug for burials and for storage of refuse. The
				drawing is based on historical descriptions as well as archaeological
				excavations conducted by The University of Tennessee from 1969-1974. The
				excavations were conducted in anticipation of the flooding of the Lower Little
				Tennessee River by the Tellico Dam Reservoir under contract with the National
				Park Service and the Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA). Principal investigator,
				Alfred K. Guthe. Field Directors, J. Worth Greene, Duane H. King, and Gerald F.
				Schroedl.</note>
               <note type="collection">Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note type="document">mm023</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Photographs</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Dwellings</term>
               <term>Salvage archaeology</term>
               <term>Historic sites</term>
               <term>Holes</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Artist http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/art">Drescher, Marion</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mm023.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Drawing of posthole pattern of Cherokee townhouse, summer
				  pavilion, and large pit-features at Chota, based on archaeological excavations
				  by University of Tennessee, 1969-1974. Drawing by Marion Drescher. This
				  information was provided by the Frank H. McClung Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
