<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl758">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1816 Jun. 2, 3 Springs [to] Joseph McMinn, Knoxville, Tennessee / Thomas Johnson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Johnson, Thomas</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl758</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1816 Jun. 2, 3 Springs [to] Joseph McMinn, Knoxville, Tennessee / Thomas Johnson</title>
               <author> Johnson, Thomas</author>
               <date when="1816-06-02">June 2, 1816</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated June 2, 1816 from Thomas Johnson to Tennessee governor Joseph McMinn in Knoxville.  The subject of the letter is the negotiation and purchase of lands, and the setting of new boundaries with Indian Nations, specifically, the Chickasaw, Chocktaw, Creek and Cherokee.  </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Joseph McMinn Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl758</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>McMinn, Joseph, 1758-1824</term>
               <term>Indians of North America</term>
               <term>Land tenure</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Johnson, Thomas, 1766-1826</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl758a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>3 Springs</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>June 2nd 1816</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>From <unclear>Reynoldsburgh</unclear>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Dickson Esq. &amp; myself wrote you jointly and inclosed a plan of the road, that we have lately surveyed__ When we arrived in the nation the chiefs were collecting in a grand counsel, principally occasioned by a letter received from the Chief of the Cherokee nation inviting a deputation from the <name>Chickasaw</name>
               <name>Chocktaw</name>
               <name>Creek</name> &amp; <name>Cherokee</name> Nations to meet at turkey town on the 27th <choice>
                  <abbr>Ult</abbr>
                  <expan>Ultimo</expan>
               </choice>. (I believe was the time) in order to settle their boundaries <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;C</abbr>
                  <expan>etcetera</expan>
               </choice>__ I attended as a spectator, the agent <choice>
                  <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Cocke produced a letter from the secretary of war making propositions for the purchase of the lands belonging to that nation North of the <name>Tennessee river</name>, they appeared much dissatisfied with that part of the letter that wished a purchase I think the proposition would have been better <choice>
                  <abbr>recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice>                           had they not been so much dissatisfied with the line run by <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice>
               <unclear>Coffee</unclear> dividing their       lands  from those of the Creeks obtained by Genl <del type="overstrike">Coffee</del>   Jackson's treaty. In counsel they had two depositions read which the agent had obtained (I believe Terry &amp; McGee)  which as well as I recollect proves that the line ought to be run from a small Creek above the <name>Mussel Shoals</name>, to flat rock (or stone) thence  to the head of <name>Black Warrior</name> and down that stream.  The <choice>
                  <orig>secretarys</orig>
                  <reg>secretary's</reg>
               </choice> letter <add>stating</add>   that if <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice>. <choice>
                  <orig>Coffees</orig>
                  <reg>Coffee's</reg>
               </choice> line was not correct, it should be Corrected appeared to give Satisfaction__ I applied individually to some of the Chiefs relative to the Saline, on lands.  They appeared very averse to leasing or selling saying <pb n="2" facs="sl758b.small.jpg"/> that they would say nothing respecting the Salt works <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> Coffees line was decided, that they only done one business at a time__ I had the pleasure of meeting <choice>
                  <abbr>Majr</abbr>
                  <expan>Major</expan>
               </choice>. Thompson &amp; W. Robertson who had letters recommending them to the agent from you I used my endeavor with them to obtain the object__ the agent was not <choice>
                  <orig>favourable</orig>
                  <reg>favorable</reg>
               </choice> to the plan <choice>
                  <orig>alledging</orig>
                  <reg>alleging</reg>
               </choice> that their dislike to Genl. Coffees line made it an <choice>
                  <orig>unfavourable</orig>
                  <reg>unfavorable</reg>
               </choice> time to prevent the proposition; However I wrote for those gentlemen you had recommended propositions which they delivered to Majr. Glover a principal Chief who promised to present it for the Consideration of the other Chiefs__ I think it probable that when the line business is complete, if commissioners were appointed by the Genl. government, that the saline lands be procured, which would be of great advantage to the Western states  &amp; territories__</p>
            <closer>
               <add>I am Sir with Esteem <choice>
                     <abbr>Yr. Obt. Sert</abbr>
                     <expan>Your Obedient Servant</expan>
                  </choice>.</add>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Thos</abbr>
                        <expan>Thomas</expan>
                     </choice> Johnson</name>
               </signed>
               <add>His Excellency <name>Joseph McMinn</name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                     <expan>Esquire</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl758c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Springfield</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>June 4th 1816</date>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>His Excellency Joseph McMinn Esqr.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>181/2 <lb/> mail <name>Knoxville</name>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>T</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>.</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
