<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0305">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1817 Apr. 19, Augusta, Georgia to Colonel Return J. Meigs, Highwassee / William Wells : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Wells, William</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0305</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1817 Apr. 19, Augusta, Georgia to Colonel Return J. Meigs, Highwassee / William Wells</title>
               <author> Wells, William</author>
               <date when="1817-04-19"> 
			 April 19, 1817</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated April 19, 1817 from William Wells to Return Jonathan Meigs regarding a business deal made some years prior. Wells is requesting payment with interest from Meigs.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> n/a</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Business enterprises</term>
               <term>Indian agents</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Wells, William</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0305a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <date>August 19th <choice>
                     <abbr>Apl</abbr>
                     <expan>April</expan>
                  </choice> 1817</date>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                        <expan>Colonel</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>R.J.</abbr>
                        <expan>Return Jonathan</expan>
                     </choice> Meigs</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I had contemplated the pleasure of seeing you during the present <unclear>summer</unclear> - but as I am not certain that it will be convenient to take a <unclear>tour</unclear> to the westward - I avail myself of <unclear>all opportunity</unclear>, by my friend <name>Mr Goodriel</name>, by <unclear>who</unclear> I beg leave to remark, any remittance you may be disposed to make me, will no doubt be safely delivered. I  <unclear>understood</unclear> that in the cause of business public &amp; private, you have of late years been blessed with much prosperity - in this I sincerely rejoice as I could not fail to do, at any increase of the wealth <unclear>of one who from</unclear> my earliest days I have been <unclear>accustomed</unclear> to respect -  and it is a gratification to me to know, that you have, the friend of  my former days, now  <unclear>feels a position</unclear> honorable to himself, &amp; important to his country.</p>
            <p>
               <unclear>Sir</unclear> your favor of <date>20th <choice>
                     <abbr>Feb</abbr>
                     <expan>February</expan>
                  </choice> 1812</date>, you <pb n="2" facs="pa0305b.small.jpg"/> contemplate an annual payment to me of 175 dollars, <choice>
                  <abbr>till</abbr>
                  <expan>until</expan>
               </choice> the account between us should be closed - as the proposed arrangement <unclear>service</unclear> through <name>
                  <unclear>mr pope</unclear>
               </name> was afterwards altered, &amp; as it has so happened that no payment  <unclear>has Since</unclear> been made me, should it be convenient to send me an amount equal, to what an annual payment of that amount to this time <unclear> could</unclear> be - it would greatly serve an accommodate <unclear>me</unclear> - it would be about four times 175 <choice>
                  <abbr>dolls</abbr>
                  <expan>dollars</expan>
               </choice>
            </p>
            <p>As probably however it may be perfectly convenient to you to settle the whole I have given Mr Goodriel a copy of your statement to me, of which I  <unclear>suffice you have the counterpart</unclear>. In your <unclear>former</unclear>of <date>20th Feb 1812</date> you mention that you had <unclear>sent</unclear> your son two hundred dollars on my account - this was perfectly satisfactory, and is the Same I presume mentioned in your statement, &amp; which at that time left a balance <unclear>due</unclear> me, as you Stated of Eleven hundred &amp; twenty six dollars 33 cents on this sum the interest will be calculated to the present time, and on <pb n="3" facs="pa0305c.small.jpg"/> each payment also, the payment will be calculated to the same period - &amp; should you &amp; Mr Goodriel make an arrangement for the amount, it will be highly <unclear>satisfactory</unclear>.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am dear sir <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>yrs</abbr>
                     <expan>yours</expan>
                  </choice> respectfully</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Wm Wells</name>
               </signed>
               <add>I wrote you a few days <unclear>Since</unclear> by mail not then knowing of this  <unclear>
                     <gap/> buity</unclear>
               </add>
               <pb n="4" facs="pa0305d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Colo <name>Return J Meigs</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Highwassee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>R Goodriel</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
