<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc060">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Speech] 1832 Jul. 4 Eulogy of Gen [eral]  Jackson / Henry Carter :a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Carter, Henry</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sc060</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51302200</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Speech] 1832 Jul. 4 Eulogy of Gen [eral]  Jackson / Henry Carter</title>
               <author>Carter, Henry</author>
               <date when="1832-07-04">July 4, 1832</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a eulogy written by Henry Carter for Andrew Jackson on July 4, 1832 while Jackson served as President of the United States. The eulogy was written to demonstrate the animosity Carter held towards Jackson. The eulogy concludes with a derogatory poem about Andrew Jackson's life, from his birth to his death.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Henry Carter</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-1344</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sc060</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Speeches, addresses, etc.</term>
               <term>Poetry</term>
               <term>Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Author http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/aut">Carter, Henry</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc060a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>Eulogy of <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Gen</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Jackson</name>!!</head>
            <p>It is very fashionable, &amp; long has been the custom for every age, and nation, to immortalize those patriot heroes, who have lived in different ages of the World, &amp; to rehearse their names and deeds, until they have become a living motto, indelibly imprinted upon the hearts of all. That long list of worthy ancestors, who have, and are now exerting their powers and resources for the happiness and prosperity of our great <choice>
                  <orig>Republick</orig>
                  <reg>Republic</reg>
               </choice>, are richly deserving the warmest pra ⁁ <add place="supralinear">i</add> ses of this free people. But in the list of worthies so often repeated, there is one, who, has received but a faint share of our encomium; and that is, the present Chief Magistrate of our Country. View his noble career thus far of his life as a philanthropist — gaze but for a moment at the sublime and almost <choice>
                  <orig>unparalel</orig>
                  <reg>unparalleled</reg>
               </choice> scene of <name type="place">New Orleans</name> — meditate but for a moment more the humane &amp; benevolent feeling that he manifested towards the <name type="person">Seminole Indians</name>, when he was sent to quell that tribe, where it is well known he not only executed many of them without Judge or Jury, but, even one or two  foreigners, who were then trading among the Indians — &amp; last of all, consider him, as one of those <choice>
                  <orig>dareing</orig>
                  <reg>daring</reg>
               </choice>, noble, illustrious, renowned, patriotic, benevolent, &amp; humane Statesmen, who has far surpassed the wisest &amp; best of his predecessors, yea, even the immortal <name type="person">Washington</name> himself, in one particular thing for which his mind seems peculiarly adapted — that is, fighting duels — when I say, we behold all their excellencies combined in this great man what <name type="person">American</name> heart is there, so cold to all the finer feelings of which our nature is susceptible, that would not burst forth with spontaneous ejaculations of praise, for such a worthy!!! Yet notwithstanding the many excellencies of this great &amp; good man, his character is slandered at  <choice>
                  <sic>an an</sic>
                  <corr>an</corr>
               </choice> unknown rate, &amp; that he by some of our most worthy citizens! I will just relate an anecdote, which will show in some degree, what the feelings of many are towards him. Two men having met in a City not far hence, (one a friend &amp; the other an opposer of <choice>
                  <abbr>Gen</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Jackson) turned their conversation to <choice>
                  <orig>polytical</orig>
                  <reg>political</reg>
               </choice> affairs. The opposer asks; on what ground, do your party claim that Jackson has a right to the seat he now occupies? Why says the Jacksonian, the reason is very  obvious. The glorious victory of New Orleans is sufficient to merit this high station. The opposer then says — In the time that the Roman Empire was enjoying its happiest days, the City of <name type="place">Rome</name> was at one time saved from distinction, by means of a flock of Geese, &amp; they never thought of put ⁁ <add place="supralinear">t</add> ing the Gander in president for life!! Any one can see, that this anecdote is calculated to carry the idea, that, this victory was more of a hit than any good wit. But after all the jokes that men can invent, (for it does not seem possible they could speak thus in earnest) we must allow this to be a complete, decided victory. I have always had the impression, that the decision of this Battle, was owing in a great measure, to the assistance which the <choice>
                  <orig>americans</orig>
                  <reg>Americans</reg>
               </choice> received from the immense number of <pb n="2" facs="sc060b.small.jpg"/>
               <unclear>bales</unclear> of Cotton, which were then at hand, which they placed before them as a breast-work, to screen themselves from the enemies shot. But what under the canopy, could have put it into the General's head to pile these bundles together,   unless it was the light of Inspiration, I am wholly unable to determine. You may search the records of history from this moment, back to the days of <name type="person">Adam</name>, &amp; you can produce no such instance of Generalship, now extant, <del type="overstrike">unless</del> except <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Boanaparts</orig>
                     <reg>Bonaparte's</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> noble trip to <name type="place">Moscow</name>. Enough has already been said with regard to his deeds, to convince any <unclear>cand</unclear> mind of his worth, &amp; now we will look at his noble descent, as we know royal blood is always valued high. I have the information recently from Washington, &amp; from such men as no one would dare impeach.This noble man was the dear Son, <lb/> Of a renowned Camp — woman; <lb/> His Sire, a <choice>
                  <orig>Brittish</orig>
                  <reg>British</reg>
               </choice> — Officer: <lb/> Such, were the Parents of this Cur !! <lb/> Does not rich Blood then swell his veins?? <lb/> He's fit to guide our <choice>
                  <orig>Publick</orig>
                  <reg>Public</reg>
               </choice> veins! <lb/> Who does his Royal <unclear>hood</unclear> accuse, <lb/> A path against conscience pursues. Oft might I drop a tender tear, <lb/> For him whom some will not <unclear>repent</unclear>;  <lb/> Whose soul's delight is to be true, <lb/> And give each fellow, all his due.  Let others think just as they please; <lb/> I'll love the Man of high degrees: <lb/> I from my soul most earnestly, <lb/> Wish Andrew safe at Tennessee. <add place="left side of page">
                  <hi rend="different hand, different ink">Henry Carter</hi>
                  <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>H L C</abbr>
                     <expan>Henry L. Carter</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/>
                  <date when="1832-07-04">July 4th <lb/>1832</date>
               </add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
