<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD">
<TEI.2 ID="sc044"> 
  <TEIHEADER> 
	 <FILEDESC> 
		<TITLESTMT> 
		  <TITLE>Biographical Album of Tennessee Governors [William
			 Trousdale--1849-1851] / J. S. Jones : a machine-readable transcription of an
			 image</TITLE> 
		  <AUTHOR>Jones, J. S.</AUTHOR> 
		  <RESPSTMT> 
			 <RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP> 
			 <NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME> 
			 <NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME> 
			 <NAME>Maha Ayesh</NAME> 
			 <NAME>Amy Mays</NAME> 
		  </RESPSTMT> 
		</TITLESTMT> 
		<PUBLICATIONSTMT> 
		  <PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</PUBLISHER> 
		  <PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE> 
		  <ADDRESS> 
			 <ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE> 
			 <ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE> 
			 <ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE> 
		  </ADDRESS> 
		  <DATE>2001</DATE> 
		  <IDNO>sc044</IDNO> 
		  <IDNO>OCLC: 50406944</IDNO> 
		  <AVAILABILITY> 
			 <P>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text.</P> 
		  </AVAILABILITY> 
		</PUBLICATIONSTMT> 
		<SOURCEDESC> 
		  <BIBL> 
			 <TITLE>Biographical Album of Tennessee Governors [William
				Trousdale--1849-1851] / J. S. Jones</TITLE> 
			 <AUTHOR>Jones, J. S.</AUTHOR> 
			 <DATE VALUE="1904-00-00">1904</DATE> 
			 <EXTENT>2p</EXTENT> 
			 <NOTE TYPE="summary">The Biographical Album of Tennessee Governors,
				dated 1904, contains 31 plates, each featuring a Tennessee Governor's photo on
				the front and biographical information on the back. This plate features William
				Trousdale, Tennessee's Governor from 1849 to 1851.</NOTE> 
			 <NOTE TYPE="Collection">Biographical Album of Tennessee
				Governors</NOTE> 
			 <NOTE TYPE="Box">n/a</NOTE> 
			 <NOTE TYPE="Folder">F435.J65</NOTE> 
			 <NOTE TYPE="Document">sc044</NOTE></BIBL> 
		</SOURCEDESC> 
	 </FILEDESC> 
	 <ENCODINGDESC> 
		<PROJECTDESC> 
		  <P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P> 
		</PROJECTDESC> 
		<EDITORIALDECL> 
		  <P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P> 
		  <P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</P> 
		  <P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P> 
		  <P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</P> 
		  <P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</P> 
		</EDITORIALDECL> 
		<REFSDECL> 
		  <P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</P> 
		</REFSDECL> 
		<CLASSDECL> 
		  <TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"> 
			 <BIBL> 
				<TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL> 
		  </TAXONOMY> 
		</CLASSDECL> 
	 </ENCODINGDESC> 
	 <PROFILEDESC> 
		<TEXTCLASS> 
		  <KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"> 
			 <LIST> 
				<ITEM>Trousdale, William, 1790-1872</ITEM> 
				<ITEM>Tennessee</ITEM> 
			 </LIST> 
		  </KEYWORDS> 
		</TEXTCLASS> 
	 </PROFILEDESC> 
  </TEIHEADER> 
  <TEXT> 
	 <BODY> 
		<DIV1 TYPE="Book"><PB N="[1]"> 
		  <P> 
			 <FIGURE> 
				<HEAD>William Trousdale.--1849-1851. [Photo]</HEAD> 
			 </FIGURE></P> 
		</DIV1> <PB N="[2]"> 
		<DIV1 TYPE="book"> 
		  <P> 
			 <NAME TYPE="person" TEIFORM=" ">William Trousdale</NAME>, Governor of
			 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Tennessee</NAME>, 
			 <DATE VALUE="1849-00-00">1849</DATE>- 
			 <DATE VALUE="1851-00-00">1851</DATE>, was known in his political days
			 as the "War Horse" of 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Sumner County</NAME>. He was of Scotch-Irish
			 descent and was born in 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Orange County, North Carolina</NAME>. Little is
			 known of his early life save that when he was but a lad his parents moved to 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Davidson County</NAME>, 
			 <ABBR EXPAN="Tennesseee">Tenn.</ABBR> At the age of twenty-three he
			 volunteered in the 
			 <NAME TYPE="person">Creek</NAME> war, and later was with 
			 <NAME TYPE="person">Jackson</NAME> at 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Pensacola</NAME> and at 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">New Orleans</NAME>. 
			 <DATE CERTAINTY="1835-00-00">1835</DATE>- 
			 <DATE VALUE="1836-00-00">1836</DATE> he represented 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Smith</NAME> and Sumner Counties in the State
			 Senate. William Trousdale was in the 
			 <NAME TYPE="person">Mexican</NAME> war and was twice wounded at the
			 battle of 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Chapultepec</NAME>. For gallant service in this
			 battle he was made Brigadier-General by Brevet in the United States army. 
			 <DATE VALUE="1849-00-00">1849</DATE> he was nominated by the
			 Democrats for Governor; his Whig opponent being 
			 <NAME TYPE="person">Neil S. Brown</NAME>. The campaign was one of the
			 most spirited in the history of the State. Trousdale was elected by a vote of
			 61,740 to 60,350. During his term of office Ex-President 
			 <NAME TYPE="person">Polk</NAME> died in 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Nashville</NAME>. The legislation of this period
			 is uninteresting. Politics was the order of the day. At the close of Governor
			 Trousdale's term he was again a candidate but was defeated by the Whigs with 
			 <NAME TYPE="person">William B. Campbell</NAME>. The vote stood for
			 Campbell 63,333, for Trousdale 61,673. After his defeat he was appointed
			 Minister to 
			 <NAME TYPE="place">Brazil</NAME>. Governor Trousdale died 
			 <DATE VALUE="1872-03-27">March 27, 1872</DATE>, at the age of 82.</P>
		  
		</DIV1> 
	 </BODY> 
  </TEXT>
</TEI.2>
