<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sc059"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1843 May 15 Hamilton Place, [to] Gen [era] l Andrew Jackson, Hermitage / Mary A. Polk : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Polk, Mary A.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sc059</idno><idno>OCLC: 51302124</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1843 May 15 Hamilton Place, [to] Gen [era] l Andrew Jackson, Hermitage / Mary A. Polk</title><author>Polk, Mary A.</author><date value="1843-05-15">May 15, 1843</date><extent>4 p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter from Mary A. Polk to her uncle, General Andrew Jackson on May 15, 1843. In the letter, Mary thanks Jackson for a picture, inquires about his health, and sends other familial greetings and expressions of happiness and love.</note><note type="collection">Mary Easton Polk</note><note type="box">MS-1216</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">sc059</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>Communication in the family</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Hamilton Place</name></addrLine><addrLine><date value="1843-05-15">May 15th 1843</date></addrLine></address><salute>My dear Uncle</salute></opener><p>I have just read your letter to <name type="person">Mr Polk</name>, with regard to the picture you were so kind as to present to us. We both regret very much that any <orig reg="misunderstanding">missunderstanding</orig> should have <orig reg="occurred">occured</orig> about it, <name type="person">Majr Lewis</name> is probably not aware that <name type="person">Mrs. Pageot</name> had presented it to you. I think on your birthday &mdash; just before I left <name type="place">Washington</name>. at least, that was always my understanding about the matter. <del type="overstrike">from</del> so of course I have always considered the picture yours, &amp; or not wonder that <add place="supralinear">you</add> did to also &mdash; I <orig reg="prize">prise</orig> it from the many pleasing <unclear>apoiration</unclear> connected with <pb n="[2]"/> it, &amp; still more as a present from yourself, however if <abbr expan="Major Lewis">Majr. L.</abbr> insists that it is  his, I will give it up &mdash; but hope that you my Dear Uncle will not feel the least mortified at what has <orig reg="occurred">occured</orig>. &mdash; for I do not wonder that you should have considered it your own with the right to do with it as you pleased</p><p>I was glad to hear from Mr. Polk that you were enjoying such comfortable health &amp; spirits. I hope that as the warm weather has at last come you may still be better.</p><p>It was with feelings of melancholy pleasure, that I heard from him that you <unclear>upprissed??</unclear> yourself, as <emph>ready</emph> &amp; <emph>waiting</emph> for the <unclear>sermons</unclear> from our Heavenly Father to your last Home.<pb n="[3]"/> &mdash; A Happy immortality, &mdash; where I hope my dear Uncle to meet you. &amp; <emph>all</emph> that we have <unclear>sacred</unclear> on earth. &mdash;</p><p>I hope to see you in the course of the summer or Fall. &mdash; Present me kindly to <name type="person">Andrew</name>, <name type="person">Sarah</name>, &amp; believe me</p><closer><salute>Your affectionate niece</salute><signed>Mary A. Polk</signed><address><addrLine>to <name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> Andrew Jackson</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Hermitage</name></addrLine></address> <pb n="[4]"/><address><addrLine>to <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> Andrew Jackson</addrLine><addrLine>Hermitage</addrLine></address></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
