<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sc057"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Legal petition] [to] Tennessee State Legislature / Citizens of Bedford County, Tennessee : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Citizens of Bedford County, Tennessee</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>sc057</idno><idno>OCLC: 51301857</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Legal petition] [to] Tennessee State Legislature / Citizens of Bedford County, Tennessee</title><author>Citizens of Bedford County, Tennessee</author><date value="1850-00-00">ca. 1850</date><extent>2 p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a legal petition signed by the citizens of Bedford County, Tennessee. The petition asks for a clause to be entered into the state Constitution that will  emancipate all of the slaves held in Tennessee by the year 1866. Both slaveholding and non-slaveholding citizens signed the petition.</note><note type="collection">Memorial to the Honorable Convention of the State of Tennessee</note><note type="box">MS-1190</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">sc057</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Legal documents</item><item>Antislavery movements</item><item>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="legal document"><pb n="[1]"/><head>MEMORIAL</head><head>To the Honorable Convention of the State of <name type="place">Tennessee</name>, to convene in <name type="place">Nashville</name> in <date value="0000-05-00">May</date> next.</head><p><add place="top right of page"><hi rend="different hand, different ink">from <name type="place">Bedford <abbr expan="County">Co</abbr></name></hi></add>WE your humble Petitioners knowing the evil of SLAVERY, and believing that our State has, and yet continues to <orig reg="labor">labour</orig> under disadvantages, which cannot be remedied while Slavery is tolerated by her laws, pray your Honorable Body, to insert a clause in the <orig reg="revised">revized</orig> or amended Constitution of this State, affecting the gradual emancipation of Slaves, so that it shall be a free state against the year <date value="1866-00-00">1866.</date></p><p><abbr expan="Second">2d.</abbr> And make it the duty of the Legislature to Colonize them, when they are emancipated and we your petitioners, as in duty bound, will ever pray.</p><p><table><row><cell>SLAVEHOLDERS</cell><cell>NON-SLAVEHOLDERS</cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Allen <unclear>Lecper</unclear></name></cell><cell><name type="person">John Fisher</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">William D. Ewing</name></cell><cell><name type="person">Ezekiel C Cook</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">James Miller</name></cell><cell><name type="person">James Battan</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Allen N Woods</name></cell><cell><name type="person">William Bills</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person"><abbr expan="Joseph">Jos.</abbr> O. Dysart</name></cell><cell><unclear><name type="person"><abbr expan="Thomas">Thos. </abbr>Coffey</name></unclear></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Sam J. Cuningham</name></cell><cell><name type="person">Andrew Miller</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person"><abbr expan="Robert">Robt</abbr> Dysart</name></cell><cell><name type="person">James W. Coffey</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">John Miller</name></cell><cell><name type="person">James L. Woods</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Samuel Ramsey</name></cell><cell><name type="person">John Dysart <abbr expan="Senior">Senr</abbr></name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">John Dysart</name></cell><cell><name type="person">Andrew Dysart</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">James L Ewing</name></cell><cell><name type="person">L D Stockton</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Sherwood Baty</name></cell><cell><name type="person">Allen Coffey</name></cell></row><row><cell><name type="person">Robert Williams</name></cell><cell><name type="person">Milton H Dysart</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">VB Martin</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">M R Wallis</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">Daniel C <unclear>Percy</unclear></name></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell><name type="person">William Martin</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person"><abbr expan="Alexander">Alexr</abbr>. C Denry</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">Joel Bradley</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">Samuel <unclear>Dyders</unclear></name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">Francis B. Woods</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">John McClarey</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">Robert W Dysert</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">John H Miller</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">James Fullerton</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">Robert Cowdon</name></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell><name type="person">Reuben Yarbrough</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">Robert C Dysart</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">Albert Anderson</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">Edwin C Hunter</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person"><abbr expan="Joseph">Jos</abbr> H Miller</name></cell></row><row><cell> </cell><cell><name type="person">James Patterson</name></cell></row></table><pb n="[2]"/><add place="top left corner">Citizens of Bedford <lb/> Slavery</add></p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
