<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sc085"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Legal Indictment] 1789 Feb. [to] the Superior Court of Law / State of North Carolina : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>State of North Carolina</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sc085</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Legal Indictment] 1789 Feb. [to] the Superior Court of Law / State of North Carolina</title><author>State of North Carolina</author><date value="1789-02-00">February 1789</date><extent>2p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a legal indictment from the state of North Carolina to the Superior Court of Law, dated February Term 1789.  This document is a ruling by the state jury that a man named Moses Rennolds stole possessions from John Rogers.</note><note type="collection">Washington District, North Carolina</note><note type="box">MS-153</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">sc085</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Legal documents</item><item>Theft</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="legal indictment"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine>Superior Court of Law</addrLine><addrLine><date value="1789-02-00">February Term 1789</date> &lcub;</addrLine></address><add place="left of address">State of <name type="place">North Carolina </name><lb/> <name type="place">Washington</name> District</add></opener><p>The Jury for the State upon <orig reg="their">there</orig> Oath present and Say  that <name type="person">Moses Rennolds</name> <orig reg="Laborer">Labourer</orig> late of the <name type="place">County of Washington</name> on the <date value="0000-08-24">twenty fourth day of August</date> last past with force and arms in the county aforesaid did <orig reg="Feloniously">Feloneously</orig> Steal take and Carry away of the personal goods of <name type="person">John Rogers</name> one Silk hand kerchief to the Value of Six pence and then and there many other wrong did unto the aforesaid John Rogers to his damage and against the peace and <unclear>assembly</unclear> of the State</p><closer><signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> Cocke</name> <abbr expan="attorney">atto</abbr></signed><pb n="[2]"/> <add place="down center of page">50 <lb/> State <lb/><abbr expan="versus">vs</abbr> <lb/> Moses Renolds <lb/>John Rogers <unclear>pro</unclear> <lb/>Witnesses <lb/><name type="person"><abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> Wilson </name><lb/><name type="person">John Arnold</name> <lb/> Sworn &amp; Test <lb/> <name type="person"><abbr expan="Francis">F</abbr> A Ramsey</name>  <lb/> <name type="person"><abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> Cocke</name> <abbr expan="attorney">atto</abbr></add><add place="left side of page, upside down"><hi rend="different hand, different ink">Not a true<lb/> price Bill <lb/> <name type="person">Andrew Greer</name> <lb/> foreman</hi></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
