<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sc088"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] ca. 1804 [to] Gen [era] l Andrew Jackson / G. W. Campbell :a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Campbell, G. W.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sc088</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] ca. 1804 [to] Gen [era] l Andrew Jackson / G. W. Campbell</title><author>Campbell, G. W.</author><date value="1804-00-00">ca. 1804</date><extent>2p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter to General Andrew Jackson from G. W. Campbell dated circa 1804. In the letter, Campbell lists the names of the people that are the managers of the impeachment of governor Claiborne.</note><note type="collection">George Washington Campbell</note><note type="box">MS-1457</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">sc088</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Impeachments -- History</item><item>Southern States</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><p>compliments very respectfully to your <gap reason="document torn"/> to any acquaintances, &amp; believe me with unfeigned &amp; very high esteem</p><closer><salute>Your most <abbr expan="Obedient">Obedt.</abbr></salute><signed><name type="person">G. W. Campbell</name></signed><address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> Andrew Jackson</name></addrLine></address><add place="bottom of page">The appointment <gap reason="hole in document"/> <name type="person">Claiborne</name> <abbr expan="Governor">Govr</abbr> of <name type="place">Orleans</name> has not yet <unclear>been infirmed</unclear> in Senate &mdash; I shall be happy &amp; expect to hear from you on <abbr expan="receipt">recd</abbr> of this &mdash; give me the news of that quarter or <unclear>advise</unclear> at near one <orig reg="o'clock">oclock</orig> The managers of the impeachment are &mdash; <name type="person">Nicholson</name> &mdash; <name type="person">J. Randolph</name> &mdash; <name type="person">Radney</name> &mdash; <name type="person">Early</name> &mdash; <name type="person">Boyle</name> &mdash; <name type="person">Nelson</name> &mdash; <name type="person"><abbr expan="G.W. Campbell">GWC</abbr></name></add><pb n="[2]"/><signed><name>G W. Campbell</name></signed><add place="below signature, sideways"><abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
