<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="sc092"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[List] 1846 Sept. 30 [List of Scholars in Pulaski, TN School District Number 3] : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Amy Emert</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">sc092</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[List] 1846 Sept. 30 [List of Scholars in Pulaski, TN School District Number 3]</title><date value="1846-09-30">September 30, 1846</date><extent>1p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a list of the scholars of the Pulaski, Tennessee School District, Number 3, as enrolled on September 30, 1846. There was a total of 35 scholars enrolled at that time.</note><note type="collection">Pulaski, Tennessee</note><note type="box">MS-1926</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">sc092</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Lists</item><item>Students</item><item>Pulaski County (Tenn)</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="list"><pb n="[1]"/><p>A List of <orig reg="Scholars">Schollars</orig> in School District <abbr expan="Number">No</abbr> 3 in <name type="place">Pulaski</name> Between the ages of 5 &amp; 18 inclusive at this late <date value="1846-09-30">30th of September 1846</date></p><p><table><row><cell>1 <name type="person">Francis E Hodge</name></cell><cell>13 <name type="person">Maria Stookey</name></cell><cell>25 <name type="person">John M Thorn</name></cell></row><row><cell>2 <name type="person">Orville W Hodge</name></cell><cell>14 <name type="person">Martha Stookey</name></cell><cell>26 <name type="person">Homer A Thorn</name></cell></row><row><cell>3 <name type="person"><abbr expan="George">Geo.</abbr> F Hodge</name></cell><cell>15 <name type="person">Frances Stookey</name></cell><cell>27 <name type="person">Lydia A Thorn</name></cell></row><row><cell>4 <del type="overstrike">Hellen Jesirance</del></cell><cell>16 <name type="person">Sheals</name></cell><cell>28 <name type="person">Sarah M Thorn</name></cell></row><row><cell>5 <name type="person">Jerome Simons</name></cell><cell>17 <name type="person">Hanah Chesebro</name></cell><cell>29 <name type="person">Cynthia Chesebro</name></cell></row><row><cell>6 <name type="person">Hellen Simons</name></cell><cell>18 <name type="person">C. G. Tyler</name></cell><cell>30 <name type="person">John Parks</name></cell></row><row><cell>7 <name type="person">Loren Stiles</name></cell><cell>19 <name type="person">S. N. Tyler</name></cell><cell>31 <name type="person">Elisha Parks</name></cell></row><row><cell>8 <name type="person">Webster Stiles</name></cell><cell>20 <name type="person">C. M. Tyler</name></cell><cell>32 <name type="person">Lois Parks</name></cell></row><row><cell>9 <name type="person">James Chesebro</name></cell><cell>21 <name type="person">Magarett Tyler</name></cell><cell>33 <name type="person">H.H. Parks</name></cell></row><row><cell>10 <name type="person">Volney Chesebro</name></cell><cell>22 <name type="person">Roxana Tyler</name></cell><cell>34 <name type="person">Edward Webster</name></cell></row><row><cell>11 <name type="person">Sarah A Hodge</name></cell><cell>23 <name type="person">Frances Thorn</name></cell><cell>35 <name type="person">Pomeroy Abbott</name></cell></row><row><cell>12 <name type="person">Theodore Stookey</name></cell><cell>24 <name type="person">Catharin A Thorn</name></cell><cell>36</cell></row></table></p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
