<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl291">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1842 Dec. 21, Nashville [TN] [to]  Martin Van Buren, Kinderhook, New York / A. J. Donelson   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Donelson, A. J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl291</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1842 Dec. 21, Nashville [TN] [to]  Martin Van Buren, Kinderhook, New York / A. J. Donelson</title>
               <author>Donelson, A. J.</author>
               <date when="1842-12-21">December 21, 1842</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to Martin Van Buren from Andrew Jackson Donelson, dated December 21, 1842. Donelson writes about his recent activities including a trip to Arkansas and long illness. Donelson also writes about a political intrigue against Van Buren and General Andrew Jackson by a Mr. Branch and Dr. Ewien.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">A. J. Donelson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> I-D-3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">7</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl291</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Donelson, Andrew Jackson, 1799-1871</term>
               <term>Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845</term>
               <term>Stressful life events</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Donelson, Andrew Jackson, 1799-1871</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl291a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Decbr</abbr>
                           <expan>December</expan>
                        </choice> 21st 1842</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                     <expan>Dear</expan>
                  </choice> Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I was obliged to take an unexpected trip to the remote portion of <name>Arkansas</name>, and <unclear>pucuin</unclear> on my return that a letter of mine to <name>Dr Bukman</name> did not reach him. My purpose was to look after some claims of my wife to lands in Arkansas which from various causes were in jeopardy. The time consumed by the journey was much greater than I anticipated, and from that cause and a confinement of some four weeks to my bed on account of a surgical operation to which I was obliged to submit, I am in arrears to much of my business, and particularly to you.</p>
            <p>I shall stay in town to night for the purpose of writing you fully, by the next mail. I <unclear>have hardly</unclear> more  than time before the mail closes, of noticing the reference you were kind enough to make to me of <name>Judge Bragg</name>s letter, on the subject of the use making in <name>North Carolina</name>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl291b.small.jpg"/> of certain declaration ascribed by <unclear>young</unclear>
               <name type="person">Branch</name> to <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Jackson</name>. I have talked with the Genl on the subject who was not more surprised than I was, and who could find no authority for such declaration in any thing he has ever said or written. Mr B is in Nashville and is I find a friend of <name>Mr Calhoun</name>, but he is without influence and I have not thought it necessary yet to let <unclear>him</unclear> know how ridiculous the truth would make his statements appear.</p>
            <p>But there is <unclear>curently</unclear> an attempt to weaken the obligation under which the Democracy stand to you, and the Genl as you will <unclear>perceive</unclear> by the enclosed copy, strikes at it in his usual fearless manner. The <choice>
                  <orig>oppurtunity</orig>
                  <reg>opportunity</reg>
               </choice> was furnished by an invitation from <name>Philadelphia</name> and I am clearly of opinion that it was right to make it available, for the purpose of <unclear>silening</unclear> all such intrigues as those of <name>Dr. Ewien</name> &amp; others. <pb n="3" facs="sl291c.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>You will see that the letter is to <unclear>ce</unclear> committee, and will be published.</p>
            <p>You will hear from me by the next mail</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>yrs				 trul</abbr>
                     <expan>yours truly</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>A J</abbr>
                        <expan>Andrew Jackson</expan>
                     </choice> Donelson</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>His excellency</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Martin Van Buren</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl291d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>His Excellency</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Martin Van Buren</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Kinder Hook</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>New York</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
