<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ch113">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Entries from the Cherokee Supreme Court Docket, 1823-1834, New Echota] 1823 Oct. 25   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">ch113</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Entries from the Cherokee Supreme Court Docket, 1823-1834, New Echota] 1823 Oct. 25</title>
               <date when="1823-10-25">October 25, 1823</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is an excerpt from the Cherokee Supreme Court docket for the years 1823 to 1834.  The Cherokee Supreme Court convened annually in New Echota beginning on the second Monday in October and lasting three weeks.  This excerpt is from the Saturday October 25, 1823 session of court.  In it,  Judge John Martin describes a case that came before him, involving a man by the name of Tarrapin Head giving another man a counterfeit Spanish coin. Entries from this Supreme Court docket cover items ch100-ch163.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Cherokee Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">10</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">ch113</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Legal Document</term>
               <term>Cherokee Nation</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Legal status, laws, etc.</term>
               <term>Georgia</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="ch113a.small.jpg"/>
            <head>Saturday 25</head>
            <p>Court convened agreeable to adjournment.   Present their Honors <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;C</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> Jurors <name>George Saunders</name>, Foreman</p>
            <p>Court is adjourned <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> 2 oclock</p>
            <p>
               <name>Cherokee Nation</name>
               <lb/>
               <name>New Town</name>
            </p>
            <p>Personally came before me <name>John Martin</name>, one of the circuit judges of the said Nation, <name>Harris Tharp</name> , and after being duly sworn, sayeth on his oath, that about the 26 of September last, that a certain Cherokee man by the name of <name>Tarrapin Head</name>, passed him a piece of metal, purporting to be  a Spanish milled dollar for ---M. bearing the date 1808 and with other marks, as a genuine Spanish dollar and on examination, the said piece of metal, <unclear>viz</unclear> above stated, is found to be a counterfeit &amp; has been presented to said Tarrapin, for redemption &amp; he refuses to do same, furthermore this deponent sayeth not sworn and subscribed  before me this <date>25 of October 1823</date> .  a true Copy</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. Martin</signed>
               <signed>Harris Tharp</signed>
               <add>Court is adjourned <choice>
                     <orig>untill</orig>
                     <reg>until</reg>
                  </choice> the Court in Course</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
