<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl264">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1850 July 16, Nashville [TN] [to] George [House] / Mary [House]   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Mary [House]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl264</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51218046</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1850 July 16, Nashville [TN] [to] George [House] / Mary [House]</title>
               <author>Mary [House]</author>
               <date when="1850-07-16">July 16, 1850</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated July 16, 1850, from Mary House to her husband George House. She writes that the cholera is starting to subside in town, and who has died from it. She reports of a cousin who is badly sick, whom she wants to accompany herself, George and their daughter on a trip. She tells George that she never wants him to travel again, and to that end, she wants him to stay gone on this trip until he is completely finished, no matter how long it takes. Their daughter Sallie adds a few lines.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl264</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communications in the family</term>
               <term>Cholera</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">House, Mary</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl264a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                     <date when="1850-07-06">July 16th 1850</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My own dear George</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Since I wrote to you last; (which was a week ago, to <name type="place">Cahawba</name>) I have received two very affectionate, (and need I say) welcome, and much prized letters from you; It thrills my heart with sincere pleasure to hear, as it were from your own lips — that you love me so fondly still, and I will do as you tell me " <unclear>meaning</unclear> your love for me, by my own".</p>
            <p>It gives me great pleasure to say that the Cholera is fast subsiding; There are now but few cases from day to day; not more than from three to six, or eight deaths in twenty four hours I went down town this morning for the first time in two weeks, and I assure you things look much more cheerful than they did then, notwithstanding I met with a good many pale, anxious faces; <name type="person">Mr Moses</name>, your next door neighbor, has lost a son, and a daughter from cholera; and I believe the whole family have had it more or less — I suppose <name type="person">Mr McClelland</name> has given you an account of his wifes attack which was a very severe one; his family are all well now <pb n="2" facs="sl264b.small.jpg"/> Our friends the "Browns" are with us yet <name type="person">Mr Brown</name> has been more alarmed about cholera than any one I have ever seen; he has stayed at home constantly during the time it raged so badly, and some of the time he did not come down stairs to <choice>
                  <orig>hi</orig>
                  <reg>his</reg>
               </choice> meals; and he scarcely eat any thing at all — cousin L, had last week, a severe hemorrhage, and <name type="person">Dr Ford</name> says it was from her lungs — she does not complain much, of feeling unwell, but looks very badly and is <choice>
                  <orig>extreamly</orig>
                  <reg>extremely</reg>
               </choice> anxious to take a trip some <choice>
                  <orig>whare</orig>
                  <reg>where</reg>
               </choice> — but it is hard to move <name type="person">Mr Brown</name> to do any thing, or go any whare — they have been talking for four weeks past, of going to <name type="place">Kingston</name> and have not gone yet — and cousin L says there is no knowing wheather they will go at all, I proposed yesterday (if she did not get off somewhare before) to go with you <del type="overstrike">and</del> Sallie and myself to the Cave, when you return; she says that trip would suit her exactly — <name type="person">Mr McIntosh</name> says he is bound to go some whare, that he may eat corn and cucumbers, and not be <choice>
                  <orig>affraid </orig>
                  <reg>afraid</reg>
               </choice>of getting sick, he says it wont do to eat them here — In the last two weeks Aunt Silvey and Jim have both died, but neither of cholera; Jim tried to cut <pb n="3" facs="sl264c.small.jpg"/> his throat, or rather did cut it, two or three weeks before he died, but that did not kill him. Louisa was pretty badly attacked last week with rheumatism, she has taken your pills and is somewhat relieved, though not entirely, I am, going out tomorrow to stay all day, <unclear>and nurse</unclear> her — My dear Husband if I am not mistaken; I asked you in my letter to <name type="place">Columbus</name>, in mercy, to tell me if you had the least shadow of an idea, at what time you would be at home, and you did not <choice>
                  <orig>grattify</orig>
                  <reg>gratify</reg>
               </choice> me so much as to pretend to give a guess about the time — you over looked that part of the letter I am sure — But I wish you to remember, that <choice>
                  <orig>altho</orig>
                  <reg>although</reg>
               </choice> I am exceedingly anxious for your return; yes more anxious than words can express; I do not by any means wish you to leave any thing undone that you intended to do when you left I want you to finish it all this time; even if it should keep you two, or three, weeks longer from home than you expected I would rather you would attend to it now, than to leave me again — I never wish you to go away from me any more, We <choice>
                  <orig>hav</orig>
                  <reg>have</reg>
               </choice> not long to live in this world at most; and while I do live I want to be with you; no one on this earth can fill your place with me. <pb n="4" facs="sl264d.small.jpg"/> Our communion season begins on Friday 19th I hope, and pray, we may have a revival of pure, and undefiled religion in all our hearts for it has never been more needed at any time; than at present <name type="person">Mr Lassley</name> and his wife left town, for her farm soon after the cholera first came; and and he (Mr <choice>
                  <abbr>L</abbr>
                  <expan>Lassley</expan>
               </choice> ) had a severe attack of it on the road — We are all well cousin Tishy and Hennie send their love to you, and <choice>
                  <abbr>H</abbr>
                  <expan>Hennie</expan>
               </choice> says she is making a travelling <unclear>dress</unclear> ready for ready for a trip some <choice>
                  <orig>whare</orig>
                  <reg>where</reg>
               </choice> when you get home, Ma sends her best love — <name type="person">Mr and Mrs Bostick</name> wish to be remembered to you most kindly <name type="person">Mr Halbert</name> and Kit regret exceedingly that you did not get to <name type="place">Columbus</name> before they left, they say they would have endeavored to have made you feel ⁁<add place="supralinear">perfectly</add> at home while <choice>
                  <orig>thare</orig>
                  <reg>there</reg>
               </choice> Rose says howdy do, and make haste home the servants wish to be remembered to you and Tobey — My dear Poppy I love you dearly, I never wanted to see you so bad in all my life — I want you to love your little daughter — You said you would bring me something pretty, I would rather have my <choice>
                  <orig>poney</orig>
                  <reg>pony</reg>
               </choice> than any thing else — Tell Toby howdy and tell him he is a <unclear>black freshman</unclear> if he talks in that way outlandish I mean you must make haste home or I will get Mr Bosticks carriage and go after you your own little daughter <name type="person">Sallie M House</name>
               <add place="top margin, rotated">I found your pants, I packed them up on saturday and then <unclear>Ray</unclear> got them out for you to ware on sunday and did not put them back in the trunk any more I am very sorry I did not put them up for you, but it cant be helped now, you will only have to buy another pair thats all</add>
               <add place="up left margin and top of page 1">I shall wait in anxious impatience, for an answer to my Cahawba letter God grant that you may be spared, and protected, and restored again to the arms of your own devoted  Mary</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
