<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl587">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1846 Jun. 6, Nashville, Tennessee [to] Maj[or] Gen[era]l Brazelton / Aaron V. Brown   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Brown, Aaron V.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl587</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1846 Jun. 6, Nashville, Tennessee [to] Maj[or] Gen[era]l Brazelton / Aaron V. Brown</title>
               <author>Brown, Aaron V.</author>
               <date when="1846-06-06">June 6, 1846</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Governor Aaron V. Brown to Major General Brazelton, dated June 6, 1946. Brown writes to discuss troop movements. He also writes about providing provisions for the soldiers. He wants the responsibility of provisions to fall to the captains of each company.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Aaron V. Brown Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl587</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Brown, Aaron Venable, 1795-1859</term>
               <term>Military planning</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr90000566"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Brown, Aaron V. (Aaron Venable), 1795-1859</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl587a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>June 6 1846</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Maj.</abbr>
                           <expan>Major</expan>
                        </choice>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                           <expan>General</expan>
                        </choice> Brazelton</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>your communication of the 1st <choice>
                  <abbr>Inst</abbr>
                  <expan>Instant</expan>
               </choice> is in hand &amp; I <unclear>thank</unclear> you for the <choice>
                  <orig>prompness</orig>
                  <reg>promptness</reg>
               </choice> with which you have repaired to your present head quarters. The presence of <name>Genl Bowles</name>, will relieve you of much the most troublesome portion of the duties assigned to you in my proclamation. The <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Selichen</orig>
                     <reg>Selection</reg>
                  </choice>
               </unclear> of companies the <unclear>general notice</unclear> there of &amp; the determining on the most reasonable &amp; satisfactory <choice>
                  <orig>rout</orig>
                  <reg>route</reg>
               </choice> for the infantry, whether by the <name>Tennessee</name> river or to Nashville is still submitted to your own action. All contracts for transporting them by the river rout &amp; provisioning thereon, will be made by him &amp; he would be expected to go along &amp; superintend the whole operation If the river rout is not <unclear>selected</unclear> &amp; the Infantry are to be brought to Nashville a different state of things at once arises. In so distant a march how are the companies to support themselves both infantry &amp; mounted men? In middle Tennessee &amp; the Western District it was very early done__ but a distance of from 2 to 4 or 500 miles makes a great difference &amp; I apprehend in many cases neither the officers nor soldiers, would  have the means by them of defraying their expenses so far, especially whilst it was uncertain whether all <add>the individuals</add> on the journey to the place of rendezvous would be <choice>
                  <abbr>receivd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice>
               <del type="overstrike">as</del> by the inspecting officers, as coming within the description required by law. Such as could not pass  much at memphis or here would be in a deplorable condition, so far from home &amp; often <unclear>without</unclear> money. Now how are these difficulties to be <pb n="2" facs="sl587b.small.jpg"/> obviated The <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>U.S.</abbr>
                     <expan>United States</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> has made the requisition, but as yet no officer has come to attend to it___ no money has been provided &amp; no directions have been given how to provide in these cases. The reasons for all which I have no doubt is a scarcely of such officers about <name>Washington</name> &amp; such quickness &amp; prompness in the movement was not expected by the <choice>
                  <abbr>sec.</abbr>
                  <expan>Secretary</expan>
               </choice> of war. I <unclear>expect</unclear> constantly such an officer to arrive but in the mean time I must make the best arrangements I can under the expectation that the <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice> Government will sanction any proceedings I therefore desire that in the march to this place by the infantry &amp; to <name>Memphis</name> by the cavalry, that the Captains should provision their own companies, buying rations for several days at a time so as  to avoid too great a multiplicity of accounts &amp; Keeping such <choice>
                  <orig>accurant</orig>
                  <reg>accurate</reg>
               </choice> accounts by Duplicates as would exhibit the precise cost of provisioning. These accounts would doubtless be <choice>
                  <abbr>allowd</abbr>
                  <expan>allowed</expan>
               </choice> &amp; paid by the proper officer at the place of rendezvous (here or memphis &amp; if no such officer was here or there, they would have to be paid by the state &amp; trust to congress &amp; the Legislature hereafter to provide for them by law if not now provided for of which I do not doubt. I am very sure that all reasonable expenses of  provisioning &amp; transportation to memphis for both infantry &amp; cavalry would have to be allowd by the <choice>
                  <abbr>U </abbr>
                  <expan>United</expan>
               </choice>States, if the troops were first  <choice>
                  <abbr>musterd</abbr>
                  <expan>mustered</expan>
               </choice> into service in <choice>
                  <abbr>E</abbr>
                  <expan>East</expan>
               </choice> Tennessee &amp; then made the march, either en masse or by <unclear>separate</unclear> companies through the state to the place of Rendezvous at Memphis. Each company would be then in the actual service of the U. States &amp; provisioning &amp; transportation provided for by each captain for his company would not only by law but of necessity have to be paid by the U. States <add>disbursment</add> officer The captain of a company <pb n="3" facs="sl587c.small.jpg"/> so musterd in &amp; being in the actual service, would have not only the authority but the necessary credit to enable him to procure provisions &amp; transportation &amp; to draw the money whenever he met with a proper U. S. officer.</p>
            <p>now there is no way for me in behalf of the state, to appoint officers &amp; to place money in their hands to go &amp; act as quarter masters <add>or <unclear>commissaries</unclear>
               </add> for such companies &amp; for the want of suitable machinery to carry on such operations it cannot be so done. The greatest practical difficulties would therefore be obviated by mustering them into service before leaving East Tennessee with the view therefore of giving my fellow citizens of your part of the state a better opportunity to enter into the volunteer service, without having to encounter the difficulties of their distant <unclear>position</unclear> , I hereby appoint you, in the absence of any united states officer appointed for the purpose, to inspect &amp; muster into the service of the United States any of the companies either of Infantry or cavalry, which may be solicited under my proclamation, which come either from <name>Knoxville</name> or Eastward of that place, observing the directions contained in the letter of the Secretary of war <choice>
                  <abbr>containd</abbr>
                  <expan>contained</expan>
               </choice> in his letter published in my proclamation. I also appoint <name>Genl G. W. Bowles</name> to inspect &amp; muster all the solicited companies lying below Knoxville, to observe likewise the directions contained in the said letter of the Secretary of War. This letter to be the Warrant &amp; Commission to both of you to inspect &amp; muster the solicitor companies as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>If the Infantry is to go down the Tennessee, they can be musterd in before embarkation. If they are to come by Nashville the same thing can be done. It is not expected that they will be embodied <pb n="4" facs="sl587d.small.jpg"/> for the purpose of being musterd in That can be done by You as they pass by Knoxville <del type="overstrike">or</del> separately or at any other convenient point at which you or Genl <choice>
                  <abbr>B.</abbr>
                  <expan>Rowles</expan>
               </choice> could readily meet them &amp; the messenger or mail that <unclear>informed</unclear> them of their selection could also inform them by whom &amp; about what time or place they would be <choice>
                  <orig>enspected</orig>
                  <reg>inspected</reg>
               </choice> . I send you a muster roll for each company which you must certify <del type="overstrike">(both of you)</del>
               <add>each of you his proper roll</add> signing triplicate rolls__ you need fill up but one, although you certify all three, as I can have <del type="overstrike">them</del> two filled up by the third. when they are their musterd into the U. States, the credit of the officers, will easily procure all the supplies necessary to the place of rendezvous. But you must admonish them not to make too many small accounts &amp; on all occasions take two receipts at least for every thing they purchase, duplicates being <choice>
                  <orig>indespensible</orig>
                  <reg>indispensable</reg>
               </choice> in their settlement <add>by</add>
               <del type="overstrike">[unclear]</del> the United States.</p>
            <p>Having given all these directions to meet the condition of the troops of East Tennessee &amp; to provide as far as possible, for their comfort &amp; dispatch, I close this letter with the hope that by the hearty cooperation of yourself &amp; Genl Rowles every thing may be done, <choice>
                  <orig>satesfactory</orig>
                  <reg>satisfactory</reg>
               </choice> to the troops &amp; useful to the public service</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>very respectfully <lb/> your <choice>
                     <abbr>obt</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>Aaron V. Brown</signed>
               <add>Please give Genl Bowles a copy <lb/> of this letter or such abstract <lb/> from it as he may deserve <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>AVB</abbr>
                     <expan>Aaron Venable Brown</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
