<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="gc046">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1839 Jun. 4, Rutherford County, Tennessee [to] James King, Tuscaloosa, Alabama  / Burl Gannaway: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Gannaway, Burl</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Harding</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>gc046</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1839 Jun. 4, Rutherford County, Tennessee [to] James King, Tuscaloosa, Alabama  / Burl Gannaway</title>
               <author>Gannaway, Burl</author>
               <date when="1839-06-04"> June 4, 1839</date>
               <extent> 4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated June 4, 1839 from Burl Gannaway to James Moore King.  The contents of the letter focus on daily life events and serves to update King on many matters of business.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">James Moore King Papers Correspondence, 1839</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">gc046</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Alabama</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Gannaway, Burl</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="gc046a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <add>miscellaneous calculations</add>
               <add>From Burl Gannaway 1839</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel</expan>
                        </choice> James. M. King</name>
                     <name>Tuscaloosa</name>
                     <name>Alabama</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>
                        <name>Murfreesboro</name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Te</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Jun</abbr>
                           <expan>June</expan>
                        </choice>.  5</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <add>paid</add>
               <add>56 1/4</add>
               <add>write me forthwith</add>
               <pb n="2" facs="gc046b.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Rutherford <choice>
                        <abbr>Tenne</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>Tuesday June 4th 1839</date>
               <salute>Dear James</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>  I <choice>
                  <orig>recievd</orig>
                  <reg>received</reg>
               </choice>  yours 23 may from <name>Hasle green</name> as well as yours from <choice>
                  <abbr>Esqy</abbr>
                  <expan>Esquire</expan>
               </choice>
               <unclear>Jamisang</unclear> I  and hasten to answer you first- I went- to <name>nashville</name> the thursday after you left in company with your man John and four bullocks the butcher agreed to give me six cents per <choice>
                  <abbr>lb</abbr>
                  <expan>pound</expan>
               </choice> but would not allow them to weigh more than 2800 I told him I would sell them weighed and ready 404-768-788 your mother 558 your notes on morgan to  <unclear>all poritid </unclear> in the bank got the coffee and sugar for Jamisan the note on Halebustan is fixed as you wanted. and mays and <choice>
                  <abbr>Ms</abbr>
                  <expan>Miss </expan>
               </choice> parrishe in the hands of y. Davis for collection the acts lately I collected <choice>
                  <orig>whain</orig>
                  <reg>when</reg>
               </choice> I went to <name>nashville</name> the sugar chest is labelled as you decided sent to <name>nashville</name> but I <choice>
                  <orig>dobt</orig>
                  <reg>doubt</reg>
               </choice> whether it has left yet as the water was falling fast- when I left but will go first chance I am just from your house this morning I stayed there last night your sister jane and Martty stayed also your family has been a little unwell but are now all about.  a boy Aaron  is up and not yet gone to work but soon will your mother has a boy at your house, (wilmington who is <choice>
                  <orig>verry</orig>
                  <reg>very</reg>
               </choice> sick taken last thursday sent to your house friday I was up there sunday morning and again last night- I thought him better this morning tell mother to not fear as he will have attention and every thing that can will be done the high forever your overseer has his crop in good order and seems to feel your interest his won.  I charged him and Henry as you directed indeed I read to them that part of your letter to me I have sold one <choice>
                  <orig>waggon</orig>
                  <reg>wagon</reg>
               </choice> load of corn <pb n="3" facs="gc046c.small.jpg"/>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Coln</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Litton talks of taking the <choice>
                  <orig>ballance</orig>
                  <reg>balance</reg>
               </choice> but has not <choice>
                  <orig>posatively</orig>
                  <reg>positively</reg>
               </choice> agreed to do so.  your flower that is ground up is the worst of all <choice>
                  <orig>oter</orig>
                  <reg>other</reg>
               </choice> matters to <choice>
                  <orig>mannage</orig>
                  <reg>manage</reg>
               </choice> there is about 2500 if it stays ten days longer the may wheat will be <unclear>cees</unclear> and be in <choice>
                  <orig>markett</orig>
                  <reg>market</reg>
               </choice> and the quantity raised I think will prevent a sale for even as good a price as it now brings and it will not be so good often it is old under all these considerations I told ship to see old man brock your <choice>
                  <orig>waggoner</orig>
                  <reg>wagoner</reg>
               </choice> have him off to <name>nashville</name>
               <choice>
                  <orig>imediately</orig>
                  <reg>immediately</reg>
               </choice> and try it-in the market it was worth 250 when I was closer. no water to to grind even if we had a <unclear>better</unclear> market for flour I will see brock and make the best <choice>
                  <orig>arangent.</orig>
                  <reg>arrangement</reg>
               </choice>  I can about it.  I have <choice>
                  <abbr>Majr</abbr>
                  <expan>Major</expan>
               </choice>. Woods ask him about his waggon he says you can have the waggon for $225 what he gave for it to his brother. in cash without clothe or bous collar &amp; and you can have them all thrown in he says it is a <choice>
                  <orig>supisous</orig>
                  <reg>suspicous</reg>
               </choice> one your colts are in the lot where the <choice>
                  <orig>leeves</orig>
                  <reg>leaves</reg>
               </choice> were and are doing well your <choice>
                  <orig>ry</orig>
                  <reg>rye</reg>
               </choice> and wheat will be ready to cut the last of next week now I would observe be as well <choice>
                  <orig>satisfyed</orig>
                  <reg>satisfied</reg>
               </choice> as the nature of the case will permit take your pleasure see your friends and stay as long as you want to stay as you have been at great trouble and experience to god want you to reap same <choice>
                  <orig>injoyment</orig>
                  <reg>enjoyment</reg>
               </choice> believing that we who are here will do our best to attend to your interest, we have had hail about a week ago and since that the weather has been too cool for cotton <del type="overstrike">you</del> I have been yours it look as well any <choice>
                  <orig>inded</orig>
                  <reg>indeed</reg>
               </choice> you have a good crop and clean little betty has been a little unwell cutting teeth ever since you left but is doing pretty well she has three <unclear>jau</unclear> teeth<pb n="4" facs="gc046d.small.jpg"/> looks pretty, loves aunt sally.  calls her mamy. and does a great many smart little things.  tell Patty. to just think of the <choice>
                  <orig>pretyest</orig>
                  <reg>prettiest</reg>
               </choice> and <choice>
                  <orig>sweetist</orig>
                  <reg>sweetest</reg>
               </choice> and most lovely little creature she ever though of and then she has not <add>began to find an</add> equal to little betty.  she will say gone in the <choice>
                  <orig>carrige</orig>
                  <reg>carriage</reg>
               </choice> many gone Shep and Henry came down Sunday evening and james went with Henry home.  when Charley got to farm he wanted to help him but James would not.  let him .  <name>Sarah gannaway</name> has had the a <unclear>flu</unclear> just recovering <name>Elizabeth Burge</name> has it ever since you left <unclear>
                  <del type="overstrike">crop</del>
               </unclear> no news home of importance I believe all about as when you left, the ballance of my family one will except <unclear>whay ely</unclear> who I believe is mending and I hope will recover  Clinton and Moor left your house yesterday morning for the district  </p>
            <p>I saw <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Binjamin Brothers yesterday that is all i know about his starting.</p>
            <p>I <gap/> Esq. Jamison yesterday all were well <gap/> J Butler says he has never written his wife has never got a letter from him <gap/> he left you will excuse my absence of mind for I cannot recollect as I once could or I would write <del>you</del> you more full however when you write me again you can let me know whether I have <choice>
                  <orig>forgotton</orig>
                  <reg>forgotten</reg>
               </choice> to name any thing that you wanted me to mention <del>prid</del> you I shall hear from I should have wrote to you two days ago but for the bay your mother jane has a letter from <gap agent="damage"/> wife and intends answering her <gap agent="damage"/> my wife join me in Presenting our best wishes to you all and Sara Says she <gap agent="damage"/> kiss little betty for his aunt Martha and <gap agent="damage"/> to kiss her again I think you certainly are tired of my Simplicity and bad diction I <choice>
                  <orig>forbare</orig>
                  <reg>forbear</reg>
               </choice> saying more </p>
            <closer>I send this by the express that you may hear from home before you go to marriage <signed>B Gannaway</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
