<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl594">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1846 May 27, Franklin, Tennessee [to] Aaron Brown, Nashville, Tennessee / Thomas H. Bradley   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Bradley, Thomas H.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl594</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1846 May 27, Franklin, Tennessee [to] Aaron Brown, Nashville, Tennessee / Thomas H. Bradley</title>
               <author>Bradley, Thomas H.</author>
               <date when="1846-05-27">May 27, 1846</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated May 27, 1846 from the Major General of the Third Division in Tennessee, Thomas H. Bradley to the Governor of Tennessee, Aaron V. Brown in Nashville.  In the letter, Bradley discusses the issue of a rendezvous point for the Cavalry companies, including the dilemma of those deemed unfit for duty.    </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Aaron V. Brown Papers			</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl594</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Brown, Aaron V. (Aaron Venable), 1795-1859</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Bradley, Thomas H.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl594a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Head Quarters &amp; Division T.M. <lb/> Franklin</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>May 27 <choice>
                     <abbr>/46</abbr>
                     <expan>1846</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date>
               <add>Miscellaneous calculations</add>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have the honor of reporting to your Excellency, that the requisition on this Division of the State for Six companies of Infantry has been filled, that the Captains of said companies have, by me, been ordered to rendezvous at <name>Nashville</name> on the first, or at the futherest by second june next, and that I have been assigned already by a portion of them, that the order will be complied with promptly.</p>
            <p>Thursday 28th next has been appointed by me as the day, upon <add>which</add> the Cavalry companies, required from this Division, will be chosen, there being already more reported than are desired for the Service__</p>
            <p>I will hereafter make a full report.  In order No. 2 from the adjutant Generals office, your Excellency has not directed a change of the time of rendezvous for the Cavalry; but if it is desired the companies of cavalry required from this Division can be at <name>memphis</name> earlier than the 15th June.</p>
            <p>I however may <add>be</add> pardoned for questioning the policy of sending volunteers to Memphis to be mustered into the Service of the <name>United States</name>.  This will be doubtless (it has always been the case heretofore) some <add>men</add> and horses rejected as unfit for duty, when they pass muster; and should <pb n="2" facs="sl594b.small.jpg"/> they be rejected at Memphis, it will place the men in a very distressing situation, as they (the rejected) are generally of that class of citizens, who are in indigent circumstances, &amp; will not be able to return home without assistance from some source. </p>
            <p>I therefore respectfully submit it to your Excellency, whether it would not be the better policy to appoint some Suitable place in the Division as a place of rendezvous for said Cavalry companies (which can be done more properly, after the companies are chosen) those to be mustered into the <choice>
                  <abbr>U.S</abbr>
                  <expan>United States</expan>
               </choice>. Service by such officer as your Excellency may designate</p>
            <p>I shall be pleased to hear from you by return mail</p>
            <closer>Yours <choice>
                  <abbr>Resply</abbr>
                  <expan>Respectfully</expan>
               </choice>. <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Tho</abbr>
                     <expan>Thomas</expan>
                  </choice> H. Bradley</signed>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Majr. Gen</abbr>
                  <expan>Major General</expan>
               </choice>  3 Division T.M__<pb n="3" facs="sl594c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Bradly <choice>
                     <abbr>ansd</abbr>
                     <expan>answered</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <unclear>"no alteration in time of Rendezvous at Memphis at present</unclear>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>FRANKLIN <choice>
                           <abbr>TEN</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>. MAY 27</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>His Excellency <choice>
                           <abbr>A.V</abbr>
                           <expan>Aaron Venable</expan>
                        </choice>. Brown Nashville <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
