<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl329">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] ca. 1848 Sep. 23, Masonic University [Clarksville, Tennessee] [to] Adam Fergusson / Wm. A. Forbes   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Forbes, Wm. A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl329</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] ca. 1848 Sep. 23, Masonic University [Clarksville, Tennessee] [to] Adam Fergusson / Wm. A. Forbes</title>
               <author>Forbes, Wm. A.</author>
               <date when="1848-09-23">September 23, ca. 1848</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from William A. Forbes to Adam Fergusson, dated September 23. It is probably from between 1848 to 1850 because those are the only years The Masonic University of Tennessee held that name. Forbes is writing to inform Fergusson about his son, William. William is behind in his studies due to neglect and is unlikely to advance with his class. Forbes is concerned for William's academic career. He writes that because he, the teachers, and the trustees of the university respect Fergusson so much, they care about William's welfare and will do what they can to help him.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers </note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">IV-G-2 b3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl329</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Forbes, Wm. A.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl329a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Masonic University <date when="--09-23">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Sept</abbr>
                           <expan>September</expan>
                        </choice> 23.</date>
                     <gap/>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your son William having returned to <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>Clarksville</unclear> for the purpose of entering the University I deem it my <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>duty</unclear> to inform you of his position so that you may advise us of your wishes as regards his future course of studies. You are awa <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>aware</unclear> that last year he by <choice>
                  <orig>abscense</orig>
                  <reg>absence</reg>
               </choice>, negligence &amp; other causes did not accomplish the required course in that class and was indulged until this session to make up his deficiency. On his return here I found that he had failed to comply with this requisition I had a long conversation with him last week in which I stated that he might if he wished, by double exertion to regain his position to  regain the good opinion of his teachers; and the friends of the College study partly in the Freshman &amp; partly in the <choice>
                  <orig>sophmore</orig>
                  <reg>sophomore</reg>
               </choice> and that I would reduce the complete course required in the Freshman Mathem <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>atics</unclear> to the smallest amount required to understand the rest of the course. If this is your wish he shall have this indulgence granted If you would prefer for him a selected course and give up the idea of graduation he can join any class he is qualified to enter I considered it my duty to set before him plainly &amp; clearly that whilst it would be our duty to aid him in advancing to a honorable position yet we were compelled to exercise towards him a strict and stern discipline. We felt that last year we had yielded too much to our feelings of delicacy towards you in not reporting to you promptly his errors; we are now compelled to pursue our simple line of duty in reporting to you promptly any evidences of want of study or other violations of regulation <del type="overstrike">comm</del>
               <add place="supralinear">which</add>
               <gap agent="damage"/> may come to our knowledge. I have also placed before him inducement to conduct himself in such a manner as to merit the good <pb n="2" facs="sl329b.small.jpg"/>
               <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>f</unclear> aculty. If he does not avail himself of the present <choice>
                  <orig>occassion</orig>
                  <reg>occasion</reg>
               </choice>
               <gap agent="damage"/> diligently I should consider it impossible for us to do <gap agent="damage"/> thing more and would then recommend that you place him elsewhere. He has now a boarding house in which I think he will be less exposed to the temptations which surrounded him  last year. You will receive from me a report showing his advance &amp; conduct at the end of this quarter. Your son has been here one week to day without entering the college the regulation forbid him remaining in town unless he does regularly enroll  <add place="supralinear">himself</add> before the end of the week, As however he informs me that he has written to you with regard to the classes he wishes to enter I have determined to suspend the regulation for the present until he receives an answer from you. I confess to you that I am anxious very anxious about him &amp; that I hardly know what to advise with regard to his studies. We will do all we can to advance his interest in our power. The respect entertained to you personally both by the Teachers and Trustees make us desire your sons welfare.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Very truly &amp; fraternally</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Wm A Forbes</name>
               </signed>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Prsd</abbr>
                  <expan>President</expan>
               </choice> pro term<address>
                  <addrLine>To <lb/>
                     <name type="person">Adam <choice>
                           <orig>Ferguson</orig>
                           <reg>Fergusson</reg>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice> }</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
