<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um086">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1843 Jan. 28,    Columbia, Tennessee [to] Col[onel] Rob[er]t J. Chester, Jackson, Tennessee / M[ary] J[ane] Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um086</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50323416</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1843 Jan. 28,    Columbia, Tennessee [to] Col[onel] Rob[er]t J. Chester, Jackson, Tennessee / M[ary] J[ane] Chester</title>
               <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
               <date when="1843-01-28">January 28, 1843</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by Mary Jane Chester to her father, Robert J. Chester, on January 28, 1843. In the letter Mary Jane states that she is in the middle of her examinations for the current session.  She states that she would like to take French, guitar, and piano lessons the next session and requests that her father to send her the money to do so.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers MS 25 (January-June 1843)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um086</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Mary Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um086a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1843-01-28">January 28th 1843</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Papa,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Again I am disappointed in not seeing you, indeed I had expected you with so much certainty that I could scarcely reconcile myself to the idea of your not coming and have determined not look for you until I see you, which I hope will be in June. <name type="person">Cousin Sam</name> let me read your letter, that he received last week he laughed at me very much about the <emph>kiss</emph> that you sent or at least in trying to get it.</p>
            <p>The Examination commenced on yesterday morning which was Friday &amp; will continue until Tuesday evening today and tomorrow omitted of course. The lower classes only, were examined yesterday. The more advanced are reserved for the two last days. I think that I am very well prepared I have two very pretty <choice>
                  <orig>peices</orig>
                  <reg>pieces</reg>
               </choice> of music to play at the Concert. There will be three or four Graduates this Winter, or account of the young ladies who live in the South, they could not return in the Summer. I wish that you would write <del type="overstrike">to</del>
               <pb n="2" facs="um086b.small.jpg"/> me, if it is your wish that I shall study French next session. We have an excellent Teacher. I am very anxious to take Guitar lessons, by taking one lesson on the Piano and two on the Guitar in a week, will have to pay exactly the same price as if I were to take whole lessons on the piano, and I think that I should learn equally as much. If it is not perfectly agreeable to you, I should rather not commence. They sell very cheap. <name type="person">Mr Smith</name> has very handsome ones for $25. You must excuse my short letters until after this Examination is over, then I intend writing you very long ones. Tell <name type="person">Rachel Trigg</name> I was very much pleased to receive her letter.</p>
            <p>Kiss <emph>Dear little <name type="person">Sam</name>
               </emph>, and the children, and Give my love to my relations.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Yours affectionately</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>M. J.</abbr>
                        <expan>Mary Jane</expan>
                     </choice> Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="below signature">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P. S.</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> Please send me some money in your next. I wish to take lessons on the Guitar, more on account of my voice than any thing else, for the Lady who teaches upon that instrument has a very superior voice and is considered an excellent teacher.</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="um086c.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="above address">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>post mark seal</figDesc>
                  </figure> 18 ¾</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Col. Robt.</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel Robert</expan>
                        </choice>  J. Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson</name>,</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address, upside down" rend="different hand, ink">My Dear Mary Jane <lb/>
                  <date when="1843-01-28">28 January 1843</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
