<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="gc009"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title> [Letter] 1820 Jun. 3, Oak Grove Madison County [to] James Moore King, Rutherford County, Tennessee / Ezekiel Moore: a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Moore, Ezekiel</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harding</name><name>Bobby Holt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>gc009</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1820 Jun. 3, Oak Grove Madison County [to] James Moore King, Rutherford County, Tennessee / Ezekiel Moore</title><author>Moore, Ezekiel</author><date value="1820-06-03">June 3, 1820</date><extent> 3p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a  letter dated June 3, 1820 from Ezekiel Moore to his nephew James Moore King.  He reports on the price and sale of cotton, the Insolvent Act, and the scarcity of money.</note><note type="collection">James Moore King Papers Correspondence 1820-1823</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">5</note><note type="document">gc009</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Financial, Personal</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/>   <opener><add cert="different hand, ink">From <name type="person"><orig reg="Ezekiel">Ezeikel</orig> Moore</name> <date value="1820-06-03">June 3rd, 1820</date>   </add><address><addrLine><name type="person"><abbr expan="Major">Maj</abbr> James M,, King</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Rutherford County </name><name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine></address><add place="left of address">by —</add>  <name type="person"><abbr expan="Mister">Mr. Jn,,</abbr>  Blackman</name><add place="below address"><figure><figDesc>Miscellaneous calculations</figDesc></figure></add> <pb n="[2]"/> <name type="place">Oak Grove Madison County</name><date value="1820-06-03"> June 3rd 1820</date></opener> <salute>Dear Nephew</salute><p> I <abbr expan="Received">Recd</abbr> a letter a few days ago from the Hazle Green <abbr expan="Post Office">P.O.</abbr> assigned by you, which I was glad to hear from you, Stating you had frequently <abbr expan="applied">applyd</abbr> to the office for letters from me but in vain, I never knew you had <abbr expan="returned">returnd</abbr> from <name type="place"><abbr expan="New Orleans">Orleans</abbr></name> whilst receiving <abbr expan="your">yr</abbr> last <abbr expan="dated">datd</abbr> the <date value="1820-05-17">17th may</date> You also stated to me that you had looked for your uncle <name type="person">James Moore</name> since the <date value="1820-04-15">15th of <abbr expan="April">Aprl</abbr></date> He may come, but will be unexpected to me I have never <abbr expan="Received">Recd</abbr> a sentence from him since the Letter by yourself last <orig reg="fall">faul</orig>, But <abbr expan="should">shoud</abbr> be glad to enjoy &caret; <add place="supralinear">his</add> company once more at my House, You also Stated to me that <name type="person">Mr Patton</name> wished to know what has been done with his notes I once put them in the hands of an <abbr expan="Attorney">Atty</abbr> for collection He returnd them to me, and stating he had made all the enquiry for them <name type="person">Mr Coffee</name> was living in <name type="place"><orig reg="Laurence">Laurance</orig> County</name> and <name reg="person">Mr Harrison</name> he <abbr expan="could">coud</abbr> hear nothing <orig reg="of">off</orig>, which I have sent the Notes by <name type="person"><abbr expan="John">Jno.</abbr> Blackman</name> to you for Mr. Patton wishing you <abbr expan="would">woud</abbr> give them to him by this giving up my <orig reg="Receipt">Recipt</orig> to you for  <abbr expan="Said">Sd</abbr> Notes my orders to the atty was to bring suit in this country only and as it <abbr expan="could">coud</abbr> not be done it was <abbr expan="dropped">dropd</abbr> without cost <pb n="[3]"/> I will also give you a small sketch of the situation of our countrys <orig reg="Laboring">Labouring</orig> under at this time and for some time past, the scarcity of money is great our produce brings is nothing in every <orig reg="sense">sence</orig> of the word our cotton has sold from 7 to 10 <abbr expan="cents">cts</abbr>— Baled <orig reg="Bacon">Beacon</orig> 7 &amp; 8 cts Tobacco of no Demand and with great difficulty in attempting to collect Debts a number of our country men has taken the benefit of the Insolvent Act I have sold some of cotton crop but has not yet collected <emph>all the money I have my Tobacco</emph> yet on hand unsold 9000 <abbr expan="pound">lb</abbr> 1st quality a Tobacco&rcub; 20,000 lb 1st <abbr expan="Ditto">Do</abbr> Seed cotton 3000 lb prime beacon&rcub; Which all is unsold from the Low prices offered <name type="person">Henry King</name> myself <del type="overstrike">and</del> has never made any collection of benefactors last spring Season the people all please the Scarcity of money and the situation we are placed in we coud <add place="supralinear">not</add> press them we shall only do tolerable business with him this spring he is in great perfection at this time and if you woud over and see us if you are in want of a little money we coud let you have some, I am in good health and all the connection,</p><closer><salute> I am with Due respect yours whilst I remain </salute><signed>Ezekiel Moore</signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
