<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="gc019"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1833 Feb. 3 [to] Walter Moore,  Rutherford County, Murfreesboro, Tennessee / T.O. Moore, Parish Rapids, Louisiana: a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Moore, T.O.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harding</name><name>Bobby Holt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>gc019</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1833 Feb. 3 [to] Walter Moore,  Rutherford County, Murfreesboro, Tennessee / T.O. Moore, Parish Rapids, Louisiana</title><author>Moore, T.O.</author><date value="1833-02-3">February 3, 1833</date><extent> 3</extent><note type="summary">Letter dated February 3, 1833 from T.O. Moore to his brother Walter Moore.  In addition to a payment of money, he urges his brother to settle on the Bayou, and writes of the wedding of their cousin.</note><note type="collection">James Moore King Papers Correspondence 1833</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">10</note><note type="document">gc019</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><add cert="different hand, ink" place="top of envelope">From <name type="person">Mr <abbr expan="Thomas">T.</abbr> O. Moore</name></add></addrLine></address><address><addrLine><name type="person">Mr Walter O Moore</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Murfreesboro</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Rutherford County</name></addrLine><addrLine><name type="place">Tennessee</name></addrLine></address><add place="left column of envelope">mail</add> <pb n="[2]"/> <address><addrLine><name type="place">Parish Rapids, Louisiana</name></addrLine></address><date value="1833-02-03"><abbr expan="February">Feb.</abbr> 3, 1833</date> <salute>Dear Brother</salute></opener><p> I acknowledge the <orig reg="receipt">recipt</orig> of your much esteemed favour of <unclear>Nov. 28th</unclear>  And <orig reg="entreat">intreat</orig> pardon for not answering it at an earlier period.  In your letter you stated <unclear><del type="overstrike">also</del></unclear>&caret; <add place="supralinear">our relations</add> were all in good health except yourself who was afflicted with pain which you were afraid would terminate in Rheumatism I was very sorry to hear you were breaking down a ready. I think it highly necessary for you to sell out &amp; remove to this country &amp; settle in Bayou <unclear>Chied </unclear> where you could have the advantage of excellent water.  And also the advantages of refreshing breezes from the gulf.  Which would brace you up &amp; almost make a new man you.    <add place="supralinear">of you</add> You could also live in the society of  Uncle Henry who speaks in very terms of you &amp; says you must write him shortly.  I <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr> my horse &amp; <orig reg="Negroes">negroes</orig> by his arrival.  <del type="overstrike">And</del> you wrote me you did not send my saddle down.  I want you to sell it if not at private, at public sale &amp; get what you can for it.  And write me word what you get for it.  &amp; if it will answer.  I will reserve in my hands.  The sum equal of the money due you from Brother Thomas.  I will remit you by this letter $50.00.  which will  <add place="supralinear">leave</add> balance due of $164.00 in my hands <pb n="[3]"/> As to the health of your relations in this County we are all good health except uncle Walter who has been confined with the gout but is recovering.  I attended the wedding of <name type="person">Cousin Emma Overton</name> a few days &amp; since.  She was married to a <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Winn a very respectable young lawyer living in <name type="place">Alexandria</name>.  he <unclear>read</unclear> law under judge Overton of <name type="place"><abbr expan="Tennessee">Tenn</abbr></name>.</p><p>I <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr> a letter a few days since from <name type="person">B.J. Thomas</name>.  who stated the sad intelligence of the death of poor little Washington.  Which must have been a heart rending shock to his parents</p><p>In your next letter I want you to write me where Cousin Lewis is &amp; what he is doing</p><p>In remitting your money by mail I will take down the number.  So as to secure it case the letter should be robbed I have nothing more to write.  After giving my respects to Cousin James  Patsy &amp; children Aunt <unclear>Jennet</unclear> and the rest of my enquiring friends &amp; relations.  And accept for yourself my Dear Brother my best wishes for your health &amp; prosperity </p><closer>Your <abbr expan="affectionate">aff.</abbr> Brother <signed><name type="person"><abbr expan="Thomas">Tho</abbr> O. Moore</name></signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
