<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="gc017"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1832 Jul. 20, Sampson Co [to] Sister / Jane Moore : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Moore, Jane</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harding</name><name>Bobby Holt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>gc017</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1832 Jul. 20, Sampson Co [to] Sister / Jane Moore</title><author>Moore, Jane</author><date value="1832-07-20">July 20, 1832</date><extent> 3</extent><note type="summary">A letter dated July 20, 1832 written by Jane Moore to her sister; with an additional page written by Jeanet Butler and is addressed to her children.  The letters express the status and condition of family members as well as a longing for the family to reunite soon.</note><note type="collection">James Moore King Papers Correspondence 1832</note><note type="box">1</note><note type="folder">9</note><note type="document">gc017</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><address><addrLine><name type="place">Sampson <abbr expan="county">Co</abbr></name></addrLine></address> <date value="1832-07-20">20th July 1832</date>  <salute>Dear Sister</salute></opener><p> we received a letter from Brother the <date value="1832-07-06">6 of July</date> which stated that  you <orig reg="were">ware</orig> all well except the <orig reg="Whooping">Hooping</orig> cough, we are all well at present and all   of our relations they have been some sickness in this <orig reg="neighborhood">neighbourhood</orig>, Uncle Henry Overton &amp; wife arrived <del type="overstrike">here</del> here the last of June he left here last sunday for the <orig reg="purpose">purpus</orig> of buying <orig reg="Negroes">negrows</orig> he wants about thirty we look for him in a few weeks he expects to return  through Tennessee I should be <orig reg="very">verry</orig> glad if we could all <orig reg="go">gow</orig> on <orig reg="together">to geather</orig> but he cant get ready by the time we want to start, we cant tell exactly when we shall start we talk of starting the <date value="1832-08-12">12 of August</date>  we expected to have been of before know but it has been <del type="overstrike">so the</del> <add place="infralinear">so</add> dry and <orig reg="warm">worm</orig> that we are <orig reg="afraid">a fraid</orig> to start for fear that we and our horses wood suffer with heat and hunger for food was since in some places as we <unclear>came</unclear> on hear, they <orig reg="haven't">havent</orig> had rain here in 4 <orig reg="weeks">weaks</orig> the crops is <orig reg="mightily">mightly</orig> burnt up it looks <del type="overstrike">looks</del> like they <orig reg="would">wood</orig> hardly make bread for <orig reg="another">a nother</orig> year, they is a great many people speaks of leaving this country, I was <orig reg="very">verry</orig> <orig reg="much">mutch</orig> pleased when I heard that B James had purchased <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> <orig reg="Laurence's">Laurences</orig> land, <add place="left margin">give my love to all of the negrows</add> <pb n="[2]"/> tell <del>O</del> Brother he did not write soon enough for all of us to <orig reg="go">gow</orig> <add place="supralinear">to</add> his fly round tell him that Mother looks as young as <orig reg="possible">posseable</orig> she drinks sider and <orig reg="fatten">fatons</orig> her and draws out the wrinkles she is know mending the pipe holes, the girls say if they come you  must have your quilt ready and have a great fly <orig reg="rousing">rouing</orig>.  tell Washington when little Jimmy comes home he will be able to throw him down he is one of the finest little boys in the world his grand Father stripes him naked and he can run all over the yard tell July Ann when she uses little Jimmy with his little <orig reg="pantaloon">pantoiels</orig> on &amp; walking she will want to eat him up for he is nearly eat up now with his grand mother and his Aunts and his little uncles</p><p>Give my love to <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> &amp; <abbr expan="Misses">Mrs</abbr> Batey &amp; Elizabeth to martha to Lyson to <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> &amp; <abbr expan="Misses">Mrs</abbr> Holdwell to <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> &amp; <abbr expan="Misses">Mrs</abbr> Beesley's and all of my inquiring friends Walter &amp; Father <del type="overstrike">&amp;</del> Mother &amp; all of the girls Joins me in love to you and Brother kiss all the little children for me and little Jimmy <del type="overstrike">give my love to all the</del> </p><closer>I for eve remain your <orig reg="affectionate">affectionat</orig> sister  <signed>Jane H Moore</signed><pb n="[3]"/> <add place="third page">My Dear Children<p>I have just return from <name type="place">capefair</name> our relations are all well your uncle Nalton looks <orig reg="poor">poore</orig> but is very <unclear>pert</unclear>, I have <orig reg="gone">gon</orig> threw all my visits I am ready &amp; willing to start home I have spent my time very agreeable ever <orig reg="since">sence</orig> I have been here, but I wish to see you all very much indeed I cant tell when we shall start to its being so dry, Walter talk of starting <orig reg="the">thea</orig> 12 of <orig reg="August">augus</orig> its is very <add place="supralinear">dry</add> hear crops looks very bad, we have all<orig reg="enjoyed"> injoyd</orig> our health ever <orig reg="since">sence</orig> we have <orig reg="been">bee </orig>hear which I feel very thankful for that great blessing, I hope my Dear Daughter these lines will find you both and all of your <orig reg="precious">prescious </orig> little children <orig reg="enjoying">in joying</orig> perfect health and all our <orig reg="families">familys</orig> and friends <del type="overstrike">I</del> your uncles &amp; aunts &amp; all of there children joins with me in our best love to you both &amp; your <orig reg="children">childran</orig> &amp; all of our inquiring friends particular to your Father &amp; mother tell  them I hope to see you all once more I cant write nothing more at this time but remains  your <orig reg="sincere">Sincear</orig> and affectionate Mother <del type="overstrike">forever</del> <add place="supralinear">for</add> ever <name type="person">Jeanet Butler</name></p></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
