<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="gc037"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1838 Jun.1, Rural Rest [to] Henry King, Ross Landing, Hamilton County, East Tennessee / Sarah Moore: a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Moore, Sarah</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harding</name><name>Bobby Holt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno>gc037</idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1838 Jun.1, Rural Rest [to] Henry King, Ross Landing, Hamilton County, East Tennessee / Sarah Moore</title><author>Moore, Sarah</author><date value="1838-06-01">June 1, 1838</date><extent> 3p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated June 1, 1838 from Sarah Moore to her cousin Henry King.  She offers him news of the family as well as the status of their health.   Moore also expresses concern over Henry King's daily routine and safety.</note><note type="collection">James Moore King Papers Correspondence, 1838</note><note type="box">2</note><note type="folder">5</note><note type="document">gc037</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><add cert="different hand, ink">paid 121/2</add> <add cert="different hand, ink">PAID</add> <address><addrLine>Coln Henderson Yoakum for Henry A.J. King Ross Landing Hawilbou Cty E T</addrLine></address><add cert="different hand, ink">From <name>Sarah W Moore</name></add> <add><figure><figDesc>Murfreesboro <abbr expan="Tennessee">Te</abbr>. <abbr expan="June">JUN</abbr> 8 </figDesc></figure></add>   <pb n="[2]"/> <address><addrLine>Rural Rest</addrLine></address> <date>June the 7 1838</date> <salute>Dear Cousin</salute></opener><p>  We <orig reg="received">recieved</orig> your letter on the 25 whitch was <orig reg="truly">truley</orig> <orig reg="gratifying">graifying</orig> to us all as we ware very <orig reg="anxious">anxeous</orig> to hear from you Albert &amp; William I was very glad to hear you have the <orig reg="fatigue">fatiegue</orig> so well Dear Cousin I hope you will keep a good resolution as that is the <orig reg="main">mane</orig> thing in a Soldier  I often think about you &amp; wish I could see you dear Cousin I hope it will be an advantage to you Henry I wont you to recollect the advice your Mother gave you <orig reg="sitting">sitin</orig> on her bed side as it is her wish for you to do well &amp; also William &amp; Albert as she has a <orig reg="feeling">feelin</orig> for you all <orig reg="tell">tel</orig> William I saw his <abbr expan="Brothers">Bros</abbr> john Jay before yesterday his Fathers family was all well <name>John Thomas</name> &amp; Lady has bin up to see us all Henry your Aunt <name>Sally Gannaway</name> has bin very sick but is <orig reg="recovering">recoverin</orig> again &amp; your Brother  <orig reg="appears">apears</orig> lost without you yet I and <orig reg="looks">lookes</orig> every evening for you he apears to look to your Mother for perfection your sweet little sister can sit alone and gnaw a piece of bread they have named her <name>Sarah Elizabeth Charles</name> after says <name>budey Henry</name> is <orig reg="going">goin</orig> to kill him one indian your Father is at <name>Franklin</name> at this time tending to the <orig reg="rascals">racles</orig> but will be home to day we are all well at this time and I hope this may <add>find</add> you and all <abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> Yocum company in good health <orig reg="tell">tel </orig><abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Snell <pb n="[3]"/> his Father has bin very sick but is <orig reg="getting">getin</orig> better <abbr expan="Cousin">Cous</abbr> Henry I am <orig reg="anxiously">anxousley</orig> <orig reg="waiting">watin</orig> for the time for you to come home as I do miss you so mutch of a night your Mother says she wonts you to act the <orig reg="part">parte</orig> of a <orig reg="Soldier">Sodier</orig> &amp; when you return home let it be in prase not like           the <name>Davidson Company</name> the looked so bad they did not make any <orig reg="halt">hault</orig> in <name>Murfreesboro</name> but went direct on I wont you to write to me &amp; let me no <orig reg="what">whot</orig> you are goin to do or <orig reg="when">whene</orig> you have to go we <orig reg="heard">hearde</orig> that one of your Solder got <orig reg="killed">kild</orig> <orig reg="accidently">accidentley</orig> Henry I wont William &amp; Albert to be careful in <orig reg="handling">handlin</orig> your <orig reg="guns">gunes</orig> <abbr expan="Cousin">Cous</abbr> mary <abbr expan="Cousin">Cous</abbr> Elizabeth and martha send <orig reg="their">thare</orig> love to yo your <abbr expan="Grand">Gran</abbr> Mothers &amp; Aunt Jane &amp; <orig reg="families">familys</orig> are all well your Mother Brother &amp; Sisters joines me in love to you William &amp; Albert may the god of Heaven shower down his blessings on you all do write to me as you promised your Mother will write to you soon </p> <closer>Your <orig reg="sincere">sinsere</orig> Cousin <signed>Sarah W Moore</signed> <add>the Negroes all send howdy to you excuse bad <orig reg="writing">writin</orig></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
