<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="gc041"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title> [Letter] 1838 Jul. 5, Rural Rest [to] Henry King, Ross Landing, Tennessee  / James King : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author> King, James </author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harding</name><name>Bobby Holt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno> gc041 </idno><idno>OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>  [Letter] 1838 Jul. 5, Rural Rest [to] Henry King, Ross Landing, Tennessee  / James King</title><author> King, James</author><date value="1838-07-05"> July 5, 1838</date><extent> 4p</extent><note type="summary">This is a letter dated July 5, 1838 from James King to his son Henry King.  In much of the letter, King  offers advice to his son concerning military matters, discipline, and the attributes of a good soldier.</note><note type="collection"> James Moore King Papers Correspondence, 1838</note><note type="box"> 2</note><note type="folder"> 5</note><note type="document"> gc041 </note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Communication in the family</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="Letter"><pb n="[1]"/>  <opener><add cert="different hand, ink">From <name><abbr expan="Colonel">Coln</abbr> <abbr expan="James">J</abbr> .  <abbr expan="Moore"> M </abbr> .  King </name></add>        <address><addrLine><name><abbr expan="Mister"> Mr</abbr>  Henry A.J. King </name> <name> Ross Landing </name> <abbr expan="Tennessee"> <name> Ten </name></abbr></addrLine></address>   <add cert="different hand, ink">miscellaneous calculations</add> <add>Nr <del type="overstrike">H</del></add> <add cert="different hand, ink"> mention <orig reg="moving">Moven</orig> again, J.K. </add> <add>Politeness of <abbr expan="Colonel">Coln</abbr> Yoakum</add> <pb n="[2]"/> <address><addrLine> Rural Rest</addrLine></address>  <date> 5th July 1838 </date> <salute> Son Henry </salute></opener><p>   I saw <abbr expan="Colonel">Coln</abbr> <name>Yoakum</name>, and <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> Harrison, they speak highly creditable of you boys, and of the whole company in their ready willingness to <orig reg="perform">purform</orig> their duties,  It is generally understood from various sources that it stand in higher estimation for its military pride, good order and <orig reg="discipline">disciplin</orig> than any company in service; this is truly gratifying to the citizens of your county, they speak of it boastingly, I think you <orig reg="soldiers">soaldiers</orig> should <orig reg="prize">prise</orig> and honour <add>&amp; hold</add> your officers in high estimation for their <del type="overstrike">good order</del> attention to good order, strict disciplin &amp; military pride; without; the best of soaldiers would be degraded,_ I under stand from <abbr expan="Colonel">Coln</abbr><orig reg="Yoakum">Yocum</orig> it is <orig reg="probable">proberbly</orig> that it will be the last of this month before his regiment will be discharged, I would rather you all had three months <orig reg="longer">longar</orig> to stay under strict disciplin that you might become better  acquainted with military duties, in camp__ <del type="overstrike">Mr Harrison, says you wanted me to <unclear>meet you</unclear> with a horse when you started home;</del></p><p>I understand their is objections to <abbr expan="Colonel">Coln</abbr> Yoakum on account of his strict disciplin, here <pb n="[3]"/> here I will remark for your instruction in future, so far as an officer acts <orig reg="consistently">consistantly</orig> in the <orig reg="performance">purformance</orig> of his duty, in keeping good order and strict disciplin in camps, he should never be complained of, but should be more highly regarded, and meritoriously applauded; and where ever their is complaints of that kind by soaldiers <add>be assured</add> it is more for the want of <add>longer</add> experience in camps, than propriety in complaining, </p><p>This you may discover in two companies, the officers of one company being disposed to use the <orig reg="authority">orthority</orig> to subject his company under good order and strict disciplin, and the other to neglect, his duty and the company to become disorderly __ </p><p>Will it not be <orig reg="perceived">preceived</orig> at once without the orderly <del type="overstrike">and strict disciplin, nothing could be done in</del> company will purform their duty with ease and facility; whilst the other is always in difficulty confusion, and never ready to do any thing,_ and the officers that will not keep good order, and strict disciplin in camps will <del type="overstrike">bring</del> degrade himself and his soaldiers,__ Mr <name>Harrison</name> informed me you wished me to meet you with a horse on your return that <add>that</add> you <orig reg="mustn't">must'nt</orig> expect, its not far, and it wont do for a <orig reg="soldier">soaldier</orig> to complain of a little fatigue tho, I <orig reg="wrote">rote</orig> to <abbr expan="Major">Majr</abbr> Molloy to get a pony for your mother, If could get one that was good conditioned and rode <orig reg="well">will</orig>, If he gets one you can have the use of it home   <pb n="[4]"/> You will inform <abbr expan="Mister">Mr</abbr> <name>Snell </name>his father died on <orig reg="Wednesday">wednesday</orig> night the 13 of June about one <orig reg="O'clock">Oclock</orig> _ <abbr expan="Doctor">Dr</abbr> <name>Becton </name>died last friday night, tell Mr <name>Ransom </name>their fathers family are well, The friends and <orig reg="neighbors">neighbours</orig> are generally well, My respects to <abbr expan="major">majr</abbr> Mollory To <abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> McLun &amp; officers and to all their <orig reg="soldiers">Soaldiers</orig> tell them we expect to give them a fine <orig reg="barbecue">Barbycue</orig>, on their return__ I saw Esgr <name>Jamison</name> and <name>Ganaway </name>yesterday them and families are well <orig reg="show">sho</orig> this to <abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> &amp; Abert, tell them <orig reg="howdy">houdy</orig>_ </p><p>Myself your mother, and family are all well and join me in love and esteem to you__ Write me__</p> <closer>Your Father <signed><abbr expan="James">Ja</abbr> <abbr expan="Moore">M</abbr> King</signed> <add>H.A J. King</add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
