<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl222">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 184[?] Sep. 17, Nashville [TN] [to] Mary House, Loweville [i.e., Louisville], Alabama / George House   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>House, George</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl222</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51217339</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>184[?] Sep. 17, Nashville [TN] [to] Mary House, Loweville [Louisville], Alabama / George House</title>
               <author>House, George </author>
               <date>September 17, 184?</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from George House to his wife Mary House, dated September 17, in the 1840's. He writes that her mother will be pleased with recovered health. He mentions that he has helped a friend get well with a medicine of his. George writes how glad he is of his son's progress in riding. He has enclosed a picture of Henry Clay for his son. Among the Democrats, he writes that Polk is losing support. He writes extensively and poetically about love.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl222</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">House, George W.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl222a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                     <date when="--09-17">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Sept</abbr>
                           <expan>September</expan>
                        </choice> 17 184<gap agent="damage"/>
                     </date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear wife</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>picture of Henry Clay</figDesc>
               </figure>I received <gap agent="damage"/> letter of 8th <choice>
                  <abbr>inst</abbr>
                  <expan>instant</expan>
               </choice> on last <gap agent="damage"/> until your Mother with Susan <gap agent="damage"/>
               <name type="person">Mary Jameson</name> had left for a <gap agent="damage"/> -land Campmeeting Near <gap agent="damage"/> in <name type="place">Wilson <choice>
                     <abbr>Co</abbr>
                     <expan>County</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>, — <name type="person">Mr Price</name>
               <gap agent="damage"/> down for her, and she took <gap agent="damage"/> along for Company— Your Mother will be greatly <choice>
                  <orig>supprized</orig>
                  <reg>surprised</reg>
               </choice> to learn your robust health — as only a few days since, she was apprehending that your health was very delicate — I am becoming very anxious to look upon your sweet rosy cheeks, and I will here mention, that  the <choice>
                  <orig>swiming</orig>
                  <reg>swimming</reg>
               </choice> in the head you Complain of, arises no doubt from your full habits — and perhaps in part for the want of proper attention to your bowels. — The Celebrated <unclear>Boor</unclear> have, said, "Keep the head Cool, the feet Warm, and the bowels open, and bid defiance to <choice>
                  <orig>desease</orig>
                  <reg>disease</reg>
               </choice> and the Physician</p>
            <p>You ask me to Come and see the rosy healthfulness of your blooming Cheeks for myself — This I shall do shortly, without accident— Mort was quite sick last week for three or four days — but my Pills <choice>
                  <orig>brot</orig>
                  <reg>brought</reg>
               </choice> him out and he is now attending to his business <gap agent="damage"/> Louisa finds <gap agent="damage"/> from the Square root I saw <gap agent="damage"/> is in last <gap agent="damage"/> and delivered your Message, she says, unless you return by the Middle of <choice>
                  <abbr>Novr</abbr>
                  <expan>November</expan>
               </choice> she will be off — but where too, she did not say — as she was interrupted — She also states, that you promised to board in the same house With her on your return, but as all things seem to Work well, I expect to remain where  I am, and for reasons which I will Communicate in due Season— as I do not wish to be premature in such Conclusions — <pb n="2" facs="sl222b.small.jpg"/>
               <gap agent="damage"/> to learn that our noble boy <gap agent="damage"/> ning such an expert rider — it will <gap agent="damage"/> ost a pity to remove him from the <gap agent="damage"/> indulging in such manly and <gap agent="damage"/> case but I suppose, there will <gap agent="damage"/> it — and he will have to  <gap agent="damage"/> when You return — Tell him <gap agent="damage"/> Papa is glad to hear of his <gap agent="damage"/> in riding — and to ride all he <gap agent="damage"/> he has a chance to do so with <gap agent="damage"/> would not answer to put him on <gap agent="damage"/> such a horse as old "Bet" Tell him— his Pa, has sent him at the top of this sheet, <name type="person">Henry Clay</name> — he must get you to cut it out, and paste it in the bottom of his, hat, or else Keep it, until he gets a new hat, and paste it in that — it is a most excellent likeness of the great statesman — The Democracy are deserting <name type="person">Mr Polk</name> in <name type="place">Pennsylvania</name> by thousands, <unclear>on up</unclear> of his opposition to the tariff — I send you a paper by this mail in which Polks inconsistencies are shown up very glaringly — and I will send You a paper also, Containing <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Jones</name> speech made at <name type="place">Lebanon</name> recently — you must read it — <name type="place">Vermont</name> has gone for the  Whigs by an increased Majority — and it is hoped that We shall get the Democratic state of <name type="place">Maine</name>, We shall Know in a few days more — I read to Em, what you said about writing she laughed <gap agent="damage"/> did not say it was unjust Bye <gap agent="damage"/> Sorry <unclear>it it</unclear> you are so sensitive about a certain subject <gap agent="damage"/> to be the burden of your Song— "Do you love me" — I did not <choice>
                  <orig>emply</orig>
                  <reg>imply</reg>
               </choice> the Want of Confidence then— oh no it was because it elicited, tones of  tender affection, which are dearer to the heart, when Coming from those We love; than any earthly treasure My object Was; not that I doubt your affection, but to Call forth some tender expression; as a <pb n="3" facs="sl222c.small.jpg"/> memorial of your love— and is it not natural My dear <gap agent="damage"/> that I should feel joy and gladness in the full assurance of <gap agent="damage"/> ever and Constant devotion — Love is a flame, unless <gap agent="damage"/> supplied with the means of  cherishing and sustaining it <gap agent="damage"/> languish — and go out— Yes the flame  must be fed — with kin <gap agent="damage"/> expressions and actions; which are loves fuel — and are as <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>necessary</unclear> to its well being and <choice>
                  <orig>exhistance</orig>
                  <reg>existence</reg>
               </choice>, and the wood to feed the fire is <gap agent="damage"/> Warms us — There is no passion — which sickens and dies so <gap agent="damage"/> from neglect; as love — particularly, where we have a right <gap agent="damage"/> expect it — You did not mean; that you did not wish me  <gap agent="damage"/> ask you the question again — You only misconstrued my meaning and when you rightly apprehend it — You will rather encourage me in it, than rebuke me, as you did in your last letter — I know there is not a more <choice>
                  <orig>sensutive</orig>
                  <reg>sensitive</reg>
               </choice> plant under the Sun, then Love — and those who would Cultivate it successfully, must guard against all intrusions from without and within "Do you love me Mary" — I know you do — but it is such a satisfaction to hear your sweet lips pronounce it — Will you not withdraw, the request in your last — " not to ask the question again" — You Certainly will — Love is like a rich gem— the more you rub it, the more it will sparkle; but lay it aside — and the rust and Canker will soon dim its lustre — I am pleased to learn that the presents, were safely delivered and that they suited so well — please say in answer to this — what I shall get for sister Nancy and <unclear>Mother</unclear> the children I can please with <gap agent="damage"/>  or something  of a like Kind — Make my love <gap agent="damage"/> my relatives — Kiss "Queen" Sally for me, bless her <gap agent="damage"/> and tell Jim his Papa loves him, and Wants to see him — we have no local news worth relating — <name type="person">Doctor Edgar</name> request, to be Kindly remembered to You Hoping I shall see You Soon — </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I remain as ever— Your devoted Husband </salute>
               <signed>George</signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl222d.small.jpg"/>
               <gap agent="damage"/> dined at Morts, to day — she looks very well — and her little daughter <gap agent="damage"/> fat — In looking over a <name type="place">Vicksburg</name>  Paper, since writing the <gap agent="damage"/> I notice the announcement of <name type="person">Judge Nicholson</name>'s death <del type="overstrike">of</del> died on the 28th last month — and Was buried with Masonic honors at <name type="person">Clinton</name> — His residence You recollect was a few miles out of town — near the road We used to go on our fishing excursions <gap agent="damage"/> the weather now is very fine — neither too warm or Cold — We have had several good rains recently — which were very acceptable — <add place="center of page, rotated">
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="person">Mrs Mary House</name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>Care of <name type="person">
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Sam J</abbr>
                              <expan>Samuel John</expan>
                           </choice> House </name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                           <expan>Esquire</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">
                           <choice>
                              <orig>Loweville</orig>
                              <reg>Louisville</reg>
                           </choice>
                        </name>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <name type="place">Alabama</name>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address>
               </add>
               <add place="down right margin, facing address">I wrote to <name type="person">Mr Stephen Chambliss</name> on last Thursday that his negroes were here in jail, and also sent him a paper with the <choice>
                     <orig>advertisment</orig>
                     <reg>advertisement</reg>
                  </choice> of the jailer — and marked the one I sent You that he would be certain of getting the information early — — <choice>
                     <abbr>H </abbr>
                     <expan>House</expan>
                  </choice>—</add> The Methodist <gap agent="damage"/> conversions at their recent Camp meeting near this <gap agent="damage"/> endeavor to bring the excitement into town — but have failed <gap agent="damage"/> to do so — <name type="person">Mrs. Elliot</name> looks very interesting and is quite well — did you show Brother the article on Wool — or rather the advertisement — Ann wishes her mother to write to her every Week — She meets me every evening With the question, "have you got a letter for me" — Says she is anxious for the session to close that she may get home — all well — say howdy to all the black ones for me — my respects to all friends —<salute> affectionately adieu</salute>
               <signed>George</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
