<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="gc050">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1839 Jun. 18, Merry Oaks, Tennessee [to] Martha King, Madison County, Hazlegreen, Alabama / Sally Gannaway: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Gannaway, Sally</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Special Collections Library</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>gc050</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of The Albert Gore Research Center, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact The Albert Gore Research Center, P.O. Box 193, Middle Tennessee State University, Murfreesboro, TN 37132.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1839 Jun. 18, Merry Oaks, Tennessee [to] Martha King, Madison County, Hazlegreen, Alabama / Sally Gannaway</title>
               <author>Gannaway, Sally</author>
               <date when="1839-06-18">June 18, 1839</date>
               <extent> 3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated June 18, 1839 from Sally Gannaway to her Aunt Martha King.  This is a very personal letter, filled with the recollections and thoughts of day-to-day life concerning the family, as well as news of the impending death of her cousin Judy.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">James Moore King Papers Correspondence, 1839</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">6</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">gc050</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 3.0 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Death</term>
               <term>Alabama</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Gannaway, Sally</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="gc050a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <add>From Sally Gannaway 1839-</add>
               <add>12 1/2</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Ms</abbr>
                        <expan>Miss</expan>
                     </choice> Martha King Madison County Hazlegreen Alabama</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>[Postmark]<name>Murfreesboro</name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr/>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>. <choice>
                           <abbr>Jun</abbr>
                           <expan>June</expan>
                        </choice> 20</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <add>ad</add>
               <pb n="2" facs="gc050b.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Merry Oaks</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>June 18th 1839</date>
               <salute>Dear Aunt</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>  To comply with your request as my promise I have seated myself at last to write to you.  I expect you begin to think me very negligent but when I tell what <del type="overstrike">h</del> I have been about you <add>will</add> pardon me. the night before you left Lizz and myself walked down to the spring and both dipped our heads in the spring and the next day Lizz had a chill but she said nothing about it and continued to have them all that week, I came home and had the real shakes all that <choice>
                  <orig>weeke</orig>
                  <reg>week</reg>
               </choice> so much for imprudence but we have bothe got over them <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> you come back so we can have an excuse to give you another siege of roguery.</p>
            <p>I have just returned from uncle Tims &amp; stayed their 2 weeks and was their when he got home and of all <choice>
                  <orig>thee</orig>
                  <reg>the</reg>
               </choice> fleshy redfaced whiskered sunburnt ugly savage looking men I ever saw he beats, but he is perfectly delighted with his trip, and says that <name>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Misoura</orig>
                     <reg>Missouri</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> is the garden spot of the world and intends <choice>
                  <orig>moveing</orig>
                  <reg>moving</reg>
               </choice> in <unclear>September</unclear>  Helen is their and doing well and behaves herself very well she says she will write to before you come home if you <choice>
                  <orig>wont</orig>
                  <reg>won't</reg>
               </choice> laugh at her letter.</p>
            <p>Cousin Henry &amp; Rufus was <choice>
                  <orig>her</orig>
                  <reg>here</reg>
               </choice> last sunday they were both well and able all was well at home I have not seen the <choice>
                  <orig>girles</orig>
                  <reg>girls</reg>
               </choice> since you left they will spend the next week with me Mary Jane was with me last week  and was very <choice>
                  <orig>axeous</orig>
                  <reg>anxious</reg>
               </choice> for both of us to write to you while she was here but I had such a good joke to tell you one that she thought I knew nothing about that I would not write untill she was gone you recollect a certain niece of yours that was going to the dancing school in <name>Murfreesboro</name>, she has certainly done move inquiry in the town than any one belle, that even visited the place, she has been the cause of more fighting, and scratching <del type="overstrike">and</del> and gouging, than you eve here of <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Gowled &amp; Mr Halum took a small fisty <choice>
                  <orig>cuffy</orig>
                  <reg>cuff</reg>
               </choice> over her. at a party not long ago <choice>
                  <abbr>sis</abbr>
                  <expan>sister</expan>
               </choice> what do you think of this I will tell you all about the fights wen you come home but M &amp; Clark have <choice>
                  <orig>blowed</orig>
                  <reg>bowed</reg>
               </choice> out and gone and I hope he may be blowed sky high or skylow I wont care which before he dies <pb n="3" facs="gc050c.small.jpg"/> little betty and jimmy is still here jimmy is the same little poke that you left him but betty is one of the sweetest little creatures in the world, if you could imagine half how sweet she talks you would be all but deranged to <choice>
                  <orig>heare</orig>
                  <reg>hear</reg>
               </choice> her she <choice>
                  <orig>calles</orig>
                  <reg>calls</reg>
               </choice> me sister and Mother Mammy and <choice>
                  <orig>appeare</orig>
                  <reg>appear</reg>
               </choice> as fond of us as she did of you and sis, I have learned her so many smart things and she looks so much better I <choice>
                  <orig>dont</orig>
                  <reg>don't</reg>
               </choice> expect you will know her when you return.  but little dick is the same crusty ugly but good little fellow.  tell Aunt Butler that I have the words and the music of old ang syne but if she will wait untill she comes home and will come down and stay a week or <choice>
                  <orig>too</orig>
                  <reg>two</reg>
               </choice> that I will learn her to play it on my piano.  I <choice>
                  <orig>kow</orig>
                  <reg>know</reg>
               </choice> it is better than any in <name>Alabama</name>, all of her friends say if she gets married their they will expect a <choice>
                  <orig>lage</orig>
                  <reg>large</reg>
               </choice>
               <choice>
                  <orig>dineing</orig>
                  <reg>dining</reg>
               </choice> on her return.  <choice>
                  <orig>O</orig>
                  <reg>Oh</reg>
               </choice>  I forgot to tell you that <choice>
                  <abbr>Mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> Sims had a large dinner given him in <name>Middleton</name>  and I had the exquisite pleasure of being one of the company I will tell you all about it when I see you, I <choice>
                  <orig>epect</orig>
                  <reg>expect</reg>
               </choice>that you are tired of <choice>
                  <orig>reding</orig>
                  <reg>reading</reg>
               </choice> such a nonsensical <choice>
                  <orig>epitle</orig>
                  <reg>epistle</reg>
               </choice> for it cant be called a letter and I must come to a close </p>
            <p>give my love to sis and tell her to write to me I have a great deal of news to tell her that I would not write on your letter, excuse bad writing and mistakes </p>
            <p>my love to Aunt &amp; uncle H and all of my relations and tell them that it appears like they never will come and see me any more poor old soul</p>
            <closer>your <choice>
                  <orig>affetionat</orig>
                  <reg>affectionate</reg>
               </choice> Niece <signed>Sally</signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Martha King </addrLine>
               </address>
               <lb/>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr> NB </abbr>
                     <expan>Nota Bene</expan>
                  </choice> Mother &amp; Father and all the children and cousins send their love to you <choice>
                     <abbr>sis</abbr>
                     <expan>sister</expan>
                  </choice> Aunt &amp; uncle. answer on the reception of this Harriet say please to come home she takes a <unclear>cry</unclear> every letter we get</add>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr> S</abbr>
                     <expan>Sally</expan>
                  </choice>
               </signed>
               <add>  I have not told you half of the good news but I will tell you some of <choice>
                     <orig>he</orig>
                     <reg>the</reg>
                  </choice> bad Cousin Judy is not expected to live until morning <choice>
                     <orig>Mothe</orig>
                     <reg>Mother</reg>
                  </choice> &amp; father has been their so much lately that when they come home it is to sleep and go back again that is the reason they have not <choice>
                     <orig>writen</orig>
                     <reg>written</reg>
                  </choice> to you </add>
               <signed>SALLY</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
