<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl121">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1837, June 27, Clover Dale, TN [to] Miss Ann Jane Bell, Philadelphia, [PA] / Sarah Bell     : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Bell, Sarah</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl121</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50512792</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1837, June 27, Clover Dale, TN [to] Miss Ann Jane Bell,  Philadelphia, [PA] / Sarah Bell</title>
               <author>Bell, Sarah</author>
               <date when="1837-06-27">June 27, 1837</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Sarah Bell to her sister  Ann Jane Bell dated June 27, 1837. She complains that her family would not let her write to Jane because they were worried Jane would not want to pay the postage.   She writes that the family has been concerned for her and that their mother wants to know what kind of medicine she is taking. Sarah updates Jane on the news from the neighborhood, sicknesses, marriages, etc.  The sisters are trying to decide between a barbecue or  a speech on temperance as their July 4th activities. Margaret has greatly enjoyed the book The Three Eras of a Woman's Life. They did not like Mrs. Cary's book because she thinks that all women should be punished for what Eve may have done, and the sisters do not agree. Sarah wants to be sure that Jane will send her a copy of her piece on Presentiment and her anecdote.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl121</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Religious thought -- 19th century</term>
               <term>Temperance and religious</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Bell, Sarah</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl121a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Clover Dale</name>. <date when="1837-06-27">June 27th 1837</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Sister.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have been very anxious to write you for some time past, but the others wished to write, and would not consent to my writing, they thought you would not like to pay the postage of so many letters, I said you must have changed very much since you left home, if you would not be willing to receive a letter from us at any time, and I intended asking you if I might not write to you when ever I wished. It has been some weeks since we received a letter from you, which makes us all feel very anxious fearing you are sick, which I hope is not the case, as I still have a strong presentiment your health will improve, and it is with pleasure I look forward to that period, which I hope is not far distant when, you will return to us as well and cheerful as ever. I miss you more and more every day, if I see hear or read any thing that strikes my fancy, I invariably think of repeating it to you, but the sad <choice>
                  <orig>recholection</orig>
                  <reg>recollection</reg>
               </choice> soon returns, you are absent. We were all agreeably surprised last week, in receiving several numbers of the Presbyterian, it is what we have often wished for, it is not as large a paper as the <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Nashvill</orig>
                     <reg>Nashville</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> Presbyterian but I think it equally as good, yesterday we received <name type="place">Atkinson's</name> Saturday evening news, if all is an it, that it speaks of, it must be quite interesting, my Father complains of the bad print. I hope they are not an additional <choice>
                  <orig>expence</orig>
                  <reg>expense</reg>
               </choice> to brother, as the directions are in your hand writing, we think you have the reading of them. Mother wishes me to say as you are an invalid, you <pb n="2" facs="sl121b.small.jpg"/> ought not to sit up late, and to rise early, she wishes to know if brother allows you much medicine and what kind you take. I saw <name type="person">Mr. Collier</name> last week, as usual, he was very polite, I delivered your message to him, he said, he was afraid he fell short of that attention which he ought to have shown you, but that he told you to attribute it altogether to his inexperience in waiting on ladies, he was glad to to hear his friends had not forgot him, and send his best respects to you all. <name type="peson">Catherine Clement</name> was married some time since, to <name type="person">Mr. Ingum</name> of <name type="place">Dover</name> a widower whose wife died of the Cholera when in that place, her request was if he ever did get married, to have <name type="person">Catherine</name>, her sister <name type="person">Mrs. <unclear>Balis</unclear>
               </name> I expect is dead, <name type="person">Mr. Collier</name> said it was thought she was dying when he left <name type="place">Yellow creek</name>. <name type="person">John Gould</name> is very low with the <choice>
                  <orig>conjestive</orig>
                  <reg>congestive</reg>
               </choice> fever, <name type="person">Dr. Hudson</name> and lady have been with him this last week, he has no hopes of his recovery, <name type="person">Mrs. <choice>
                     <abbr>G.</abbr>
                     <expan>Gould</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> has been in a very low state of health all Spring, I am afraid it will go very hard with her, your company would do her good at this time. <name type="person">Caroline</name> and <name type="person">Margaret</name> read the introduction to <name type="person">Mrs. Cary's</name>letters, and condem<add place="supralinear">n</add>ed the whole book, they thought her too severe in the course of life a woman should lead, if <name type="person">Eve</name> did eat the forbiddin<del type="overstrike">g</del> fruit, they were not <name type="person">Eve</name>, and had no right to make themselves servants for what she had done. <name type="person">Margaret</name>has just finished reading the Three Eras of a womans life, she says it is the first time her eyes have been opened to he difference in the <choice>
                  <orig>charactor</orig>
                  <reg>character</reg>
               </choice> of persons, and thinks it will do her more good than any book she ever read. <name type="person">Dr Carter</name> is to have a barbecue near his house the <date when="1837-07-04">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>fouth</orig>
                     <reg>fourth</reg>
                  </choice> of July</date>, <name type="person">Mr. Pope</name> is to give us  Temperance oration the <pb n="3" facs="sl121c.small.jpg"/> same day at <name type="place">New Hope</name>, and as usual, <name type="person">Margaret</name> is at a stand which to give up. <name type="person">Mr. Vanlier</name> does not expect to go on to your city before fall, <name type="person">Mr.<choice>
                     <abbr> C.</abbr>
                     <expan>Collier</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> says if you are as anxious to see home as you were where he left, you will return with <name type="person">Ellennora</name>, and not wait for spring. You speak of  writing a piece on Presentiment which you must be sure to send us, you have not sent us that original anecdote which you promised we should see. My Father says he has no recollection of <name type="person">Dr. Starks</name> and does not know where he ever saw him. What <name type="person">Mrs. Bell</name> is it you <choice>
                  <orig>speack</orig>
                  <reg>speak</reg>
               </choice> of in your letters? Let us know when you heard from cousin <name type="person">Eliza</name> and her Mother and how they are prospering in their New Country.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Margaret</name>desires you to tell <name type="person">Ellennora</name>
               <name type="person">Mr. <choice>
                     <abbr>C.</abbr>
                     <expan>Collier</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> intends writing to <name type="person">Mr. Henry</name> to thank him for h <gap agent="damage"/> attention to her during his absence.</p>
            <p>It is reported <name type="person">Amanda Napier</name> is going to be married to a <name type="person">Mr. Barrow</name> of <name type="place">Nashville</name> Since I wrote the above, I have understood <name type="person">John Gould</name> is much better. <name type="person">Caroline</name> and I were at preaching yesterday.<name type="person"> Mr. Marshal</name> returned home with us, he is a very <choice>
                  <orig>plesant</orig>
                  <reg>pleasant</reg>
               </choice> and agreeable man, he inquired very particularly for you, and if you had become reconciled, I hope their prayers will be blessed to the salvation of our souls, Write often my dear sister as nothing gives us more pleasure than to receive a letter from you. They all join me in love to you and brother</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>your ever affectionate Sister</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Sarah Bell</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl121d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Charlotte <choice>
                           <abbr>Tn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1837-07-02">July 2</date>
                     <add place="right of return address">}</add>
                     <add place="right of address">25</add>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Miss Ann Jane Bell</name>.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Care of <name type="person">Dr. John Bell</name>.</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Philadelphia</name>.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="down th right side of page below address" rend="different hand">Answered <date when="1837-08-01">August 1st</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
