<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl477">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1800 Mar. 14, Philadelphia [Pennsylvania, to] David Henley, Knoxville [Tennessee] / William C.C. Claiborne: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Claiborne, William C.C.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl477</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1800 Mar. 14, Philadelphia [Pennsylvania, to] David Henley, Knoxville [Tennessee] / William C.C. Claiborne</title>
               <author>Claiborne, William C.C.</author>
               <date when="1800-03-14">March 14, 1800</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from U.S. Representative William Charles Cole Claiborne to David Henley, dated March 14, 1800. Claiborne is giving his opinion on a proposed reduction in the Army. Though he does not worry about an invasion, he still believes that a strong defence is necessary. Claiborne also writes that the Army would not be able to withstand an attack if one did occur. He believes they should concentrate on training and equipping the militia as a permanent protection force.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">David Henley Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">35</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl477</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>United States -- Army</term>
               <term>Claiborne, William Charles Cole, 1775-1817</term>
               <term>Henley, David, 1749-1823</term>
               <term>Militia</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Claiborne, William C. C.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl477a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Philadelphia</name>
                     <date>March 14th 1800</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I had the pleasure to receive yesterday, your friendly Letter of the <date>20th ultimo</date>, and am much obliged to you for the attention you have paid to the requests contained in my last communication</p>
            <p>With respect to the disbanding of the additional Army I still think, that the measure would have been proper;__ An Invasion of our Territory, is a possible, but (in my opinion) not a probable event one thing however is very certain that the existence of the additional Army would not avert an Invasion if one is intended &amp; if it should be effected, the additional Army, would be inadequate to the repelling of an invading Foe;__ the militia of the Country must be resorted to, send to them we should look for the permanent defence of our Country__</p>
            <p>But you are certainly accurate in saying that we should combine discipline with force; But this discipline should be applied to the militia, and every <pb n="2" facs="sl477b.small.jpg"/> every shilling , which the reduction of the additional Regiments, would have retained in the Treasury, &amp; should have wished expended in furnishing Arms for the Militia, and for paying old &amp; experienced officers, to be employed in the different States, for the purpose of training the Officers and privates of the militia_</p>
            <p>I am very far however, from wishing the Army entirely reduced, on the contrary I am a firm friend to the permanent Regiments, &amp; shall always think, that a small military Force to garrison the Forts established on the Frontiers and Sea_ Board, will always be necessary_</p>
            <p>I agree with you, that unanimity in our National Council should be encouraged, on <gap/>
               <del type="overstrike">thing</del>
               <add>one Subject</add> however I believe there is no difference of opinion, which is to reject foreign aggression <del type="overstrike">for</del> from every quarter, and believing that a simi <pb n="3" facs="sl477c.small.jpg"/> lar  disposition is possessed by the Citizens of the Union, for myself, I dread not the Power of <name>France</name>, or even of all <name>Europe</name> combined</p>
            <p>The enclosed paper, will give you the latest News__</p>
            <p>Accept my best wishes</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I am <choice>
                     <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                     <expan>Dear</expan>
                  </choice> Sir <lb/> Your friend &amp; <choice>
                     <abbr>Servt</abbr>
                     <expan>Servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>William C. C. Claiborne</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl477d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                        <expan>Colonel</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name>David Henley</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Knoxville</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Philadelphia</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>March 14th 1800</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>WCC </abbr>
                        <expan>William Charles Cole</expan>
                     </choice> Claiborne</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
