<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc011">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1793 Aug. 31, [to] David Henley Esq[ui]r[e] / Henry
			 Knox: a machine-readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Knox, Henry</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Mays</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno>sc011</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50008623</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1793 Aug. 31, [to] David Henley Esq[ui]r[e] / Henry
				Knox</title>
               <author>Knox, Henry</author>
               <date when="1793-08-31">August 31, 1793</date>
               <extent>6p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This document is a letter written by Henry Knox,
				Secretary of War, to David Henley on August 31, 1793. In the letter, Knox
				appointed Henley as an agent for the War Department in the Southwest Territory.
				Knox further detailed the duties of Henley's new position, which mostly
				included regulating payments and supplies of all sorts for the troops of the
				Southwest Territory and also preventing and correcting improper expenditures.
				David Allison was appointed as a subordinate paymaster, who would be working
				under Henley. Henley's position was initially established on a temporary basis
				in response to recent occurrences in the Southwest Territory that required the
				deployment of more troops and greater expenditures by the War
				Department.</note>
               <note type="Collection"> David Henley, 1748-1823</note>
               <note type="Box">n/a</note>
               <note type="Folder">MS-736</note>
               <note type="Document">sc011</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>United States Politics and government, 1789-1797</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>Knox, Henry, 1750-1806</term>
               <term>Henley, David, 1749-1823</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n50042395"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Knox, Henry, 1750-1806</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc011a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To 
				  <name type="person">David Henley</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Esqr.</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice> Agent for the War
				  Department</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>in the 
				  <name type="place"> territory <choice>
                           <orig>South
					 west</orig>
                           <reg>southwest</reg>
                        </choice> of the Ohio</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The objects of <choice>
                  <orig>expence</orig>
                  <reg>expense</reg>
               </choice> having been
			 considerably multiplied by recent occurrences in the territory of the Unites
			 States South of the Ohio, it has been deemed <choice>
                  <orig>adviseable</orig>
                  <reg>advisable</reg>
               </choice> with the approbation of the President of the
			 United States to appoint you as an Agent of the War Department in that
			 territory. This appointment will have a temporary aspect until other and more
			 regular measures shall be ordained by the Congress of the 
			 <name type="place">United States</name>.</p>
            <p>All the supplies in the Quarter masters, Ordnance, Clothing, Pay,
			 Commissaries of Provisions Departments or other objects within the general
			 Department of War, will come under your cognizance.</p>
            <p>You are in all cases to use the highest vigilance to prevent all
			 abuse or injury to the public interests which may arise from negligence or
			 design.</p>
            <p>All militia which have been or shall be raised at the
			 <choice>
                  <orig>expence</orig>
                  <reg>expense</reg>
               </choice> of the Union are to be regularly and rigidly
			 mustered and inspected upon entering and quitting the service. The regular
			 troops are to be mustered monthly, and all militia who shall serve more than
			 two months, are also besides <add place="bottom right">the</add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sc011b.small.jpg"/>			 the before mentioned musters at entering and quitting the service also to be
			 mustered and inspected monthly in all practicable cases. This duty is if
			 possible to be performed by a regular Officer in your presence, but if a
			 regular Officer cannot be obtained you will appoint some respectable character
			 for the purpose. 
               </p>
            <p>All returns of public property belonging to the Quarter Master's,
			 Ordnance, or Provisions Departments must be signed by the commanding Officer of
			 the Battalion or Regiment, and all deficiencies must be accounted for at each
			 inspection.</p>
            <p>The payment of the regular troops and militia to be made according
			 to the rules established by the Comptroller of the Treasury herewith delivered
			 you, together with the explanations of the Accountant of the War
			 Department.</p>
            <p>You are considered in the aforesaid territory as vested with the
			 powers of Pay Master to the troops. 
			 <name type="person">David Allison</name> is appointed a subordinate
			 pay master and Storekeeper of all public property within your cognizance, and
			 he is to obey your orders in all things relatively to the modes of issuing the
			 Stores and keeping of the Accounts.</p>
            <p>Mr. Allison is to make the actual payments when the persons having
			 just claims shall appear for the purpose of receiving them. In all other cases
			 you <add place="bottom right">are</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sc011c.small.jpg"/> are to hold the money in
			 possession until it is to be paid to the person entitled to it.
               </p>
            <p>You have also herewith delivered to you the forms of accounts for
			 the Indian Department established by the Comptroller of the Treasury which must
			 be rigidly observed. The Indian Goods are to be delivered to the written orders
			 of 
			 <name type="person">Governor Blount</name>, and also all other stores
			 destined for the militia troops.</p>
            <p>The following mode of payment of the militia in the territory South
			 of the Ohio is to be observed as to the accounts already settled at the pay
			 Office  The money to be advanced in the first instance to you as Agent
			 for the Department of War upon Warrants of the Secretary of War.  To be
			 paid by you to Mr Allison subordinate paymaster and storekeeper upon Warrants
			 of Governor Blount countersigned by you, each of which Warrants will be for the
			 whole sum expressed on a payroll of a company or detachment.</p>
            <p>But the money is to be advanced to Mr Allison by you in parcels,
			 that is, in sums upon account of each Warrant in proportion as they shall be
			 wanted for actual <choice>
                  <orig>disbursment</orig>
                  <reg>disbursement</reg>
               </choice>. These advances
			 to be made weekly, receipts for each advance to be endorsed on the Warrant.</p>
            <p>To obtain them Mr. Allison will furnish you with a
			 <add place="bottom right">statement</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sc011d.small.jpg"/> statement of the sum
			 probably wanted from period to period, and when a further sum is applied for a
			 statement of the <choice>
                  <orig>disbursment</orig>
                  <reg>disbursement</reg>
               </choice> of the preceding
			 advance to be rendered to 
			 <name type="person">Mr Glowell</name>, Accountant of the War
			 Department, who will furnish copies of the pay abstracts as settled.
               </p>
            <p>It is difficult if not impracticable to detail with precision the
			 different parts of your duty, such details can only arise from experience. But
			 it is proper to be observed that you are to be placed in the territory South of
			 the Ohio as the public eye to regulate payments and supplies of all sorts for
			 the troops  to prevent and correct every improper expenditure relatively
			 to the Indians on Military Departments. The Government are desirous that all
			 stipulations or legal supplies shall be furnished most punctually; but at the
			 same time that energy pervades every Department, it is necessary it should be
			 accompanied by discretion purity and economy.</p>
            <p>You will therefore diligently endeavor to observe the public
			 interests in all respects  that you take all means in your power to
			 prevent or remedy <choice>
                  <orig>every thing</orig>
                  <reg>everything</reg>
               </choice> which may be wrong
			 by making the necessary representations to the commanding Officers and to this
			 Office  <add place="bottom right">while</add>
               <pb n="5" facs="sc011e.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>While you are correcting abuses in others, you must be peculiarly
			 circumspect with respect to yourself. For this purpose you will not hold any
			 public property in your possession, but deliver such as may come into your
			 possession to the persons who have been, or may be appointed to distribute
			 them, making all persons accountable to you for their receipts and
			 expenditures.</p>
            <p>You will make monthly reports to this office of all objects under
			 your direction, keeping each separate by itself </p>
            <p>You may in this business necessarily require assistance, which you
			 will obtain upon the best terms. All objects of reasonable expenditure
			 connected with the safety of the public stores, or the advancement of the
			 public business will be allowed you.</p>
            <p>Given at the War Office of the United States the 
			 <date when="1793-08-31">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>thirty first</orig>
                     <reg>thirty-first</reg>
                  </choice>
				day of August, in the year of our Lord One thousand seven hundred and ninety
				three</date>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>H</abbr>
                        <expan>Henry</expan>
                     </choice> Knox
				  </name>
                  <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Secy</abbr>
                     <expan>Secretary</expan>
                  </choice> of War
                  </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="sc011f.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>War Office</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1793-08-31">August 31  1793
				  </date>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Instructions from</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>H </abbr>
                        <expan>Henry</expan>
                     </choice> Knox</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Secretary of War</addrLine>
               </address>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
