<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl708">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> 1808 Jun. 5, Port Royal, Montgomery County, Tennessee [to] John Sevier /  Montgomery County, Tennessee [citizenry] : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Montgomery County [citizenry]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl708</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> 1808 Jun. 5, Port Royal, Montgomery County, Tennessee [to] John Sevier /  Montgomery County, Tennessee [citizenry]</title>
               <author>Montgomery County [citizenry]</author>
               <date when="1808-06-05"> 
			 June 5, 1808</date>
               <extent>6p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from the Montgomery citizenry to Governor John Sevier, dated June 5, 1808. The citizenry is requesting that Sevier call a special session of the General Assembly to address economical problems that have occurred due to the Embargo Act of 1807. The letter points out that other states like Georgia and Virginia have already done this. The citizenry would also like to use the session to address political problems inherent in the form of government that Tennessee has undertaken.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor John Sevier Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl708</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government to 1865</term>
               <term>Embargo, 1807-1809</term>
               <term>Law and legislation</term>
               <term>Southern states</term>
               <term>Politics, society, and economy</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Montgomery County [citizenry]</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl708a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To his Excellency</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>John Sevier</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Governor of the State of <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>At a time when the evils of a serious nature threaten the public prosperity we are impelled by Self preservation to turn our attention towards the proper source of <choice>
                  <orig>protution</orig>
                  <reg>prodition</reg>
               </choice> . The constitution and the voice of the people having invested your Excellency with the power of convening the Legislature we respectfully submit to your consideration the propriety of <unclear>Exercising</unclear> that important prerogative at this time. We presume it to be well known to your excellency that at the period when the political establishments of our common wealth were brought into existence the state was In its infancy; its inhabitants had but lately emigrated from various states with notions prejudices and political opinions better suited to their old than their New abode; the States had but recently emerged from British oppression; the people had been so <choice>
                  <orig>zealiously</orig>
                  <reg>zealously</reg>
               </choice> employed in resisting foreign aggressions and savage depredations that they had not sufficiently reflected on the impropriety the unfitness and the destructive consequences which would attend the adoption of the political institutions laws and maxims of that corrupt and <choice>
                  <orig>tyranical</orig>
                  <reg>tyrannical</reg>
               </choice> government from <add>whose</add> devouring grasp they had escaped with toil and bloodshed.</p>
            <p>Experience had not then taught them to Substitute theories more congenial with their interest and convenience and unnatural imitations of their ancient government were incorporated into their political fabric which destroys its beauty and utility. Our Judiciary System in particular is found by experience to be <choice>
                  <orig>oppresive</orig>
                  <reg>oppressive</reg>
               </choice>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl708b.small.jpg"/> Inconvenient and inefficacious. The almost universal disapprobation of the theory and practice of that branch of our government which has been gradually manifesting itself for years has by late discussions and publications become so general that in our humble opinion it merits the attention of the Legislature. A period of public peace and domestic quietness like the present appears most appropriate in which to effect such salutary changes in our political institutions as experience has pointed out to be necessary; Should they be <choice>
                  <orig>omited</orig>
                  <reg>omitted</reg>
               </choice> till another year it is to be feared that accumulation of other business or perhaps the <del type="overstrike">contagious</del> contagion of war being caught from <name>Europe</name> may interfere and prevent the desired improvements.</p>
            <p>Another consideration of much weight and more urgent necessity arises from the political situation of the general government. far be it from us to shrink from our share of the common calamity which the nation for the purpose of preserving its independence has inflicted on itself. the effects of the embargo are felt perhaps as severely in this state as in any other; and the proportion of severity is <choice>
                  <orig>encreased</orig>
                  <reg>increased</reg>
               </choice> by the circumstances of the general credits which have been extended to the great mass of community by Venders of imported articles. The stagnation of trade whilst it prevents the influx of Specie raises its value: hence the monied and the creditor class of community have great and undue advantage of the debtor class to remedy evils of this nature the Legislatures of <name>Maryland</name> and <name>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Vergenia</orig>
                     <reg>Virginia</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> have Suspended during the Continuance of the embargo the sale of property by public auction in consequence of Judgements obtained in court. The same salutary measures has been effected by the constitu <add>te</add> d authority of the state of <name>Georgia</name> the debtor citizens of those and perhaps of other states are protected from ruin by the Just and benevolent <pb n="3" facs="sl708c.small.jpg"/> Interference of public authority as it respects mercantile concerns it is most undoubtedly unfair to suffer the Merchants of the <name>atlantic</name> cities who are themselves relieved from the pressure of the law to have the advantage of law here to compel the payment of those sums from our merchants which must at last be Extracted by the unrelenting hand of the law from the hard earned property of our farmers and <choice>
                  <orig>mechanicks</orig>
                  <reg>mechanics</reg>
               </choice> . many <choice>
                  <orig>Sacrafices</orig>
                  <reg>Sacrifices</reg>
               </choice> of property have already taken place; at public sales ready money produces double <choice>
                  <orig>treble</orig>
                  <reg>trouble</reg>
               </choice> and sometimes quadruple its former value these circumstances are calculated to carry ruin into the habitations of a worthy portion  of the community. and unless some s <add>p</add> eedy remedy is afforded incalculable calamity will be inflicted on those people who have been in the habit of looking to your Excellency for protection in the day of <unclear>vicissitudes</unclear> and the hour of danger; they are confident that you fe <add>e</add> l their distress and will extend all the relief in your power; they know that any oppressive System which is calculated to add misery to the distressed__ to distress the weak and  to elevate the Strong to make the poor poorer and rich richer will meet with your entire disappobation: Therefore for these and the aforementiontioned reasons We the Subscribers do respectfully request that you will call a Session of the general assembly as speedily as may be consistent with your opinion of the urgency of the case to take into their wise consideration these important Subjects of public complaint and to devise such remedy as in their wisdom they may deem expedient <date>July 5 1808</date>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Port Royal</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>State of Tennessee</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Montgomery county</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl708d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc> signatures of the citizens of Montgomery County Tennessee</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <pb n="5" facs="sl708e.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>signatures of the citizens of Montgomery County Tennessee</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <pb n="6" facs="sl708f.small.jpg"/>
               <add>meeting held <date>June 10, 1808</date>
                  <lb/> asking <choice>
                     <abbr>Gov.</abbr>
                     <expan>Governor </expan>
                  </choice> Sevier to <choice>
                     <orig>convin</orig>
                     <reg>convene</reg>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/> the Legislature in Extra ordinary <lb/> Session <choice>
                     <abbr>etc</abbr>
                     <expan>etcetera</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <add>In Senate <choice>
                     <abbr>apl</abbr>
                     <expan>april</expan>
                  </choice> 3 1809 <lb/> read and Sent to <lb/> to the House of <choice>
                     <abbr>rep</abbr>
                     <expan>representatives</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/>
                  <unclear>Jo M Anderson</unclear>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
