<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc227">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1849 Mar. 19, Nashville, Tennessee [to] D. C[lint]  Douglass Lebanon, Tennessee / Alfred William Douglass : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Douglass, Alfred William</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc227</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1849 Mar. 19, Nashville, Tennessee [to] D. C[lint]  Douglass Lebanon, Tennessee / Alfred William Douglass</title>
               <author> Douglass, Alfred William</author>
               <date when="1849-03-19">March 19, 1849 
			 </date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated March 19, 1849 from Alfred William Douglass to his cousin Clint.  Douglass died on August 23, 1849 as the result of a bout with cholera, it was only five months after writing this  letter.  Douglass is writing from Nashville, Tennessee and tells his cousin of many lively and interesting happenings in that area.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Douglass Letter</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">New Accessions</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc227</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Douglass, Alfred William</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc227a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <name>Nashville</name>
               <date>March 19th 1849</date>
               <salute>Dear Clint,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Various causes have conspired to make this letter so long in coming, but it is bootless to tell.  Let them pass.  I am once again in this town of "wooden men__" left old Sumner this morning, and although "le cholera" is still at work and with increased malignity, I could stand "les bleus" no longer, and so "vamoosed".  I expect to remain here until I make a final adjournment in favor of <name>Arkansas</name>, <name>Texas</name>, <name>Oregon</name> or <name>California</name>.  Time passed but slowly and heavily in the country, for of all situations in this world, that of a "gentlemen of leisure" with nothing to do and no where to go is the most intolerably irksome to me.  venerable gobblers, with reverend beards, are not to be found every day__ they are decidedly "rarae aves"__ trout are only found in certain remote and un-come-at-a-ble creeks__  Squirrels, hares, robins and such "varmits" are beneath the notice of grave Academies as well as acute jurio- consults- "where by <unclear>(saffarans lo quitier!)</unclear> being out of employment I have rashly returned to this forlorn part of boredom, and may be found at office on Cherry <choice>
                  <abbr>St.</abbr>
                  <expan>Street</expan>
               </choice>  at all hours, unless absent or professionally, or otherwise engaged, c. </p>
            <p>Our school increases daily__  We have thirty-one students, and several more promised__ and by the end of this session we expect fifty or sixty, but I have so great repugnance to towns that it is no gratification to succeed.  I will, however, cheerfully endure the inflictions of a city life, since so it must be.    Others may go to the <choice>
                  <orig>amiferous</orig>
                  <reg>omnifarious</reg>
               </choice>  vale of <name>San <choice>
                     <orig>Sacrimento</orig>
                     <reg>Sacramento</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name>, others may attend concert, wedding, rout, revel, soiree, convensagoine, or write for amateur literary clubs, ay, others may rouse the dull eye of right with "torch and <pb n="2" facs="sc227b.small.jpg"/> flambeau fast arrayed," and wake the shuddering echoes from their loins in cave or cedar thicket by the wild screams of terror struck and helpless robins, fluttering in the hands of savage captors, and vainly appealing for mercy to eyes that gloat in triumph over arresting innocence, others may amuse themselves with ascertaining by what, or whether by any tenure <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jno.</abbr>
                     <expan>John</expan>
                  </choice> Smith</name> holds the property which he calls his own, or whether Peter Jones on a certain or some other occasion, and with a stick, gun, knife, bludgeon, or other implement did commit <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c, &amp;c, &amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>etcetera, etcetera, etcetera</expan>
               </choice>__  But for me__ I am here! Helas!__</p>
            <p>Nothing has transpired since your visit, that I know of.  I suppose, as usual, you will be in Sumner when this reaches you__  No matter.__ I came very near coming to your fair village last Friday to attend <choice>
                  <abbr>bro</abbr>
                  <expan>brother</expan>
               </choice> Plummer's Quarterly Meeting__ but I had made up my mind to come down here, and bro. Acton told me he was going over himself, and I knew <choice>
                  <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                  <expan>Doctor</expan>
               </choice>. Green would retire and conclude it would be best not to overwhelm you with such an avalanche of great men, ergo, I staid away!!</p>
            <p>I am anxious to hear what conclusion you have come to about going to the West next fall.  I think it would be better for you to stay another year at Law School, although  advice is usually useless__ No young man in any profession is in danger of becoming too well versed in his business, and more time and money are saved by spending both in mature preparation, <choice>
                  <orig>expecially</orig>
                  <reg>especially</reg>
               </choice> in law, as I think observation has long since taught me.  A mere pettifogger, a bully of the criminal court, can be made by six weeks reading of Statutes, and a <choice>
                  <orig>sufficency</orig>
                  <reg>sufficiency</reg>
               </choice> of impudence and ill breeding but a decent lawyer, a man worthy of that honorable title, is a flight <choice>
                  <orig>beyound</orig>
                  <reg>beyond</reg>
               </choice> that mark in my humble notion, and is the result of long and patient training before, after, and all the time.  So say I. <pb n="3" facs="sc227c.small.jpg"/>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>P.S.</abbr>
                  <expan>Post Script</expan>
               </choice> I am finishing this hasty scrawl in my room Tuesday afternoon.  I would be very glad to see you in my vacation about the first half of April__  Write as soon as you get this, and tell me how you are pleased with your work this session, and all the news of your vicinity.  These late days, it seems to me there is more life, good wholesome life, in Lebanon (from your representations) than in my part of the country I know of, therefore write! Our friends are all well.  <name>Charlie Abston</name> is, <unclear>horo du  combat</unclear> (cornfield?) yet, and I am unable to tell what ails him.  Is your "Iunian" flourishing?__  Can't you send me a copy?__  Do, Clint, steal one.  Twould; no question, be "grand larceny," but so well practised a barrister ought to know how such things may be done with impunity!__</p>
            <p>I have just got a copy of Macaulay's History of England, and expect a fine treat in its perusal from the specimens I have glanced at in the journals of the day.  It is yet unfinished. Have you much time for reading?  See that none be wasted.  The two years ahead of you, will be worth a half dozen of what may come ten years hence.  Will you come over next &amp; Friday week, and let me know of it beforehand, so that we may take a regular fishing "phsolique"__   Write and tell me of it__ </p>
            <p>There is no alarm here about cholera, though there are some deaths nearly every day__ A very respectable gentleman, named Ford, I believe, book keepers of H. &amp; B. Douglas, died last night after a few hours illness.__ I shall look for a letter soon__ as all events before I leave for vacation which will  commence the last day of March__ Be sure to write__  Be a good boy__ study hard__ catch robins and minnows__ write and do, in earnest__ and come over to Sumner as I directed__ Good bye.  Your affectionate cousin, </p>
            <closer>
               <name>A.W. Douglass</name>
               <pb n="4" facs="sc227d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>D.C. Douglass <choice>
                        <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>.  Lebanon, <abbr>Tenn</abbr>.</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
