<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="tl027">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1797 Jan. 12, Knoxville, [Tennessee to] warriors and
			 Chiefs of the Cherokee Nation / John Sevier, Governor of the state of
			 Tennessee: a machine-readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Sevier, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Holly Adams</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno>tl027</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 47826412</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, Tennessee. It may be used freely by individuals for
				research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability
				is included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1797 Jan. 12, Knoxville, [Tennessee to] warriors and
				Chiefs of the Cherokee Nation/ John Sevier, Governor of the state of
				Tennessee</title>
               <author>Sevier, John</author>
               <date when="1797-01-12">January 12, 1797</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary"> This document is a letter addressed to the
				warriors and chiefs of the Cherokee Nation, written by Governor John Sevier of
				Tennessee (1796-1801) and dated January 12, 1797. The letter was given to
				Cherokee agent Silas Dinsmore to be read aloud to the Cherokee. In his letter,
				Sevier accused some Cherokees of stealing horses and plundering wagons that had
				passed through the Cumberland road. Sevier laid the blame on "foolish young
				people" within the Cherokee Nation but hoped the chiefs and warriors were not
				encouraging such acts. Sevier urged the Cherokee leaders to work with Dinsmore
				in getting the stolen property returned. Sevier also expressed condolences for
				the murder of an Indian and stated that he doubted any of his people would do
				such a thing. The letter was initially ended on a note of warning to the
				Cherokee, as Sevier insinuated that if they continued their aggressive
				behavior, war would be option. However, the last two sections of the original
				letter were deleted from the final text.</note>
               <note type="Collection">Governor John Sevier Papers</note>
               <note type="Box">1</note>
               <note type="Folder">3</note>
               <note type="Document">tl027</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Government relations</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Claims against</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Violence against</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr89016779"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Sevier, John, 1745-1815</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tl027a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Knoxville</name>
                     <date when="1797-01-12">12th January 1797</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Brothers</salute>.</opener>
            <p>I have just now arrived at this place, and am Sorry to be informed
			 that some of your foolish young people have been taking horses and plundering
			 <choice>
                  <orig>waggons</orig>
                  <reg>wagons</reg>
               </choice> on the 
			 <name type="place">Cumberland</name> road; such conduct will soon
			 darken the bright chain of friendship that now so happily is joined to each
			 nation. I hope you that are Warriors and chiefs, do not encourage such
			 proceedings, and I have a better opinion of you, than to Suppose you would any
			 longer Suffer it to be done.  You have no reason to think I wish any
			 ill, neither does the great majority of the white people, in case your nation
			 will be friendly. You know I have always advised you, not to let foolish young
			 fellows destroy the good understanding between us. I request you will proceed
			 to make inquiry after the <lb/> horses <pb n="2" facs="tl027b.small.jpg"/> horses and other property
			 that have lately been taken by your people <del type="overstrike">and if you
			 can find any</del>
               <add place="supralinear">and</add> send the same into
			 this place, in order that the owners may have it again, by which means our
			 friendship will continue to be firm and Strong. I have wrote to 
			 <name> 
                  <reg>person</reg> Mr Dinsmore</name> on this Subject, and hope you
			 will pursue such measures as will enable you and him to recover the Stolen
			 property.
                  
               </p>
            <p>
               <add place="between paragraphs">Your friend brother (Signed) 
			 <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>J</abbr>
                        <expan>John</expan>
                     </choice>
				Sevier</name>
               </add>
               <del type="overstrike">Brothers I am Sorry to hear one of
		  our red friends has lately been killed, and if I can find out that any of our
		  people has been guilty of such a dark and unfriendly action I will have them
		  punished, but I have great reason to hope and believe that it was not any of
		  our people, 
		  <choice>
                     <abbr>altho</abbr>
                     <expan>although</expan>
                  </choice> there is bad men in every nation,
		  yet I am Sure it was not done by a person belonging to our State.</del>
            </p>
            <p>
               <del type="overstrike">I have always told you , that I wished your
		  nation to do well, and I hope they may always live in <pb n="3" facs="tl027c.small.jpg"/> peace, and
		  raise their Children in friendship with their <choice>
                     <orig>neighbours</orig>
                     <reg>neighbors</reg>
                  </choice> and brothers the white people.  My
		  brothers you know if stealing of horses is Suffered to be done, peace
		  <choice>
                     <orig>wont</orig>
                     <reg>won't</reg>
                  </choice> last long, and you must be sensible your
		  Situation will be dangerous; you are but few in numbers and war will ruin you
		  if ever you engage in it again.
                  </del>
            </p>
            <p>
               <del type="overstrike">Our people lives very near you, and reason
		  will teach you that they <choice>
                     <orig>dont</orig>
                     <reg>don't</reg>
                  </choice> wish to have any
		  disturbances or quarrel with you.</del>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your friend and brother</salute>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Warriors and Chiefs of </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>the Cherokee Nation </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="tl027d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>Letter<lb/> the Cherokees 
			 <date when="1797-01-12">12th <lb/> January 1797
                     </date>
               <lb/>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>No</abbr>
                  <expan>Number</expan>
               </choice> 14 (enclosed in a circle)
			 <add> Recorded </add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
