<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl428">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1847 Mar. 15, Carthage, Tennessee [to] Bromfield S. Ridley / A[dam] Fergusson: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Fergusson, A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl428</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1847 Mar. 15, Carthage, Tennessee [to] Bromfield S. Ridley / A[dam] Fergusson</title>
               <author>Fergusson, A.</author>
               <date when="1847-03-15">March 15, 1847</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Adam Fergusson to Bromfield S. Ridley, dated March 15, 1847. Fergusson is writing on behalf of two of his nephews. They  have both applied for the position of clerk and master of Chancery Court in Macon County. Fergusson gives his opinion that either will be a fine candidate, although he only describes the accomplishments of one.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fergusson Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">IV-G-1, B6</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">3</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl428</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Local government</term>
               <term>Working life</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Fergusson, Adam</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl428a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Carthage</name>
                     <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>15th March 1847</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Mr <name>Ira Fergusson</name> bearer <choice>
                  <orig>hereoff</orig>
                  <reg>hereof</reg>
               </choice> will hand you this. The unexpected death of Mr <name>A I Wade</name>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                  <expan>Esquire</expan>
               </choice> clerk &amp; master of the Chancery court at <name>Lafayette</name>
               <name>Macon county</name> has created a vacancy in the office of clerk which you will be called on to fill by appointment. Mr Wade was taken Sick on wednesday last and died on friday night with <choice>
                  <orig>inflamation</orig>
                  <reg>inflammation</reg>
               </choice> of the brain; and is one of those instances to remind us how frail is man. My nephew above named is an applicant for the office. Mr <name>Daniel D Claibourne</name> another nephew is also an applicant I regret this as they are both nephews one a brothers and the other a Sisters Son consequently I could Say nothing in <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice> of one more than the other they are both sprightly young men and either will make a good clerk by a little experience. Their <choice>
                  <orig>politicks</orig>
                  <reg>politics</reg>
               </choice> (Democrats) are the Same Should you feel unwilling to decide between them, I have instructed Ira Fergusson bearer hereoff to withdraw his claims as an act of generosity towards an absent relative I also include his <add>Claibournes</add> letter to me as an act of Justice towards him every word of which is Substantially true. I did as far back as last December or before that time promise to aid him <add>Daniel D Claibourne</add> in the obtaining this <choice>
                  <orig>verry</orig>
                  <reg>very</reg>
               </choice> office Should Mr wade resign. You will therefore See by Mr Clibournes letter his real Situation He has been Licenced as <pb n="2" facs="sl428b.small.jpg"/>
               <gap/> Lawyer writes a beautiful hand <add>(see his letter)</add> has been a <unclear>merchant</unclear>
               <gap/> and is a good calculator an <choice>
                  <orig>eSential</orig>
                  <reg>essential</reg>
               </choice> qualification in a clerk &amp; master and although you may not be <choice>
                  <orig>acquanted</orig>
                  <reg>acquainted</reg>
               </choice> with him will please you if you appoint him. As to the <choice>
                  <orig>Publick</orig>
                  <reg>Public</reg>
               </choice> interest I think it entirely Safe in the appointment of either and I am willing to Stand as Security in the appointment of either. I am well acquainted with the whole population of macon county and know of no other persons more Suitable there may be Some young Lawyers from <name>Kentucky</name> who have Settled in Lafayette for their own particular interest These have no Sympathy whatever with the old established citizens except Self interest and I hope their claims will not have the Same weight with you Should any of them be urged before <add>you</add> I know it is usual to obtain the letters of Some of the members of the bar in favour of the applicants. In the event you require this I will try and forward Some to meet you at <name>Smithville</name> or at McMinnville</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>with great respect and esteem <lb/> I remain yours truly</salute>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>A.</abbr>
                     <expan>Adam</expan>
                  </choice> Fergusson</signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Honble</abbr>
                        <expan>Honorable</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <name>Bromfield S Ridley</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Chancellor <choice>
                        <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                        <expan>etcetera</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>PS</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> You will please return my Brothers letter to me after you read it <lb/> Respectfully <lb/> A Fergusson</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
