<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl361">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1837 Jan. 31, Leighton, Ala[bama] [to] Finis Ewing, Lexington. M[issouri] / Ja[me]s Smith   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Smith, James</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl361</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1837 Jan. 31, Leighton, Ala[bama] [to] Finis Ewing, Lexington. M[issouri] / Ja[me]s Smith</title>
               <author>Smith, James</author>
               <date when="1837-01-31">January 31, 1837</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated January 31, 1837. It is Rev. Finis Ewing from  Rev. James Smith. Smith is travelling and relates the state of the Cumberland Presbyterian churches he has visited. He is very upset and disheartened. He writes that the Methodists are making converts, and that many of the churches lose so many members that the are no more. Smith is upset that there are many in the church with differing theologies. He describes the unorthodox beliefs of some. Smith  is worried that heresy will take over the church. Smith mentions that this trip has been bad for his business at home, and that he has been borrowing money from different people.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Finis Ewing Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">I-A-4</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">17</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl361</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Alabama</term>
               <term>Cumberland Presbyterian Church</term>
               <term>Religious thought - 19th century</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Smith, James</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl361a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Br,,</abbr>
                     <expan>Brother</expan>
                  </choice> Ewing</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <add>January 1837</add>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Beleiving</orig>
                  <reg>Believing</reg>
               </choice> that I owe you a letter and having stopped at a Brothers for the night and finding myself without company as without employment and seeing the old stump of an old pen thick with ink and dirt. I have concluded to save myself from the blues by whiling off the time in addressing you but as I am very much in the suds I think it probable you will but be much edified it is consolation forever to think that being <choice>
                  <orig>afflected</orig>
                  <reg>afflicted</reg>
               </choice> with the <name>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Hipo</orig>
                     <reg>Hippo</reg>
                  </choice>
               </name> I may by the effort communicate some of that delectable <choice>
                  <orig>desease</orig>
                  <reg>disease</reg>
               </choice> even to you away off in Missouri.</p>
            <p>To begin In travelling along I  have this day been looking at the state of our church and whether it is owing to the sombre state of my mind or an absolute truth I cannot tell but it appears to me she is under the influence of an eclipse or about to experience an Earthquake There is the College for instance after all the  blowing made about <add>it  it is</add> likely to <choice>
                  <orig>toter</orig>
                  <reg>totter</reg>
               </choice> to the ground <name>Barnet</name> having so managed that the association cant get it out of his hands he and <unclear>Lssit at  words prints</unclear> and he and myself on no very agreeable terms. There in <name>Alabama</name> you may find churches almost dead nearly plucked up by the roots Preachers buried among Negro quarters of no <unclear>care</unclear> to themselves nor any body old Elsewhere Methodism stalking at noon day among the preachers making converts to its heterodoxy <pb n="2" facs="sl361b.small.jpg"/> By the way, did you no my short sermon on imputation &amp; the article "are all men corrupt?" There were <choice>
                  <orig>writen</orig>
                  <reg>written</reg>
               </choice> at the request of a certain by little brother by the name of <name>Bell</name> in <name>Wilson County</name> whose object I find is to get into notice, he is a <unclear>competition</unclear> but full of vanity <unclear>so</unclear> Uncle Finis put your foot upon him in the papers  if this is not done speedily she will be over run with all manner of heresy and you may live to see sad headburnings on D <gap/>
               <unclear>Doctrinal</unclear> nal matters in the Church. There is a  brother who holds that Adam did not represent his race there is one who holds that infants are <choice>
                  <orig>inocent</orig>
                  <reg>innocent</reg>
               </choice> depraved beings fit for neither heaven nor hell do tell him where to put these <choice>
                  <orig>anomolies</orig>
                  <reg>anomalies</reg>
               </choice> in nature when they quit this world <unclear>Nynder</unclear> is one <choice>
                  <orig>sturddy</orig>
                  <reg>sturdy</reg>
               </choice> contending that <del type="overstrike">that</del> the soul  at conversion is as holy as it will be in heaven blaming his poor body for all its lusts and <choice>
                  <orig>abberations</orig>
                  <reg>aberrations</reg>
               </choice> And there is one who doubts the Divinity of the <name>Lord Jesus Christ</name> all <name>Cumberlands</name>  good Cumberlands orthodox Cumberlands verily if these are the men who are to instruct my children in the great matters of their salvation when I am dead and gone I if I can will pack up and put out for old <unclear>Lutherand</unclear> that reminds me of your inquiry about my <unclear>continuing</unclear> there I cant enter upon it here only the Editor of the periodical devoted to the Church of <name>Scotland</name> get hold of a copy of the <choice>
                  <abbr>C. P.</abbr>
                  <expan>Cumberland Presbyterian</expan>
               </choice> and quoted from &amp; remarked on it and on the church myself in particular <pb n="3" facs="sl361c.small.jpg"/> to put <unclear>voluntaryism</unclear> in the shade, I wrote a <choice>
                  <orig>tery</orig>
                  <reg>teary</reg>
               </choice> epistle about the enormous lies he told on me for a <choice>
                  <orig>pereodical</orig>
                  <reg>periodical</reg>
               </choice> there, &amp; threatened him with another dose concerning the lies he told on the Church, I have since seen the <unclear>beg be</unclear> he told on me some of my friends there have made him take back &amp; put in his pocket. The other matter is not yet settled but you will hear all about it by &amp; bye the young freshman is back  in <name>America</name>
               <gap/> preaching in <name>Michigan</name>. He would <gap/> for that country. I must go there <gap/> and if it be Gods will I shall go The Magazine was ready for publication <add>when I left</add> only waiting for your letter. I wrote you three copies of the 1st <unclear>tho</unclear> .</p>
            <p>To come back to my old gloominess here am I packing about the country to the great injury of my business at home calling on one <unclear>subereber</unclear> for $5. another for $3 another for $10. to meet demands at home Uncle Fine I cant stand this it is too <choice>
                  <orig>lait</orig>
                  <reg>late</reg>
               </choice>  and there is little <name>Haines</name> with his Pittsburgher a Unitarian  in sentiment a <unclear>believe in Infant Irishsscation</unclear> , three years ago quit the Church rode as a Methodist <unclear>bercutuder</unclear> &amp; came back and was made Elder  <choice>
                  <orig>verely</orig>
                  <reg>verily</reg>
               </choice> we Cumberlands are strange <choice>
                  <orig>sett</orig>
                  <reg>set</reg>
               </choice> But I  say I cant stand it next Assembly will settle the hash with me. and I <pb n="4" facs="sl361d.small.jpg"/> having effected this I may close by praying that God of his great grace may have mercy upon our <unclear>feeble</unclear> church &amp; save it from becoming a <unclear>hessing &amp; a byard</unclear>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Yours <unclear>yet</unclear> affectionately</salute>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Jas.</abbr>
                     <expan>James</expan>
                  </choice> Smith</signed>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P. S</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> Lowry declined coming to <name>Nashville</name> until spring I fear it will then be too late <add>
                     <address>
                        <addrLine>
                           <name>Leighton</name>
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>ala</abbr>
                              <expan>Alabama</expan>
                           </choice>
                        </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>
                           <date>31 <choice>
                                 <abbr>Jany</abbr>
                                 <expan>January</expan>
                              </choice>
                           </date>
                        </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>
                           <name>
                              <choice>
                                 <abbr>Revd</abbr>
                                 <expan>Reverend</expan>
                              </choice> Finis Ewing</name>
                        </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>
                           <name>Lexington</name>
                        </addrLine>
                        <addrLine>
                           <name>Missouri</name>
                        </addrLine>
                     </address>
                  </add>I expect with Cumberland college too new I presume you are about as gloomy &amp; melancholy as myself and </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
