<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc190">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1844 Feb. 8, Smithville, Tennessee [to] Parsons  &amp; Walker / M.M. Brien,  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Brien, M.M. </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc190</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1844 Feb. 8, Smithville, Tennessee [to] Parsons  &amp; Walker / M.M. Brien, </title>
               <author>Brien, M.M. </author>
               <date when="1844-02-08"> 
			 February 8, 1844</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated February 8, 1844 from M.M. Brien to the law firm Parsons &amp; Walker.  In the letter, Brien asks for an update on a pending case, and offers the attorneys additional information.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Brien Letter</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-1870</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc190</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Judicial proceedings 1790-2000.</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Brien, M. M.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc190a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Smithville</addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Feby 8th /44</abbr>
                     <expan>February 8th, 1844</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Mess</abbr>
                     <expan>Messuiers</expan>
                  </choice> Parsons &amp; Walker</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Gentlemen, permit me again to trouble you with a line or two on the subject of <name>Tubbs &amp; Reynolds</name> suit <choice>
                  <abbr>Vs</abbr>
                  <expan>versus</expan>
               </choice> Driver and others.  I wish to know what steps has been taken  has the defendants been served with papers.  if they have has the defendants answered if they have I should like to know the substance &amp; points <unclear>ordered</unclear> on by them.  This is only for my own information and if there is any proof <unclear>warranted</unclear> I want to know what it is in order that as may be taking it  as we may be <choice>
                  <orig>redy</orig>
                  <reg>ready</reg>
               </choice> for trial at the may term.  we want the case brought to a close as soon as possible.  we have <choice>
                  <orig>lerned</orig>
                  <reg>learned</reg>
               </choice> that <choice>
                  <abbr>Col</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Hendrson has again hired out the negroes for the present year.  and sold the land &amp; we also have learned that the suit against Driver in the <name>Louisiana</name> circuit court was tried and judgement went against Driver for some 7 or 8 $ which is not more than half the value of the negores sued for, but we learn that Henderson has got the negroes for the judgement.  if he has <choice>
                  <orig>don</orig>
                  <reg>done</reg>
               </choice> that it will do. but I do not know  how what is in your last letter you wrote that the suit had not been tried but shortly we  learn by a letter from  Henderson to <name>John Reynolds</name> that it had been tried so we imagine you was mistaken I wish you to pay some Little attention to the way Henderson is hiring the negroes.&amp; see what he has done with Ours negores.  Write me fully on receipt of this what has been done.  Tubb &amp; Reynolds is very anxious, to hear.  &amp; whether it is necessary for any of us to come out. &amp; see it any thing in person that we ought to attend to.  We want the cause trial at may if any chance.  <choice>
                  <orig>Tho</orig>
                  <reg>Though</reg>
               </choice> I suppose therewill have to be an <unclear>accout</unclear> ordered the first thing, so write me on the subject </p>
            <closer>Respectfully <signed>M.M. Brien</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
