<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm041">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Photograph of the posthole pattern of a Cherokee townhouse at
			 the former site of the mid-18th century Cherokee town of Toqua, taken in 1977]
			 / [by Robert D. Newman]: a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Newman, Robert D.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Catherine Michelle Love</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name>
               <name>Tara Hottenstein</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. 3k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2000</date>
            <idno>mm041</idno>
            <idno>OCLC:45095075</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Museum, University of
				Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Photograph of the posthole pattern of a Cherokee townhouse at
				the former site of the mid-18th century Cherokee town of Toqua, taken in 1977]
				/ [by Robert D. Newman]</title>
               <author>Newman, Robert D.</author>
               <date>1977</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This is a photograph of the posthole pattern of
				a Cherokee winter townhouse at the former site of mid-18th century Toqua.
				Winter townhouses were cone-shaped and appeared to look like small mountains
				from a distance. Townhouses were used for all public, social, and political
				events. Some were large enough to hold 500 people. The seats were arranged like
				an amphitheater with the seats rising one above another, leaving an area in the
				center for a fire. Excavations were conducted by the University of Tennessee in
				1977 in anticipation of the flooding of the lower Little Tennessee River by the
				Tellico Dam Reservoir. The excavations were conducted under contract with the
				National Park Service and the Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA). Principal
				investigator, Jefferson Chapman. Field Director, Robert D. Newman</note>
               <note type="collection">Frank H. McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note type="document">mm041</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Photographs</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Dwellings</term>
               <term>Holes</term>
               <term>Salvage archaeology</term>
               <term>Historic sites</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n86838538"
                        role="Photographer http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/pht">Newman, Robert D.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mm041.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Posthole pattern of Cherokee townhouse at Toqua, mid-18th
				  century. Excavations by the University of Tennessee, 1977. Photograph by Robert
				  D. Newman. This information was provided by the Frank H. McClung
				  Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
