<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc219">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title> [Letter] 1815 Sep. 18, Swan Pond, Tennessee [to] James G[ettys] M[cGready] Ramsey, Washington College [near Jonesboro] Tennessee / F[rancis] A[lexander] Ramsey : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Ramsey, Francis Alexander</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc219</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1815 Sep. 18, Swan Pond, Tennessee [to] James G[ettys] M[cGready] Ramsey, Washington College [near Jonesboro] Tennessee / F[rancis] A[lexander] Ramsey</title>
               <author>Ramsey, Francis Alexander</author>
               <date when="1815-09-18"> 
			 September 18, 1815</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Francis A. Ramsey to his son, James, dated September 18, 1815. The letter is also for another son, possibly William Baine Alexander Ramsey. James is attending Washington College. Francis expresses concern that he has not yet heard from his son. He mentions some news of the family and neighbors at Swan Pond. Francis requests that James write to him to tell him how James is planning to travel home at the end of the term. Francis regrets that he has no money to send James at this time.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Ramsey Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS 253, B1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">F1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc219</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Ramsey family</term>
               <term>Family communications</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2007053135"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Ramsey, Francis A. (Francis Alexander), 1764-1820</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc219a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Swan pond</name>
                     <date>September 18, 1815</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My Dear Sons)</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>we have been very anxious about you for some time past, not having heard any thing from you since your better by <name>Mr Brails</name>__ <name>Mr McCall</name> came here yesterday, which has given me an unexpected opportunity of writing to you__ your <unclear>Ma</unclear> has been <gap/> at the <name>yellow Spring</name> got home last <unclear>Tuesday</unclear> morning, appears to have got  benefit by the water there, Grand Pa has had as good health as well the rest well _ _ your Uncle some what better, old <name>Robert Patton</name> died the 4th instant__ no other alterations in the neighborhood I expected to have heard from you before now to have known what way you expected to get home at the end of the present <gap/> whether you would get horses or whether I must send <gap/> to you ___ I have now no money or I would have Sent by the present opportunity_ enclosed is a letter to Mr Carmichail , I want you to go over to him perhaps he may give you some money upon it_ you can go this week and if he fails let me know by mail next week I would have <gap/> mail before now but was about last week bringing Ma home __ My Dear Sons remember a Fathers <unclear>anxiety</unclear> for your being good and doing good By Ma and the rest I am joined in prescribing Our <choice>
                  <orig>Tinderest</orig>
                  <reg>Tenderest</reg>
               </choice> affections to you both_ may god of his infinite Mercy Bless you both is the  earnest Prayer of your anxious and affectionate Father</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>FA</abbr>
                        <expan>Francis Alexander</expan>
                     </choice> Ramsey</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P.S.</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> present our Friendly Salutations to the <unclear>Family</unclear> where you live also to <unclear> Tel</unclear>
               </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sc219b.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>James <choice>
                           <abbr>G MG</abbr>
                           <expan>Gettys McGready</expan>
                        </choice> Ramsey</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <unclear>located at</unclear>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Washington College</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>By the <unclear>politeness</unclear> of <lb/>
                  <name>Mr Patterson</name>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
