<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl599">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1846 Dec. 31,  Matamoros, Mexico [to] R.B. Farmer / M.A. Haynes : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Haynes, M.A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl599</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1846 Dec. 31,  Matamoros, Mexico [to] R.B. Farmer / M.A. Haynes</title>
               <author>  Haynes, M.A.</author>
               <date when="1846-12-31"> 
			 December 31, 1846</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter from Captain Haynes to General R.B. Turner regarding the muster rolls for his company in Matamoros, Mexico during the Mexican War. The letter also contains details of the company's marches through various towns and cities in Mexico.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Aaron V. Brown Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">B1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">F5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl599 </note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Mexican War 1846-1848</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Haynes, M.A.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl599a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Matamoros, Mexico </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date>Decr. 31. 1846</date>
               <salute>Dear Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Herewith you will find enclosed a very hastily prepared Muster Roll of my Company       as it is on this day, together with a brief notice  of its march &amp; its future  condition</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Maj Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>Major General</expan>
               </choice> Patterson's Division, is to day &amp; will be tomorrow  in Victoria, the Capital of the State of Tamaulipas __ 230 miles South S. West from this place.</p>
            <p>I went to San Fernando, 90 miles, but was on the 28th ordered to march back to this place, to procure supplies for the army.</p>
            <p>No Troops are now, or will be left on this route.__With 50 or 60 men, &amp; about 100 teamsters I am ordered to march to Victoria, through the bilingo country. We do not expect opposition yet we know that any of the Towns intervening, together with a few neighboring ranchos, could assemble 4 or 500 men, to dispute our passage.  We do expect it, because we believe, that a majority of the people are averse to engaging in our military expedition__ <choice>
                  <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                  <expan>General</expan>
               </choice>. Couales, is said to be 30 or 40 miles north of San Fernando, with from100 to 500 Rancheros: again he is reported to be within  a few miles of  the  City.  Yesterday, when we came in sight of Town,  a sectorial reported 500 Cavalry in sight; a patrol was sent to resist us, &amp; the whole city seemed to be quite alarmed, until they saw we were friends, and not Mexicans under Couales.<pb n="2" facs="sl599b.small.jpg"/> Tomorrow we leave, again to march the dry, &amp; hot plains, this side of San Fernando: again to march from morning to night without water for ourselves or horses.</p>
            <p>
               <choice>
                  <orig>N. inporte!</orig>
                  <reg>Not important</reg>
               </choice> We can not complain. We came to serve our country, &amp; we are now doing it.</p>
            <p>"The two <del type="overstrike">points</del> great points of our army says a great General, are the front &amp; rear: &amp; of the two the rear is the more important" So you see, although placed in the rear, we have a more dangerous march than if we had gone in front.</p>
            <p>Your kindness in forwarding the Muster Roll is gratefully felt. Please accept my thanks, therefore.</p>
            <p>Please present my dutiful respects to his Excellency, Gov. Brown, &amp; say to him that I shall endeavor hereafter to send a copy of each Muster Roll of my company to your office, to be filed there, according to his request.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have the honor to be very much your <choice>
                     <abbr>mo. obt</abbr>
                     <expan>most obedient</expan>
                  </choice>. friend</salute>
               <signed>Milten A. Haynes</signed>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Capt</abbr>
                     <expan>Captain</expan>
                  </choice>. Giles C Trooper <unclear>Ten Rich Cavalry</unclear>
               </add>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Genl</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice>. R. B. Turner <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Adj.</abbr>
                     <expan>Adjutant</expan>
                  </choice> Genl. <lb/> Tennessee}</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl599c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>N.B.</abbr>
                     <expan>Nota Bene</expan>
                  </choice> Please allow Mr Burton, of the <unclear>osthiopolita</unclear> office have the use of the Roll if he desires it. M.A.H.</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl599d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Muster Roll <lb/> of Capt. M. Haynes<lb/> co. from <lb/> Matamoras</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
