<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um019">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1831 Feb. 6, Nashville [to] Susan Gallagher, Bangor Maine / J. Baynard Snowden : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Snowden, Baynard J.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um019</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50200142</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1831 Feb. 6, Nashville [to] Susan Gallagher, Bangor Maine / J. Baynard Snowden</title>
               <author>Snowden, Baynard J.</author>
               <date when="1831-02-06">February 6, 1831</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated February 6, 1831 to Susan Gallagher from her brother J. Baynard Snowden of Nashville, Tennessee. Snowden writes of a friend moving to Cincinnati, Ohio in order to protect his children from the effects of slavery. He also writes that he dined with President Andrew Jackson at the Hermitage. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">R. B. Snowden Family Papers 1807-1950, MS65</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um019</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Slavery</term>
               <term>Jackson, Andrew 1767-1845</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Snowden, Baynard J.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um019a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <add place="near address">from J. Baynard Snowden</add>
               <add place="above address">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>postmark</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mrs. Susan Gallagher</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Bangor, Maine</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="bottom">
                  <name type="person">J. Baynard Snowden</name>
                  <date when="1831-02-06">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Feb</abbr>
                        <expan>February</expan>
                     </choice> 6, 1831</date>
               </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="um019b.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date when="1831-02-06">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Feby</abbr>
                     <expan>February</expan>
                  </choice> 6th 1831</date>
               <salute>My Dear Sister</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The tenderest thoughts arise in my-<add place="supralinear">mind</add> whenever I call you to remembrance. no time or distance abates the constancy of my affection towards you. Indeed the recollection that we are so far removed from each other is to me a source of great regret. How many are the thoughts I wish to present ⁁<add place="infralinear">to you</add> which are now precluded. nothing I assure you could afford me greater satisfaction than the pleasure of beholding my beloved sister and participating in the agreeable conversation of her interesting little Family. The anticipation that I shall <unclear>ever</unclear> —  enjoy that pleasure, affords me a great deal of happiness. Mama has raised my curiosity to the highest pitch by her relation of the many, wonderful feats that little Samuel has performed. he must be a charming little fellow, <emph>She</emph> thinks <emph>him</emph> quite a prodigy—</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Doct</abbr>
                     <expan>Doctor</expan>
                  </choice> Hayes</name> &amp; family left this place a week or Two since for <name type="place">Cincinnati</name>where he intends locating himself  for life. He will continue the Drug Business as well as the practice of Medicine. his prospects are good, the children are improving fast. Mary will be very handsome Snowden is unusually smart. in fact they are all interesting Children.  The <choice>
                  <abbr>Doct</abbr>
                  <expan>Doctor</expan>
               </choice> assigns as his   reason for <pb n="3" facs="um019c.small.jpg"/> leaving Nashville that he could not bear the idea of raising a family of children among slaves, exposed to all the baneful <choice>
                  <orig>affects</orig>
                  <reg>effects</reg>
               </choice> of slavery. he thinks it would be endangering <choice>
                  <orig>there</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice> morals as well as <choice>
                  <orig>there</orig>
                  <reg>their</reg>
               </choice> everlasting salvation. I need scarcely inform you that Brother Samuel is happy in the society of his beloved wife. he appears to enjoy the marriage State exceedingly. I think you would be pleased with the selection he has made. She is kind &amp; affectionate in her disposition, easy and agreeable in her manners, &amp; Brother Samuel thinks beautiful in her person, above all, She has secured her title to another and a better kingdom &amp; bids fair for a seat at the right hand of god. She partook of the sacrament on last Sabbath for the first time, Brother Samuel is remarkable for his piety and his <unclear>engagedness</unclear> in the cause of religion. He takes a very active part in every thing that tends to the advancement of the Redeemers Kingdom. He is principal agent of the American Tract Society &amp; furnishes the state of <name type="place">Tennessee</name> with tracts.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">President Jackson</name> made us a visit last summer, I met him at several private parties &amp; had the honour of dining with him at the Hermitage. found him sociable and perfectly agreeable. there is a something in the <emph>turn</emph> of his <emph>sarcastic</emph> eye, contrasted with the benign expression of his countenance when conversing with him, that <pb n="4" facs="um019d.small.jpg"/> makes an impression at once favorable to the man, be you prejudiced ever so derogatory to a favorable conception of his character,</p>
            <p>The winter has been unusually cold for this country The Thermometer has been as low as Two degrees below 0 I dont know how you stand it in the cold regions of the north. it must be very severe, In wishing you the compliments of the season may the richest of heavens blessings rest upon you and yours. not only through this <emph>year</emph> upon which we have just now entered but to the end of your days. &amp; at last when this house of <choice>
                  <abbr>Yr</abbr>
                  <expan>Your</expan>
               </choice>
               <del type="overstrike">but</del> earthly <choice>
                  <orig>tuburnicle</orig>
                  <reg>tabernacle</reg>
               </choice> is dissolved. that you may with an unshaken confidence know that you have a house ready to <gap agent="damage"/> you, a building of gods. a house not made with <gap agent="damage"/> eternal in the having, My best respects to <name type="person">Mr Gallagher</name>, and accept for yourself a testimony of an attachment worthy a brother</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Yours truly</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>J. Baynard Snowden</name>
               </signed>
               <add place="bottom of page">
                  <note>
                     <p>P.S. I expect to be in<name type="place"> New York</name> in March next for the purpose of purchasing goods. It will not be in my power to visit <name type="place">Sacketts</name>. any communication directed to my address will be thankfully received yours <choice>
                           <abbr>J.B.S.</abbr>
                           <expan>J. Baynard Snowden</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </p>
                  </note>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
