<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="pa0219">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1816 May 27, Department of War [to] Col. Return J. Meigs, Cherokee Agency / William H.Crawford : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Crawford, William Harris</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003 
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">pa0219</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 45869989</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>  [Letter] 1816 May 27, Department of War [to] Col. Return J. Meigs, Cherokee Agency / William H.Crawford </title>
               <author>  Crawford, William Harris</author>
               <date when="1816-05-27">May 27, 1816</date>
               <extent>4 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This letter, dated May 27, 1816 was written to Col. Return J. Meigs, agent to the Cherokee Indians from William H. Crawford concerning the government purchase of Cherokee lands for a sum of twenty thousand dollars. Compensation to be given to the Cherokee in return for the lands are also outlined in the letter.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-2033</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> pa0219</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Cherokee Indians -- Land tenure</term>
               <term>Southern States</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n84054922"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Crawford, William Harris, 1772-1834</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="pa0219a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Department of War,<date>May 27th,, 1816.</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The Senators and representatives from <name>Tennessee</name>, before <add>the</add> adjournment of Congress, presented an address to the President, urging the expediency of extinguishing the <name>Cherokee</name> title to the lands north of the Tennessee, within the limits of that state. As there is no game upon the lands, and I believe, no Indians settled upon it, but <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Col.</abbr>
                     <expan>Colonel</expan>
                  </choice> Lowry</name>, it would appear to be their interest to sell it for a fair consideration. By giving Lowry a present, equal to the value of his possessions, it is probable, that a purchase can be effected of all their lands to the north of the river. The President desires, that you shall make every exertion to obtain this cession at their next national council. To enable you to affect this, you are <choice>
                  <orig>authorised</orig>
                  <reg>authorized</reg>
               </choice> to give them, either by way of annuity, or to be paid at one or more payments after the ratification, the sum of Twenty thousand dollars, and to distribute presents among them to the amount of five thousand dollars; and to Lowry, the value <add>of</add>
               <pb n="2" facs="pa0219b.small.jpg"/> of his possessions north of the Tennessee river. It will be proper to ascertain the relative value of the lands belonging to Tennessee, compared with that in the <name>Mississippi</name> territory, as the state of Tennessee ought and must pay her proportion of it.</p>
            <p>
               <name>Major Walker</name>, in private conversation told me, that he thought the Cherokee nation would sell the land which we attempted to purchase last winter. It is deemed expedient to make the effort. You are therefore authorised to offer them for their claims to the lands lying west of a line to be run due south from that point on the Tennessee river which is intersected by the Eastern boundary of <name>Madison county</name>, to the line agreed upon by the late treaty, an annuity of six thousand dollars a year in perpetuity. Considering that the most of this land is claimed by the <name>Chickasaws</name>, and that there is little or no game upon it, there is some reason to believe, that this offer will not be rejected by the nation, in their grand council.</p>
            <p>The President calculates upon the exercise of all your influence in effecting these objects. No commissioner will be appointed, as it is deemed inexpedient to make an impression upon them, that we are extremely solicitous to obtain the cessions in question. <pb n="3" facs="pa0219c.small.jpg"/> question.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have the honor to be, <lb/> Your most <choice>
                     <abbr>obedt</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient</expan>
                  </choice>. &amp; <lb/> very humble servant,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm H.</abbr>
                        <expan>William Harris</expan>
                     </choice> Crawford</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel</expan>
                        </choice>. Return J. Meigs</name>, Cherokee Agency }</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1">
            <pb n="4" facs="pa0219d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>letter from <choice>
                  <abbr>Secy</abbr>
                  <expan>Secretary</expan>
               </choice> war Treaty with the Cherokees copied 27th May 1816</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
