<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mc007">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1835 Apr. 8, Walnut Grove, Rutherford C[oun]ty, Tennessee [to] Cha[rle]s F. Welcker, Taladega [i.e., Talladega], Alabama / J M Mitchell  : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Mitchell, J. M.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>mc007</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50442393</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1835 Apr. 8, Walnut Grove, Rutherford C[oun]ty, Tennessee [to] Cha[rle]s F. Welcker, Taladega [i.e., Talladega], Alabama / J M Mitchell</title>
               <author>Mitchell, J. M.</author>
               <date when="1835-04-08">April 8, 1835</date>
               <extent>4 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a letter dated April 8, 1835, from J. M. Mitchell in Walnut Grove, Tennessee, to Charles F. Welcker in Talladega, Alabama.  Mitchell writes the letter to discuss Welcker's horse breeding business.  Mitchell advises Welcker that it is in the interest of his business to come to Walnut Grove, and he also informs Welcker of his plans of starting a cotton business in Mississippi.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Welcker Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1833</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mc007</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Business enterprises</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name>Mitchell, James C.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mc007a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Walnut Grove</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Rutherford <choice>
                           <abbr>Cty</abbr>
                           <expan>County</expan>
                        </choice> Tennessee</name>
                     <date when="1835-04-08">April 8th 1835</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Charles</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Here upon this torn Sheet of fools cop I attempt to offer you a few suggestions for your immediate Consideration &amp; action in relation to your partnership Stock of horses as I Should like you to come here immediately and attend to them, I mean it is my opinion that you to do the best for yourself Should come here and take one or more of the Colts as the oldest colt is now of the proper age to be put into market and is in fine order to sell and Father wishes you as you are already interested to have a better bargain and a chance of making more <choice>
                  <orig>proffit</orig>
                  <reg>profit</reg>
               </choice> off of the Stock than <choice>
                  <orig>any one</orig>
                  <reg>anyone</reg>
               </choice> else.</p>
            <p>We must sell off all our Stock of every kind except Such as we can employ Constantly and <choice>
                  <orig>proffitably</orig>
                  <reg>profitably</reg>
               </choice>, for we have bought a large track of land in <name type="place">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Maddison</orig>
                     <reg>Madison</reg>
                  </choice>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Cty</abbr>
                     <expan>County</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Mi.</abbr>
                     <expan>Mississippi</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> for the purpose of <choice>
                  <orig>rasing</orig>
                  <reg>raising</reg>
               </choice> Cotton largely and have already Commenced operations there having Sent all the hands we had on this place to that and we design living there for 8 months in each year.  We are to go down in <date when="--09">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Septr</abbr>
                     <expan>September</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date> next.  We plant there this year 400 acres of cotton.  We will in all probability Sell this plantation Shortly as purchasers; as rather, a <emph>quantum sufficit</emph> of bidders for it hold their purses in <choice>
                  <orig>rediness</orig>
                  <reg>readiness</reg>
               </choice> to make the purchase.  So you see the reason <add place="supralinear">in part</add> why I urge you to come up here.  Again I need hardly <choice>
                  <orig>advertize</orig>
                  <reg>advertise</reg>
               </choice> you that blooded Stock cannot be properly &amp; raised and located <pb n="2" facs="mc007b.small.jpg"/>  in the State of <name type="place">Mississippi</name> when each Smaller concern is forced to give place to the more important one of Cotton making.</p>
            <p>Were you here to see this havock filly Atalanta I then should not find it necessary to Say a word to <choice>
                  <orig>induse</orig>
                  <reg>induce</reg>
               </choice> you to do that which I am convinced is your high interest, I mean to take Atalanta paying us half the Value of her and keep for breeding or other purposes or perhaps also the whole stock as we are obliged by circumstances to sell out our entire interest in Hood horses and as blooded Stock at this time in this country is abundant and untried will not bring its  full value.</p>
            <p>I must attempt to give you an idea of this filly and that without the gloss of fanciful words and well turned periods, then to say the least her <choice>
                  <orig>colour</orig>
                  <reg>color</reg>
               </choice> is certainly a beautiful &amp; rich dappled Chestnut <choice>
                  <orig>Sorrell</orig>
                  <reg>Sorrel</reg>
               </choice> her hair is short Soft and fine her nostril is wide — her eyes are clear glancing and animated, full, large, and far between — her ear long, thin, tapered, and pointed — her neck gently arched and raising <choice>
                  <orig>beautifuly</orig>
                  <reg>beautifully</reg>
               </choice> from her horizontal Shoulders and deep, full, breast — her back and loin are fine the bone unusually strong — her ribs are rounding — her quarters well turned —  her hip bones lay in Close and point to the Shoulder — her limbs are all of the kind proper for beauty strength and action placed well under her and the whole as perfect as <gap agent="damage"/> you ever saw or ever will see.</p>
            <p>Now Charles after all this I tell you she would untrained as She is not sell at any rate for more than 350. or 400. perhaps not so much whereas if trained and tried She would bring you from 600. to 1000 or 1300.$ this is a difference worth attending to and if you choose, you know you can come here and live with us when your living <pb n="3" facs="mc007c.small.jpg"/> will Cost you nothing and you Can have her trained with or without a partner at a small expense.</p>
            <p>If you take her now instantly in the time whether you train or sell her again — if <choice>
                  <orig>any one</orig>
                  <reg>anyone</reg>
               </choice> buys her it will be to train — now is the time to begin the preparatory lessons of breaking exercise and galloping — Colts will not be in demand <add place="supralinear">again</add> or an opportunity of <unclear>remaining</unclear> them till next fall a year <unclear>h?ner</unclear> — Therefore what you do, do <emph>instanter, do decisively</emph>, and let me know <emph>without fail by the return mail</emph> as this is now Friday and next Monday week County <choice>
                  <abbr>Crt</abbr>
                  <expan>Court</expan>
               </choice> sits in <unclear>Nbo?</unclear> and if an opportunity offers we will sell, (without further advice from you), at that time.</p>
            <p>Calypso has a colt of this spring by Havock a horse colt <choice>
                  <orig>sorrell</orig>
                  <reg>sorrel</reg>
               </choice> red marked in the face Similar to the Dame — is about a month old — is a fine colt but I perhaps ought not to <add place="supralinear">say</add> a Superior colt the mare is in good condition and not put to the horse yet So much for horses—</p>
            <p>The family all are well at this time and would be glad to see you — your little <choice>
                  <orig>neice</orig>
                  <reg>niece</reg>
               </choice> and nephews would shout at your arrival if they recognized you.</p>
            <p>I should have written you sooner but that I just returned the day before yesterday from <choice>
                  <abbr>Mi.</abbr>
                  <expan>Mississippi</expan>
               </choice> and thereby have given you more leisure in coming; but come any how.</p>
            <p>That which is equivalent to saying your friend I shall subscribe myself</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>as usual</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">J M Mitchell</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Chas</abbr>
                           <expan>Charles</expan>
                        </choice> F Welcker</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="mc007d.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <add place="top, right">18 ¾</add>
               <add place="top, left">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>postal stamp May 11</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Chas.</abbr>
                        <expan>Charles</expan>
                     </choice> F. Welcker</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <orig>Taladega</orig>
                           <reg>Talladega</reg>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Alabama</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left">haste</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
