<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl380">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1836 Apr. 25, Head Quarters West Department, Camp East of the Sabine Waters, To the Commander in chief of the Army of Mexico operating against Texas / Edmund P. Gaines: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Gaines, Edmund P.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl380</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>   [Letter] 1836 Apr. 25, Head Quarters West Department, Camp East of the Sabine Waters, To the Commander in chief of the Army of Mexico operating against Texas / Edmund P. Gaines</title>
               <author>Gaines, Edmund P.</author>
               <date when="1836-04-25">April 25, 1836</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written by Edmund Pendleton Gaines, commander of the Western Division of the US Army, dated April 25, 1836.  It is addressed to the commander in chief of the Mexican Army during the Texan war for independence.  Gaines reports that he has been commanded to prevent Native Americans from crossing the unmarked boundary line between the US and Mexico, protect the inhabitants on either side of the line, and maintain the neutrality of the United States during the conflict between Mexico and Texas.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Gaines Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">I-C-3</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl380</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Sabine River</term>
               <term>Gaines, Edmond Pendleton, 1777-1849 Correspondence.</term>
               <term>Frontier Patrols</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n88277194"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Gaines, Edmund Pendleton, 1777-1849</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl380a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Head Quarters West Department</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Camp East of the <name>Sabine Waters</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date>April 25, 1836</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>(Copy)</add>
               <salute>General</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The undersigned Major General, Commanding the United States Western Department, having been ordered by the President of the United States, to the Western frontier of the State of <name>Louisiana</name>, for the purpose of restraining the indians residing within our limits from crossing the unmarked Line between the United States and <name>Mexico</name>   and from committing depredations upon the Inhabitants on the Mexican or <name>Texas</name> side of the unmarked Line; and for the purpose of maintaining the neutrality of the United States during the disturbances which unhappily exist among our western <choice>
                  <orig>neighbours</orig>
                  <reg>neighbors</reg>
               </choice> of Mexico and Texas_being desirous to correct error and obviate misconception in reference to the objects of his late and intended movement has deemed it proper to <choice>
                  <orig>authorise</orig>
                  <reg>authorize</reg>
               </choice>
               <name>Major C. A. Hitchcock</name> Acting Inspector General, the bearer hereof to repair to the interior of Texas accompanied by Surgeon<name> Findlay</name>  and <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Lieut.</abbr>
                     <expan>Lieutenant</expan>
                  </choice> Griffen</name>, with a Small Escort of mounted men bearing a Flag to see and confer with the commanders of the Mexican and Texan forces in that quarter; to each one of whom he will freely communicate the powers, views and purposes of the undersigned, particularly guarding the said Commanders against any movement in arms across the <name>Sabine Bay</name> or any of the principal water courses Emptying into the Bay; or across the country lying North thereof and between the Said waters and the <name>Red river</name> near <name>Fort Towson</name> or across any other part of the said unmarked or Supposed Boundary line between the United States <pb n="2" facs="sl380b.small.jpg"/> and Mexico, and more especially guarding  the Said Commanders against the employment by Either of them, of any of the Indians belonging to or usually resident with the nations or tribes residing on the <choice>
                  <abbr>U.</abbr>
                  <expan>United</expan>
               </choice> States side  of the above mentioned <add>National</add> Boundary Line; and he will distinctly Say to them should any such Indian Warriors be found in hostility against the Inhabitants  residing upon Either side of the said unmarked boundary line that the undersigned will not hesitate to use the force confided to his command to inflict on the Indians as well as those who may be found acting with, and aiding them, such summary punishment as shall afford to the Said frontier inhabitants that protection and security against the cruelties of Savage War, which the Laws of War and of <choice>
                  <orig>civilised</orig>
                  <reg>civilized</reg>
               </choice> nations warrant, and which is Expressly provided for in the 33d. Article of the Treaty between the United States of America and Mexico.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>I have the honor to be <choice>
                     <abbr>&amp;c.</abbr>
                     <expan>et cetera</expan>
                  </choice> &amp;c.</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>Edmund P. Gaines</name>
               </signed>
               <add>
                  <note>
                     <p>
                        <date>2d May</date>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>P. S.</abbr>
                           <expan>Post Script</expan>
                        </choice> Since writing my letter of which the foregoing is a copy, I have heard rumors of a battle in Texas which suggest the propriety of the remarks which follow.</p>
                     <p>Should the fortunes of war place you in a situation requiring or rendering desirable the humane Offices of a friendly neighbour, I will take great pleasure in Extending to you, any act of kindness in my power not incompatible with the laws governing the Conduct of Neutrals</p>
                  </note>
               </add>
               <signed>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>E. P. G.</abbr>
                     <expan>Edmund P. Gaines</expan>
                  </choice>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To the Commander in chief</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>of the Army of Mexico</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>operating against Texas.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl380c.small.jpg"/>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>No</abbr>
                  <expan>Number</expan>
               </choice> 4 <lb/> Major General Gaines <lb/> To <lb/> The General in chief of the Mexican Army operating in Texas  <lb/>
               <date>25 <choice>
                     <abbr>Aprl.</abbr>
                     <expan>April</expan>
                  </choice> 1836</date>
               <lb/> a similar letter was at the same time written to <name>General Houston</name>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
