<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl388">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1844 Feb. 5, Paris, Tennessee [to] William Fitzgerald, Jackson, Tennessee / E.A. Fitzgerald   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Fitzgerald, E.A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl388</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1844 Feb. 5, Paris, Tennessee [to] William Fitzgerald, Jackson, Tennessee / E.A. Fitzgerald</title>
               <author>Fitzgerald, E.A.</author>
               <date when="1844-02-05">February 5, 1844</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter dated February 5, 1844 from E.A. Fitzgerald in Paris, Tennessee to her husband William Fitzgerald.  In the letter she tells her husband news and conditions of their home as Mr. Fitzgerald is away. </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Fitzgerald - Williams -Greer Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl388</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Fitzgerald, E.A.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl388a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>near <address>
                  <addrLine>Paris</addrLine>
               </address>Friday <add>morning</add> , 8 clock <date> 5th <choice>
                     <abbr>Feb</abbr>
                     <expan>February</expan>
                  </choice> 1844</date>
               <salute>My Dear Husband</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I know by this time you have become anxious to hear from home and with a thankful heart to Almighty God for the many facilities and high privileges which we continually enjoy through his mercy I sit down to fulfill my engagement to you.</p>
            <p>we have had a pleasant week the weather has been fine.  vegetation is putting forth beautifully and our home in the country is more and more desirable.  another call for gratitude our little babes which you left sick have got well, a louder call for gratitude no danger's affliction or misfortunes have fallen to our lot.  but on contrary.  every   thing about us, and relating to us.  is calculated to add to our comforts.  and render life a blessing, and not a curse.  louder and continual call's for gratitude and obedience.,   my Dear. will <add>you</add> bear with me for the spirit in which I am writing this morning for I feel so great a sense of the goodness. and mercy.  and long forbearance. of him <del>that</del>
               <add>who</add> made us.  and to whom we are accountable that had I half the capacity of expression that I have for perceiving and feeling these things I could speak of them to you something like Paul did when he was addressing Felix and Festus.  and would have some more hope of persuading you to be a christian,__ but as the power to convince is of god and not man I do hope.</p>
            <p>a most distressing accident happened on Tuesday last to <choice>
                  <abbr>mr</abbr>
                  <expan>Mister</expan>
               </choice> looney's Family, Posthelwaite and <pb n="2" facs="sl388b.small.jpg"/> some other Boys went out gunning. on horse__ back.  his horse took fright and threw him as he fell his went off and shot <add>him</add> through the head he died in short time, poor boy he was wild wicked and profane.  he has met an untimely fate may it be a warning to his associates he has left behind.  </p>
            <p>William has got a greek testament here. he only need's a Dictionary.  he is regular at school and in good health.</p>
            <p>if you do not get home in a week or two yet please send me some money.  as negro clothing and some other necessaries have exhausted my purse.</p>
            <p>mr williams was out yesterday they are all well.  write as often as you can.</p>
            <p>it is certainly wise that our smaller should yield to our greater interests.  but when I look at the comfort and advantages of our present residence I am sorry to change it.  I say this in view of the probability <del>of leaving to</del> of removing to <name>Jackson</name>, however. for a few reasons <add>which</add> are important.  I am willing if you conclude to do so. </p>
            <closer>Your <choice>
                  <orig>affetionate</orig>
                  <reg>affectionate</reg>
               </choice> wife <signed>E A Fitzgerald</signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl388c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Paris <choice>
                        <abbr>Ten</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>Apl</abbr>
                  <expan>April</expan>
               </choice> 5 <add>100</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>William Fitzgerald, <choice>
                        <abbr>esqr</abbr>
                        <expan>esquire</expan>
                     </choice> Jackson Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
