<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl102">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>   [Letter] 1826 Nov., Nashville [to] Mrs. Anne Bell, Dickson County, Tenn[essee] / Jane [Bell] : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Bell, Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl102</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50489087</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1826 Nov., Nashville [to] Mrs. Anne Bell, Dickson County, Tenn[essee] / Jane [Bell]</title>
               <author>Bell, Jane</author>
               <date when="1826-11">November 1826</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a letter, dated November 1826, written from Jane Bell in Nashville, to her mother Anne Bell in Dickson County, TN.  The letter is written over a period of two days, and in it Jane writes  that a Mr. Campbell will soon be in Charlotte to preach, and she urges her family to attend. She also writes about her recent visitors and how she keeps herself busy at prayer meetings with Mr. and Mrs. Campbell.    </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Bell Collection IV-H-1</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl102</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Religious gatherings</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Bell, Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl102a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>, <date when="1826-11">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Nov.</abbr>
                           <expan>November</expan>
                        </choice> 1826</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>It was my intention to have written by last mail but I forgot that Tuesday was mail day 'till it was too late to write, and I regret it as I had good news to communicate.  <name type="person">Mr. Campbell</name>  will preach in <name type="place">Charlotte</name> the first Sunday in December, and I hope it will be convenient not only for you and my Father to attend, but also the little ⁁<add place="supralinear">girls</add> and <name type="person">William</name>, if he is not much altered, will be delighted, to attend, preaching, and I am very desirous he should hear <name type="person">Mr. Campbell</name>, that the want of new clothes may not be one apology for his not attending, I send him a new suit by <name type="person">Mrs. Gould</name> had it not been for this preaching I would not have given them to him 'till Christmas and made them up myself. at present I have no measure to cut by, I hope it will be convenient for you to make them but if not employ <name type="person">Mrs. Stokes</name> , and I will pay her for them.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="sl102b.small.jpg"/>
            <p>Last Sabbath was a <choice>
                  <orig>Sacremental</orig>
                  <reg>Sacramental</reg>
               </choice> Sabbath in the Presbyterian church, and we had a very agreeable meeting, how sincerely did I wish that you had been here to enjoy it.  <name type="person">Mr. Farrar</name> was here, and <name type="person">Charles</name> informed me that he had seen my Father last week, <name type="person">Fredonia Marable</name>   spent a day in town last week, and came to see me, the Doctor was also in town, but when Fredonia was here, he was at <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Gen.</abbr>
                     <expan>General</expan>
                  </choice> Jacksons</name>   at a great dinner, which was given to the members of the Legislature.  I am always delighted to see any of my friends from <name type="place">Dickson</name> or <name type="place">Montgomery</name>, and I regret very much it has not been in my power  to spend more of my time with <name type="person">Mrs. Gould</name> since she has been in town, I intend to spend tomorrow with her.</p>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <opener>
               <dateline>Monday 20th —</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>I went early on Saturday to <name type="person">Dr. Waters</name>' to spend the day with <name type="person">Mrs. Gould</name> but how great was my surprise to find she had set out for <name type="place">Charlotte</name>.  I regretted it very much, particularly on my little  <name type="person">Parsons</name> account, whom I know will feel much disappointed about his clothes but at all events take him to hear <pb n="3" facs="sl102c.small.jpg"/>
               <name type="person"> Mr Campbell</name> — he informed me yesterday that he would administer the <choice>
                  <orig>Sacrement</orig>
                  <reg>Sacrament</reg>
               </choice> in <name type="place">Charlotte</name> when he preached there, I wish very much he was not going 'till Christmas, but I cannot think of leaving  here till after our examination, and also at the Academy so that I shall not in all probability reach home till the <date when="1826-12-24">24th <choice>
                     <abbr>Decr—</abbr>
                     <expan>December</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date> I have not heard from brother <name type="person">John</name> since I wrote to you, nor can I account for his silence   I spent last Saturday with <name type="person">Mrs Peyton Robertson</name>, she desired me to present her love to you and the little  girls.  My whole time is devoted to the School and the <gap agent="damage"/> parties I attend are prayer meetings and <gap agent="damage"/> my escorts are <name type="person">Mr. &amp; Mrs. Campbell</name>, who  <gap agent="damage"/> polite as to call for  me.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">Mr. Wade</name>   has returned from the <name type="place">Western District</name>, the reason why he did not call at your house was because he had a large party with him.</p>
            <p>Excuse the brevity of this epistle but I have not time to write any more at present.  Please present my love to all the family and believe me</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your affectionate Daughter</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Jane</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl102d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="above address">10<figure>
                     <figDesc>postmark for Nov. 21</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mrs. Anne Bell</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>near Charlotte</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Dickson County</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
