<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mm055">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Photograph of the Fort Marr Blockhouse in Benton, Tennessee] /
			 [by Gerald F. Schroedl] : a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <author>Schroedl, Gerald F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Mays</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>ca. k</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2001</date>
            <idno>mm055</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 47997318</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work in the property of the Frank H. McClung Museum,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. All other use is prohibited without the
				express written permission of the copyright holder.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Photograph of the Fort Marr Blockhouse in Benton, Tennessee]
				/ [by Gerald F. Schroedl] </title>
               <author>Schroedl, Gerald F.</author>
               <date when="1980">1980</date>
               <extent>1p</extent>
               <note type="summary">This photograph is of the Fort Marr Blockhouse
				located at Benton in Polk County, Tennessee. Fort Marr, also known as 'The Old
				Fort,' was constructed around 1814 near Old Fort, Tennessee. The fort was
				positioned along the Old Federal Road and housed troops who were assigned to
				protect white travelers using the road and the Cherokees from Creek
				retaliation. The fort was also said to have been used to safeguard supplies and
				as a campsite for soldiers in transit during the Creek War of 1814-1815. The
				name Fort Marr was established when the fort was renovated into a stockade to
				use during the removal of the Cherokee people to the west. It is believed that
				the fort was named after George Washington Lent Marr, who served under Andrew
				Jackson during the War of 1812 and the campaign of 1813-1814. After being
				relocated times since its construction, it was moved to its present location at
				Benton in 1965. In 1980, Fort Marr became the property of the Conservation
				Department of the state of Tennessee to be maintained and used as a historic
				site.</note>
               <note type="collection">Frank H.McClung Museum Photographic
				Collection</note>
               <note type="document">mm055</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Prepared for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Photographs</term>
               <term>Cherokee Indians--Antiquities</term>
               <term>Fortification</term>
               <term>Fort Marr (Tenn.)</term>
               <term>Historic sites</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n78090514"
                        role="Photographer http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/pht">Schroedl, Gerald F.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mm055.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>This is a photographic image of the 
				  <name type="place">Fort Marr Blockhouse</name> located in 
				  <name type="place">Benton</name>, 
				  <name type="place">Tennessee</name>. Photograph by 
				  <name type="person">Gerald F. Schroedl</name>. This information
				  was provided by the 
				  <name type="person"> Frank H. McClung</name> Museum.</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <note>This document consists of one image only.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
