<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sc247">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1835 Dec. 13, Washington [to] Mrs. Hugh Lawson White / Hugh Lawson White : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> White, Hugh Lawson</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sc247</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> [Letter] 1835 Dec. 13, Washington [to] Mrs. Hugh Lawson White / Hugh Lawson White</title>
               <author> White, Hugh Lawson</author>
               <date when="1835-12-13"> 
			 December 13, 1835</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter written in 1835 by Hugh Lawson White to his wife. White writes about social events and political goings on in Washington.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Hugh Lawson White Letter</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">New Accessions</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sc247</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letter</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2017180154"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">White, Hugh Lawson, 1773-1840</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sc247a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Washington</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Sunday Evening <choice>
                        <abbr>Decr</abbr>
                        <expan>December</expan>
                     </choice> 13th 1835</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My best of Wives,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>This is the only place I ever saw where a man can be always busy and yet do nothing. I have been striving to write you a letter ever since you left me and have never been able to get time to do so. As soon as I sit down to write some <choice>
                  <orig>on</orig>
                  <reg>one</reg>
               </choice> calls and I am interrupted. Do not suppose that I have an increase of company this winter. The <unclear>reserve</unclear> is the <unclear>fact</unclear> ; <name>Forsyth</name> and <name>Dickerson</name> have called, none of the other dignitaries altho we have <name>Mrs Woodberrys</name> invitation for the Evening of the 17th</p>
            <p>Our Miss is composed of <name>Mr &amp; Mrs Peyton</name>
               <name>Mr Wine</name> of Va <name>Mr Lawler</name> of <name>Alabama</name>, <name>Mr Maury</name>
               <name>Mr Lea</name>, <name>Mr Bunch</name> and <name>Mr. Standifer.</name>
            </p>
            <p>I understand my old friend <unclear>tylor</unclear> forth largely about me to some of his visitants. He cannot well compare me, in his freaks to any one except his old friend <name>Mr. Burn</name>.</p>
            <p>These things disturb me not. Several of the Anti Masons from Harrisburg have been corresponding with me about Masonry; I imagine my answer will be unsatisfactory__ I tell them I am not and never was a Mason_ That I must decline giving an opinion about the principles and obligations of Masons because I have not sufficient in formation to enable me to form one satisfactory to myself <pb n="2" facs="sc247b.small.jpg"/> I am told the Boats to <name>Philadelphia</name> are locked up in the ice. If <choice>
                  <abbr>Colo</abbr>
                  <expan>Colonel</expan>
               </choice> Bell has gone up and cannot return it will be a misfortune as his friends wish him <unclear>here</unclear>
            </p>
            <p>Karnes death will <unclear>provide a stir</unclear> in <name>Illinois</name>, the legislature is now in session and if it <unclear>suited</unclear> him I should like to see <name>Governor Duncan</name> succeed him; but of that I suppose there is but little prospect</p>
            <p>I feel satisfied <name>Lynch</name> is the Governor of <choice>
                  <abbr>Miss</abbr>
                  <expan>Mississippi</expan>
               </choice> and that a large majority of the Legislature are <unclear>Anti Van</unclear>__  My name sake Dunlap whom you saw is <unclear>elected</unclear>
            </p>
            <p>Did anyone suppose I was afraid to go  and wait on the <choice>
                  <abbr>Presed</abbr>
                  <expan>President</expan>
               </choice> unless I had a guard, or Did they suppose I came here to quarrel with him personally or politically My course has been as usual thus far, and I intend it shall be so, unless a departure by others from my principles separates them from me.</p>
            <p>I want your society very much; yet think you ought to make a comfortable visit as to duration &amp;c My wife and children are my only sources of comfort. Others are all very well in their place; but you know I have no relish for society. How far I ought to confide in strangers or my family connection those only tell who know how I have been and am treated by those for whom I have done most; but I complain not While I have the warm and devoted attachment of my wife and <pb n="3" facs="sc247c.small.jpg"/> children the world may take the rest, if it is profitable to do so.</p>
            <p>Bell has been Polked out of the speakers chair because he would not sell out___ There may be more sacrifices for the public <unclear>We al</unclear> before next June. We'll see what the public good requires, and so far as depends on me, it shall be done faithfully and fearlessly.</p>
            <p>I will send for the card tomorrow__ Tell Sam P he must be a good boy, please his father and Mother by doing whatever they wish and we'll see to the Poney by and bye.</p>
            <p>Make yourself comfortable, and your husband can make out some how; if he freezes you will never be censured, except by the President and other friends who may sometimes miss the automaton's vote</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My love to all and believe me <lb/> As usual and Ever Yours</salute>
               <signed>HL White</signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mrs Hugh Lawson White</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>Did you ever know me write so long a letter with nothing in it.</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sc247d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>My Husband <lb/> Dec 13th 1835</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
