<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mc002">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1832 Aug. 13, West Point, N[ew] York [to] Charles F. Welcker, Kingston, E[ast] Tennessee /  George L. Welcker : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Welcker, George L.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent> ca. </extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>mc002</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50436118</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1832 Aug. 13, West Point, N[ew] York [to] Charles F. Welcker, Kingston, E[ast] Tennessee /  George L. Welcker</title>
               <author>Welcker, George L.</author>
               <date when="1832-08-13">August 13, 1832</date>
               <extent>3 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a letter dated August 13, 1832, from George L. Welcker in West Point, NY to his brother, Charles F. Welcker, in Kingston.  George writes to inform his family of his well-being since arriving at the military academy, and he inquires about the latest news from  home.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Welcker Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1831-32</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mc002</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Military education</term>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Welcker, George Lewis</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mc002a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">West Point <choice>
                           <abbr>N.</abbr>
                           <expan>New</expan>
                        </choice> York</name>
                     <date when="1832-08-13">August 13th 1832 </date>—</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I take up my pen to write you a very short and hasty letter — I would write more lengthily but I have only a few minutes time, and the letter is intended merely as a kind of introductory one — The circumstance are these, <name type="person">Mr. Yoakum</name> of <name type="place">Tennessee</name> was here a short time since and spent several days at this place, and while here I promised to write a number of introductory letters by him to persons in <choice>
                  <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                  <expan>Tennessee</expan>
               </choice> — This promise I fulfilled, before he left here, by writing to them all <del type="overstrike">before</del> except yourself, and I would have written to you at the same time, but he started rather sooner than I expected — <name type="person">Mr. Fain</name> of <name type="place">Rogersville <choice>
                     <abbr>Tenn.</abbr>
                     <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name> is just about setting out for home, and will overtake Mr Yoakum about <name type="place">Washington City</name>, and I send this letter by Fain to Yoakum, who will deliver it to you — Mr. Yoakum promised me that he would see Father and yourself, for I knew that it would be gratifying to both of you to see some person who had seen me at this place and who could give you any information you might desire respecting it <del type="overstrike">place</del>
            </p>
            <p>When I arrived at this place Mr. Yoakum <choice>
                  <orig>receivd</orig>
                  <reg>received</reg>
               </choice> me more like a brother, than like a stranger, and while I remained here, which was about twenty days, he treated me with the greatest respect and took considerable pains to give me every necessary information respecting this institution <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera</expan>
               </choice> — This course of conduct towards me was not only marked by the most disinterested friendship and benevolence, but he <choice>
                  <orig>confered</orig>
                  <reg>conferred</reg>
               </choice> on me many little articles which will be, not only Convenient and useful to me, but which will also save me considerable expense in purchasing them —</p>
            <p>I know it would always afford you the highest pleasure to pay a due degree of attention to any gentleman, but <pb n="2" facs="mc002b.small.jpg"/> if Mr. Yoakum should call I would ask you, on my account, to be particularly attentive to him —</p>
            <p>So far I have no fault to find with this place. We still remain in camp and it is even probable that we will not leave it sooner than the <date when="--10-01">1st of <choice>
                     <abbr>Oct.</abbr>
                     <expan>October</expan>
                  </choice>
               </date>  — It is thought that it is best to remain in camp as long as possible on account of the Cholera — This place is entirely healthy. — We pay no attention to books in camp, and attend to nothing but military duty —</p>
            <p>I have written two letters home since I arrived here and would have been very glad if I could have heard from there before this time, but I <choice>
                  <orig>hav</orig>
                  <reg>have</reg>
               </choice> now been more than three months from home and have not heard a word from any of you since I left there — If you have not written to me when you receive this I hope you will write to me immediately — I wish to know how you succeeded in <name type="place">Alabama</name> — I want to know what has become of the affair in <name type="place">Jefferson <choice>
                     <abbr>Cty</abbr>
                     <expan>County</expan>
                  </choice>
               </name>, and in short, I wish to know about <choice>
                  <orig>every thing</orig>
                  <reg>everything</reg>
               </choice> at home, in the <choice>
                  <orig>neighbourhood</orig>
                  <reg>neighborhood</reg>
               </choice>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>&amp;c. &amp;c.</abbr>
                  <expan>et cetera, et cetera</expan>
               </choice> — My health is as good, or better than it ever was — Give my love to the family, my compliments to all friends and <choice>
                  <orig>neighbours</orig>
                  <reg>neighbors</reg>
               </choice> — and I hope you will accept this hasty but sincere assurance of the continued love and esteem of your brother</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">George L. Welcker</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To. <choice>
                        <abbr>C.</abbr>
                        <expan>Charles</expan>
                     </choice> F. Welcker }</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="bottom">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>P.S.</abbr>
                     <expan>Post Script</expan>
                  </choice> This letter is directed to you, but of course, I could not object to its being seen by any of the family <choice>
                     <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                     <expan>et cetera</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>G. L. W</abbr>
                     <expan>George L. Welcker</expan>
                  </choice> —</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="mc002c.small.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mr. Charles F. Welcker</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Kingston</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name> 
                        <reg>place</reg> 
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>E.</abbr>
                           <expan>East</expan>
                        </choice> Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>pr. Lieut.</abbr>
                     <expan>private Lieutenant</expan>
                  </choice> Yoakum }</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
