<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="mc038">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1836 Jun. 19, E[ast] Ten[nessee] College [to] Henry Welcker, Kingston, Tenn[essee] / F[rederick] A. Welcker : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Welcker, Frederick A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">mc038</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the McClung Historical Collection, Knox County Public Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Manager of the McClung Historical Collection, 500 West Church Avenue, Knoxville, TN, 37902-2505.  (865) 215-8801. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1836 Jun. 19, E[ast] Ten[nessee] College [to] Henry Welcker, Kingston, Tenn[essee] / F[rederick] A. Welcker</title>
               <author>Welcker, Frederick A.</author>
               <date when="1836-06-19">June 19, 1836</date>
               <extent>3 p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a letter dated June 19, 1836, to Henry Welcker of Roane County, TN, from his son Frederick at East Tennessee College (currently the University of Tennessee).  Frederick writes about the cost of some land belonging to his late brother William, as well as  other financial matters.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Welcker Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">MS-12, b2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1836</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">mc038</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Financial, Personal</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Welcker, Frederick A.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="mc038a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>E. Ten.</abbr>
                           <expan>East Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice> College</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Sunday evening <date>June 19th 36</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear father.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Your letter of the 13th <choice>
                  <abbr>inst.</abbr>
                  <expan>instant</expan>
               </choice> containing two letters, and two five Dollar bills has been more than welcomely <choice>
                  <abbr>recd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice>.-</p>
            <p>On yesterday morning I left for <name>Clinton</name>; and William's land was bid off to me as your agent for the twenty six Dollars &amp; 6 ¼._   I then increased the bid by laying your claim upon <add>it</add>; so that if any other individual should redeem the land within two years, he will be compelled to refund the amount at which the land was bid off, and to satisfy your claim._  </p>
            <p>In the division of the land it was agreed that William's lot should pay to another one 20 dollars; and this will have to be done by you to <name>Richard Olivar</name>._  The whole cost of the land will consequently be forty six dollars &amp; 6 ¼._ The Sheriff was unable to make a deed, because the land had not been surveyed._  But <name>Major Jarnagin</name> Clerk of Circuit Court at Clinton will receive it when made and convey it to <name>Knoxville</name>.- <name>Galbreath</name> is tending the land in corn as a renter; and whoever holds the land is entitled to the rent._ One of the <name>Mr Butlers</name> was willing to give a hundred dollars for your interest in the land; but this offer was not accepted <del type="overstrike">on</del> in as much as it was not <choice>
                  <orig>eaqual</orig>
                  <reg>equal</reg>
               </choice> the sum of the amount at which the land was bid off, the cost attending it and your claim; _ all of which would have been the <unclear>rise</unclear> of $120._ Those best acquainted with this division of the tract represent <pb n="2" facs="mc038b.small.jpg"/>   it to be worth $250; and it is highly probable that <name>Eskridge</name> will redeem it in order to secure something for his own claims._ And let the matter now end as it can you will certainly receive the amount of your debt.- If I had not attended the sale, your proportional part of the amount of land brought after deducting cost would have been only between two and three dollars; so it may be considered fortunate that I went._</p>
            <p>Having paid out 26 dollars towards the land, and expended about five dollars for books, which could not be procured from the library, in consequence of their having been taken out the first week before we arrived, we shall need a least thirty dollars more._ It is now time for me to commence my lesson, and as I am in <choice>
                  <orig>possion</orig>
                  <reg>possession</reg>
               </choice> of no news of a special nature I beg leave to close this hasty scroll by requesting you to give my respects to the family and <del type="overstrike">requesting</del> to recieve the same for yourself._  </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>F.</abbr>
                        <expan>Frederick</expan>
                     </choice> A Welcker</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To Henry Welcker</addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="3" facs="mc038c.small.jpg"/>
               <add>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>postmark stamp: Knoxville, Ten., June 22</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </add>
               <add>Single</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Mr. Henry Welcker</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Kingston</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn.</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>mail</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
