<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl610">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter]  1834 Oct. 13, Sommerville, Tennessee [to] W[illia]m Carroll / Peter Hudspeth : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Hudspeth, Peter</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl610</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title> 1834 Oct. 13, Sommerville, Tennessee [to] W[illia]m Carroll / Peter Hudspeth</title>
               <author> Hudspeth, Peter</author>
               <date when="1834-08-13"> 
			 October 13, 1834</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Peter Hudspeth to Governor William Carroll, dated October 13, 1834. Hudspeth is writing to notify Carroll of two murders that have taken place in his county. The murderers are on the run and Hudspeth wants Carroll's cooperation in apprehending them.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor William Carroll Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">5</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl610 </note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Crimes</term>
               <term>Justice.</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Hudspeth, Peter</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl610a.small.jpg"/>
            <p>To his excellency <name>William Carroll</name> Governor of the state of <name>Tennessee</name>, whereas two most appalling murders have been recently committed by, and upon the citizens of This county__ The first was committed by <name>Edward Willingham</name>, on the <date>13 of July</date> Last, up on the person <add>of</add>
               <name>Thomas speers</name> This was a cool and deliberate murder, having followed the deceased eight or Ten miles, way laid, and shot him, and made his escape which would produced Immediate death, The second murder was committed by <name>John Ross</name> on the <date>19th of september</date> last on the body of <name>Joel, y, Graves</name> who died Instantly in the road where he was assaulted, from having received 8 or 9 stabs with a knife or dirk, <del type="overstrike">A</del> Edward Willingham is a man of the Common Statue, rather slender made, little or no, <choice>
                  <orig>baird</orig>
                  <reg>beard</reg>
               </choice>, light Hair, &amp; blue Eyes, __ he is a very profane, and rough man in his department,___ John Ross <add>is</add> a man under the common Height by no means rough in his manners, black or yellow eyes, generally goes decently clad in Home spun cloth, and when in Company has not very much to say, and is about 23 or 4 years of age, &amp; we suppose willingham to be about 30, or 35 years of age, We the undersigned feeling as we do a lively interest in the well being of this community, cannot in <pb n="2" facs="sl610b.small.jpg"/> Justice to ourselves, and <add>the</add> people the conservators of whose peace we <unclear>all</unclear>, pass by such bloody atrocities unnoticed. we therefore request that your excellency Shall (if you think proper) forthwith advertize with a suitable <add>reward</add> annexed for the apprehension of the above named, murderers who made their escape, we recommend some paper printed at <name>Nashville</name>, also one At <name>Little Rock</name>
               <name>Arkansas</name>, Territory, and one of the most Generally circulated papers of the State of <name>Mississippi</name>, as the organs through which, the communication shall be made to the public., Unanimously adopted at the October Term,  of our court of pleas, and quarter sessions, on the <date>13th day of october, 1834</date> in the Town of <name>Sommerville</name> in the county of <name>Fayette</name>, and State Tennessee______</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <name>Peter Hudspeth</name>
               </signed>
               <add>Chairman <lb/> of Fayette County Court</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl610c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To His Excellency <choice>
                        <abbr>Wm</abbr>
                        <expan>William</expan>
                     </choice> Carroll</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>governor of the</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>State of Tennessee</addrLine>
               </address>
               <add>mail</add>
               <add>County Court of <lb/> Fayette about <lb/> murder <lb/> October 13 1834</add>
               <add>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>E</abbr>
                     <expan>Edward</expan>
                  </choice> Willingham<unclear> Frazitn <lb/> Rewards <lb/> E Runds</unclear>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
