<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um076">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1841 May 23, Jackson, Tenn[essee] [to] Miss Mary Jane Chester, Female Institute, Columbia, Ten[nessee] / Elizabeth Chester   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Elizabeth</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um076</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50316382</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1841 May 23, Jackson, Tenn[essee] [to] Miss Mary Jane Chester, Female Institute, Columbia, Ten[nessee] / Elizabeth Chester</title>
               <author>Chester, Elizabeth</author>
               <date when="1841-05-23">May 23, 1841</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">The following document is a letter, dated May 23, 1841, from Elizabeth Chester to her daughter Mary Jane at the Female Institute in Columbia, TN.  Chester scolds her daughter for speaking of politics and fears that such talk with threaten her father's political career.  Also included in this document is a letter written to Mary Jane from her father, Colonel Robert J. Chester.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers MS-25 (May/Jun 1841)</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">9</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um076</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- History</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Elizabeth</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um076a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson <choice>
                           <abbr>Tenn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <date when="1841-05-23">May 23 41</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My <emph>Dear Dear</emph> Daughter</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <add place="left margin">have you had any <gap agent="damage"/> made, what will be the uniform at <gap agent="damage"/> examination do wish <gap agent="damage"/> have one made here and <name type="person">aunt Narcissa</name> take it up with her if you have a good milliner you had better have it made</add>
               <add place="top">there she will go prepared to defray all <choice>
                     <orig>expences</orig>
                     <reg>expenses</reg>
                  </choice> read this  part of my letter to <name type="person">Mrs Smith</name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>E</abbr>
                     <expan>Elizabeth</expan>
                  </choice> Chester</add> I received your long and interesting letter <add place="supralinear">on thursday last</add> I was truly delighted to hear that you had entirely recovered from your indisposition, it is disagreeable to be sick at any time but at this particularly so <del type="overstrike">now</del> as I fear that it will prevent you from qualifying yourself for the examination, which is happily drawing very <emph>near</emph>. My dear Child you should have nothing to do with <choice>
                  <orig>politicks</orig>
                  <reg>politics</reg>
               </choice> I cannot have any patience to hear you say any thing on the subject you are very young and can know nothing about it your Father holds appointment under the present President his Family by imprudence in talking might be the cause of his <emph>removal</emph> that I know will deter you from saying any thing that is disagreeable and on the subject of religion you are in a <emph>Episcopal Institution</emph> that should teach you <choice>
                  <orig>prudance</orig>
                  <reg>prudence</reg>
               </choice>, learn to be moderate in all <emph>thing</emph> do not my dear Child be hurt at what I write it is my great  <pb n="2" facs="um076b.small.jpg"/> anxiety for you that induces me to be thus plain I am extremely sorry to hear of the <unclear>somber</unclear> indisposition of <name type="person">Mrs Walker</name> their kindness to you on a former sickness deserves and has our sincere thanks and gratitude <del type="overstrike">they must</del> they could not have known how sick you were, or I feel confident that they would have been to see you, you have ere this received my last letter telling you that your sister <name type="person">Martha</name> had entirely <emph>recovered</emph> indeed I am astonished that you had not received it before you wrote your last as I wrote by return mail I have my dear daughter to give you the painful information of the indisposition of your dear Father he was <del type="overstrike">taken</del> attacked with <emph>Bilious <unclear>plucring</unclear>
               </emph> in <name type="place">Memphis</name> had a violent attack he is now thank god at home and well I think my dear child when we are again all united at home I shall not be <gap agent="damage"/> induced to let any <choice>
                  <orig>seperation</orig>
                  <reg>separation</reg>
               </choice> occur that I can prevent, what even music that you wish if it is not at the institute send your Father a list and he can have it filled for you  as you know not how very anxious we are to have you home with us be patient and prudent a little longer our prayers and love attend you may you have the care and protection of our Lord and saviour Jesus <pb n="3" facs="um076c.small.jpg"/>
               <emph>Christ</emph> all of our relations are well <name type="person">Sam</name> is walking and talking, &amp; now I must conclude  by saying that disagreeable word <emph>adieu</emph> with great love and affection</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>your Mother</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Elizabeth Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Miss Mary Jane Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <p>Last night brought us to our home, your Dear Ma Mit me  on Wednesday last at your <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>unkle</orig>
                     <reg>uncle</reg>
                  </choice>
                  <emph>Sams</emph>
               </name>  we <choice>
                  <orig>remand</orig>
                  <reg>remained</reg>
               </choice> there one day and on our return stayed all night at <name type="person">Aunt McLillan's</name>   — I am now perfectly well with the Exception of my strength, will be at my regular <choice>
                  <orig>busness</orig>
                  <reg>business</reg>
               </choice> tomorrow   — I am sorry to see the tone of dissatisfaction which <gap agent="damage"/> your last letter, hope you will have more of  the good Sense for which you know always have distinguished that to let any Expression, on <gap agent="damage"/> can of Leaving. escape which would leave <gap agent="damage"/> implies and after reflection — your Aunt <choice>
                  <abbr>N.</abbr>
                  <expan>Narcissa</expan>
               </choice> and brother <name type="person">John</name>  will be up for you &amp; if I can I will also. but about that the is some <unclear>uncertainty</unclear>
            </p>
            <p>All are now well, my absence for 18 days permits me from an attempt at  news, you will <choice>
                  <orig>here</orig>
                  <reg>hear</reg>
               </choice> from some of us next week — with our kind regards to your kind relatives I am My <choice>
                  <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                  <expan>Dear</expan>
               </choice> Child, with my Constant prayers for your health &amp; happiness.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>your affectionate Father</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Rob.</abbr>
                        <expan>Robert</expan>
                     </choice> J. <emph>Chester</emph>
                  </name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="um076d.small.jpg"/>
               <add place="above address">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>post mark seal</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <emph>Paid</emph> 18 ¾</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Miss Mary Jane Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Female Institute</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia <choice>
                           <abbr>Tn</abbr>
                           <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="below address, upside down">My Dear Mother <lb/>
                  <date when="1841-05-23">23 May 1841</date>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
