<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl639">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1838 Jul. 6, Nashville, Tennessee [to] Wm. McClain, Sparta, Tennessee / N[ewton] Cannon : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author> Cannon, N[ewton]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name>Bobby Holt</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee
			 </addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996
			 </addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2003
		  </date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl639</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals for research,
				teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is
				included in the text. For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312. (615)
				741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1838 Jul. 6, Nashville, Tennessee [to] Wm. McClain, Sparta, Tennessee / N[ewton] Cannon</title>
               <author>Cannon, N[ewton]</author>
               <date when="1838-07-06"> 
			 July 6th, 1838</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to Wm. McClain from Governor Newton Cannon, dated July 6, 1836. Cannon is writing to discuss the Bank of Tennessee and it's branches. McClain has just had a convention in Sparta on this topic. Cannon writes about the disagreement over the branches within the Legislature.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Governor Newton Cannon Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true"> sl639</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Law and legislature</term>
               <term>Banks and banking</term>
               <term>
                  <name ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/nr93017180"
                        role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Cannon, Newton, 1781-1841</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl639a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <add>Executive <choice>
                     <abbr>Dept</abbr>
                     <expan>Department</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>
                        <del>Nashville</del>
                     </name>
                     <date>July 6th 1838</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>To <name>Wm McClain</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice> President and the members of the convention at <name>Sparta</name>
                     <add>also</add> the citizens of the state by them represented or interested gentlemen</addrLine>
               </address>
            </opener>
            <p>Your memorial of the 15th <choice>
                  <abbr>ult</abbr>
                  <expan>ultimo</expan>
               </choice> has Just been <choice>
                  <abbr>recievd</abbr>
                  <expan>received</expan>
               </choice>
               <choice>
                  <abbr>accompanyd</abbr>
                  <expan>accompanyed</expan>
               </choice> by the central gazette containing a copy of the proceeding of <choice>
                  <orig>you</orig>
                  <reg>your</reg>
               </choice> convention at Sparta of the same date. with an address to the people of our state, on the subject of the Location of the Branches of the    Bank of <name>Tennessee</name>, On which I entertain no doubt, you have just cause of complaint provided it is admitted that this Bank is to confer Benefits equally and generally to the citizens of our state, _ Whatever may be the inconsistent and conflicting provisions of its charter, or the variety of motives, which actuated those who were instrumental in bringing it into existence, and however difficult too carry the same into effect it would now be useless to paint <del type="overstrike">[unclear]</del>out or enquire into them, as it is now the Law of our land, the <choice>
                  <orig>setled</orig>
                  <reg>settled</reg>
               </choice> policy of our state <pb n="2" facs="sl639b.small.jpg"/> and becomes the duty of all <choice>
                  <abbr>concernd</abbr>
                  <expan>concerned</expan>
               </choice> in its administration, to make the best they can of it_</p>
            <p>That the accommodation of all parts of the State, in the location of the branches of this Bank was deemed impracticable by a majority of the Legislature, Seems most obvious, from their having <choice>
                  <abbr>refusd</abbr>
                  <expan>refused</expan>
               </choice> to locate the Branches themselves as was <choice>
                  <abbr>urgd</abbr>
                  <expan>urged</expan>
               </choice>. and <choice>
                  <abbr>believd</abbr>
                  <expan>believed</expan>
               </choice> by some to be their duty.</p>
            <p>Whether the Laudable objects held forth by the advocates of this amalgamated Scheme of state policy, are to be realized, generally by our citizens, or not, time alone with its practical operations and Lasting effects, must determine but In as much as the injustice of which you complain, and Justly too, I doubt not, (relates only to borrowing your portion of <add>to many</add> of this Bank, at an inconvenient point to the citizens of that district of country and not having equal facilities in that respect, with other portions of the state) is a right or <choice>
                  <orig>priviledge</orig>
                  <reg>privilege</reg>
               </choice>, not <choice>
                  <abbr>deemd</abbr>
                  <expan>deemed</expan>
               </choice> of the highest or most vital import, <pb n="3" facs="sl639c.small.jpg"/>
               <del type="overstrike">therefore</del>I trust I do not presume too much, on the forbearance, and patriotism of this portion of my fellow citizens, by delaying the <del type="overstrike">immediate</del>exercise of this important power, <del type="overstrike">now <choice>
                     <abbr>placd</abbr>
                     <expan>placed</expan>
                  </choice> in my hands do hands to be <choice>
                     <abbr>desird</abbr>
                     <expan>desired</expan>
                  </choice>
               </del>
               <choice>
                  <orig>untill</orig>
                  <reg>until</reg>
               </choice> we can see more clearly, the practical operation of this system throughout the state, also whether or not, it is competent to extend the relief desird, without <choice>
                  <orig>imposeing</orig>
                  <reg>imposing</reg>
               </choice> on the state, the <choice>
                  <orig>expence</orig>
                  <reg>expense</reg>
               </choice>, or on our representatives of the Legislature, the unpleasant duty, of assembling again, for the purpose of either, correcting, their own errors or that of those on whom, they have imposd this difficult and unpleasant duty___</p>
            <p>Should a <choice>
                  <abbr>calld</abbr>
                  <expan>called</expan>
               </choice> session be <choice>
                  <abbr>deemd</abbr>
                  <expan>deemed</expan>
               </choice> necessary it is surely important, that sufficient information and experience should be had, in relation to the object as to enable the Legislature to know, with greater certainty, than before, what ought to be done, and to enable them to avoid similar errors of equal or greater importance __ In the mean time <pb n="4" facs="sl639d.small.jpg"/> you may rest <choice>
                  <abbr>assurd</abbr>
                  <expan>assured</expan>
               </choice> that the interest of every portion of the state will be zealously <choice>
                  <abbr>observd</abbr>
                  <expan>observed</expan>
               </choice> with readiness for the exercise of any power. with which I am constitutionally or Legally invested, at <del type="overstrike">the</del>
               <add>such</add>time <add>as</add>it may become <choice>
                  <orig>indispensible</orig>
                  <reg>indispensable</reg>
               </choice>, to the safety &amp; prosperity of the people of the state, or to rescue them from evils of sufficient magnitude growing out of <add>our</add>Legislative proceedings either directly or indirectly</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>With the highest respect <lb/> I have the honor to be <lb/> your <choice>
                     <abbr>obt servt</abbr>
                     <expan>obedient servant</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>N,,</abbr>
                        <expan>Newton</expan>
                     </choice> Cannon</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Wm MClain Esqr <choice>
                        <abbr>Prest</abbr>
                        <expan>President</expan>
                     </choice> &amp;</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>The members of the convention</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>at sparta &amp; others</addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
