<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl215">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1849 Feb. 4, Clinton [MS] [to] Joseph D. Hamilton, Nashville, Tennessee / Mary [Hamilton]   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Mary [Hamilton]</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl215</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51212932</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1849 Feb. 4, Clinton [MS] [to] Joseph D. Hamilton, Nashville, Tennessee / Mary [Hamilton]</title>
               <author>Mary [Hamilton] </author>
               <date when="1849-02-04">February 4, 1849</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter to Joseph D. Hamilton from his sister Mary, dated Feb. 4, 1849. She informs him that her Dr. Hamilton has bought a plantation but that they have not  yet built a house on it. She has been boarding in a tavern. She writes that many people have gone out to California for the gold rush. She wants to go for the weather, not the gold. She hopes that Joseph does not want to go as it is very dangerous.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Orr Collection IV-J-2</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">11</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl215</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Communication in the family</term>
               <term>Gold mines and mining</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>California</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Hamilton, Mary</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl215a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Clinton</name>
                     <date when="1849-02-04">Feb. 4th 1849</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>Dear Brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I received your letter several weeks ago but as I was moving at the time and have been sick almost ever since I have not had time to answer you I do not think however that any of you can complain of me for I have written to both Mother and brother George since I received any letters from them</p>
            <p>
               <name type="person">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Doct.</abbr>
                     <expan>Doctor</expan>
                  </choice> Hamilton</name> has sold his house in <unclear>town</unclear> and purchased in three miles of <name type="place">jackson</name>. I have been boarding here at the tavern since the eleventh of last month and shall continue to board until there is a house built on the plantation. I know not for what reason but I have felt for several weeks  as if there was some storm of trouble hanging over me which is yet to burst on my head. I can not bring myself to think that I shall ever live on the plantation I feel as if there was to some thing going to happen to prevent its ever being  my home.</p>
            <p>But why should I trouble you with my sad <pb n="2" facs="sl215b.small.jpg"/> forebodings! They may never be  realized but when the body is diseased the mind will be tinged with gloom and I have been suffering from a violent affection of the lungs for some weeks.</p>
            <p>I am also uneasy about your brother. His cough is much worse — he has fallen off very much and it oppresses my spirits to see his health failing so much. Do not let mother see this letter for it may cause her uneasiness and it would do no good. The <name type="place">California</name> fever is raging here violently. The men old and young are almost deranged on the subject</p>
            <p>There are not many who will however for money is very scarce and the wives of the married men are opposed to their going.</p>
            <p>My Brother brought his wife and child down to Father's yesterday. Brother has sold his plantation on the river and expects to leave for the land of gold about the first of  March. He will go and see the country and if he is pleased he will return to take his family there.</p>
            <p>The gold I care not for but the climate I believe would agree with the Doct. and Papa and for that reason I wish to go there to live. I fear however that the Doct. will not move there. He speaks some times of going without me but that I will not hear of God alone Knows <choice>
                  <orig>wheather</orig>
                  <reg>whether</reg>
               </choice> he would live to get home and I can never consent to <pb n="3" facs="sl215c.small.jpg"/> his leaving me. I hope you have not the fever for going for it is a dangerous experiment.</p>
            <p>I have the blues so badly that I can not write any more. I have not heard from <name type="person">Mrs Morgan</name> for some time. I should have gone to see her but there has been nothing but rain <unclear>scarcely</unclear> for two or three months and the roads are almost impassible for a carriage so I could not get to see her. The Doct. would join me in love to Mother and all the other relations but he is now down in the barroom. Write to me soon and let me Know all the  news. If you can get the notes to the <choice>
                  <orig>Seperation</orig>
                  <reg>Separation</reg>
               </choice> and the broken hearted please send them to me by the first opportunity. Do not let the children forget "Aunt Gizzy." Farewell. God bless you pray</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your ever <choice>
                     <abbr>affec.</abbr>
                     <expan>affectionate</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/> Sister</salute>
               <signed>
                  <unclear>Sigis</unclear> Mary</signed>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl215d.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Joseph D. Hamilton</name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Esq</abbr>
                        <expan>Esquire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Nashville</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
