<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl354">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1839 Jul. 30, Lebanon [Tennessee] [to] [Finis] Ewing / Geo[rge] Donnell   : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Donnell, George</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl354</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1839 Jul. 30, Lebanon [Tennessee] [to] [Finis] Ewing / Geo[rge] Donnell</title>
               <author>Donnell, George</author>
               <date when="1839-07-30">July 30, 1839</date>
               <extent>2p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from Rev. George Donnell to Rev. Finis Ewing, dated July 30, 1839. Donnell is updating Ewing on the progress of gaining subscribers  for a new paper for the Cumberland Presbyterian Church.  He mentions that another periodical is being formed as well. Donnell expresses fear that there is a split happening within the church. He does not think that it is appropriate for there to be conflict among Christians. Donnell writes that politics are the most popular diversion in his area.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Finis Ewing Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true"> I-A-4</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">8</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl354</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Cumberland Presbyterian Church</term>
               <term>Donnell, George</term>
               <term>Religion Periodicals</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Donnell, George</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl354a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Lebanon</name>
                     <date>July 30th 1839</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>
                  <name>Father Ewing</name>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have just received your letter, and hasten to answer it ___ The <choice>
                  <orig>discrepency</orig>
                  <reg>discrepancy</reg>
               </choice> between the minutes of convention &amp; my letter, to which you allude, grew out of my being <choice>
                  <orig>prematurly</orig>
                  <reg>prematurely</reg>
               </choice> sanguine in relation to obtaining a sufficient list for the paper by the fall meetings of Presbyteries ___ During the setting of conventions the prevailing <choice>
                  <orig>oppinion</orig>
                  <reg>opinion</reg>
               </choice> was, that less than 3000 subscribers would not pay the expenses of  publication of the paper ___; Since that time the <choice>
                  <orig>commeettee</orig>
                  <reg>committee</reg>
               </choice> has concluded that 2500 would cover all expenses __ I felt very confident, that if the presbyteries represented in convention, with those who were in favor of the enterprize would make any like a simultaneous effort during the camp-meeting season, that there could be no doubt of a sufficient list being obtained by october ___ with that sort of confidence I thought it would a good policy to save <add>a</add> second canvass of all the ground, for subscribers to send their money up to Presbytery __ I am now persuaded however, that I was to sanguine, and took too much responsibility on myself in the case ___ I have not sent such <unclear>in <gap/> hutions</unclear> generally, and when I have, they can easily be countermanded ____ My principle reason for thinking now that I was premature is found in the fact, that there will be what I suppose might be termed an opposition paper ___ <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Br</abbr>
                     <expan>Brother</expan>
                  </choice> Smith</name> has sold his list of subscribers to <name>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>bro</abbr>
                     <expan>brother</expan>
                  </choice> Rice Harris</name>, who will shortly <unclear>commenssing</unclear> the <choice>
                  <abbr>C</abbr>
                  <expan>Cumberland</expan>
               </choice> Presbyteries at <name>Springfield</name>
               <name>Roberton City</name> ___ That paper will of <pb n="2" facs="sl354b.small.jpg"/> course prevent our getting a list as soon as we would otherwise have done, so we may expect nothing more by the meeting of Presbyteries than a list of names, without the money ___ I am obliged to you for your instruction and information ___ I will forward minutes and prospectus by the next mail ___ I have sent about 700 of each to points <unclear>seatered</unclear> pretty much throughout our bounds; and so far as I have heard from them, they are doing  well ___ At this post office there will be about 75 copies of the paper taken ___ I will send the minutes of convention &amp; prospectus for our paper to  Bro Harris so soon as he <unclear>commences issuing</unclear> and request him to publish them to all his list ____ I am <choice>
                  <orig>distrest</orig>
                  <reg>distressed</reg>
               </choice>
               <add>with</add> fears of a division of the ranks in our beloved Church __ Of one part of the Church opposing the other, the feelings which ought never to be cherished in the bosoms of the <choice>
                  <orig>deciples</orig>
                  <reg>disciples</reg>
               </choice> of Christ.  When I look back and see the union &amp; brotherly love that prevailed only a few years since, and compare it with the present state of things, my heart sickens at the contrast ___ may the good Lord preserve that mutual confidence, and brotherly love which are so <choice>
                  <orig>esential</orig>
                  <reg>essential</reg>
               </choice> to success in the gospel of Christ Religion is at a low ebb here ___ Politicks precluding every thing else ___ when the <unclear>election is over</unclear> we hope for better times ___ Father Ewing- pray for me, and give me all the instruction, that, at any time you may think I need ___</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Yours most truly</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Geo</abbr>
                        <expan>George</expan>
                     </choice> Donnell</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
