<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl175">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1839 Nov. 25, Bastrop [TX] [to] Col. Joseph Brown, Maury County, Tennessee / David Franklin Brown      : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Brown, David Franklin</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl175</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 51165443</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1839 Nov. 25 Bastrop [TX] [to] Col. Joseph Brown, Maury County, Tennessee / David Franklin Brown      </title>
               <author>Brown, David Franklin </author>
               <date when="1839-11-25">November 25, 1839</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter written by David Franklin Brown to his father Colonel Joseph Brown on November 25 1839. David Brown writes that his crops have failed due to lack of rain and that they still have problems with Indians.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Joseph Brown Papers</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">THS-JB</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">148-165</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl175</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>Crop losses</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Brown, David F.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl175a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Bastrop</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <date when="1839-11-25">Nov. 25th 1839</date>
               <salute>Dear Father</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I take this opportunity of addressing you a few lines by<name type="person">
                  <unclear> L. T.</unclear>Porter</name>We have all enjoyed good health this summer or at least better health than we have done <choice>
                  <orig>hertofore</orig>
                  <reg>heretofore</reg>
               </choice> We have worked pretty hard but have had but a poor return for our labour as yet but of 75 or 80 acres of ground we have not raised  corn to bread us in consequence of its being never grained planted late &amp; having no rain in the latter part of the season but we are now preparing to sow another crop with better prospects we expect to put in 100 acres next season &amp; it is pretty well ascertained that if corn is planted early here that it cant intensely fail even if there should be no rain. I am relying almost exclusively on farming for a living the practice dont agree with me &amp; I am determined not to <choice>
                  <orig>follo</orig>
                  <reg>follow</reg>
               </choice> it if I can get along without. <name type="person">Joseph</name> expects to get an appointment at the <choice>
                  <orig>citty</orig>
                  <reg>city</reg>
               </choice> of <name type="place">austin</name> &amp; move up there in a short time he is  in nomination for notary republic which will be worth 4 or 5 thousand dollars per annum <pb n="2" facs="sl175b.small.jpg"/> Our <choice>
                  <orig>indean</orig>
                  <reg>indian</reg>
               </choice> difficulties still continue but we are under very little apprehension here as the country above us is settling <unclear/> in consequence of the location of the seat government Our money is very bad &amp; the consequence is that, we are almost unable to procure necessaries from abroad &amp; when we do get them they are <unclear>very high</unclear>
               <name type="person">Jane</name> says she is still determined to visit the <name type="place">United States</name> next <choice>
                  <orig>fawl</orig>
                  <reg>fall</reg>
               </choice> should she do so she expects to spend some months in <name type="place">Maury</name> Porter is ready to start &amp; Jane wants to go to <unclear>preaching</unclear> so I must bring this letter to a close we have plenty of preaching here of all sorts</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Rush Yours</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>DF</abbr>
                        <expan>David Franklin</expan>
                     </choice> Brown</name>
               </signed>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl175c.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Col Jos.</abbr>
                           <expan>Colonel Joseph</expan>
                        </choice> Brown</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Maury County</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr/>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="cover envelope">Postmark and miscellaneous notes</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
