<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um044">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1837 Nov. 19, Watertown [to] Ethel H. Porter, Raleigh, Tennessee / H. Scoville : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Scoville, H.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um044</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50281721</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1837 Nov. 19, Watertown [to] Ethel H. Porter, Raleigh, Tennessee / H. Scoville</title>
               <author>Scoville, H.</author>
               <date when="1837-11-19">November 19, 1837</date>
               <extent>3p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated November 19, 1837 to Ethel H. Porter of Raleigh, Tennessee, from H. Scoville. Scoville catches Porter up on family matters and tells him of the death of  many relatives due to whooping cough and typhus fever.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Porter-Rice Family Papers, MS 154, 180-1839</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um044</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Diseases</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Scoville, H.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um044a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Watertown <choice>
                           <abbr>Ct</abbr>
                           <expan>Connecticut</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                     <date when="--11-23">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Nov</abbr>
                           <expan>November</expan>
                        </choice> 23</date>25<name>Ethel H. Porter <choice>
                           <abbr>Esqr</abbr>
                           <expan>Esquire</expan>
                        </choice>
                     </name>
                     <name type="place">Raleigh Shelby <choice>
                           <abbr>Coy</abbr>
                           <expan>County</expan>
                        </choice> Tennessee</name>
                     <pb n="2" facs="um044b.small.jpg"/>Watertown <date when="1837-11-19">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Nov. </abbr>
                           <expan>November</expan>
                        </choice>19th 1837 —</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Dr</abbr>
                     <expan>Dear</expan>
                  </choice> Brother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>A long time has elapsed since we have written or received a letter from you or your Family— although we are far separated<add place="supralinear">
                  <choice>
                     <abbr> fro</abbr>
                     <expan>from</expan>
                  </choice>
               </add> you yet you are daily the subject of our conversation and anxiety—We have had 3 children 2 Boys &amp; 1 Girl— The oldest a Little Girl 6 years old next May named <name type="person">Mariam Foote</name> the second a boy 4 years old in October named <name type="person">Alfred Foote</name> after their Uncle &amp; Aunt in <name type="place">New York</name> the third a fine little <add place="supralinear">Boy</add> 19 months old the <date when="1837-03-24">24th of last March</date> on which day he died of whooping cough and teething— He died a hard death with fits for 4 days— He was a promising Child run alone at 10 months talked at 15 as well as the other children—but the God that gave saw fit to take him from us and blessed be his name— We have been visited this summer with severe sickness My Father Lay 80 days &amp; <name type="person">Elisa</name> 45 with Typhus Fever at the same time— Their sickness commenced the 21 &amp; 22d of July but all recovered— Elisa was not dangerous but my Father did but just survive—<pb n="2" facs="um044b.small.jpg"/> Old grandmother Porter died last June and squire Porters wife in July following of consumption— The old Lady fell from a Bed in <name type="place">Waterbury</name> the first Monday in April and Broke her Hip which caused her Death Uncle <name type="person">David Manvill</name> and wife <choice>
                  <orig>a</orig>
                  <reg>are</reg>
               </choice> living and in good health but very old people— They live Comfortably Your <name type="person">Uncle Siras</name> was married a short time since to a good woman from<name type="person"> Litchfield</name>— He found her here— She took care of Elisa during her sickness— <name type="person">Phenias Bradley</name> &amp; Wife &amp; Family are all well— Doing a good business— He suffered considerably last spring from <name type="person">General Jackson </name>experiments but I hope will not lose much— He however does not Complain of the Medicine which he helped to make— The times in this section of the country is very hard— Business entirely at a stand— No confidence nor no exchanges on the South— We have a fine farm of 130 acres first rate buildings and are out of debt so that times does not affect us but little— We keep Public House as usual— Keep one hired man &amp; woman and live very pleasantly— <name type="person">Mr &amp; Mrs Holcomb</name> are well if you come to this part of the country you must come and see us without fail write soon</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Affecty</abbr>
                     <expan>Affectionately</expan>
                  </choice> yours <choice>
                     <abbr>&amp;c</abbr>
                     <expan>and et cetera</expan>
                  </choice>
               </salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">H Scoville</name>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
