<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD">
<TEI.2 ID="pa0011"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>Abstract of disbursements made by Return J. Meigs on account of the Indian Department, 1810 June 30 - 1810 Oct. 1, Tennessee: a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>pa0011</IDNO><IDNO>OCLC: 44921932</IDNO><AVAILABILITY STATUS="FREE"><P>This work is the property of The University of Tennessee Special Collections Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>Abstract of disbursements made by Return J. Meigs on account of the Indian Department, 1810 June 30 - 1810 Oct. 1, Tennessee</TITLE><DATE VALUE="1810-06-30">June 30, 1810</DATE><DATE VALUE="1810-10-01">October 1, 1810</DATE><EXTENT>1p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">This document is a summary of the disbursements made by Return J. Meigs, U.S. agent to the Cherokees, at the Cherokee agency in Tennessee from June 30, 1810 through October 1, 1810.  Expenses included payment of the Cherokee annuity, payment of claims by and against the Cherokees for stolen property, salaries of various agents and interpreters, and the  purchase of articles for spinning and weaving.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">Special Collections Library, The University of Tennessee Knoxville</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box">1</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder">12</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">pa0011</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Expense accounts</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Claims</ITEM><ITEM>Indian agents</ITEM><ITEM>Tennessee</ITEM></LIST> </KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="financial account"><PB N="[1]"><P><TABLE><HEAD>Abstract of Disbursements made by <NAME TYPE="person">Return J Meigs</NAME> Agent of war in <NAME TYPE="place">Tennessee</NAME> on account of the Indian Department between the <DATE VALUE="1810-06-30">30th June</DATE> &amp; the <DATE VALUE="1810-10-01">1st of October 1810</DATE> except certain receipts marked x</HEAD><ROW><CELL>date of payments.</CELL><CELL>No.</CELL><CELL>payments to whom made</CELL><CELL>Nature of Disbursements.</CELL><CELL>Amount.</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1810-06-20">June 20th</DATE></CELL><CELL>1</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Samuel Morton</NAME></CELL><CELL>Pay for a Negro slave the property of <NAME TYPE="person">Mr. Morton</NAME> killed by a <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee Indian</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">500.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" 29</CELL><CELL>2</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Gideon Blackburn</NAME></CELL><CELL>use of schools in the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">100.00</CELL>
<CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1810-07-11">July 11th</DATE></CELL><CELL>3</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME></CELL><CELL>Their Annuity for the current year &amp; on <ORIG REG="installment">instalment</ORIG> on account of a Convention dated <DATE VALUE="1816-01-07">7th January 1816</DATE>.</CELL><CELL REND="right">11000.00</CELL>
<CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>4</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Black Fox</NAME> <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> King.</CELL><CELL>Being the amount of Annual Stipend for the current year received by his Proxy</CELL><CELL REND="right">100.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>5</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Caleb Starr</NAME></CELL><CELL>Blacksmiths work for <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">10.75</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>"  12th</CELL><CELL>6</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Alexander">Alexr</ABBR> Gavock</NAME></CELL><CELL>Pay for 2 Horses Stolen by whitemen</CELL><CELL REND="right">120.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>7</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Caleb Starr</NAME></CELL><CELL>Pay for 2 Looms for <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">16.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>8</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Charles Rogers</NAME></CELL><CELL>Indemnity for property stolen from him by white men</CELL><CELL REND="right">2.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>9</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Richard Taylor</NAME></CELL><CELL>For hire of packhorses</CELL><CELL REND="right">31.00</CELL>
<CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>10</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">William Cox</NAME></CELL><CELL>For a horse Stolen from him by <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">60.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>11</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="William">Wm</ABBR> Downing</NAME> a <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME></CELL><CELL>for a horse Stolen from him by a white man</CELL><CELL REND="right">60.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>12</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="William">Wm</ABBR> Carrol</NAME></CELL><CELL>pay for Fleas or weavers reeds</CELL><CELL REND="right">20.58</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>"  "</CELL><CELL>13</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Richard Taylor</NAME></CELL><CELL>Horse hire for Interpreter</CELL><CELL REND="right">3.00</CELL><CELL REND="right">12023.33</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" 13th.</CELL><CELL>14</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="William">Wm</ABBR> Luteys</NAME></CELL><CELL>Cards for <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">27.50</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>15</CELL><CELL> <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="John">Jno. </ABBR>Thompson</NAME></CELL><CELL>For Blacksmiths work for <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">17.33</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>16</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Robert Neely</NAME></CELL><CELL>For <ABBR EXPAN="ditto">do. do.</ABBR></CELL><CELL REND="right">15.80</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>17</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="John">Jno. </ABBR> Lowrey</NAME></CELL><CELL>For <ABBR EXPAN="ditto">do. do.</ABBR></CELL><CELL REND="right">24.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>18</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Peter Berry</NAME></CELL><CELL>For Ferriage of <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> 6 days while receiving their Annuity</CELL><CELL REND="right">12.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>19</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">The Frogg</NAME> (a <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME>)</CELL><CELL>for making <ORIG REG="spinning">spining</ORIG> wheels</CELL><CELL REND="right">8.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" 14</CELL><CELL>20</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">John Love</NAME></CELL><CELL>For 1 <ORIG REG="spinning">spining</ORIG> wheel</CELL><CELL REND="right">3.33</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" 22nd</CELL><CELL>21</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="John">Jno. </ABBR> Hildebrand</NAME></CELL><CELL>For his wages &amp; subsistence at miller at the <ORIG REG="Public">Publick</ORIG> Mill in the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> for the 2nd <ABBR EXPAN="quarter">qr</ABBR> year</CELL><CELL REND="right">51.84</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" 26</CELL><CELL>22</CELL><CELL> <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="George">Geo:</ABBR> Smith</NAME></CELL><CELL>For Iron &amp; utensils of husbandry for the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">41.64 1/4</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>"  " </CELL><CELL>23</CELL><CELL>"  "</CELL><CELL>Pack horse hire bringing money from <NAME TYPE="place">Nashville</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">7.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>"  " </CELL><CELL>24</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">James Howel</NAME></CELL><CELL>For Fleas or weavers reeds</CELL><CELL REND="right">3.75</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>"  31st</CELL><CELL>25</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Henry Stevenson</NAME></CELL><CELL>For 1 Spinning wheel</CELL><CELL REND="right"><UNCLEAR>3.33</UNCLEAR></CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1810-08-04">August 4th</DATE></CELL><CELL>26</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="John">Jno.</ABBR> Gambold</NAME></CELL><CELL>For the support of Schools in the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee nation</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">100.00</CELL><CELL REND="right">314.94</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>27</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Hance McKain</NAME></CELL><CELL>Indemnity for a Rifle Gun Stolen by Indians</CELL><CELL REND="right">20.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>28</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person"><UNCLEAR>Tiery</UNCLEAR> Robinson</NAME></CELL><CELL>For <ORIG REG="spinning">spining</ORIG> wheels for <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">23.33</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" 12</CELL><CELL>29</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">James Eddington</NAME></CELL><CELL>Indemnity for a Horse Stolen by <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">60.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" 16</CELL><CELL>30</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person"><UNCLEAR>Tiery</UNCLEAR> Robinson</NAME></CELL><CELL>For <ORIG REG="spinning">spining</ORIG> wheels for <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">20.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>"  22</CELL><CELL>31</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">James Boyd</NAME></CELL><CELL>For a Rifle Gun, Gunstock <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera">&amp;c.</ABBR> Stolen by an Indian</CELL><CELL REND="right">21.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" 30</CELL><CELL>32</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Samuel">Saml.</ABBR> McDaniel</NAME></CELL><CELL>For Blacksmiths work for <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">48.79</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1810-09-16"><ABBR EXPAN="September">Septemr.</ABBR> 16</DATE></CELL><CELL>33</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="William">Wm</ABBR> Richmond</NAME></CELL><CELL>For <ABBR EXPAN="ditto">do. do.</ABBR></CELL><CELL REND="right">14.74</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" 19</CELL><CELL>34</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Jeremiah Pate</NAME></CELL><CELL>For Indemnity for hogs stolen by Indians</CELL><CELL REND="right">20.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" 21</CELL><CELL>35</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="William">Wm</ABBR> Lutee</NAME></CELL><CELL>For <UNCLEAR>Cotton</UNCLEAR> Cards for <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">4.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" 22</CELL><CELL>36</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Wilson Scott</NAME></CELL><CELL>For Keeping Stray horses</CELL><CELL REND="right">98.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" 26</CELL><CELL>37</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="William">Wm</ABBR> Pratt</NAME></CELL><CELL>For Tobacco for the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">3.25</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" 30</CELL><CELL>38</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Richard Taylor</NAME></CELL><CELL>Interpreter his salary &amp; subsistence for the 3rd <ABBR EXPAN="quarter">qr</ABBR> current year.  <DATE VALUE="1810-00-00">1810</DATE></CELL><CELL REND="right">104.44</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" 30</CELL><CELL>39</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="William">Wm</ABBR> Ls. Lovely</NAME> (A. Agent)</CELL><CELL>his <ABBR EXPAN="ditto">do. do. do. do.</ABBR></CELL><CELL REND="right">129.44</CELL><CELL REND="right">566.99</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>40</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">James Carey</NAME>, Interpreter</CELL><CELL>For his salary &amp; subsistence for the 3rd <ABBR EXPAN="quarter">qr.</ABBR> of the current year <DATE VALUE="1810-00-00">1810</DATE></CELL><CELL REND="right">91.25</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>41</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">Samuel Riley</NAME></CELL><CELL><ABBR EXPAN="ditto">do.</ABBR> For <ABBR EXPAN="ditto">do. do. do. do.</ABBR></CELL><CELL REND="right">104.44</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>" "</CELL><CELL>42</CELL><CELL><NAME TYPE="person">John Walker</NAME></CELL><CELL>For Blacksmiths work for <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">59.92</CELL><CELL REND="right">255.61</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL> </CELL><CELL REND="right">$13,160.87</CELL></ROW></TABLE></P></DIV1></BODY></TEXT></TEI.2>
