<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="pa0046"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title> [Articles of Agreement] 1805 Jun. 1 [between the United States and the Cherokee Nation] : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harden</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">pa0046</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title> [Articles of Agreement] 1805 Jun. 1 [between the United States and the Cherokee Nation]</title><date value="1805-06-01">June 1, 1805</date><extent>2 p</extent><note type="summary">This document dated June 1, 1805 is an article of agreement between the United States and the Cherokee Nation for a turnpike across the mountains of Tennessee into Georgia.</note><note type="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note><note type="box">MS-2033</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">pa0046</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Legal documents</item><item>Cherokee Indians -- Government relations</item><item>Turnpikes</item><item>Georgia</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="legal document"><pb n="[1]"/><p>Whereas it was Stipulated in an Agreement between the <name>United States</name> &amp; the <name>Cherokee nation</name> <add>on the <date>20 <abbr expan="October">Octo.</abbr> 1803</date></add> that on the opening of a road <abbr expan="through">thro.</abbr> the said nation from the State of <name>Tennessee</name> to the State of <name>Georgia</name> that the Cherokees with <orig reg="their">there</orig> Connections might form a Turnpike Company for the purpose of keeping constantly the said road in good repair for the travelling of Carriages &amp; Horses &amp; that the regulation of the said road with respect to the rates of toll &amp;<del type="overstrike">c</del> <add>Ferriage</add> should be in the direction of the United States.  And the underwritten having formed themselves into a Company for the purposes <orig reg="aforesaid">aforsaid</orig> Pray the United States to recognize them for the purposes intended &amp; Stipulated for in the aforesaid agreement.  Hereby offering themselves to enter into Bonds for a <orig reg="faithful">faithfull</orig> execution of the duties that may be <unclear>annexed</unclear> <add>required</add> &amp; to be performed on their part &amp; <add>they <del type="overstrike">may be</del>  thereby enabled</add> to receive the rates of toll according to custom <add>shall be established</add> in such cases <del type="overstrike">: also to have provisions &amp; restrictions as may be thought necessary to prevent travellers from evading the payment of toll on the said road.</del>  as soon as Commissioners shall make report that the same is <add>in good</add> repair &amp; condition for travelling on as aforsaid.  the underwritten also pray that they may be empowered to make such <pb n="[2]"/> <orig reg="By-laws">Bye laws</orig> not inconsistent with the laws of the United States as shall be formed necessary by them to apportion amongst themselve such facts of the said road as shall be found necessary with more convenience &amp; the more certainty to keep the <add>same</add> <gap/> in a good state of repair for the public benefit &amp; the said underwritten  <unclear>your</unclear> Petitioners as in duly bound will <unclear>ever</unclear> pray</p><p>Down in the Cherokee nation this <date>1st day of June AD 1805</date>.</p><closer><signed><name>James Vann</name> <lb/> <name><abbr expan="John">Jno.</abbr> Rogers</name> <lb/> <name>Ke,la,was,kee</name> <lb/> <name>Wil,li,oe</name> <lb/> <name>Jno. Walker</name> <lb/> <name>Quo,te,gus,kee</name> <lb/> <name>Chil,li,cul,la</name></signed> <add><unclear>?</unclear> <lb/> To keep the road in repair to the Junction <unclear>of the Road</unclear> <lb/> To keep the Tellico road to <unclear>S?</unclear> ferry to the Junction <lb/> to keep the road from <unclear>the Junction of the Roads to Kusotawee</unclear> <lb/> To keep the road from <name>Kosotawee</name> to <name>Buffingtons</name> <lb/> To keep from Buffingtons to the Georgia Boundary line</add> <add><table><head>The rates of Toll to be as follows <unclear>viz</unclear></head>  <row><cell>For each wagon &amp; Tem</cell><cell>1 Dollar</cell></row><row><cell>For each 4 wheeled Carriage for the conveyance of persons</cell><cell>1.50</cell></row><row><cell>For each Chair &amp; Horse</cell><cell>.75</cell></row><row><cell>For each 2 wheeled cart &amp; team</cell><cell>.50</cell></row><row><cell>For each man &amp; horse</cell><cell>.20</cell></row><row><cell>For each led Horse</cell><cell>.10</cell></row><row><cell>For each heavy cattle, Hogs, or sheep</cell><cell>1 &frac12;</cell></row><row><cell>For each taxable Poll travelling on foot</cell><cell>6 &frac12;</cell></row><row><cell>Provided that no toll can be exacted from any Cherokee Indian or white man having land a <unclear>resident</unclear></cell></row></table></add></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
