<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="pa0039"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title> [Letter] 1818 May 4, Cherokee Agency [to] Colo[nel] Geo[rge] Gillespie / Jos[eph] McMinn : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>McMinn, Joseph</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harden</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">pa0039</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1818 May 4, Cherokee Agency [to] Colo[nel] Geo[rge] Gillespie / Jos[eph] McMinn</title><author>McMinn, Joseph</author><date value="1818-05-04">May 4, 1818</date><extent>4 p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated May 4, 1818, from Tennessee Governor Joseph McMinn to Colonel George Gillespie.  Governor McMinn writes this letter in regards to the compensation Gillespie will receive for his work as commissioner for valuing Cherokee improvements.  The letter also includes a table of goods received to be distributed amongst the Cherokee.  </note><note type="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note><note type="box">MS-2033</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">pa0039</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Cherokee Indians -- Government relations</item><item>Tennessee</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name>Cherokee agency</name> <date>4th May 1818</date></addrLine></address><salute>Sir</salute></opener><p>pursuant to a request from the <abbr expan="Honorable">Honl.</abbr> <name>John C Calhoun</name> Secretary of War.  First to settle your compensation as commissioner for valuing Cherokee improvements.  I propose that you receive Five Dollars for each and every day you are actually engaged in discharging the duties of your office, and a like sum for every thirty miles <orig reg="Traveling">Travling</orig> to the place of beginning.  and the same for every thirty miles travling home from the place where you may close your business.  I propose this as being the allowance made by the Legislature of the state of Tennessee, to her commissioners for similar services, which will be paid to you by orders of the Secretary of War.  article 6th provides that the Rifles, <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;c</abbr> stipulated to be given to the poor warriors shall be in full consideration for the improvements they may leave.  and to those emigrants <orig reg="whose">who is</orig> improvements add real value to the land, the U.States are to pay a full valuation which expression will be <orig reg="construed">construded</orig> by some as imposing upon you the duty of making a very liberal allowance, to suppress such an Idea amongst the claimants where rigid Justice alone must govern.  It could not be unjust to keep in view, and even to suggest where such insinuation were made, that those <orig reg="claimants">clamants</orig> had <orig reg="received">recevied</orig> the <orig reg="precise">preecise</orig> amount- <pb n="[2]"/> amount, in Rifles, Boats, Blankets, &amp;c, that had <orig reg="fallen">follen</orig> to the lot of the poor warriors, with regard to the number of improvements which have been estimated as adding real value to the Land, I have never heard of any <orig rend="claim">clame</orig>, except by <name>Mr. John Rogers Jr.</name> and <name><abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr> John Jolly</name> , nor have I any reason to believe there are any others which have been <orig reg="surrendered">surendered</orig> within the last six months.</p><p>I submit for your information the following estimate which will exhibit the amount paid by the U. States for the <orig reg="removal">removel</orig> of each Indian <orig reg="family">famely</orig>, consisting of four persons as  the <orig reg="average">avreage</orig> number thereof.</p><p>which sum may fairly be <orig reg="estimated">istimated</orig> (and so expressed by you where it becomes necessary) as the current price <orig reg="actually">actully</orig> paid for each emigrants improvements including both rich and poor warriors, which on principles of General calculation will far exceed <orig reg="their">there</orig> real value. <add>Statements</add></p> <pb n="[3]"/> <p><table><row><cell>To the Head of each Family</cell><cell>1 Rifle Gun</cell><cell>$25.00</cell></row><row><cell>" " " "</cell><cell>1 Blanket</cell><cell>5.00</cell></row><row><cell>" " " "</cell><cell>1 <orig reg="Kettle">Kittle</orig></cell><cell>7.00</cell></row><row><cell>" " " "</cell><cell>12 <unclear>tts</unclear> Lead</cell><cell>2.50</cell></row><row><cell>" " " "</cell><cell>4 <unclear>tts.</unclear> <orig reg="powder">powdir</orig> flints</cell><cell>3.50</cell></row><row><cell>" " " "</cell><cell>70 Rations 10 <abbr expan="cents each">cts ea.</abbr></cell><cell>7.00</cell></row><row><cell>" " " "</cell><cell>1/20 par of Boat</cell><cell>6.00 <add>$56.00</add></cell></row></table><table><row><cell>To each person in the family say 3.210 Rations</cell><cell>21.00</cell></row><row><cell>3/20th parts of a Boat eat $6.00</cell><cell>18.00</cell></row><row><cell>" <unclear>presants &amp; contigerce</unclear></cell><cell>10.00 <add>$49</add></cell></row><row><cell>aggregate debt</cell><cell>$105.00</cell></row></table></p><p>If any difficulties should arise in your mind touching any point of <add>your</add> duty, it will always afford me <orig reg="great">grate</orig> pleasure to exchange Ideas with you, <orig reg="Independent">Independant</orig> of any thing which I have communicated.  it will be necessary to keep a Journal of time and distance in traveling.  you will please acknowledge the receipt of this and advise me how far it meets your approbation.</p><closer><salute>You <abbr expan="obedient Humble Servant">obd. Huml. sert.</abbr></salute><signed><name><abbr expan="Joseph">Jos</abbr> McMinn</name></signed> <address><addrLine><name><abbr expan="Colonel George">Colo. Geo.</abbr> Gillespie</name></addrLine></address> <pb n="[4]"/> Copy No 29 <lb/> Geo. Gillespie <lb/> 4th May 1818 <lb/> Subject <lb/> Instructions and fixing to Colo Gillespie Commisioner of valuing Cherokee improvements</closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
