<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="pa0044"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title> [Letter] 1836 Feb. 6, Spring Place, GA [to] W[illia]m Schley, Gov[ernor] of Georgia / Ben[jamin] F. Currey : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Currey, Benjamin F.</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harden</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">pa0044</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title> [Letter] 1836 Feb. 6, Spring Place, GA [to] W[illia]m Schley, Gov[ernor] of Georgia / Ben[jamin] F. Currey</title><author>Currey, Benjamin F.</author><date value="1836-02-06">February 6, 1836</date><extent>1p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated February 6, 1836, from Benjamin Currey, U.S. agent to the Cherokee Nation, to Governor William Schley of Georgia. Currey warns Schley that the Cherokees in Georgia may be enlisting the help of the Creek Indians in order to resist removal west of the Mississippi River.</note><note type="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note><note type="box">MS-2033</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">pa0044</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Letters</item><item>Cherokee Indians -- Claims against</item><item>Creek Indians -- Claims against</item><item>Relocation</item><item>Georgia</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letter"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><address><addrLine><name>Spring Place <abbr expan="Georgia">Ga</abbr></name> <date><abbr expan="February">Feby</abbr> 6 1836</date></addrLine></address><add>Copy</add><address><addrLine>To His Excellency</addrLine><addrLine><name><abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> Schley</name></addrLine><addrLine><abbr expan="Governor">Govr</abbr> of Georiga</addrLine></address> <salute>Sir</salute></opener><p>I have the honor to transcribe to you the copy of a communication from myself to the commissioner of <abbr expan="Indian Affairs">Ind Affs</abbr> And at the same time to advise you that while large numbers of the <name>Creeks</name> are flocking into the <name>Cherokee</name> settlements of Georgia intimations have been made by vindictive Cherokees that at a short notice they could avail themselves of all the physical force of the creek nation to resist the contemplated removal of the cherokees from your Territory </p><p>Although in the sequel these intimations may all be found to be momentary <orig reg="ebullitions">ebulitions</orig> of fancy or passion more than any settled  design to commence hostilities hereafter, it is considered highly proper that you should as the Executive officer of the state be informed of all that militates against your local laws and directly or remotely threatens evil to your citizens</p><closer><salute>Very Respectfully <lb/> I have the honor to be Your most <abbr expan="Obedient Servant">Obt Servt</abbr></salute> <signed><name><abbr expan="Benjamin">Ben.</abbr> F. Currey</name></signed></closer></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
