<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD">
<TEI.2 ID="pa0006"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>[Account of] Return J. Meigs, 1805 Oct. 1 - 1808 Oct. 1, Tennessee: a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>pa0006</IDNO><IDNO>OCLC: 44921575</IDNO><AVAILABILITY><P>This work is the property of the University of Tennessee Special Collections Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>[Account of] Return J. Meigs, 1805 Oct. 1 - 1806 Oct. 1, Tennessee</TITLE><DATE VALUE="1805-10-01">October 1, 1805</DATE><DATE VALUE="1808-10-01">October 1, 1808</DATE><EXTENT>2p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">This document is an account of the pay and expenses of Return J. Meigs, principal U.S. agent to the Cherokee Indians, from October 1, 1805 through October 1, 1808.  The ledger contains descriptions of his various duties, the dates they were carried out, and the expense incurred for each.  The majority of his activities with the Cherokees were carried out in Tennessee.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">Special Collections Library, The University of Tennessee Knoxville</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box"></NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder"></NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">pa0006</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for the University of Georgia Libraries Electronic Text Center</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL>
</TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Expense accounts</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians</ITEM><ITEM>Indian agents</ITEM><ITEM>Tennessee</ITEM></LIST></KEYWORDS>
</TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="financial account"><PB N="[1]"><P><TABLE><HEAD>The <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>: To <NAME TYPE="person">Return J. Meigs</NAME> A. War in <NAME TYPE="place">Tennessee</NAME>.  Dr..</HEAD><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1808-10-01">1808 October 1st</DATE></CELL><CELL>To salary commencing <DATE VALUE="1805-10-01">1st October 1805</DATE>, ending <DATE VALUE="1808-10-01">1st October 1808</DATE>.-3 years at 1400 $ <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> year</CELL><CELL REND="right">4200.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To subsistence commencing <DATE VALUE="1805-10-01">1st October 1805</DATE>, ending <DATE VALUE="1806-10-01">1st October 1806</DATE>. 365 days, 6 rations <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> day 2190 ration at 14. <ABBR EXPAN="cents">cts</ABBR></CELL><CELL REND="right">306.60</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To subsistence commencing <DATE VALUE="1806-10-01">1st October 1806</DATE>. ending <DATE VALUE="1806-10-01">1st October 1808</DATE>. 731 days. 6 rations <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> day 4386 <ABBR EXPAN="ration" TYPE="suspension">ra</ABBR>: at 15 &frac12; cts</CELL><CELL REND="right">679.83</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To forage for 1 Horse commencing <DATE VALUE="1805-10-01">1st October 1805</DATE> ending <DATE VALUE="1808-10-01">1st October 1808</DATE>, 36 months at 6 $ <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> month</CELL><CELL REND="right">216.00</CELL><CELL REND="right">5402.43</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To cash expended on a Tour to <NAME TYPE="place">Eustinalee</NAME> at the request of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> Chiefs, 14 days, including Packhorse &amp; provisions</CELL><CELL REND="right">28.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1806-04-30">April 1806. 30</DATE></CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1806-05-27">May 27</DATE></CELL><CELL>To cash expended on 2 journeys to <NAME TYPE="place">Tellico</NAME>, on account of a <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> man having been killed by a whiteman</CELL><CELL REND="right">6.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1806-07-05">July 5</DATE></CELL><CELL>To cash expended on a Journey to <NAME TYPE="place">Colberts ferry</NAME> by order of The Secretary of war 20 days. 150 cents <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> day</CELL><CELL REND="right">30.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1806-07-05">"</DATE></CELL><CELL>To  "  to <UNCLEAR>Sawta</UNCLEAR> 16 days at 150.00. <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> day</CELL><CELL REND="right">24.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1806-08-08">August 8</DATE></CELL><CELL>To cash expended on a Journey to <NAME TYPE="place">Knoxville</NAME> to procure money 6 days at 150 cents <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> day</CELL><CELL REND="right">9.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1806-08-24">"  24</DATE></CELL><CELL>To <ORIG REG="expenses">expences</ORIG> 5 days for self &amp; surveyor on laying out the site for building the Garrison at <NAME TYPE="place">Highwassee</NAME> 2 $ <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> day</CELL><CELL REND="right">10.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1806-09-04">September 4</DATE></CELL><CELL>To <ORIG REG="expenses">expences</ORIG> at <NAME TYPE="place">Knoxville</NAME> on the prosecution of <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="John">Jno.</ABBR> Ferguson</NAME> for Killing an Indian in may last</CELL><CELL REND="right">3.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL REND="right">110.00</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1806-11-17">November 17</DATE></CELL><CELL>To cash expended with 2 Horses on a Journey to <NAME TYPE="place">Knoxville</NAME> to procure money 5 days, 2$ <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> day</CELL><CELL REND="right">10.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1806-11-29">November 29</DATE></CELL><CELL>To 7 days expenses, tour to <NAME TYPE="place">Highwassee</NAME> to pay the troops 2$ <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> day</CELL><CELL REND="right">14.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1806-12-02">December 2</DATE></CELL><CELL>To cash expended on a Journey to <NAME TYPE="place">Tellico</NAME> 3 days to pay the troops</CELL><CELL REND="right">4.50</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1806-12-19">December 19</DATE></CELL><CELL>To "  "  with 2 horses 4 days to procure money 2 $ <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> day</CELL><CELL REND="right">8.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1807-01-30">1807 January 30</DATE></CELL><CELL>To cash paid <NAME TYPE="person">Thomas N. Clark</NAME> for 5 quires paper &amp; box wafers</CELL><CELL REND="right">2.35</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1807-04-10">April 10</DATE></CELL><CELL>To  "  "  on Journey to <NAME TYPE="place">Tellico</NAME> to pay the troops</CELL><CELL REND="right">2.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1807-04-12">April 12</DATE></CELL><CELL>To  "  6 days  "  to <NAME TYPE="place">Knoxville</NAME> to procure money</CELL><CELL REND="right">6.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1807-04-22">April 22</DATE></CELL><CELL>To  "  "  with 2 horses <UNCLEAR>brot.</UNCLEAR> 3000$</CELL><CELL REND="right">7.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1807-05-07">May 7</DATE></CELL><CELL>To  "  "  with 2 horses to <NAME TYPE="place">Knoxville</NAME> for money</CELL><CELL REND="right">5.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL REND="right">58.85</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1807-05-13">May 13</DATE>.<DATE VALUE="1807-05-14">14</DATE>.<DATE VALUE="1807-05-15">15</DATE>.<DATE VALUE="1807-05-16">16</DATE></CELL><CELL>To  "  expended having 3 pack horses &amp; 2 men for a guard from <NAME TYPE="place"><ABBR EXPAN="South">So.</ABBR> West point</NAME> to <DEL TYPE="overstrike">Knox</DEL> <NAME TYPE="place">Highwassee</NAME> having in charge 7870 $ 5 days going &amp; returning</CELL><CELL REND="right">7.56</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1807-06-22">June 22nd</DATE></CELL><CELL>To cash expended 5  "  going to <NAME TYPE="place">Knoxville</NAME> for money 150 cts <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> day</CELL><CELL REND="right">7.50</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1807-08-01">August 1</DATE></CELL><CELL>To  "  "  5 days going to <NAME TYPE="place">Tellico</NAME> to pay the troops</CELL><CELL REND="right">7.25</CELL><CELL><DATE VALUE="1807-08-03">  "  3</DATE></CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  paid <NAME TYPE="person">James Rogers</NAME> for bringing 1000$ 40 miles</CELL><CELL REND="right">2.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1807-11-09"><ABBR EXPAN="November">Novemr</ABBR> 9</DATE></CELL><CELL>To  "  expended with <NAME TYPE="person">Col. Earle</NAME> looking for Iron ore 12 days</CELL><CELL REND="right">24.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1808-01-01">1808 January 1</DATE></CELL><CELL>To  "  "  Journey to <NAME TYPE="place">Knoxville</NAME> for money &amp; to <NAME TYPE="place">Tellico</NAME> to pay the troops.  2 horses 10 days</CELL><CELL REND="right">15.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1808-02-02"><ABBR EXPAN="February">Feby</ABBR> 2</DATE></CELL><CELL> To cash expended going to <NAME TYPE="place">Knoxville</NAME> to obtain money to pay the troops at <NAME TYPE="place">Highwassee</NAME> &amp; <NAME TYPE="place">Tellico</NAME>  absent 10 days with 2 horses. 2$ <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> day</CELL><CELL REND="right">20.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1808-04-02">April 2</DATE></CELL><CELL>To cash expended  on journey to <NAME TYPE="place">Kingston</NAME> for money <DATE VALUE="with">wh.</DATE> 2 horses 5 days</CELL><CELL REND="right">10.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL><DATE VALUE="1808-07-26">June 26</DATE></CELL><CELL>To cash paid <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Benjamin">Benja.</ABBR> White</NAME> mail carrier for carrying in his stage 2000$ from <NAME TYPE="place">Carthage</NAME> to the turnpike 90 miles to <NAME TYPE="place">Highwassee</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">5.00</CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To cash paid <NAME TYPE="person">Brittain Goodwin</NAME> to carry the same money 35 miles</CELL><CELL REND="right">2.50</CELL><CELL REND="right">100.81</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL REND="right">$5672.09</CELL></ROW></TABLE></P></DIV1></BODY><BACK><DIV1 TYPE="financial account"><PB N="[2]"><P>No 16<LB><NAME TYPE="person">Return J. Meigs</NAME> acct.<LB>Dollars <HI>5672.09</HI></P></DIV1></BACK></TEXT></TEI.2>
