<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD">
<TEI.2 ID="pa0016"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>[Letter], 1802 June 30, Chickamoga [i.e. Chickamauga], [to] Maj[or] William Lovely [Tennessee?] / Daniel Ross : a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><AUTHOR>Ross, Daniel H. (Daniel Hicks)</AUTHOR><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>pa0016</IDNO><IDNO>OCLC: 44923177</IDNO><AVAILABILITY><P>This work is the property of the University of Tennessee Special Collections Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>[Letter], 1802 June 30, Chickamoga [i.e. Chickamauga], [to] Maj[or] William Lovely [Tennessee?] / Daniel Ross</TITLE><AUTHOR>Ross, Daniel H. (Daniel Hicks)</AUTHOR><DATE VALUE="1802-06-30"> June 30, 1802</DATE><EXTENT>4p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">Daniel Ross, Indian Agent, writes to Major William Lovely and informs him that some horses were stolen out of his possession. He thinks that the horses ought to be paid for by the government in agreement with the Tellico Treaty. Daniel Ross believes there is sufficient evidence to name Estridge as the thief, and he would like action to be taken against him and his family, June 30, 1802.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">Special Collections Library, The University of Tennessee Knoxville</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box"></NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder"></NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">pa0016</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for the University of Georgia Libraries Electronic Text Center</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL>
</TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Letters</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Treaties</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Claims</ITEM><ITEM>Tennessee</ITEM></LIST></KEYWORDS>
</TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="letter"><PB N="[1]"><OPENER><DATELINE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE><NAME TYPE="place">Chickamoga</NAME></ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE VALUE="1802-06-30"> June 30th 1802</DATE></DATELINE><SALUTE>Sir</SALUTE></OPENER><P>As you have at length returned <SIC CORR="from">from from</SIC> <NAME TYPE="place">S. W. Point</NAME>. It is time to know how the horses stolen out of my possession belonging to the family are to be paid for, There being no <UNCLEAR>positive</UNCLEAR> (<ORIG REG="although">altho</ORIG> very strong circumstantial) proof against <NAME TYPE="person">Estridge</NAME>, it appears plain to me those horses ought to be paid for by the Government, agreeable to <NAME TYPE="place">Tellico</NAME> Treaty &amp; I may add <ORIG REG="agreeable"> agreable</ORIG> to <NAME TYPE="person">Col Meigs</NAME> own decision at the green corn dance held at <NAME TYPE="place">Wellstown</NAME>, which <ORIG REG="agreeable"> agreable</ORIG> to <NAME TYPE="person">Wm Vann</NAME>s report, of <NAME TYPE="person">Wm Hicks</NAME>, the public Interpreter <UNCLEAR>runs this</UNCLEAR>. That <NAME TYPE="person">Shorey</NAME> ought to Seize so much of <NAME TYPE="person">Estridge</NAME>'s property as would be sufficient to indemnify the <ORIG REG="losers"> loosers</ORIG> of the horses, and if there was not sufficiency found the <NAME TYPE="place">UStates</NAME> would make up the remainder, ,, as both <NAME TYPE="person">Wm Hicks</NAME> &amp; <NAME TYPE="person">Wm Vanns</NAME> speaks. I understand the <NAME TYPE="person">English</NAME> well, we could not suppose they could be deceived in the Colonel's meaning. I presume to think if any Indian horses stolen by whites are  intended to be paid for under the treaty<PB N="[2]">
those I mention undoubt<ADD PLACE="supralinear">ed</ADD>ly have, These happening to be stolen out of my possession does not lessen the claim of the nation. Natives may send their horses on their necessary business to any post within their own boundaries, &amp; if stolen out of those boundaries by Whites, their claims on the <NAME TYPE="place">UStates</NAME> are as strong as if stolen out of the range. <ABBR EXPAN="Honorable" TYPE="suspension">Hon</ABBR> <NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Colonel" TYPE="suspension">Colo</ABBR> Meigs</NAME> in whose integrity I have high confidence should afterwards deviate from his decision at <NAME TYPE="place">Wellstown</NAME>. I cannot <ORIG REG="account">accounte</ORIG> for otherwise than by the false &amp; malicious statements of Enemies, who, I am well informed, told the Colonel that one of the horses for which payment was <ORIG REG="demanded">demmanded</ORIG> was mine, <ORIG REG="though">tho</ORIG> the contrary is well known &amp; can be made more manifest if required. You recollect on <NAME TYPE="person">Estridge</NAME>s return to the nation last winter, the grounds of the charge against him was submitted to your judgement, after <ORIG REG="a fair">afair</ORIG> &amp; candid investigation you passed conditional judgement against him <PB N="[3]">which afterwards, by his own conduct became final, but the <ORIG REG="losers">loosers</ORIG> of the horses have not been able to derive any benefit from that sentence, &amp; this failure is in a <UNCLEAR>measure</UNCLEAR> owing to the Colonels granting him some instrument <SIC CORR="of">of of</SIC> writing, the contents of which I can say nothing about, only from report, but <ADD PLACE="supralinear">be</ADD> the contents what it may, it appears it served to <ORIG REG="favor">favour</ORIG> his flight from this part of the nation &amp; to obtain from the <NAME TYPE="person">Tortle at home</NAME>, the horses lodged in his hands as security, he is now gone to <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, but whether he will have the audacity to return is uncertain</P><P>You will excuse me Sir if I observe that an Agent could not exercise the function of an Agent to better advantage to the <NAME TYPE="place">UStates</NAME> , than to order all the <NAME TYPE="person">Estridges</NAME> out of the Nation, which I think may now be done  without opposition. <NAME TYPE="person">Calwell</NAME> &amp; <NAME TYPE="person">Miles</NAME> have lived in every Indian Nation to the Southward &amp; have rendered themselves obnoxious to them all.  The <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> have become their last retreat to the South, it <PB N="[4]">would be well to compel them to seek their fortune further abroad &mdash; <NAME TYPE="person">Shorey</NAME> would be obliged to you to let him know as soon as possible whether he has any expectations from the Chief Agent on this subject or not.</P><CLOSER><SALUTE>With due consideration I remain<LB>Sir your most <ABBR EXPAN="Obedient Servant" TYPE="Suspension">Ob Servt</ABBR></SALUTE><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person">Daniel Ross</NAME></SIGNED><LB><NAME TYPE="person">Major William Lovely</NAME> <UNCLEAR><ABBR EXPAN="Tennessee Agent" TYPE="suspension"><NAME TYPE="place">Te</NAME>Agt</ABBR></UNCLEAR></CLOSER></DIV1></BODY></TEXT></TEI.2>
