<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD"><TEI.2 ID="pa0014"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>Duplicate account of money paid the Cherokee Nation on account of annuity, 1817: a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>pa0014</IDNO><IDNO>OCLC: 44922835</IDNO><AVAILABILITY STATUS="FREE"><P>This work is the property of The University of Tennessee Special Collections Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>Duplicate account of money paid the Cherokee Nation on account of annuity, 1817</TITLE><DATE VALUE="1817-00-00">1817</DATE><EXTENT>2p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">This is a copy of an account of funds disbursed to the Cherokee Nation relative to the annuity for 1817, under the authority of Return J. Meigs, U.S. Agent to the Cherokees in Tennessee.  The payments recorded primarily include subsistence and transportation expenses.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">Special Collections Library, The University of Tennessee Knoxville</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box">1</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder">16</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">pa0014</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Expense accounts</ITEM><ITEM>Annuities</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Nation</ITEM><ITEM>Tennessee</ITEM></LIST> </KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="financial account"><PB N="[1]"><P><HI REND="b">A</HI> <DATE VALUE="1817-00-00">1817</DATE>.<LB>Duplicate account of money paid the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee nation</NAME> on orders for money &amp; for <UNCLEAR>Com</UNCLEAR> on account of Annuity for 18<GAP REASON="document damaged"> <LB><DATE VALUE="1817-00-00">1817</DATE></P><P>$29593,,46</P><P><TABLE><ROW><CELL REND="right">. $21394.</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL REND="right">29593</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>&horbar;</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL REND="right">$50987,,</CELL></ROW></TABLE></P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="financial account"><PB N="[2]"><P><TABLE><HEAD>The <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> To <NAME TYPE="person">Return J Meigs</NAME>    <ABBR>Dr</ABBR><LB><DATE VALUE="1817-00-00">1817</DATE>.</HEAD><ROW><CELL>To cash paid <NAME TYPE="person">John Ross</NAME> for Sundry Orders, <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME>,</CELL><CELL REND="right">915</CELL><CELL REND="right">37 &frac12;</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  an Order for </CELL><CELL REND="right">96</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">Bigg Cabbin</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">8</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">John Hildebrand</NAME>, corn</CELL><CELL REND="right">75</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  3 Orders, <NAME TYPE="person">James Brown</NAME>, Corn</CELL><CELL REND="right">1734</CELL><CELL REND="right">50</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">John Riley</NAME> for delivering corn</CELL><CELL REND="right">8</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To cash paid <NAME TYPE="person">John McGee</NAME> for Corn</CELL><CELL REND="right">1620</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL REND="right"><ADD PLACE="left" CERT="appears to be in different ink"> checkmark</ADD> 4456</CELL><CELL REND="right">87 &frac12;</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">John Ross</NAME> for Corn</CELL><CELL REND="right">971</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">Samuel Riley</NAME> for Corn</CELL><CELL REND="right">300</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">Richard Riley</NAME> for Corn</CELL><CELL REND="right">94</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To Cash paid <NAME TYPE="person">John Jolly</NAME> for perogue</CELL><CELL REND="right">8</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">Rev. John Gambold</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">75</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL REND="right"><ADD PLACE="left" CERT="appears to be in different ink"> checkmark</ADD> 1448</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  an Order in favor of <NAME TYPE="person">Bigg Cabbin</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">75</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To Cash paid <NAME TYPE="person">James Morrison</NAME> for Corn &amp; Boat,  &amp;</CELL><CELL REND="right">765</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>  and flour for <NAME TYPE="person">Toochelee Glass</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">16</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To Cash paid <NAME TYPE="person">James Brown</NAME> for Corn</CELL><CELL REND="right">530</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">Capt. Taylor</NAME> for Boat to convey corn to Creek path</CELL><CELL REND="right">20</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">Henry Nave</NAME> for Corn</CELL><CELL REND="right">163</CELL><CELL REND="right">50</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">Rev. Cyrus Kingsberry</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">225</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To Cash paid <NAME TYPE="person">Joseph Coodey</NAME> for Corn </CELL><CELL REND="right"><UNCLEAR>166</UNCLEAR></CELL><CELL REND="right"><UNCLEAR>50</UNCLEAR></CELL><CELL REND="right"><UNCLEAR>1961</UNCLEAR></CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">John Ross</NAME> for Corn</CELL><CELL REND="right">875</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  An Order in favor of <NAME TYPE="person">the Bark</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">56</CELL><CELL REND="right">25</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To cash paid <NAME TYPE="person">David Russels</NAME>  <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr</ABBR> Order</CELL><CELL REND="right">20</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "	"   <NAME TYPE="person">Michael H<GAP DESC="il" REASON="document damaged">derbrand</NAME>'s Order</CELL><CELL>100</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">L. Ross</NAME> <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr</ABBR> O<GAP DESC="r" REASON="document damaged">der of <NAME TYPE="person">Testanwalloskey</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">20</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To cash paid <NAME TYPE="person">John M<GAP DESC="c" REASON="document damaged">Gee</NAME> for Corn</CELL><CELL REND="right">117</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">Joshua Johnson</NAME><ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> Order in favor of <NAME TYPE="person">James Ore</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">29</CELL><CELL REND="right">50</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME REG="Hicks?" TYPE="person">Charles Hix</NAME> <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> Order in favor of <NAME TYPE="person">Stephen Hanes</NAME></CELL><CELL REND="right">427</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">James Lastly</NAME> <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> Order</CELL><CELL REND="right">42</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL REND="right"><ADD PLACE="left" CERT="appears to be in different ink"> checkmark </ADD> 1686</CELL><CELL REND="right">75</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">James Reid</NAME> for Corn</CELL><CELL REND="right">255</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">Francis</NAME> &amp; <GAP REASON="document damaged"> for 850 bushels Corn at 125<ABBR EXPAN="cents per">cts pr</ABBR><LB>Bushel and One Boat at 30 dollars making</CELL><CELL REND="right">1092</CELL><CELL REND="right">50</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To cash paid to <NAME TYPE="person">N. Byers</NAME> <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> Orders</CELL><CELL REND="right">271</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL REND="right"><ADD PLACE="left" CERT="appears to be in different ink">checkmark</ADD> 1618</CELL><CELL REND="right">50</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">Caleb Star</NAME> for Corn</CELL><CELL REND="right">317</CELL><CELL REND="right">50</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">Samuel Riley</NAME> for Corn</CELL><CELL REND="right">915</CELL><CELL REND="right">37 &frac12;</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To cash paid <NAME TYPE="person">G. Morgan</NAME> for <NAME TYPE="person">R. Morgan</NAME>  <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr.</ABBR> Order</CELL><CELL REND="right">1425</CELL><CELL REND="right">"</CELL><CELL REND="right"><ADD PLACE="left" CERT="appears to be in different ink">checkmark</ADD> 2657</CELL><CELL REND="right">87 &frac12;</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">John Walker</NAME> <ABBR EXPAN="per">pr</ABBR> Orders</CELL><CELL REND="right">7008</CELL><CELL REND="right">33 1/3</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">John McGee</NAME> for corn &amp; Boat</CELL><CELL REND="right">2354</CELL><CELL REND="right">50</CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To  "  "  <NAME TYPE="person">John McGee</NAME> for corn</CELL><CELL REND="right"><ADD PLACE="bottom">error 10 $ short</ADD> 1402</CELL><CELL REND="right">50</CELL><CELL REND="right">10765</CELL><CELL REND="right">33 1/3</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL REND="right">$2459<DEL TYPE="overstrike">3</DEL><ADD PLACE="supralinear" CERT="appears in different ink">4</ADD></CELL><CELL REND="right">46</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL>To cash paid for improvements, as per Treaty<LB>concluded at <NAME TYPE="place">Turkey Town</NAME> <DATE VALUE="1816-10-04">4 Oct. 1816</DATE></CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL REND="right">5000</CELL><CELL REND="right">..</CELL></ROW><ROW><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL> </CELL><CELL REND="right">$29593</CELL><CELL REND="right">46</CELL></ROW></TABLE><LB><ADD PLACE="bottom" CERT="appears in different ink">and <UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR> with <ABBR EXPAN="account">act. </ABBR> A. B. &amp; C <UNCLEAR></UNCLEAR></ADD></P></DIV1></BODY></TEXT></TEI.2>
