<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD">
<TEI.2 ID="pa0004"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>Articles of agreement between the United States and the Cherokee Nation, for opening a road through the said nation from the state of Tennessee to the state of Georgia, 1803 Oct. 20: a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>pa0004</IDNO><IDNO>OCLC: 44888929</IDNO><AVAILABILITY><P>This work is the property of the University of Tennessee Special Collections Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>Articles of agreement between the United States and the Cherokee Nation, for opening a road through the said nation from the state of Tennessee to the state of Georgia, 1803 Oct. 20</TITLE><DATE VALUE="1803-10-20">October 20, 1803</DATE><EXTENT>4p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">This document, dated October 20, 1803, is a copy or draft of an agreement between the United States and the Cherokee Nation for opening a road from Tellico in Tennessee into Georgia in the direction of the University of Georgia at Athens, Georgia.  The articles of the agreement enumerate the specific rights and powers reserved to the Cherokee Nation respecting tolls, ferries, and travel along the road.  The completed document, with signatures of Cherokee chiefs, also appears in the Southeastern Native American Documents Database as <XREF>pa0003</XREF>.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">Special Collections Library, The University of Tennessee Knoxville</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box"></NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder"></NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">pa0004</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for the University of Georgia Libraries Electronic Text Center</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tag</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Legal documents</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Government relations</ITEM><ITEM>Post roads</ITEM><ITEM>Georgia</ITEM><ITEM>Tennessee</ITEM></LIST></KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="legal agreement"><PB N="[1]"><HEAD>Articles of Agreement between the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> and the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME>, for opening a Road through the Said nation from the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Tennessee</NAME> to the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>.&mdash;</HEAD><P>The <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> Chiefs having taken into consideration the request of their Father the President of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> to grant that a road may be opened through their nation from the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Tennessee</NAME> to the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, &amp; being desirous to evince to their father the President of the good people of the <NAME TYPE="place">U-States</NAME> of their goodwill &amp; friendly disposition &mdash; Do hereby agree that a road may be opened from the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Tennessee</NAME> to the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> with the reservations, &amp;   <ORIG REG="provisions">provissions</ORIG>  , as in the following articles is expressed.</P><P>Article 1st,  The principal <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> Chiefs acting in behalf of the whole <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> do hereby give their Consent that a convenient communication for the citizens of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> may be opened at the sole <ORIG REG="expense">expence</ORIG> of the said <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, commencing at two points Viz.  At <NAME TYPE="place">South West point</NAME> on the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> grounds &amp; at <NAME TYPE="place">Tellico</NAME> also on the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> grounds &amp; continued on the best &amp; most practicable courses <ORIG REG="until">untill</ORIG> they shall intersect on the South Side of the <NAME TYPE="place">Hiwassee River</NAME> &amp; its two great branches- &amp; then be continued in one road in the nearest direction on the most practicable ground for a road  <ORIG REG="until">untill</ORIG> it shall strike that part of <NAME TYPE="place">Jackson County</NAME> <ADD PLACE="supralinear">in the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME></ADD> in the direction of the site of the College at <NAME REG="GA" TYPE="place">Athens</NAME> in said county.</P><P>Article 2d, In order to define the width of the road &amp; prevent disputes on that road it is hereby stipulated that the same shall not exceed sixty feet, except on such broken ground where it may be necessary to make Occasional variation from the course of the said road.</P><P>Article 3rd, The income arising from the Ferries at <NAME TYPE="place">South West point</NAME>, <NAME TYPE="place">Tellico</NAME> <NAME TYPE="place">Hiawassee river</NAME>,&amp; its two great Branches, <NAME TYPE="place">Eustinale River</NAME>, &amp; such other waters where Boats may be wanted, and such places on the said road as may be <DEL TYPE="overstrike">for the benefit of the</DEL> found necessary for the <ORIG REG="establishment">establisment</ORIG> of houses of entertainmen<ADD PLACE="supralinear">t</ADD><PB N="[2]">for the accommodation of travellers, is all reserved for the benefit of the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME>.</P><P>Article 4th, The principal Chiefs in behalf of the Nation hereby engage that good &amp; suitable Boats for the passage of travellers shall be provided at all such places as were it shall be found necessary, &amp; Houses of Entertainment shall also be established at the said Ferries &amp; other places of the said road, not exceeding Ten in the whole</P><P>Article 5th, The <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> shall make such regulations from time to time relating to the said Ferries &amp; other Establishments on the said road as may be deemed necessary for restraining licentiousness &amp; for preserving good order throughout the <ORIG REG="whole">whol</ORIG> of said Road, shall establish the rates of Ferriage for men, Horses, <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera">&amp;c</ABBR> , that may travel on the said road.</P><P>Article 6th, Officers Civil &amp; military &amp; all military men of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> when on public service. Public Expresses &amp; Mail carriers shall be exempted from any demand for Ferriage on any part of the said road- and all <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> with their Horses, Carriages, <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera">&amp;c</ABBR> shall be exempted from paying any ferriage on the said road.</P><P>Article 7th, If the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> should deem it proper to permit that the said road should be made a Turnpike road.  It is hereby stipulated that some of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> Chiefs in their own or in behalf of the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME>, shall have a right to become Members of a Turnpike Company for the <DEL TYPE="overstrike">fee</DEL> purpose of keeping said Road in good condition for travellers for the public benefit, &amp; it is hereby stipulated that as in the case Ferriage The <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> shall be exempted from paying anything for passing on the said road.</P><P>Article 8th, Commissioners shall be appointed by the <NAME TYPE="place">U. States</NAME> to explore Survey &amp; mark the trees where the said road shall be opened, &amp; the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> shall appoint<PB N="[3]">four of their principal Chiefs to assist the commissioners aforesaid in exploring the said Road of which they shall have timely notice from the agent.</P><P>Article 9th, It is hereby agreed in case the 7th Article shall not meet the approbation of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> The said articles shall be expunged from this agreement, which shall never the less not in any way effect The remaining Articles, but They shall <DEL TYPE="overstrike">also have timely notice from the agent</DEL> remain in full force &amp; be binding on the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> &amp; on the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME>.</P><P>Article 10th, There shall be triplicates of this agreement made,  One of which shall be sent to the Secretary of war- One delivered to the principal <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> Chief, and one lodged in the hands of the Agent for the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME>.</P><CLOSER>Done at <NAME TYPE="place">South West point</NAME> The <DATE VALUE="1803-10-20">20th Day of October in The year of our Lord one thousand Eight hundred &amp; three</DATE></CLOSER></DIV1></BODY><BACK><DIV1 TYPE="legal agreement"><PB N="[4]"><P><DATE VALUE="1803-10-00">Oct. 1803</DATE></P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="legal agreement"><P>Articles of Agreement</P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="legal agreement"><P>Cite. <DATE VALUE="1803-00-00">1803</DATE></P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="legal agreement"><P>Memorandum preparatory to an Agreement for Road <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera et cetera et cetera">&amp;c &amp;c &amp;c</ABBR></P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="legal agreement"><P>Minutes of the Council of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> on The <DATE VALUE="1803-10-20">20th Octo. 1803</DATE> on granting the Road &amp; leasing the Ferries</P></DIV1></BACK></TEXT></TEI.2>
