<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "teilite1" "TEILITE1.DTD" [
<!ENTITY #DEFAULT CDATA "">
]>
<TEI.2 ID="pa0003"><TEIHEADER><FILEDESC><TITLESTMT><TITLE>Articles of agreement between the United States and the Cherokee Nation for opening a road from the state of Tennessee to the state of Georgia through the Cherokee Nation / [recorded by] Return J. Meigs: a machine-readable transcription</TITLE><RESPSTMT><RESP>Creation of machine-readable version:</RESP><NAME>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</NAME><NAME>Debra Jean Roney</NAME></RESPSTMT></TITLESTMT><PUBLICATIONSTMT><PUBLISHER>The University of Tennessee Libraries</PUBLISHER><PUBPLACE>Knoxville, TN</PUBPLACE><ADDRESS><ADDRLINE>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>The University of Tennessee</ADDRLINE><ADDRLINE>Knoxville, TN 37996</ADDRLINE></ADDRESS><DATE>2000</DATE><IDNO>pa0003</IDNO><IDNO>OCLC: 44888553</IDNO><AVAILABILITY STATUS="FREE"><P>This work is the property of The University of Tennessee Special Collections Library, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.</P></AVAILABILITY></PUBLICATIONSTMT><SOURCEDESC><BIBL><TITLE>Articles of agreement between the United States and the Cherokee Nation for opening a road from the state of Tennessee to the state of Georgia through the Cherokee Nation / [recorded by] Return J. Meigs</TITLE><DATE VALUE="1803-10-20">October 20, 1803</DATE><EXTENT>3p</EXTENT><NOTE TYPE="summary">This document is an agreement between the United States and the Cherokee Nation for opening a road from Tellico in Tennessee into Jackson County, Georgia in the direction of the University of Georgia in Athens, Georgia.  The articles of the agreement enumerate the specific rights and powers reserved to the Cherokee Nation respecting tolls, ferries, and travel along the road.  The agreement was set down by Return J. Meigs and bears the signature of a number of Cherokee leaders including Charles Hicks, Pathkiller, James Vann and Black Fox.</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="repository">Special Collections Library, The University of Tennessee Knoxville</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="box">1</NOTE><NOTE TYPE="folder"></NOTE><NOTE TYPE="document">pa0003</NOTE></BIBL></SOURCEDESC></FILEDESC><ENCODINGDESC><PROJECTDESC><P>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</P></PROJECTDESC><EDITORIALDECL><P>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</P><P>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</P><P>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</P><P>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed. </P><P>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</P></EDITORIALDECL><REFSDECL><P>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</P></REFSDECL><CLASSDECL><TAXONOMY ID="LCSH"><BIBL><TITLE>Library of Congress Subject Headings</TITLE></BIBL></TAXONOMY></CLASSDECL></ENCODINGDESC><PROFILEDESC><TEXTCLASS><KEYWORDS SCHEME="LCSH"><LIST><ITEM>Legal documents</ITEM><ITEM>Cherokee Indians--Government relations</ITEM><ITEM>Post roads</ITEM><ITEM>Georgia</ITEM><ITEM>Tennessee</ITEM></LIST> </KEYWORDS></TEXTCLASS></PROFILEDESC></TEIHEADER><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="legal agreement"><PB N="[1]"><P>The <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> having taken into consideration the request of their father the President of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> to grant that a Road may be opened through their Nation from the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Tennessee</NAME> to the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> and being desirous to evince to their father the President and the good people of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, their good will and friendly disposition do hereby agree that a road may be opened from the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Tennessee</NAME> to the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> with the reservations and provisions as in the following articles are expressed, and further to evince <ADD PLACE="supralinear">to</ADD> our father the President we are not influenced by Pecuniary motives we make a present of this <UNCLEAR>road</UNCLEAR> to the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME></P><DIV2><P>Article 1st. We the head men and warriors of the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME>, do consent that the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> may open a communication from the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Tennessee</NAME> to the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME>, solely at the expense of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, commencing at two points to wit, on the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> grounds <ADD PLACE="supralinear">at <NAME TYPE="place">South West Point</NAME> and <NAME TYPE="place">Tellico</NAME></ADD> and continued on the most <ORIG REG="practicable">practacable</ORIG> grounds for good road <ORIG REG="until">untill</ORIG> they shall intersect, on the South side of the <NAME TYPE="place">Highwassee River</NAME> and its two great branches, thence to be continued in one road to <NAME TYPE="place">Jackson County</NAME> in the State of <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> in the direction of the site of the College at <NAME REG="GA" TYPE="place">Athens</NAME> in said county, the said road shall not exceed sixty feet in width.</P><P>Article 2nd,  The <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> reserve to themselves the income of the Ferries and the Stands on the road for houses of entertainment and agree that one ferry shall be kept at <NAME TYPE="place">SouthWest point</NAME>, one at <NAME TYPE="place">Tellico</NAME>, and one at the river <NAME REG="River" TYPE="place">Chatahuchee</NAME> where the said road shall cross the said River, the Ferry at <NAME TYPE="place">South West Point</NAME></P><PB N="[2]"><P>shall be put into the hands of our Beloved <NAME TYPE="person">Chief Doublehead</NAME>, the other two shall be rented by our Agent to Citizens of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, to the highest bidder, the preference in renting these <ORIG REG="Ferries">Ferrys</ORIG> shall be in favor of persons having connections in the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME>, other things being equal</P><P>Article 3rd,  The <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> shall establish houses of entertainment on the said <ADD PLACE="supralinear">road</ADD> at three places to wit at <NAME TYPE="place">South West point</NAME>, <NAME TYPE="place">Tellico</NAME> &amp; <NAME REG="River" TYPE="place">Chatahuchee</NAME>, at the Ferries aforesaid, and it is hereby stipulated that after the said road shall be opened by the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> with their connections will form a Turnpike Company for keeping the said road constantly in <ADD PLACE="supralinear">good</ADD> repair for travellers with carriages &amp; Horses <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera">&amp;c</ABBR>, and in order to preserve good order on the said road, it is the request of the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> that the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> will place not less than a Subaltern's Command at or near the Point where the said road shall intersect the <NAME TYPE="place">Georgia</NAME> line as aforesaid, for the <ORIG REG="convenience">conveniency</ORIG> of said command a sufficient quantity of ground within their own boundary shall be appropriated for wood <ABBR EXPAN="et cetera">&amp;c</ABBR>.  The <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> shall make such regulations as may be found proper to prevent persons from evading the payment of Ferriage or Toll and shall fix the rates of ferriage and toll according to custom in such cases.</P><P>Article 4th,  In order to prevent disorder from being communicated to the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> live stocks, no Meat Cattle from the Southern States shall be driven through the said Nation and in order to prevent the stealing of Horses, or purchasing them without license, or other impositions affecting the Horses and Cattle of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME>.  A description of horses, and their number shall be inserted <ADD PLACE="supralinear">in</ADD> the passports of those persons who may be taking them through the said Nation, and the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> shall not be answerable for <UNCLEAR>estrays</UNCLEAR> from the Citizens of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> on said road.</P><P>Article 5th,  All officers civil and military and all military men of <PB N="[3]">the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME>, when on public service, mail carrier, with their horses and carriages shall be exempted from paying toll or ferriage on said road- also all <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> with their horses, cattle and all white men residing in the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> shall be exempted from any demands for toll or ferriage on said road.</P><P>Article 6th.  Commissioners shall be appointed by the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> to explore, survey, and mark the trees where the said road shall be opened.  And the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> shall appoint four of their Chiefs to attend with the said Commissioners on that business.</P><P>Article 7th.  Triplicates of this agreement shall be made, one of which shall be sent to the Secretary of War, one delivered to the principal <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> Chiefs and one kept in the office of the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokee</NAME> Agent.</P><P>Done at <NAME TYPE="place">South west Point</NAME> the <DATE VALUE="1803-10-20">twentieth day of October in the Year of our Lord One thousand  Eight hundred and three</DATE></P><CLOSER><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person">Return J. Meigs</NAME></SIGNED> <UNCLEAR>F.</UNCLEAR> agent for the <NAME TYPE="person">Cherokees</NAME> in behalf of the <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME><LB>Before signing the within agreement the note on the margin was made.  Witnesses present.<LB>In explanation to article 1st. it is understood that there is to be only one fork on the said communication as expressed in said first article, that no other branch or branches shall ever be permitted to be opened without the consent of the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> and when opened the direction of the road shall not be changed.<SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person">Frances Johnson</NAME> Capt 2nd <NAME TYPE="place">United States</NAME> Reg. Infantry <LB><NAME TYPE="person"><UNCLEAR>Klaus Lt</UNCLEAR></NAME>  <NAME TYPE="place">US</NAME> <ABBR EXPAN="Regiment Artillery">Regt Arty</ABBR><LB><NAME TYPE="person"><UNCLEAR>Jo</UNCLEAR> Brahan</NAME> 1st Lieut. 2nd Regiment Infantry &amp; Paymaster district of <NAME TYPE="place">Tennessee</NAME><LB><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="Thomas">Tho.</ABBR> Van Dyke</NAME> Surgeons mate<LB><NAME TYPE="person">Merriwether Smith</NAME><LB><NAME TYPE="person"><ABBR EXPAN="William">Wm</ABBR> Lovely</NAME><LB><NAME TYPE="person">Charles Hicks</NAME><LB><NAME TYPE="person">Black  Fox</NAME>  X  <ABBR EXPAN="Principal">P.</ABBR> Chief<LB><NAME TYPE="person">Pathkiller</NAME>  X<LB><NAME TYPE="person">Glass</NAME>  X<LB><NAME TYPE="person"><UNCLEAR>Tugustuskee</UNCLEAR></NAME><LB><NAME TYPE="person">Kutagiskee</NAME>  X<LB><NAME TYPE="person"><UNCLEAR>Chulioa</UNCLEAR></NAME> <NAME TYPE="person">Creek</NAME> Interpreter  X<LB><NAME TYPE="person"><UNCLEAR>Tuluntuskee</UNCLEAR></NAME>  X<LB><NAME TYPE="person">Tulleat Home</NAME> X<LB><NAME TYPE="person">Tuneegetchee</NAME>  X<LB><NAME TYPE="person">Warriors Nephew</NAME>  X<LB><NAME TYPE="person">Chief Satchee</NAME>  X<LB><NAME TYPE="person"><UNCLEAR>Eusanatee</UNCLEAR></NAME>  X<LB><NAME TYPE="person">Will Elders</NAME>  X</SIGNED><PB N="[4]"><SIGNED><NAME TYPE="person">James Vann</NAME></SIGNED></CLOSER></DIV2></DIV1></BODY><BACK><DIV1 TYPE="legal agreement"><P>An agreement for opening a road <ORIG REG="through">thro</ORIG> the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> concluded the <DATE VALUE="1803-10-20">20th  day of October 1803</DATE>.</P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="legal agreement"><P>continued on file of <DATE VALUE="1822-00-00">1822</DATE></P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="legal agreement"><P>Agreement for opening roads <ORIG REG="through">thro</ORIG> the <NAME TYPE="place person">Cherokee Nation</NAME> <DATE VALUE="1803-10-20">20 Oct. 1803</DATE></P></DIV1><DIV1 TYPE="legal agreement"><P>A Triplicate</P></DIV1></BACK></TEXT></TEI.2>
