<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../../Rules/teixlite_tei.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="pa0209"> 
  <teiHeader> 
	 <fileDesc> 
		<titleStmt> 
		  <title>[Letter] 1812 Mar. 28, Maury County, Tennessee [to] Elias Earle / James Holland : a machine readable transcription of an image</title> 
		  <author>Holland, James S.</author> 
		  <respStmt> 
			 <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 <name>Debra Roney</name> 
			 <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
			 <name>Danielle Hardin</name> 
			 <name>Bobby Holt</name> 
		  </respStmt> 
		</titleStmt> 
		<publicationStmt> 
		  <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections
			 Library</publisher> 
		  <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace> 
		  <address> 
			 <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>University of Tennessee 
			 </addrLine> 
			 <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996 
			 </addrLine> 
		  </address> 
		  <date>2003 
		  </date> 
		  <idno type="SPCID">pa0209</idno> 
		  <idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 45830990</idno> 
		  <availability> 
			 <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library,
				University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN. It may be used freely by individuals
				for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of
				availability is included in the text. For all other use contact the Special
				Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401
				Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p> 
		  </availability> 
		</publicationStmt> 
		<sourceDesc> 
		  <bibl> 
			 <title>[Letter] 1812 Mar. 28, Maury County, Tennessee [to] Elias Earle / James Holland </title> 
			 <author> Holland, James S.</author> 
			 <date value="1812-03-28"> 
			 March 28, 1812</date> 
			 <extent> 4p</extent> 
			 <note type="summary">This is a copy of a letter from Major James Holland to Elias Earle dated March 28, 1812. Holland discusses the establishment of an iron works factory in the Cherokee Nation and briefly outlines the grounds on which the land for the factory was to be obtained by Earle.</note> 
			 <note type="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note> 
			 <note type="box">MS-2033</note> 
			 <note type="folder">55</note> 
			 <note type="document">pa0209</note> 
		  </bibl> 
		</sourceDesc> 
	 </fileDesc> 
	 <encodingDesc> 
		<projectDesc> 
		  <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		</projectDesc> 
		<editorialDecl n="4"> 
		  <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal
			 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p> 
		  <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p> 
		  <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		</editorialDecl> 
		<refsDecl> 
		  <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p> 
		</refsDecl> 
		<classDecl> 
		  <taxonomy> 
			 <bibl> 
				<title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
			 </bibl> 
		  </taxonomy> 
		</classDecl> 
	 </encodingDesc> 
	 <profileDesc> 
		<textClass> 
		  <keywords> 
			 <list> 
				<item>Letters</item><item>Cherokee Indians -- Land tenure</item><item>Iron-works</item><item>Factories</item><item>Tennessee</item><item>Holland, James S., 1754-1823</item> 
			 </list> 
		  </keywords> 
		</textClass> 
	 </profileDesc> 
  </teiHeader> 
  <text> 
	 <body> 
		<div1 type="Letters"><pb n="1"/> 
		  <opener><address><addrLine>Maury County</addrLine></address><dateline>28th March 1812</dateline></opener><salute>Dear sir</salute><p>In yours of the 27th <abbr expan="Ultimo">Ult</abbr> I am requested to give you a statement of the propositions of <name>Mr Jefferson</name> &amp; <name>H Dearborn</name>, the then President &amp; Secretary of War_Touching your Erecting Iron works <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp;c</abbr> in the <name>Cherokee</name> Country_ which were so far as my memory serves me as follows-- You was to use your influence to procure a purchase of a tract of land for that purpose, and if accomplished to Erect works there on and to manufacture Such Iron instruments of Husbandry as the Government, <orig reg="annually">anually</orig> supplies the Indians with for which you was to be allowed a fair price</p><p>You was to have a fee simple in the land, or a long lease, &amp; in the latter case you was to be paid for all permanent improvements, at the end of the lease, and if a fee simple, You was to <orig reg="reimburse">reimburce</orig> the moneys expended in the Extinguishment of the Indian title_I further recollect that after you had by treaty Obtained a grant from the Indians for the above purpose and had returned to <name>Washington</name>- nothing appeared to prevent the progress of the proceedings but a <pb n="2"/> doubt of the tract being within <del type="overstrike">within</del> limits of <name>Tennessee</name>- In which case measures were to be taken to obtain a title from the State or to vary the place to come within the <name>United States</name></p> 
		<closer><signed><name>James Holland</name></signed></closer></div1> 
	 </body> 
  <back><div1 type="Letters"><pb n="3"/><p><figure><figDesc>Page is blank</figDesc></figure></p><pb n="4"/><p>Copy <lb/> <abbr expan="Major">Majr</abbr>. Hollands Letter 28th March 1812 to <name>Elias Earle </name> <lb/> 1812 Cherokee</p></div1></back></text>
</TEI.2>
