<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "../rules/teixlite.dtd">
<TEI.2 id="pa0206"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>[Letter] 1808 Apr. 10, Greenville, So[uth] Carolina [to] Return J. Meigs, Highwassee / Col[onel] Elias Earle : a machine readable transcription of an image</title><author>Earle, Elias</author><respStmt><resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp><name>Holly Adams</name><name>Debra Roney</name><name>Maha Ayesh</name><name>Danielle Harden</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher><pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace><address><addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine><addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine><addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine></address><date>2002</date><idno type="SPCID">pa0206</idno><idno type="OCLC">OCLC: 45823652</idno><availability>                   <p>This work is the property of the Special Collections Library, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Special Collections Librarian, Hoskins Library, University of Tennessee, 1401 Cumberland Avenue, Knoxville, TN 37996. (865) 974-4480.</p></availability></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl><title>[Letter] 1808 Apr. 10, Greenville, So[uth] Carolina [to] Return J. Meigs, Highwassee / Col[onel] Elias Earle</title><author>Earle, Elias</author><date value="1808-04-10">April 10, 1808</date><extent> 4p</extent><note type="summary">This document is a letter dated April 10, 1806 from Colonel Elias Earle to Return J. Meigs, agent for Indian affairs. Earle informs Meigs that an unnamed treaty recently signed with the Cherokees has not been ratified and speculates that the failure is attributable to an inaccurate map of the United States. Earle mentions a memorial sent by [James] Vann and [Charles] Hicks. He also discusses the storage of corn at Highwassee as opposed to Chickama[u]ga Creek, both inside the Cherokee Nation. Earle was a congressman from Greenville, South Carolina.</note><note type="collection">Penelope Johnson Allen Collection</note><note type="box">MS-2033</note><note type="folder">n/a</note><note type="document">pa0206</note></bibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><projectDesc><p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p></projectDesc><editorialDecl n="4"><p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p><p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p><p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p><p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p><p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p></editorialDecl><refsDecl><p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p></refsDecl><classDecl><taxonomy><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy></classDecl></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass><keywords><list><item>Cherokee Indians--Treaties</item><item>Letters</item><item>Map reading</item><item>Southern States</item><item>Treaties--Ratification</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div1 type="letters"><pb n="[1]"/><opener><dateline><address><addrLine><name>Greenville</name></addrLine></address><date>10th April 1808</date></dateline><salute>Sir</salute></opener><p>after days since I had the pleasure to receive your <orig reg="favor">favour</orig> <date>12th March</date> by <name>Capt. Shackleford</name>, and am Truly glad to find that you have been kind Enough to him to let the corn be stored at- <name>Highwassee</name> a place that suits me much  better than at <name><orig reg="Chickamauga">Chickamaga</orig></name> under Every circumstance- You have no doubt before this been advised by the Secretary at war that the Treaty was not ratified, &amp; the reasons why it was not; I believe that there would not have <add>been</add> the Least doubt of it, had it not <orig reg="appeared">apeard</orig> to have been in the State of <name>Tennessee</name>, by Examining <name>Bradley</name>s map of the <name><abbr expan="United States">U.S.</abbr></name> upon making the <orig reg="inquiry">enquiry</orig> It was thought best to let it Lay over till <orig reg="another">an other</orig> session then was Several Very well wrote memorials sent on against it by <name>Vann Hicks</name> &amp; party, which went to protest against other <orig reg="Treaties">Treatys</orig> on the Head of <name>Elk</name> &amp; <name>Duck rivers</name> <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp; c</abbr> made <pb n="[2]"/> Lately- all that they could have done would not have had any influence <del type="overstrike">on</del> If the Cession had been made in the Land below <name>Nickajack</name>, or <abbr expan="South">So.</abbr> of 35th Degree Latitude- which land is Solely under the direction of the <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> Government. However as Tennessee has obtained Leave to purchase all within her Limits of the <name>Indians</name> as first as they will Sell- It is probable that there will be some provision made for the purchase at <orig reg="Chickamauga">Chickamaga</orig> - the Secretary at war promised me that he would Take what corn I had purchased, &amp; that he would write <orig reg="Immediately">Imediately</orig> to you on the subject If he has &amp; you have it in you power, to forward me the money by a safe hand or by mail, I will Take it as a Very Singular <orig reg="favor">favour</orig> for I assure <add>you</add> that cash has become a very scarce article in this part of the country- I suppose owing to the Embargo- Cotton, which is our Staple will not bring more than 12 1/2 cents at <orig reg="market">markett</orig>, a price that we are all unwilling to sell at - I will thank you to give Me the Earliest information when the next annuity <pb n="[3]"/> is at Highwassee, as I wish to attend to Say my business before the Chiefs <abbr expan="et cetera">&amp; c</abbr></p><closer><salute>I am Sir With great regret you Most <abbr expan="Obedient Servant">Obt Servt.</abbr></salute><signed><name>Elias Earle</name></signed><add><abbr expan="Post Script">P.S.</abbr> <orig reg="please">pleas</orig> to Direct your letter for Me<lb/> <name>Greenville Court House</name> <name><abbr expan="South">So</abbr> Carolina</name><lb/></add><signed><abbr expan="Elias Earle">E.E.</abbr></signed></closer></div1></body><back><div1><pb n="[4]"/><p><address><addrLine>Greenville <abbr expan="court house">c.h.</abbr> <abbr expan="South Carolina">So. C</abbr></addrLine></address><date>April 13th. 1808</date></p></div1><div1><p>Free</p></div1><div1><p><address><addrLine><name><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Return J. Meigs</name></addrLine><addrLine>Agent for Indian affairs</addrLine><addrLine>Highwassee</addrLine><addrLine><name>Kingston</name>  <unclear>p</unclear> office</addrLine></address></p></div1><div1><p><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Earles Letter informs <abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Meigs that he may sell his corn- &amp;; why the Treaty was not <orig reg="ratified">ratifyed</orig><lb/><date>10th April 1808</date></p></div1></back></text></TEI.2>
