<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl441">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter]    1844 Jan. 17, Nashville, Tennessee / Thos. Pritcher [et al]: a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Pritcher, Thos.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno type="SPCID">sl441</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">OCLC:</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>1844 Jan. 17, Nashville, Tennessee / Thos. Pritcher [et al]</title>
               <author>Ritcher, Thos.</author>
               <date when="1844-01-17">January 17, 1844</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This is a letter from the Central State Corresponding Committee dated January 17, 1844. It is to an unknown recipient. The committee represents the Democratic Convention of Tennessee. They express outrage over the fact that Martin Van Buren did not win the presidential election of 1840, and that he is a favorite for the current nomination. The committee writes that they want James K. Polk to run for Vice-President. A copy of the address stating this decision is included.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Laughlin Papers</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">2</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl441</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl n="4">
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Tennessee -- Campaigns</term>
               <term>Van Buren, Martin, 1782-1862</term>
               <term>Polk, James K., 1795-1845</term>
               <term>Presidential elections</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Pritcher, Thos.</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl441a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Nashville</name>, <choice>
                        <abbr>Tenn.</abbr>
                        <expan>Tennessee</expan>
                     </choice>
                     <date>January 17th. 1844</date>.</addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>To <lb/> Dear Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>The undersigned, members of the Central state corresponding Committee, appointed by the Democratic state convention of Tennessee, on the <date>23rd. day of November</date> last, herewith enclose you a copy of <del type="overstrike">the</del>
               <add>an</add> Address <add>made by</add>
               <del type="overstrike">by by</del>
               <add>
                  <del type="overstrike">published by</del> a General State</add> committee, of which <del type="overstrike">Genl</del>
               <add>Gov.</add>
               <name>William Carroll</name> is chairman, <del type="overstrike">appointed by the convention,</del> published by authority of the convention, and respectfully solicit its publication in (Leave a blank here of at least half a line)</p>
            <p>Although the late state convention, from a sincere wish to promote and preserve harmony in the democratic party made nomination of a candidate for the Presidency; yet it would be doing great injustice to the democracy of Tennessee, <del type="overstrike">to suppose</del> and to the Convention, to suppose that they did not feel a warm and decided preferences <add>for <name>Mr. Van Buren</name>
               </add> among the prominent <del type="overstrike">candidates</del>
               <add>aspirants</add> for that high office, whose names it <choice>
                  <orig>ixpected</orig>
                  <reg>expected</reg>
               </choice> will be submitted to the national convention. The democracy of this state however, will, in all sincerity and good faith, earnestly and zealously support the nominee of the national convention, whoever he may <add>be</add> ; but at the same time, Mr. Van Buren is well known to be the first choice of a very large majority of our democracy. This was plainly <add>and fully</add> indicated, by resolutions of preference, <del type="overstrike">expressed</del>
               <add>passed</add> almost unanimously by the people, in primary meeting, in <choice>
                  <orig>narly</orig>
                  <reg>nearly</reg>
               </choice> all the counties and districts of the state, previous to the meeting of the convention in November <add>last</add> . In the language of a distinguished American historian, the democracy Tennessee, <del type="overstrike">received the defeat</del> believed, and yet believe, that in the defeat of Mr. Van Buren in 1840, the democratic <pb n="2" facs="sl441b.small.jpg"/> principle was defied, insulted, and trampled upon; and that that principle demands to avenge itself_ not as an affair of human passion or personal ambition. It is a movement from the higher sphere of truth and right; and it is the law of the moral world, that truth and right cannot with impunity be outraged. The Democratic principle, having for a time been overwhelmed by arts and misrepresentations, has gathered energy to throw off the weight that bore it down; it will rise once more in its majesty, to be the guiding light of our nation and the hope of humanity." Actuated by these deep and abiding sentiments, the democracy of our state, entertaining at the same time the highest confidence in the other distinguished citizens brought forward for the office, and willing to support any one of them who may be nominated, we need not assure you, that <del type="overstrike">we we and our democratic <choice>
                     <orig>brethern</orig>
                     <reg>brethren</reg>
                  </choice> would be desired the  greater gratification from the nomination of Mr Van Buren through Mr Van Buren is our first choice and his nomination now</del>
            </p>
            <p>though Mr. Van Buren is the first choice of the greater numbers of our democracy, yet either of his distinguished competitors for the nomination, will, if selected as the candidate of the party, receive the undivided and ardent support of <del type="overstrike">our party</del> the democratic party in Tennessee.</p>
            <p>The undersigned beg leave, respectfully, to call your attention to the following resolution, <add>unanimously</add> passed by our convention, and incorporated in its <add>published</add> proceedings. The resolution regards the Vice Presidency, and the claims of our own distinguished fellow citizen, <choice>
                  <abbr>Gov.</abbr>
                  <expan>Governor</expan>
               </choice>
               <name>James K. Polk</name>. The resolution is as follows: <pb n="3" facs="sl441c.small.jpg"/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <p>By the selection and nomination of Gov. Polk, whose claims are amply discussed in the accompanying Address, we believe, in perfect sincerity, and from a <add>fair</add> view of the whole ground that more strength would be brought to the democratic ticket, than by the selection of any <add>other</add> candidate who has been named by our friends in any division of the union. His friends in Tennessee, feel confident, that with his name on the <add>democratic</add> ticket, our beloved state would be redeemed in the contest from her present federal position; and we feel free to declare, that his friends in Tennessee, in urging his promotion to the second office in the government, his claims to which have been so faithfully and dearly earned, have not the slightest wish, desire, or anticipation of in any manner forestalling, or in any manner interfering with, the prospective claims of distinguished <choice>
                  <orig>asperants</orig>
                  <reg>aspirants</reg>
               </choice> , and older men of our party, in any section of the union, in regard to their claims, prospects or rights in the Presidential election of 1848. We make this declaration fully impressed with <del type="overstrike">the amp</del> its import, and in the spirit of sincerity and condone which becomes ourselves and the occasion.</p>
            <p>We <add>in Tennessee</add> are the more earnest in pressing the claims of  Gov. Polk, because we believe, without his name on our ticket, that Tennessee may, and most probably will, continue to occupy her present unnatural and false political position. With <add>his</add>
               <del type="overstrike">Gov. Polks</del> name on our ticket, all our best talents will <del type="overstrike">deem</del>
               <add>take</add> the field, and the battle will be waged with a vigor and confidence of success which must result in certain victory. Without his name, we fear that a spirit of despondency of local success may, <del type="overstrike">paralize</del> in an unfavorable degree, paralize our <del type="overstrike">exertion</del> best exertions in the good cause. But <del>for the</del> whatever the result of the nominations may be <add>our friends may every where rest obscured that</add>
               <del type="overstrike">our best</del> our best exertions, and the faithful <add>(Leave this out, and make four fair copies of the balance)</add>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl441d.small.jpg"/> exertions of our <choice>
                  <orig>brethern</orig>
                  <reg>brethren</reg>
               </choice> in Tennessee, will be cheerfully accorded in <del type="overstrike">their</del>
               <add>its</add> support.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>We are, very respectfully,</salute>
               <signed>your fellow citizens</signed>
               <add>Copy of Address prepared for Central Committee at Nashville 1844</add>
               <add>mere memoranda: <lb/>
                  <name>Thos. Pritcher</name>, <choice>
                     <abbr>Esq.</abbr>
                     <expan>Esquire</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/> Ed. R. Eng. <lb/>
                  <name>Redmond</name>, <choice>
                     <abbr>Va</abbr>
                     <expan>Virginia</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>Hon.</abbr>
                     <expan>Honorable</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <name>Henry Horm</name>, <lb/>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Philad.</abbr>
                        <expan>Philadelphia</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Pa.</abbr>
                        <expan>Pennsylvania</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>E. Crosswell</name>, Eq. <lb/> Ed. Al. Ang. <lb/>
                  <name>Albany</name>, <choice>
                     <abbr>Ny.</abbr>
                     <expan>New York</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <lb/> Hon <name>
                     <add>Isaac</add> Toucey</name>, <lb/>
                  <name>Hartford</name>, <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Ct.</abbr>
                        <expan>Connecticut</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>
                  <lb/> His <choice>
                     <abbr>Excel</abbr>
                     <expan>Excellency</expan>
                  </choice>
                  <name>Henry Hubbord</name>, <lb/>
                  <name>Portsmouth</name>, <lb/>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>N. H.</abbr>
                        <expan>New Hampshire</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>
                  <lb/> Hon. <name>B. F. Hallett</name>, <lb/>
                  <name>Boston</name>, <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>Mass.</abbr>
                        <expan>Massachusetts</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>
                  <lb/> Hon <name>B. F. Butler</name>, <lb/>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>N.</abbr>
                        <expan>New</expan>
                     </choice> York</name>
                  <lb/> Hon <name>Danl. Sheffer</name>, <lb/>
                  <name>York Springs</name>, <lb/>
                  <name>Adams <choice>
                        <abbr>Co.</abbr>
                        <expan>County</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name> Pa.</add>
               <add>Hon. <name>Felix Bosworth</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>Carrollton</name>, <name>Carroll Par.</name>
                  <lb/>
                  <name>
                     <choice>
                        <abbr>La.</abbr>
                        <expan>Louisiana</expan>
                     </choice>
                  </name>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
