<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="sl149">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1819 Oct. 20, Edinburgh, [to]     G[eorge] W[ashington] Campbell, St. Petersburgh, Russia / Duncan Matheson : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Matheson, Duncan</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Danielle Hardin</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>sl149</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50563814</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and Archives, Nashville, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the Tennessee State Library and Archives, 403 Seventh Avenue North, Nashville, TN 37243-0312.  (615) 741-2764.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1819 Oct. 20, Edinburgh,     [to] G[eorge] W[ashington] Campbell, St. Petersburgh, Russia / Duncan Matheson</title>
               <author>Matheson, Duncan </author>
               <date when="1819-10-20">October 20, 1819</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated October 20, 1819, addressed to Tennessee politician George Washington Campbell in St. Petersburg, Russia during his tenure as US minister there, from his nephew Duncan Matheson.  Matheson writes about his brother James, who had travelled to the East Indies to become engaged in the mercantile business, and had ended up in Canton, China.  Duncan asks his uncle to appoint James to the office of Vice Consul in Canton.  </note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">George Washington Campbell Papers IV-F-4</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">n/a</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">21</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">sl149</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Tennessee -- Politics and government -- To 1865</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Matheson, Duncan</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="sl149a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Edinburgh</name>
                     <date when="1819-10-20">20th October 1819</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Uncle</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Having had the pleasure to correspond for some time past with my Uncle <name type="person">Colin Campbell</name> of <name type="place">North Carolina</name>, and having <choice>
                  <orig>learnt</orig>
                  <reg>learned</reg>
               </choice> from him a variety of interesting particulars concerning you I have long cherished the wish to attempt a more direct and personal intercourse with you; but have been checked by the reflection that you  might not think the attempt worthy of your countenance, and indeed that your high &amp; important official functions would preclude you in point of time from knowing me with any notice.  Understanding however from your brother  that my name &amp; situation are not unknown to you.  I have mustered resolution enough to trouble you on a piece of business which is shortly as follows.</p>
            <p>My Brother <name type="person">James</name> went out to a mercantile house in <name type="place">Calcutta</name>  in <date when="1815">1815</date>; and through their <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice> and his own deserts, he has  now, at the age of only 23, been lucky enough to get himself established with considerable patronage as a Chinese Agent at <name type="place">Canton</name>, where if he remains for some time, he has every prospect of  making a handsome fortune.  He writes me however that so far as <emph>British Subjects</emph> are  concerned, our English East <name type="place">India</name> Company have the <emph>monopoly</emph> of the <name type="place">China</name> Trade, so that any subject of this Country can only remain there by the <emph>indulgence</emph> of the East India Company's Superb <gap agent="damage"/> ous, and are liable to be removed at their pleasure. Now <choice>
                  <orig>tho</orig>
                  <reg>though</reg>
               </choice> this right is sel <gap agent="damage"/> and perhaps never very arbitrarily, it must be a most desirable ob <gap agent="damage"/> aid of so grievous a restraint upon h <gap agent="damage"/> liberty; and one <gap agent="damage"/> ed, and an individual made in <gap agent="damage"/> of the English Su <gap agent="damage"/> mself nominated, as is the case with <gap agent="damage"/>     either <emph>Consul</emph> or <emph>Vice C</emph>
               <gap agent="damage"/> for some foreign power; as every foreign power has the same right there with <gap agent="damage"/> English East India Company, whose monopoly  takes effect against their own Country men only.</p>
            <p>James has met with a <name type="person">Mr Wilcocks</name>at Canton who is Consul there for the <emph>
                  <name type="place">United States of America</name>
               </emph>, and from whom  he thought he had experienced considerable civility from his connection with you, with whom he understood Mr <add place="bottom right">Wilcocks</add>
               <pb n="2" facs="sl149b.small.jpg"/> Wilcocks to say, that he has heretofore    carried on some official correspondence. There is no <emph>Vice Consul</emph> however for the United States at Canton; and the object for which I have ventured to address you, is to see whether it would be possible to procure this nominal appointment and character for my Brother James.  There is no Salary I believe attached to the office: At least my Brother has no such thing in view; so that it would cost nothing whatever to the American Government, and if at all attainable would I should hope require no other sacrifice from you, but the trouble  of making an application.  If I can vouch for any thing I think I can assure you he will be no discredit to you; for he is universally allowed to be an uncommonly fine, steady, and well educated, young man — Should you be Kind enough therefore to take this trouble for him it would be conferring the greatest <choice>
                  <orig>favour</orig>
                  <reg>favor</reg>
               </choice>  on him; and be the result what it may, I shall have to facilitate myself in  making the request, if it shall procure for me the honor of any Answer or notice from so distinguished a relation.</p>
            <p>I cannot express to you how much I felt <choice>
                  <orig>tantalised</orig>
                  <reg>tantalized</reg>
               </choice> by the Accounts in our Newspapers of your stay at  <name type="place">Cowes</name> in the <name type="place">Isle of Wight</name>. Had I anticipated that the Hurricane had done any thing more than touch there, or that you would not have been off before I could possibly <gap agent="damage"/>
               <unclear>ha</unclear> ve arrived after the very first noticed, I should certainly have made it a poin <gap agent="damage"/> one to wait on you.  May I <gap agent="damage"/> ct that a similar opportunity will be afford <gap agent="damage"/>
               <name type="place">Great Britain</name>
               <emph>on your</emph>
               <gap agent="damage"/> In the course of the last wint <gap agent="damage"/> in with a Mr <gap agent="damage"/> from <name type="place">Virginia</name>, and who I beli <gap agent="damage"/> ne either in North  or <name type="place">South Carolina</name>, that stated himself to have <gap agent="damage"/> with you, and gratified us by speaking of you.  <unclear>Unbelievably</unclear> however it was <gap agent="damage"/> us departure from Edinburgh that I fell in with him, so that <choice>
                  <abbr>tho'</abbr>
                  <expan>though</expan>
               </choice> I waited on him to solicit his further acquaintance, I had only an opportunity of meeting him once.  The intercourse between the two Countries however is now so pleasant and liberal; and there is  <emph>in Edinburgh</emph> at least, such a resort of pleasant well informed American Gentlemen every winter, for the University as well as for travelling, that meeting with acquaintances or friends <add place="bottom, right">of</add>
               <pb n="3" facs="sl149c.small.jpg"/> of yours may hereafter be more frequent — I need not assure you how much the pleasure would be enhanced if you put it in my power to <emph>show attention</emph> to any friends of yours by an introduction — I am also <choice>
                  <orig>authorised</orig>
                  <reg>authorized</reg>
               </choice> to make a similar assurance on the part of my Brother if he can be of use to any of your friends that may have occasion to go to China.  But I must not obtrude on your time further than to request the favor of a reply when you find it convenient, and to subscribe myself, with great respect.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My dear Uncle</salute>
               <salute>Your <choice>
                     <abbr>afft</abbr>
                     <expan>affectionate</expan>
                  </choice> Nephew</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Duncan Matheson</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>His Excellency</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>The <name type="person">
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>Honble G. W.</abbr>
                           <expan>Honoroable George Washington</expan>
                        </choice> Campbell</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <pb n="4" facs="sl149d.small.jpg"/>
               <add>Is this in English??</add>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>His Excellency</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>The <choice>
                        <abbr>Honble G. W.</abbr>
                        <expan>Honorable George Washington</expan>
                     </choice> Campbell</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Ambassador from the United States of America</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">St. Petersburgh</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Russia</name>
                     <add place="below addres, to right">107</add>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left, on side">
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>
                        <gap agent="damage"/>
                        <unclear>Duncan</unclear> Matheson</addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <gap agent="damage"/>
                        <unclear>Edinbu</unclear> rgh <date when="1819-10-20">20 <choice>
                              <abbr>oct.</abbr>
                              <expan>October</expan>
                           </choice> 1819</date>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <gap agent="damage"/>
                        <unclear>Duncan</unclear>
                        <date when="1819-11">
                           <choice>
                              <abbr>Nov.</abbr>
                              <expan>November</expan>
                           </choice> 1819</date>
                     </addrLine>
                     <addrLine>
                        <date when="1819-11-27">27 <choice>
                              <abbr>Nov.</abbr>
                              <expan>November</expan>
                           </choice> 1819</date>
                     </addrLine>
                  </address> ― says his brother ⁁ <add place="supralinear">James</add> went to the East Indies in 1815 &amp; was in Canton &amp; knew Mr. Wilcocks</add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
