<TEI.2 id="tl005"> 
  
   <teiHeader> 
	 
      <fileDesc> 
		
         <titleStmt> 
		  
            <title>[Article of agreement], 1794 Oct. 12, Knoxville, [Tennessee] /
			 David E. Moore and William Blount, Governor of the State of Tennessee: a
			 machine-readable transcription of an image</title> 
		  
            <author>Moore, David E.</author> 
		  
            <author>Blount, William</author> 
		  
            <respStmt> 
			 
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 
               <name>Holly Chadwell</name> 
			 
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name> 
			 
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name> 
			 
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
		  
            </respStmt> 
		
         </titleStmt> 
		
         <extent>ca. k</extent> 
		
         <publicationStmt> 
		  
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher> 
		  
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace> 
		  
            <address> 
			 
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine> 
		  
            </address> 
		  
            <date>2001</date> 
		  
            <idno>tl005</idno> 
		  
            <idno>OCLC: 47798498</idno> 
		  
            <availability> 
			 
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, Tennessee. It may be used freely by individuals for
				research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability
				is included in the text.</p> 
		  
            </availability> 
		
         </publicationStmt> 
		
         <sourceDesc> 
		  
            <bibl> 
			 
               <title>[Article of agreement], 1794 Oct. 12, Knoxville, [Tennessee] /
				David E. Moore and William Blount, Governor of the State of Tennessee</title> 
			 
               <author>Moore, David E.</author> 
			 
               <author>Blount, William</author> 
			 
               <date value="1794-10-12">October 12, 1794 </date> 
			 
               <extent>4p</extent> 
			 
               <note type="summary"> This document is an article of agreement made
				between William Blount, Governor of territories south of the Ohio River and
				superintendent of Indian Affairs for the southern district, and David Moore of
				Knoxville, Tenn. Dated October 12, 1794, the article was written in reference
				to a large flat bottomed boat, travelling down the Tennessee River, that was
				carrying goods belonging to the Chickasaw and Choctaw. Moore agreed to take
				charge of the boat and administer its journey down the Tennessee River to the
				mouth of Bear Creek, as so directed by Chickasaw chief Opoia Mingo. Moore would
				also be responsible for protecting the boat against attacks by the Creek and
				Cherokee, as well as protecting Opoia Mingo and his tribe. Furthermore, the
				article outlined how Moore and his crew would be paid for their
				services.</note> 
			 
               <note type="Collection"> William Blount Papers </note> 
			 
               <note type="Box">1</note> 
			 
               <note type="Folder">5</note> 
			 
               <note type="Document">tl005</note>
            </bibl> 
		
         </sourceDesc> 
	 
      </fileDesc> 
	 
      <encodingDesc> 
		
         <projectDesc> 
		  
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		
         </projectDesc> 
		
         <editorialDecl> 
		  
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p> 
		  
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p> 
		  
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		
         </editorialDecl> 
		
         <refsDecl> 
		  
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p> 
		
         </refsDecl> 
		
         <classDecl> 
		  
            <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
			 
               <bibl> 
				
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl> 
		  
            </taxonomy> 
		
         </classDecl> 
	 
      </encodingDesc> 
	 
      <profileDesc> 
		
         <textClass> 
		  
            <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
			 
               <list> 
				
                  <item>Legal documents</item> 
				
                  <item>Chickasaw Indians--Government relations</item> 
				
                  <item>Choctaw Indians--Government relations</item> 
				
                  <item>Creek Indians--Claims against</item> 
				
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Claims against</item> 
				
                  <item>Tennessee</item> 
			 
               </list> 
		  
            </keywords> 
		
         </textClass> 
	 
      </profileDesc> 
  
   </teiHeader> 
  
   <text> 
	 
      <body> 
		
         <div1 type="article">
            <pb n="[1]"/> 
		  
               <p>Articles of agreement made and entered into between 
			 <name type="person">William Blount</name> Governor in and over the
			 territory of the 
			 <name type="place">United States of America</name> south of the river
			 
			 <name type="place">Ohio</name>, and superintendent of
			 <orig reg="Indian">indian</orig> affairs for the southern district on the part
			 of the 
			 <name type="place">United States</name> on the one part and 
			 <name type="person">David Moore</name> of 
			 <name type="place">Knoxville</name> on the other part, respecting the
			 working a large flat bottomed boat from this place down the 
			 <name type="place">
                     <orig reg="Tennessee">tennessee</orig>
                  </name> with
			 a quantity of goods belonging to the 
			 <name type="place">Chickasaw</name> and 
			 <name type="place">
                     <orig reg="Choctaw">Chactaw</orig>
                  </name> nations
			 of <orig reg="Indians">indians</orig> being the same goods that were given by
			 the 
			 <name type="place">United States</name> to the said nations and in 
			 <date value="0000-07-00">July</date> last delivered at 
			 <name type="place">
                     <orig reg="Philadelphia">philadelphia</orig>
                  </name> to 
			 <name type="person">Opoia Mingo</name> and others of his nation than
			 at 
			 <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> Witness, that the said 
			 <name type="person">David Moore</name> engages to hold himself in
			 readiness to take charge of the said boat now laying in the 
			 <name type="place">
                     <orig reg="Holston River">holston
				river</orig>
                  </name> near the camp of the said 
			 <name type="person">Opoia Mingo</name>about four hundred yards below
			 this place on <orig reg="Saturday">saturday</orig> the 
			 <date value="0000-00-18">18th</date> instant, by which time it is
			 supposed the whole of the said goods will have arrived at that place and be put
			 on board the said boat in the character of commander thereof and to provide six
			 good oarsmen by the aforesaid day to work the said boat down the 
			 <name type="place">
                     <orig reg="Tennessee">tennessee</orig>
                  </name> to
			 the mouth of 
			 <name type="place">Bear Creek</name>, or to such other place above as
			 
			 <name type="person">Opoia Mingo</name> shall <pb n="[2]"/> direct the
			 said goods to be landed, and he the said 
			 <name type="person">David Moore</name> further engages and agrees
			 with the said William Blount that in the character of commander of the said
			 flat bottomed boat he will use the utmost of his skill and abilities in
			 commanding conducting and defending her with her lading down the 
			 <name type="place">
                        <orig reg="Tennessee">tennessee</orig>
                     </name>
			 against all attacks that may be made upon the said boat by any hostile party or
			 parties of 
			 <name type="person">Creeks</name> or 
			 <name type="person">Cherokees</name> and that he will take special
			 care of 
			 <name type="person">Opoia Mingo</name> and his party of 
			 <name type="person">Chickasaws</name> who are to pass down the 
			 <name type="place">
                        <orig reg="Tennessee">tennessee</orig>
                     </name> in
			 the said boat with the goods as before described belonging to the 
			 <name type="person">Chickasaws</name> and 
			 <name type="person">
                        <orig reg="Choctaws">Chactaws</orig>
                     </name>_ and
			 the said 
			 <name type="person">William Blount</name> engages on the part of the 
			 <name type="place">United States</name> 
                     <unclear>that the said 
			 <name type="person">David Moore</name> shall be paid for his own
			 skill trouble and--this line is very faded</unclear> service in commanding and
			 conducting the said boat to the mouth of 
			 <name type="place">Bear Creek</name> or to such other place above as 
			 <name type="person">Opoia Mingo</name> shall order their goods to be
			 landed two hundred dollars and that each of the six oarsmen shall be paid one
			 dollar per day for their services counting from the time they appear at the
			 boat ready to go on board provided such appearance be not before the 
			 <date value="0000-00-18">18<hi>th</hi>
                     </date> instant to the day they
			 return to this place provided more than twenty <add place="supralinear">			 four</add> days shall not be allowed to return to this place from the place
			 where the goods shall be landed.  and it is further agreed that
			 provisions shall be put on board the said boat at this place at the cost of
			 <pb n="[3]"/> the 
			 <name type="person">United States</name> in such quantity as shall be
			 judged sufficient for the said 
			 <name type="person">David Moore</name> and the six oarsmen for the
			 voyage down the river and for their support on their return, but in case of
			 deficiency no allowance shall be claimed on their return for such deficiency.
			  <lb/> 
			 
                           <address> 
				
                              <addrLine> 
				  
                                 <name type="place">Knoxville</name> 
				  
                                 <date value="1794-10-12">October 12th 1794</date>
                              </addrLine> 
			 
                           </address>
                        
                     
                  
               </p> 
		  
               <closer> 
			 
                  <signed> 
				
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr> Blount</name>
				
                     <lb/> 
				
                        <name type="person">David E Moore</name>
                     
                  </signed>
                  <add place="bottom, left">Witness <lb/> 
			 
                        <name type="person">James King</name> 
                        <lb/> 
			 
                           <name type="person">Willie Blount</name>
                        
                     
                  </add>
               </closer> 
		
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </body> 
	 
      <back> 
		
         <div1>
            <pb n="[4]"/> 
		  
               <p> 
		  
                  <address> 
			 
                     <addrLine>Articles of agreement</addrLine> 
			 
                     <addrLine> 
				
                        <name type="person">Governor Blount</name>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                     <addrLine>with</addrLine> 
			 
                     <addrLine> 
				
                        <name type="person">David Moore</name>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                     <addrLine> 
				
                        <date value="1794-10-12">October 12th 94</date>
                     </addrLine> 
		  
                  </address>
               </p> 
		
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </back> 
  
   </text>
</TEI.2>
