<TEI.2 id="tl021"> 
  
   <teiHeader> 
	 
      <fileDesc> 
		
         <titleStmt> 
		  
            <title> [Letter] 1793 June 17, Withe County, [Tennessee to] General
			 Smith / William Blount, Governor of the state of Tennessee: a machine-readable
			 transcription of an image</title> 
		  
            <author>Blount, William</author> 
		  
            <respStmt> 
			 
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 
               <name>Holly Adams</name> 
			 
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name> 
			 
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name> 
			 
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
		  
            </respStmt> 
		
         </titleStmt> 
		
         <extent>ca. k</extent> 
		
         <publicationStmt> 
		  
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher> 
		  
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace> 
		  
            <address> 
			 
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine> 
		  
            </address> 
		  
            <date>2001</date> 
		  
            <idno>tl021</idno> 
		  
            <idno>OCLC: 47822409</idno> 
		  
            <availability> 
			 
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, Tennessee. It may be used freely by individuals for
				research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability
				is included in the text.</p> 
		  
            </availability> 
		
         </publicationStmt> 
		
         <sourceDesc> 
		  
            <bibl> 
			 
               <title> [Letter] 1793 June 17, Withe County, [Tennessee to] General
				Smith / William Blount, Governor of the State of Tennessee</title> 
			 
               <author>Blount, William</author> 
			 
               <date value="1793-06-17">June 17, 1793 </date> 
			 
               <extent>3p</extent> 
			 
               <note type="summary">This document is a letter from William Blount,
				Governor of the state of Tennessee from 1790 to 1795, to General Smith, dated
				June 17, 1793. In his letter, Blount stated that he had been informed that the
				President and Secretary of War were awaiting his arrival in order to discuss
				business regarding the Indians in the South. Blount and others were apparently
				unhappy with the Indians, and Blount suggested that a full-scale war was the
				only way to coerce them into acting in accordance with the US's wishes. Blount
				also discussed providing arms for the frontier settlers.</note> 
			 
               <note type="Collection"> Tennessee Historical Society</note> 
			 
               <note type="Box">2</note> 
			 
               <note type="Folder">n/a</note> 
			 
               <note type="Document">tl021</note>
            </bibl> 
		
         </sourceDesc> 
	 
      </fileDesc> 
	 
      <encodingDesc> 
		
         <projectDesc> 
		  
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		
         </projectDesc> 
		
         <editorialDecl> 
		  
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p> 
		  
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p> 
		  
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		
         </editorialDecl> 
		
         <refsDecl> 
		  
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p> 
		
         </refsDecl> 
		
         <classDecl> 
		  
            <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
			 
               <bibl> 
				
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl> 
		  
            </taxonomy> 
		
         </classDecl> 
	 
      </encodingDesc> 
	 
      <profileDesc> 
		
         <textClass> 
		  
            <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
			 
               <list> 
				
                  <item>Letters</item> 
				
                  <item>Indians of North America--Government relations</item> 
				
                  <item>Indians of North America--Warfare</item> 
				
                  <item>Southern States</item> 
			 
               </list> 
		  
            </keywords> 
		
         </textClass> 
	 
      </profileDesc> 
  
   </teiHeader> 
  
   <text> 
	 
      <body> 
		
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[1]"/> 
		  
               <opener> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <name type="place">Withe County</name> 
				  
                        <date value="1793-06-17">June 17th 1793</date>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                  </address> 
			 
                  <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
               </opener> 
		  
               <p>I have just <orig reg="received">receved</orig> a letter from 
			 <name type="person">Mr Allison</name> by 
			 <name type="person">Mr David Deadrick</name>dated the 
			 <date value="0000-05-15">15 th May</date> in which he informs me that
			 I am anxiously expected by the <orig reg="President">Presdent</orig> and the
			 Secretary of War and that he has every Reason to believe that on my arrival
			 something decisive will be determined on against the Southern Indians 
			 If anything depends on me my Easterns in <orig reg="favor">favour</orig> of the
			 Southwestern Frontiers will not be wanting  a vigorous
			 <hi rend="underlined">national</hi> war only can bring the Indians to act as
			 they ought, and that I hope we shall have this Fall.  Had you not best
			 postpone the finding my part of 
			 <name type="person">Kerr</name>'s Company to the Passing of 
			 <name type="place">Cumberland</name> until the Fine advertised for
			 the Guard to meet the families and then if Nothing is done with 
			 <name type="person">Kerr</name> let him as his Irishmen make a Part
			 of it.  I do not see how any of the arms <pb n="[2]"/> can be safely got
			 to 
			 <name type="place">Cumberland</name> .  I would advise the
			 letting the Frontier People of 
			 <name type="place">Washington District</name> have such as they want
			  A 
			 <name type="person">Mr. Freeman</name> a friend of 
			 <name type="person">Mr. Aukard</name> , a Clerk in the war office is
			 appointed <orig reg="quartermaster">quarter Master</orig> but he will not
			 shortly be out that is he will not leave 
			 <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> before my arrival.
               </p> 
		  
               <p>I shall pass the Mountain with 
			 <name type="person">Mrs Blount</name> who with her Party has there
			 bare arrived safe the day after tomorrow and the next day leave her and turn
			 <orig reg="off">of</orig> for 
			 <name type="place">Richmond</name> from whence I shall take the stage
			  I am and shall be truly anxious to hear from you pray
			 <orig reg="embrace">enbrace</orig> every opportunity to gratify me say to
			 relieve my anxiety  I will be back as soon as possible.  I
			 entreat you to advise, admonish and if possible govern 
			 <name type="person">Mr. <unclear>Opdrn</unclear>
                  </name> for his own
			 good with precise esteem,</p> 
		  
               <closer> 
			 
                  <salute>I am  
				<abbr expan="et cetera">c</abbr>  
				
                     <abbr expan="et cetera">c</abbr>
                  </salute> 
			 
                  <signed> 
				
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="William">Wm</abbr>
				  Blount</name>
                  </signed> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <name type="person">
                           <abbr expan="General">Gen.</abbr>
					 Smith</name>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                  </address>
               </closer> 
		
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </body> 
	 
      <back> 
		
         <div1 type="letter"> 
		  
            <p>
               <pb n="[3]"/> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <name type="person">General Smith</name>
                     </addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <name type="place">Knoxville</name>
                     </addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <name type="person">
                           <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr>
					 Bryan</name>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                  </address>
                  <add place="left, on side">Published in the  
			 <date value="1901-07-00">July 1901</date>
                     <lb/> American Historical
			 Magazine <lb/> 
			 
                           <abbr expan="Volume">Vol</abbr> 6, 
			 <abbr expan="Number">No</abbr> 3, page 224
                     
                  </add>
                  <add place="below"> 
			 
                     <date value="1793-06-17">June 17th, 1793</date>,  Going East
			 to see the Presi<lb/>dent of the 
			 <name type="place">
                           <abbr type="United States">U.S.</abbr>
                        </name>
			 
                     
                  </add>
               
            </p> 
		
         </div1> 
	 
      </back> 
  
   </text>
</TEI.2>
