<TEI.2 id="tl024"> 
  
   <teiHeader> 
	 
      <fileDesc> 
		
         <titleStmt> 
		  
            <title>[Letter] 1788 Aug. 3, Nashville, [to] Honorable Alexander
			 McGillivray / James Robertson. [Explanation of a letter] 1859, "Opposition of
			 McGillivray the Great Chief of the Creeks" / A.W. Putnam: a machine-readable
			 transcription of an image</title> 
		  
            <author>Robertson, James</author> 
		  
            <respStmt> 
			 
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 
               <name>Holly Adams</name> 
			 
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name> 
			 
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name> 
			 
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
		  
            </respStmt> 
		
         </titleStmt> 
		
         <extent>ca. k</extent> 
		
         <publicationStmt> 
		  
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher> 
		  
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace> 
		  
            <address> 
			 
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine> 
		  
            </address> 
		  
            <date>2001</date> 
		  
            <idno>tl024</idno> 
		  
            <idno>OCLC: 48060881</idno> 
		  
            <availability> 
			 
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, Tennessee. It may be used freely by individuals for
				research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability
				is included in the text.</p> 
		  
            </availability> 
		
         </publicationStmt> 
		
         <sourceDesc> 
		  
            <bibl> 
			 
               <title>[Letter] 1788 Aug. 3, Nashville, [to] Honorable Alexander
				McGillivray / James Robertson. [Explanation of a letter] 1859, "Opposition of
				McGillivray the Great Chief of the Creeks" / A.W. Putnam</title> 
			 
               <author>Robertson, James</author> 
                         
               <date value="1788-08-03">August 3, 1788</date>
                         
               <date value="1859-00-00">1859</date>
			 
               <extent>20 p</extent> 
			 
               <note type="summary">This document, entitled "Opposition of
				McGillivray the Great Chief of the Creeks" is comprised of two parts. The first
				is a letter written by Colonel James Robertson to Creek chief Alexander
				McGillivray on August 3, 1788. In that letter, Robertson discussed episodes of
				violence between the Creeks and/or Cherokees and American settlers and troops.
				Robertson also offered McGillivray a gun and some land in the Cumberland
				region. The second part of the document is a detailed explanation of
				Robertson's letter written by A.W. Putnam in 1859. Putnam provided an analysis
				of the historical context of the letter as well as his own opinions of the
				situations at hand at the time the letter was written. Putnam described the
				hostilities that existed between the Creeks and the American frontier settlers.
				He painted a portrait of the Creeks and the other tribes of the region as
				"treacherous and wily and cruel savages" who were working with foreign
				governments, particularly the Spanish, to undermine American aims. Putnam
				analyzed the connotation of Robertson's words to McGillivray, by stating that
				it was both threatening and complementing at the same time. Putnam also related
				details of the state of the American government at the time, particularly the
				shift from the initial loose confederacy of states to the current federalist
				form of government. He discussed how the initial instability, particularly in
				the South, of the newly formed United States, desires to settle West, and
				ongoing conflicts with the Spanish complicated relations with the Native
				American tribes, specifically the Creeks. Putnam also reported his analysis of
				McGillivray's character. McGillivray is presented as a cunning, influential man
				who was after his own interests and who was working with the Spanish to thwart
				American settlement. To Putnam, Robertson's letter presented McGillivray with a
				compromise--that his financial and political success would be guaranteed as
				long as he used his influence to encourage American aims in the frontier. As
				Putnam noted, two years after Robertson's 1788 letter, a treaty was concluded
				which established secure Indian land boundaries, ceded a large territory of
				land to the US, and gave McGillivray the rank of Brigadier General and a salary
				from the government. Thus, the US government was able to allay the Creek
				Nation. </note> 
			 
               <note type="Collection">Tennessee Historical Society</note> 
			 
               <note type="Box">10</note> 
			 
               <note type="Folder">n/a</note> 
			 
               <note type="Document">tl024</note>
            </bibl> 
		
         </sourceDesc> 
	 
      </fileDesc> 
	 
      <encodingDesc> 
		
         <projectDesc> 
		  
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		
         </projectDesc> 
		
         <editorialDecl> 
		  
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p> 
		  
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p> 
		  
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		
         </editorialDecl> 
		
         <refsDecl> 
		  
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p> 
		
         </refsDecl> 
		
         <classDecl> 
		  
            <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
			 
               <bibl> 
				
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl> 
		  
            </taxonomy> 
		
         </classDecl> 
	 
      </encodingDesc> 
	 
      <profileDesc> 
		
         <textClass> 
		  
            <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
			 
               <list> 
				
                  <item>Letters</item> 
				
                  <item>Creek Indians--Warfare</item> 
				
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Violence against</item> 
				
                  <item>McGillivray, Alexander</item> 
				
                  <item>Creek Indians--Government relations</item> 
				
                  <item>Creek Indians--Treaties</item> 
				
                  <item>Tennessee</item> 
			 
               </list> 
		  
            </keywords> 
		
         </textClass> 
	 
      </profileDesc> 
  
   </teiHeader> 
  
   <text> 
	 
      <body> 
		
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[1]"/> 
		  
               <opener>
                  <add place="top, left"> 
			 
                     <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> A.W.
				Putnam</name>
                  </add>
                  <add rend="top, middle"> 
			 
                     <name type="person">McGillivray</name> the great 
			 <name type="person">Creek</name> chief</add> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <name type="place">Nashville</name> 
				  
                        <date value="1788-08-03">August 3 1788</date>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                  </address> 
			 
                  <salute>Sir</salute>,</opener> 
		  
               <p>I received your <orig reg="favors">favours</orig> by 
			 <abbr expan="Misters">Messrs</abbr> 
			 
                  <name type="person">Hoggatt</name>  
			 
                  <name type="person">Ewing</name>, which have given great satisfaction
			 to the country in general. I transmitted copies to 
			 <name type="person">Governor Caswell</name> and have since seen them
			 published in the 
			 <name type="place">Kentucky</name> Gazette.</p> 
		  
               <p>The Indians still continue their incursions in some measure, 
			 <abbr expan="though">tho'</abbr> trifling to what we experienced in
			 the Spring. I imagine it must be 
			 <name type="person">Cherokees</name> or some outlying 
			 <name type="person">Creeks</name> who are not acquainted with your
			 orders.</p> 
		  
               <p> 
			 
                  <name type="person">
                     <abbr expan="Colonel"> Colo. </abbr> Anthony
				Bledsoe</name> was killed by a small party about two weeks ago.
			 <del type="erasure">B</del>
               </p> 
		  
               <p>It is reported that the Inhabitants of 
			 <name type="place">Holston</name> and the 
			 <name type="person">Cherokees</name> are at war; but we have not
			 received any account that may be depended on,  nor whether you and the 
			 <name type="person">Georgians</name> are likely to terminate your
			 disputes.</p> 
		  
               <p>From 
			 <name type="person"> Mr Hoggatt's</name> account we have expected
			 some of the 
			 <name type="person">Creeks</name> in from you; but none have yet
			 arrived. I have provided a gun which 
			 <name type="person"> Mr Hoggatt</name> thinks will please you. I have
			 caused a Deed for a Lot in 
			 <name type="place">Nashville</name> to be recorded in your name, and
			 beg you will let me know whether you will accept of a tract or two of Land in
			 our young country.</p> 
               <pb n="[2]"/> 
		  
                  <p>I could say much to you concerning this same country; but am fully
			 sensible you are better able to judge what <hi rend="underlined">may</hi> take
			 place in a few years, than myself.  In all probability we cannot long
			 remain in our present state and if the 
			 <name type="person">British</name> or any commercial nation who may
			 be in possession of the mouth of the 
			 <name type="place">
                        <orig reg="Mississippi"> mississippi</orig>
                     </name>
			 would furnish us with trade and receive our produce, there cannot be a doubt
			 but the people on the West side of the 
			 <name type="place">
                        <orig reg="Appalachian">Apalachian</orig>
				mountains</name> will open their eyes to their real interests.</p> 
		  
                  <p>I should be very happy to hear <del type="overstrike">from you</del>
		  your sentiments on this matter.</p> 
		  
                  <p>Myself and the Inhabitants of this country return you our most
			 <add place="supralinear">grateful</add> thank <del type="overstike">ful</del>
                     <add place="supralinear">s</add> for your very polite
		  treatment of 
		  <abbr expan="Misters">Messrs</abbr> 
		  
                     <name type="person">Hoggatt</name>  
		  
                     <name type="person">Ewing</name>, and shall always be happy to render
		  you any service in our power.</p> 
		  
                  <p>I hope you will honor me with a correspondence,  shall do
			 myself the pleasure of writing by every opportunity.</p> 
		  
                  <closer> 
			 
                     <salute>I am Sir, <lb/> with the greatest esteem <lb/> Your most 
				<abbr expan="obedient">obt</abbr>,
                        
                     </salute> 
			 
                     <signed> 
				
                        <name type="person">James Robertson</name>
                     </signed> 
			 
                     <address> 
				
                        <addrLine> 
				  
                           <name type="person">Honorable Alexander McGillivray
					 </name>
                        </addrLine> 
			 
                     </address>
                  </closer>
                  <pb n="[3]"/> 
		
                  
               
            
         </div1> 
		
         <div1 type="letter"> 
		  
            <p>
               <add place="top, right">2</add> The foregoing letter contains matter
			 of much variety and deep historical interest. It is bound in the first volume
			 of the letters and correspondence of 
			 <name type="person">
                  <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> James
				Robertson</name> : It is in the handwriting of that master-Clerk and amanuensis
			 
			 <name type="person">Andrew Ewing</name> ,  
			 <name type="person">
                  <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr>
				Robertson</name> being but a very indifferent scholar and pensman.</p> 
		  
            <p>The design to offer some remarks upon its various paragraphs and
			 facts:</p> 
		  
            <p>And first, we notice that it is in reply to communications; 
			 <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr> by the hands of two prominent
			 citizens of the 
			 <name type="place">Cumberland District</name>, 
			 <abbr expan="Misters">Messrs</abbr> 
			 
               <name type="person">Hoggatt</name> and 
			 <name type="person">Ewing</name>.</p> 
		  
            <p>These gentlemen had gone on an important mission to the 
			 <name type="place">Creek nation</name> early in the spring of this
			 year, and bore with them a joint letter from 
			 <name type="person">
                  <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Bledsoe</name>
			  
			 
               <name type="person">
                  <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Robertson</name>
			 to 
			 <name type="person">
                  <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr>
				McGillivray</name>, the distinguished 
			 <name type="person">Creek</name> Chief.</p> 
		  
            <p>The reasons and objects of this step were various. The Indians had
			 recently killed or taken away captive a number of persons from these
			 settlements, and among others had cruelly murdered 
			 <name type="person">Peyton</name> , the son of 
			 <name type="person">
                  <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr>
				Robertson</name>. In his letter to 
			 <name type="person">McGillivray</name> in regards to this affliction,
			 
			 <name type="person">
                  <abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> 
                  <pb n="[4]"/>				Robertson
               </name> gave vent to the grief of a bereaved father,  but
			 wisely refrained from threats of vengeance </p> 
		  
            <p>The spirit which would have sought revenge for such personal wrong,
			 was held in check by a high sense of duty and patriotic regard for the
			 well-being and safety of the community in which he occupied so prominent a
			 place.</p> 
		  
            <p>But it was important to learn the particular causes for these
			 outrages committed in violation of professions of peace  friendship And
			 when it was discovered that these murders and depredations were committed by
			 the 
			 <name type="person">Creeks</name> who lived at a great distance 
			 on the other side of the 
			 <name type="place">Tennessee river</name>  a nation claiming
			 none of the land on this side of that river, and with whose territories the
			 people of 
			 <name type="place">Cumberland</name> did not intermeddle, strong
			 suspicions arose in the minds of the whites that there must be
			 <add place="infralinear">some</add> deep and dangerous murder plot, 
			 some evil and foreign influence at work, to bring this mischief upon innocent
			 heads. </p> 
		  
            <p>The leading men here were not wholly ignorant of the intrigues and
			 policy of nations who had laid claim to this rich valley region, and were
			 jealous of each <pb n="[5]"/> other and alike <add place="supralinear">jealous</add> of the powers and consequences of 
			 <name type="person">American</name> government upon the rivers
			 leading into 
			 <name type="place">the Gulf</name>.
            </p> 
		  
            <p>The settlers on the 
			 <name type="place">Cumberland</name> and in 
			 <name type="place">Kentucky</name> , were placed in
			 <hi rend="underlined">great straits</hi> not only 'betwixt two', but many
			 perplexities; treacherous and wily and cruel savages on all sides, and the
			 insidious and crafty machinations of agents of foreign governments tampering
			 with these savages and with their fellow citizens. They conceived then of none
			 of <add place="supralinear">the</add> modern facilities of intercourse and
			 business across those mountains over which they had clambered with so much
			 difficulty  peril; and very wisely looked to the great natural canal and
			 its tributary waters <del type="overstrike">as their</del> to bear their
		  produce to any available and profitable market; and that whatsoever power had
		  its controlling  strong hand upon the great artery could and would control
		  the circulation of the young and growing commerce of these vast western
		  regions: Every act affecting the free and uninterrupted flow of these important
		  life-streams, startled the youthful but giant freemen upon their borders. And
		  if there was a momentary cessation or occasional irregularity in the pulsation
		  of the great 
		  <name type="person">American</name> heart, and consequent disordered
		  motions in the limbs  extremities,  so that the State of 
		  <name type="place">North Carolina</name> 
               <pb n="[6]"/> hesitated and
		  refused for a time to adopt the Constitution and become one of the glorious
		  Union:  though all saw  and acknowledges that the old Confederacy
		  was but a rickety and imbecile form of Government; and that something far
		  better framed  compacted was needed not only for common weal, but to
		  preserve the liberties and independence so laboriously and dearly obtained;
		   and in all these views,  even in the rejection of the new and
		  admirable form of government under which all the States have been so highly
		  prospered, and their number more than double, their population increased seven
		  fold and their commerce and business a thousand fold:  we say that
		  though the two delegates or representatives from the three counties of the 
		  <name type="place">Cumberland District</name> concurred in these
		  sentiments and in their own exclusion from the Union, 
		  <hi rend="underlined">it was not</hi> that they or any of them entertained
		  anti-republican opinions or were alienated from their republican brethren on
		  the Eastern side of the mountains. If they were to be detached from the great
		  family of free states, they looked to such popular government for themselves
		   their posterity, and that to a separate organization they would only
		  resort from <hi rend="underlined">dire necessity</hi>, and with the sincere
		  hope that a truce and way <pb n="[7]"/> 
                     <add place="top, right">4</add> would
		  ere long appear for a happy and more solid Union, and better guarantee for
		  mutual and general advantage.
               
            </p> 
		  
            <p>There was a variety of influences at work; 
			 <del type="overstrike">conflicting</del> feelings and interests so conflicting
		  as must ever move an intelligent and independent people. There were the strong
		  ties arising from birth, education, association,  all strengthened by a
		  participation in the recent struggle for general independence. . It was hard to
		  sever these: But it must be noticed that from neither the State or Confederated
		  Government had the inhabitants on this side of the mountains received aid or
		  protection;  what they had gained and accomplished, was through their
		  own toil and suffering. <del type="overstirke">And</del> They were separated at
		  that time from their friends and compatriots by mountain barriers little less
		  formidable, and rendering the connection little less distant and difficult,
		  than the broad 
		  <name type="place">
                  <orig reg="Atlantic">atlantic</orig>
               </name> spread
		  out between the States and the mother country from which <hi rend="underlined">they</hi> had recently obtained an acknowledgment of
		  independence</p> 
		  
            <p>The very character of late and prominent events, and the condition
			 of affairs and exigencies of the <pb n="[8]"/> times forced the question of
			 self-reliance and independence upon the people: But they were in no haste to
			 divide it,  they cherished no such desire: they loved their fellow
			 citizens of the States or 'settlements,' and the liberties they had gained, and
			 the institutions they had adopted, <orig reg="nonetheless">none the
			 less</orig>, because they were 'over the hills and far away,'  and they
			 were reluctant to take a part in diplomacy, craft and intrigue: But as others
			 sought to play the game with them, and for them, as a stake, in which they were
			 to be won or lost,  it became the part of wisdom  duty for the
			 party so deeply interested to use some policy <orig reg="likewise">like
			 wise</orig>. <add place="left margin"> 
			 
                     <date value="1783-05-06">6th May 1783</date>
			 
                     <unclear>Mallory</unclear>
                  </add>
               
            </p> 
		  
            <p>The language used by 
			 <name type="person">
                  <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr>
				Robertson</name> is complimentary to the intelligence and foresight of the
			 great King of the 
			 <name type="place">Creek nation</name>: "You are better able to judge
			 what may take place in a few years, than myself."</p> 
		  
            <p>Now this was 'dust <orig reg="skillfully">skilfully</orig> thrown'
			 <del type="overstrike">by 
		  <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> Robertson</del> in<del type="overstrike">to</del> the eyes of this wily chief <add place="supralinear">and his advisers</add>. 
		  <name type="person">
                  <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> Robertson</name>
		  knew that such a communication would be seen by other eyes and that the wishes
		  and the necessities of the people West of the 
		  <name type="place">Appalachian mountains</name> were for
		  <del type="overstrike">the</del> opening <add place="supralinear">the</add>
		  navigation of the 
		  <name type="place"> Mississippi</name>: As they were threatened and
		  tempted by officers and emissaries of foreign governments,  and were so
		  situated that of necessity <pb n="[9]"/> they had to consult, negotiate, decide
		  and act without the authority or sanction of an established government: for, as
		  to the supervision and case of the State of 
		  <name type="place">
                     <abbr expan="North">N.</abbr> Carolina</name> so far
		  as they had knowledge of either, they were unreliable or vexatious,  and
		  so continued "to the end of the chapter"  when the State of 
		  <name type="place">Tennessee</name> became one of the
		  <hi rend="underlined">Union</hi>. The good 'old North State' had a multitude of
		  cares and toils at home or within her old  organized settlements, 
		  and could not extend her strong arm across the mountains to defend these
		  'children in the woods,'  but rather left <orig reg="through">threw</orig> to the perils to which they had exposed themselves
		   "to perils in the wilderness, to perils in robbers,' to perils of
		  foreigners  'to perils of their own <orig reg="countrymen">country
		  men</orig>."
            </p> 
		  
            <p>We should bear in mind that virtually there was at this period
			 <hi rend="underlined">no American Confederacy</hi>, <hi rend="underlined">no
			 American Union</hi>,  but, what this very Indian Chief called "an
			 <hi rend="underlined">Interregnum</hi>." The old Confederacy was dissolving and
			 without power, and the present form of 
			 <name type="place">United States</name> government was adopted by but
			 eleven States: That 
			 <name type="place">North Carolina</name> had refused to adopt the
			 Constitution:</p> 
		  
            <p>
               <hi rend="underlined">She was then not in the Union</hi>, 
			 and the State of 
			 <name type="place">Franklin</name> in 
			 <name type="place">East Tennessee</name>, and the Government of the
			 Judges of the 
			 <name type="place">Cumberland</name> were ordained in great measure,
			 from necessity, and designed to secure  promote the rights and interests
			 of the people.</p> 
		  
            <p>On the 
			 <date value="0000-09-17">17th 
				<abbr expan="September">Sep.</abbr>
               </date>
               <add place="left margin">			 
			 
                  <date value="1788-00-00">1788</date>
               </add> our present form of 
			 <name type="place">
                  <abbr expan="United States">U.S.</abbr>
               </name>
			 Government was agreed upon in Convention,  <pb n="[10]"/> but
			 <del type="overstrike">not</del> 
                  <add place="supralinear">only</add> made known
			 and submitted to the States for ratification by Resolution of 
			 <date value="0000-00-28">28th</date> :  And on that same 
			 <date value="0000-09-07">17th 
				<abbr expan="September">Sep.</abbr>
                  </date> the Fourth Constitution
			 at 
			 <name>Danville 
				<abbr expan="Kentucky">Ky.</abbr>
                  </name> had resolved unanimously
			 in favor of separation from 
			 <name type="place">Virginia</name>, and again to ask admission into
			 the Union: And yet there were so many obstacles thrown in the way of her
			 attainment of this distinction, that the question was seriously discussed
			 whether it would not be for the interest of her people to unite with others
			 upon the western waters in the formation of a separate government.
            </p> 
		  
            <p>The conduct of some of the Eastern States served greatly to urge
			 this question upon these people. There, measures were proposed to discourage
			 emigration to the West. Even such a Statesman as 
			 <name type="person">
                  <orig reg="Governor">Governeur</orig>
				Morris</name> expressed decided opposition to <orig reg="sewing">sowing</orig>
			 seed from home on the broad lands west of the mountains, which would, in time,
			 grow into such a population as to control the parent States: and one scheme or
			 proposal was so to fix and settle the ratio of representation in Congress that
			 the old States could, in all coming time, enjoy the political
			 <orig reg="ascendancy">ascendency</orig>.</p> 
		  
            <p>Therefore we find a willingness to yield for a series of years, or
			 to sacrifice entirely, (as Some construed the sentiment,)  the
			 navigation of the 
			 <name type="place"> Mississippi</name>  and especially if
			 thereby the commercial interests of the Eastern or sea-board States, could be
			 promoted. (A)</p> 
		  
            <p>If we consider all the elements then in commotion, all the intrigues
			 on foot, all the influences at work, all the threats  fears, all the
			 interests at stake, all the difficulties <pb n="[11]"/> 
                  <add place="top, right">8</add> 
                  <add place="top, left">(difficulties)</add>
			 oppressing; all the embarrassments and dangers seemingly accumulating, 
			 how many and how varied were all these, and with what artifice and ingenuity
			 they were urged upon the <del type="overstrike">se</del> Western people,
			  we can only be surprised that the 
			 <name type="place">Alleghanies</name> were not made the
			 <del type="overstrike">permanent</del> 
                  <add place="supralinear">Western</add>
			 limit to the old confederated States,  at least for a time
            </p> 
		  
            <p>Consider for a moment a few passages in the Speech or Report
			 <add place="supralinear">of 
			 <name type="person">Mr Monroe</name>
               </add> to the 
			 <name type="place">Virginia</name> Convention which ratified the
			 Federal Constitution; <del type="overstrike">made</del>
            </p> 
		  
            <p>"There was a time  when even 
			 <name type="place">Virginia</name> in some measure abandoned the 
			 <name type="place"> Mississippi</name> by <orig reg="authorizing">authorising</orig> its cession to the Court of 
			 <name type="place">Spain</name>. The southern States were overrun
			  in possession of the enemy. The government of 
			 <name type="place">
                  <abbr expan="South">S.</abbr> Carolina</name> and 
			 <name type="place">Georgia</name> prostrate, and opposition there at
			 an end. 
			 <name type="place">
                  <abbr expan="North">N.</abbr> Carolina</name> made
			 but a feeble resistance; and 
			 <name type="place">Virginia</name> herself was greatly
			 <orig reg="harassed">harrassed</orig> by the enemy in force at that time in the
			 heart of the country, and by impressments for her own and the
			 <orig reg="defense">defence</orig> of the Southern States. In addition to this,
			 the finances were in a deplorable condition, if not totally exhausted; and 
			 <name type="place">France</name> , our ally seemed anxious for peace;
			 and as the means of bringing the war to a more happy and speedy conclusion, the
			 object of their cession was the hopes of uniting 
			 <name type="place">Spain</name> in it with all her forces:"</p> 
		  
            <p>Fortunately for us  
			 <name type="place">Spain</name> was too <orig reg="intriguing">intrigueing</orig>, too avaricious, too <hi rend="underlined">diplomatic</hi>: She desired more than the control of the
			 mouth of the 
			 <name type="place"> Mississippi</name>,  and truly, so did
			 these 
			 <name type="person">American</name> settlers; and wakeful and crafty
			 as were the <lb/> 
			 
                  <name type="person">Spaniards</name>, <pb n="[12]"/>			 
                     <add place="top, right">9</add> 
			 
                     <name type="person">Spaniards</name>,  the 
			 <name type="person">
                        <orig reg="Americans">americans</orig>
                     </name>
			 neither 'slumbered nor slept,'  until they were in full and undisputed
			 possession, not only of the river in its entire length, with all its
			 tributaries and all the invaluable lands through which they flow. 'This
			 boundless continent is ours."
               
            </p> 
		  
            <p> 
			 
               <name type="person">Mr Monroe</name> further says, "The Northern
			 States were inclined to yield the navigation; that it was their interest to
			 prevent an augmentation of the Southern influence and power;  and they
			 would relinquish that river in order to <hi rend="underlined">depress</hi> the
			 Western country, and prevent the Southern interest from preponderating." </p> 
		  
            <p>Such a sentiment was quite prevalent in the 
			 <name type="place">New England</name>States. The immense territory
			 <hi rend="underlined">northwest</hi> of the 
			 <name type="place">
                  <orig reg="Ohio River">ohio river</orig>
               </name>,
			 had been <hi rend="underlined">Southern property</hi>, yielded up for new
			 States, and the prevailing idea was, that the intercourse and interests of its
			 future inhabitants would be chiefly with the Southern people  going with
			 their business down these great natural highways to the 
			 <name type="place">Gulf</name> and the 
			 <name type="place">Atlantic</name>.</p> 
		  
            <p>No one at that day foresaw the construction of <orig reg="Railroads">Rail Roads</orig>  which now afford facilities of travel
			 and business over and through the mountains to all the Eastern 
			 <name type="place">Atlantic</name> shore, surpassing the many rivers
			 flowing to the Southern 
			 <name type="place">Atlantic</name> coasts. By these there is created
			 and sustained a sympathy  a prejudice, and interest tending more to the
			 East <add place="supralinear">#</add> than to the South:<add place="supralinear">#</add> from whence also most of the settlers came:</p> 
		  
            <p>And we object not to such preferences, only desiring to extend,
			 multiply, invigorate and cultivate there, by the construction of like lines
			 <lb/> of <pb n="[13]"/> 
                     <add place="top, right">10</add> lines for intercourse
			 and business, connecting with all the South, with all the West, with all the
			 East,  and that business  travel may forever <hi rend="underlined">brighten</hi> these <del type="erasure">ban</del> 
                     <lb/> 'Bands
			 of iron and hooks of steel.' <lb/> 
			 
                           <name type="person">
                              <abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr>
				Robertson</name> resorts to very customary means of gaining favor in his
			 negotiations with this powerful chieftain and crafty politician:
                     
                  
               
            </p> 
		  
            <p>"I have provided a <hi rend="underlined">gun</hi>, which 
			 <name type="person">Mr. Hoggatt</name> thinks will please you":</p> 
		  
            <p>This was not, in every respect, an empty compliment; a good rifle,
			 at that day, was an article of value and highly prized by chiefs and
			 followers.</p> 
		  
            <p>" I have also caused a <hi rend="underlined">Deed</hi> for a
			 <hi rend="underlined">Lot</hi> in 
			 <name type="place">Nashville</name> to be recorded in your name,
			  and beg you will let me know whether you will accept of a tract or two
			 of land in our young country!"</p> 
		  
            <p>This great Indian chief <del type="overstrike">was</del> had
		  commingled in his veins, the blood of the 
		  <name type="person">
                  <orig reg="Scotsman">Scotchman</orig>
               </name>, the 
		  <name type="person">Frenchman</name> and the 
		  <name type="person">Spaniard</name> with the noble blood of the 
		  <name type="person">'Wind family'</name> or 'Wild-Wind'  the
		  aristocratic family of the 
		  <name type="place">Creek Nation</name>: the spirit of the Indian and 
		  <name type="person">Spaniard</name> seemed to predominate.</p> 
		  
            <p>With all his haughty pride, he could be conciliated: he could be won
			 by kindness and by <unclear>doncears</unclear>. Rich and powerful as he was or
			 was supposed to be, 
			 <name type="person">
                  <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> Robertson</name>
			 thought that he would not be insulted by offering him an interest here.</p>
		  
            <pb n="[14]"/> 
		  
               <p>
                  <add place="top, right">11</add> To our mind 
			 <name type="person">
                     <abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr>
				Robertson</name> seems to say;  "Mr Indian, this is a new settlement,
			  now a mere 'Lodge in the Wilderness,'  "a young country," but we
			 are a great people; <del type="overstrike">and</del> we intend to make this a
		  great town,  and highly to improve the lands around; 
		  <del type="overstrike">and</del> We will give you a lot and a tract or two of
		  land here, if you will command your rascally hunters to remain at home and not
		  cross 
		  <name type="place">The Tennessee</name> to steal our cattle, to kill
		  our people, to disturb us in our possessions and operations;'  and we
		  doubt not if this Indian chieftain had ever seen proper to visit 
		  <name type="place">Nashville</name> in the life-time of 
		  <name type="person">
                     <abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> Robertson</name>,
		  a lot could have been pointed out as the one deeded to him,  and so, had
		  he expressed a desire for "a tract or two of land in this young country," he
		  would have been complimented by such presents.</p> 
		  
               <p>There was perhaps a <orig reg="coert">cooert</orig> meaning, a
			 significant intimation in this proposition It was like saying  'We know
			 your opposition to our settlements on the 
			 <name type="place">Cumberland</name> ; We know your intimacy with the
			 
			 <name type="person">Spaniards</name> who wish to draw
			 <add place="supralinear">or drive</add> us away,  offering lands upon 
			 <name type="place">the Mississippi</name> free of cost, exempt from
			 taxation, and the navigation of the river without obstruction: We know you keep
			 the 
			 <name type="person">Creeks</name>, the 
			 <name type="person">Cherokees</name> and other savages at enmity with
			 us here and on the 
			 <name type="place">Holston</name>: But now, Mr Indian,  Be it
			 known unto you and to all our enemies, that we are here in possession, the
			 <hi rend="underlined">owners</hi> of town lots and <pb n="[15]"/>			 
                     <add place="top, right">12</add> 
                     <add place="top, left">and</add> all of these
			 broad lands,  and we can give you a <hi rend="underlined">Deed</hi>
			  the only sure title, <del type="overstrike">to</del> a fee simple here.
			 We would be pleased to be at peace with all the tribes; you can exert much
			 influence upon their predatory and warlike spirit, and if it may be any
			 inducement, you can say so, and what we have offered, shall be given: We know
			 how readily your friends, the 
			 <name type="person">Spaniards</name>, conclude their professions of
			 friendship with the compliment,  "may you live a thousand years!"
			  Will you have a lot in our town a tract of two of land in our young
			 country?" 
               </p> 
		  
               <p>These compliments did not cost much and the lands were then very
			 cheap.</p> 
		  
               <p>We do not find any such titles to this 'Big Indian' for property
			 here; nor can we assert that the offers had any certain influence to pacify
			 this warrior or others,  other measures were soon adopted,  other
			 and larger grants were soon to be made to him and his sub-chiefs, which should
			 withdraw them from the influence of the 
			 <name type="person">English</name> , the 
			 <name type="person">French</name> and the 
			 <name type="person">Spanish</name>regents, and establish peace.</p> 
		  
               <p>These measures and compensations  their results may be
			 discovered in the brief sketch of the life and character
			 <add place="supralinear">of this King of the <hi rend="underlined"> 
			 
                        <name type="place">Creek Nation</name>
                     </hi>
                  </add> with which we shall
			 conclude this article.</p> 
		  
               <p> 
			 
                  <name type="person">Alexander McGillivray</name> was indeed a man of
			 superior mind, of good education, of commanding influence, of unquestioned
			 bravery  of peculiar tact in diplomacy.</p> 
               <pb n="[16]"/> 
		  
                  <p>His father or grandfather was a 
			 <name type="person">Scotchman</name>, his mother a 
			 <name type="person">Creek</name> of the 
			 <name type="person">Wind Tribe</name> ,  but there were marked
			 traces of the 
			 <name type="person">Castilian</name> and of the 
			 <name type="person">Gaul</name>,  so that he was
			 <del type="overstrike">some</del> 
                     <add place="supralinear">at</add> times
		  called a 
		  <name type="person">Spaniard</name>, a 
		  <name type="person">Frenchman</name>, an 
		  <name type="person">Englishman</name>,  and yet always an Indian
		  of the half blood.</p> 
		  
                  <p>He was educated in 
			 <name type="place">Charleston</name>, and at an early age assumed the
			 position at Indian councils to which his talents, his appearance and his
			 influential <del type="overstrike">tribe</del> 
                     <add place="supralinear">family</add> entitled him; and throughout the War for 
		  <name type="person">American</name> Independence he was devoted to the
		  measures of 
		  <name type="place">England</name>.</p> 
		  
                  <p>At the close of that war, he entered into close alliance with the 
			 <name type="person">Spanish</name> authorities of 
			 <name type="place">Florida</name> and 
			 <name type="place">Louisiana</name> : In that treaty he represented
			 the 
			 <name type="person">Creeks</name> and 
			 <name type="person">Seminoles</name>,  engaged to use all his
			 influence and artifice with the 
			 <name type="person">Chickasaws</name>, 
			 <name type="person">Cherokees</name> and 
			 <name type="person">Choctaws</name> against the people of the 
			 <name type="place">United States</name>: This alliance was formed in 
			 <date value="1784-00-00">1784</date>, and he assigned as his excuse
			 or justification, that the 
			 <name type="person">Whigs</name> of the Revolution had confiscated
			 his estates and committed many offensive acts against his family connections;
			 and in compliance with his engagements he exerted himself, and most
			 successfully too, to keep the Indians in an unfriendly state of excitement and
			 enmity against the 
			 <name type="person">Americans</name> .</p> 
		  
                  <p>The settlers upon the 
			 <name type="place">Cumberland</name> had no knowledge of any such
			 engagements between him and the 
			 <name type="person">Spaniards</name>,  perhaps could not have
			 credited the statement, had it been made: for at this time they were receiving
			 many professions of friendship, many profess <pb n="[17]"/>			 
                        <add place="top, right">14</add> 
                        <add place="top, left">g</add> liberality from
			 the 
			 <name type="person">Spanish</name> authorities
                  </p> 
		  
                  <p>But in letters and documents which have since come to light, we
			 discover that this powerful chief was intent upon promoting the
			 <del type="overstrike">wishes</del> 
                     <add place="supralinear">aims</add> of the 
		  <name type="person">Spanish</name> government,  to break up the
		  settlements on the 
		  <name type="place">Cumberland</name> or to induce the people to seek
		  the protection of the 
		  <name type="person">Spaniards</name> rather than longer to rely upon
		  any support or benefits from States of government East of the mountains.</p> 
		  
                  <p>In a letter which he addressed to 
			 <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> Pickens</name>
			 in 
			 <date value="1785-09-00">
                        <abbr expan="September">Septr.</abbr>
				1785</date>, he makes a remark about the "settlements on the 
			 <name type="place">Cumberland</name>,  that, people there would
			 do well to show a regard to the rights of others, and avoid further
			 aggressions'</p> 
		  
                  <p>The <orig reg="acknowledgment">acknowledgement</orig> has been made
			 by 
			 <name type="person">American</name> Historians that 
			 <name type="person">McGillivray</name> was always artful and skillful
			 enough to defeat our State and national governments in negotiations with the
			 Indians,  until he attained his private ends,  full indemnity for
			 his <orig reg="alleged">alledged</orig> losses.</p> 
		  
                  <p>In further proof of his spirit, we quote the following remark from a
			 long letter written by him in 
			 <date value="1788-09-00">
                        <abbr expan="Septermber">Septr.</abbr>
				1788</date>, to <hi rend="underlined"> 
			 
                        <name type="person">Panton</name>
                     </hi>, a 
			 <name type="person">Spanish</name> merchant whom he had made a man of
			 immense wealth by <orig reg="privileged">priviliged</orig> dealings among the
			 Indians: It will be noticed that this letter is only a month later in date than
			 the one written to 
			 <name type="person">McGillivray</name>, at <sic corr="the">the
			 the</sic> beginning of our communication:</p> 
		  
                  <p>Speaking of proposed treaties for peace and <lb/> boundaries
			 <pb n="[18]"/> boundaries, he says, "Experience has proved that such matters are
			 only to be attained by the <hi rend="underlined">longest fire</hi> and
			 <hi rend="underlined">point of sword</hi>,  particularly with 
			 <name type="person">Americans</name>." And in this same letter he
			 speaks boastingly of "an attack made by "a party of 
			 <name type="person">Cherokees</name> on a body of the
			 <hi rend="underlined"> 
			 
                              <name type="place">Franklin</name>
                           </hi> troops,'  in which he
			 rejoices that the latter were completely routed,  and that this being
			 "The first check they ever got in that country, the drooping spirits of the 
			 <name type="person">Cherokees</name> were thereby revived."
                     
                  </p> 
		  
                  <p>This, no doubt, is alluded to in that paragraph of 
			 <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr>
				Robertson's</name> letter where he says, "It is reported that the inhabitants
			 of 
			 <name type="place">Holston</name> and the 
			 <name type="person">Cherokees</name> are at war."</p> 
		  
                  <p>In another letter to 
			 <name type="person">Panton</name> 
			 
                     <date value="1789-08-00">
                        <abbr expan="August">Augt.</abbr>
				1789</date>,  he says, "I have in a letter to 
			 <name type="person">
                        <abbr expan="Governor">Gov.</abbr> Mero</name>,
			 approved his policy of settling 
			 <name type="person">Americans</name> on the west side of the 
			 <name type="place"> Mississippi</name>  and I truly wish it
			 was in compass of our power to <hi rend="underlined">drive them all from the 
			 <name type="place">Cumberland</name> 
                     </hi>and 
			 <name type="place">Ohio</name> , to seek the <hi rend="underlined">new asylum</hi>  out of our way!"</p> 
		  
                  <p>These words tell the secret of the many depredations of the 
			 <name type="person">Creeks</name> upon the white settlements on the 
			 <name type="place">Cumberland</name> : The 
			 <name type="person">Creeks</name> had no settlements and claimed no
			 territory upon that river or between the 
			 <name type="place">Cumberland</name> and the 
			 <name type="place"> Tennessee</name>, so that it could not be truly
			 alledged that these settlements encroached upon the land of that Nation </p> 
		  
                  <p>At this date Commissioners were appointed by the 
			 <name type="place">
                        <abbr expan="United States">U.S.</abbr>
                     </name> 
			 
                     <abbr expan="Government">Govt.</abbr> to negotiate with 
			 <name type="person">McGillivray</name> , and they proposed to pay him
			 for his confiscated property about $100,000. This pleased him. <pb n="[19]"/>			 
                        <add place="top, right">16</add> And he was induced to promise to make a visit
			 to 
			 <name type="place">New York</name> and 
			 <name type="place">Philadelphia</name> to see 
			 <name type="person">President Washington</name>
                     
                  </p> 
		  
                  <p>In compliance with this promise, he did, in 
			 <date value="1790-08-00">
                        <abbr expan="August">Augt.</abbr>
				1790</date>, visit the President, and a Treaty was concluded;  a treaty
			 of peace, for the protection of the Indians, establishing boundaries, 
			 and making a cession of large territory: an amunity of $1,500 per annum was
			 granted to the 
			 <name type="place">Creek nation</name>.</p> 
		  
                  <p> 
			 
                     <name type="person">McGillivray</name> was tickled also with a
			 feather in his cap; he received the <hi rend="underlined">Rank of Brigadier
			 General</hi> and the yearly pay of $1,200.</p> 
		  
                  <p>Thus this Indian Chief became one of the 
			 <name type="person">American</name> Generals, <del type="overstrike">(and the friend of the United States<add cert="appears to be different ink">?</add>, and these wars were at an end for
		  many years)</del>  and the intrigues of the 
		  <name type="person">English</name>, the 
		  <name type="person">French</name> and 
		  <name type="person">Spanish</name> were spoiled.</p> 
		  
                  <p>The young 
			 <name type="person">American</name> Eagle was perched upon the
			 mountain heights, his Keen eye surveyed this great continent, his broad, strong
			 and growing wings spread out from the 
			 <name type="place">Atlantic</name> to the 
			 <name type="place">Pacific</name> Oceans; he is "monarch of all the
			 surveys;" 'This vast continent is ours;' </p> 
		  
                  <p>'May his shadow never be less.' 'May his eye never see any more wars
			 within our borders, never any reduction of our limits, never any separation or
			 alienation of one portion from another:</p> 
		  
                  <p>May we indeed 'live a thousand years' a United, happy, prosperous
			 people,  "whose God is the Lord!" </p> 
		  
                  <closer> 
			 
                     <signed> 
				
                        <name type="person">A.W.<abbr expan="Putnam">P.</abbr>
                        </name>
				 
				
                        <date value="1859-00-00">1859</date>
                     </signed>
                  </closer> 
		
               
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </body> 
	 
      <back> 
		
         <div1 type="letter"> 
		  
            <p>Opposition of 
			 <name type="person">McGillivray</name> , <lb/> the great Chief of the 
			 <name type="person">Creeks</name> , <lb/> to the settlements on the 
			 <name type="place">Cumberland</name> , <lb/> his character,  
			 <name type="person">
                           <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr>
				Robertson's</name> 
                        <lb/> correspondence with him.<add place="bottom"> 
			 
                              <name type="person">
                                 <abbr expan="Secretary">Sec.</abbr>
				Haywood</name> 
			 
                              <abbr expan="pages">pp.</abbr> 338-39 </add>
                        
                     
                  
               
            </p> 
		
         </div1> 
	 
      </back> 
  
   </text>
</TEI.2>
