<TEI.2 id="tl038"> 
  
   <teiHeader> 
	 
      <fileDesc> 
		
         <titleStmt> 
		  
            <title>[Order] 1797 Mar. 19, State of Tennessee, [to] the sherriff
			 [sic] of Hawkins County / John Sevier: a machine-readable transcription of an
			 image</title> 
		  
            <author>Sevier, John</author> 
		  
            <respStmt> 
			 
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 
               <name>Holly Adams</name> 
			 
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name> 
			 
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name> 
			 
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
		  
            </respStmt> 
		
         </titleStmt> 
		
         <extent>ca. k</extent> 
		
         <publicationStmt> 
		  
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher> 
		  
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace> 
		  
            <address> 
			 
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine> 
		  
            </address> 
		  
            <date>2001</date> 
		  
            <idno>tl038</idno> 
		  
            <idno>OCLC: 47828218</idno> 
		  
            <availability> 
			 
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, Tennessee. It may be used freely by individuals for
				research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability
				is included in the text.</p> 
		  
            </availability> 
		
         </publicationStmt> 
		
         <sourceDesc> 
		  
            <bibl> 
			 
               <title>[Order] 1797 Mar. 19, State of Tennessee, [to] the sherriff
				[sic] of Hawkins County / John Sevier</title> 
			 
               <author>Sevier, John</author> 
			 
               <date value="1797-03-19">March 19, 1797 </date> 
			 
               <extent>4p</extent> 
			 
               <note type="summary">This document is an order issued by John Sevier,
				Governor of Tennessee from 1796-1801, to the sheriff of Hawkins County. Sevier
				stated that he had been informed by the governor of Kentucky of the murders of
				two Cherokees committed by Edward Mitchell and John Levingston, both citizens
				of the state of Tennessee and inhabitants of Hawkins County. In compliance with
				the demand of Governor Garrard of Kentucky, Sevier commanded the sheriff to
				apprehend Mitchell and/or Levingston and have them taken to the public jail of
				Kentucky. He also ordered that all civil and military officers aid the sheriff
				in the capture and transport of Mitchell and Levingston. This document was
				signed and sealed on March 19th, 1797. </note> 
			 
               <note type="Collection"> Governor John Sevier Papers</note> 
			 
               <note type="Box">1</note> 
			 
               <note type="Folder">3</note> 
			 
               <note type="Document">tl038</note>
            </bibl> 
		
         </sourceDesc> 
	 
      </fileDesc> 
	 
      <encodingDesc> 
		
         <projectDesc> 
		  
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		
         </projectDesc> 
		
         <editorialDecl> 
		  
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p> 
		  
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p> 
		  
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		
         </editorialDecl> 
		
         <refsDecl> 
		  
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p> 
		
         </refsDecl> 
		
         <classDecl> 
		  
            <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
			 
               <bibl> 
				
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl> 
		  
            </taxonomy> 
		
         </classDecl> 
	 
      </encodingDesc> 
	 
      <profileDesc> 
		
         <textClass> 
		  
            <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
			 
               <list> 
				
                  <item>Executive orders</item> 
				
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Government relations</item> 
				
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Violence against</item> 
				
                  <item>Hawkins County (Tenn.)</item> 
				
                  <item>Kentucky</item> 
			 
               </list> 
		  
            </keywords> 
		
         </textClass> 
	 
      </profileDesc> 
  
   </teiHeader> 
  
   <text> 
	 
      <body> 
		
         <div1 type="order">
            <pb n="[1]"/> 
		  
               <opener> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine>State of 
				  <name type="place">Tennessee</name>
                     </addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine>To the <orig reg="Sheriff">Sherriff</orig> of 
				  <name type="place">Hawkins County</name>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                  </address> 
			 
                  <salute>Sir</salute>
               </opener> 
		  
               <p>I am just <add place="supralinear">now</add> informed by an express
			 from the Governor of the state of 
			 <name type="place">Kentucky</name> , that a Most Cruel daring and
			 unprovoked murder was perpetrated by 
			 <name type="person">Edward <orig reg="Mitchell">mitchel</orig>
                  </name>
			 and 
			 <name reg="person">John Levingston</name>, Citizens of this State And
			 inhabitants of 
			 <name type="place">Hawkins <orig reg="County">county</orig>
                  </name> ,
			 on two <orig reg="Indians">indians</orig> of the 
			 <name type="place">Cherokee Nation</name> (one of the name of 
			 <name type="person">
                     <orig reg="Red">red</orig> Bird</name>) who was
			 hunting in the state of 
			 <name type="place">Kentucky</name>, On the waters of 
			 <name type="place">Kentucky river</name>.</p> 
		  
               <p>The perpetration of <del type="overstrike">so</del>
		  
                  <add place="supralinear">Such <del type="overstrike">a</del>
                  </add> horrid and
		  unwarranted <del type="overstrike">An</del> 
                  <add place="supralinear">an</add>
		  Act is contrary to the treaties existing between The 
		  <name type="place">
                     <orig reg="United">united</orig> States</name> and
		  the <orig reg="Indian">indian</orig> tribes, as also All laws human and divine,
		  and Such aggressions Ought to meet <orig reg="exemplary">examplary</orig> and
		  adequate punishment <del type="overstrike">According</del>
		  
                  <add place="supralinear">Suitable</add> to the demerit of
		  <del type="overstrike">the</del> 
                  <add place="supralinear">their</add> Crimes,
		  <orig reg="agreeably">agreably</orig> to the laws <pb n="[2]"/> they have, so
		  flagrantly and wantonly violated.
               </p> 
		  
               <p>In conformity to the demand made by his Excellency the Governor of
			 the State of 
			 <name type="place">Kentucky</name>, and <orig reg="Agreeably">Agreably</orig> to an act of Congress in such Cases made and
			 provided: I do hereby command you, to take the Aforesaid 
			 <name type="person">Edward <orig reg="Mitchell">Mitchel</orig>
                  </name>
			 and 
			 <name type="person">John Levingston</name>, or either of them if to
			 be found in your County, and them or either of them Safely and Securely to
			 convey Unto the public Jail of 
			 <name type="place">Kentucky</name>, then and there, them or either of
			 them, you are to deliver unto the keeper thereof.</p> 
		  
               <p>In order that you may be the better enabled to apprehend, take, and
			 convey the said 
			 <name type="person">Edward <orig reg="Mitchell">mitchel</orig>
                  </name>
			 and 
			 <name type="person">John Levingston</name> , or either of them as
			 aforesaid, you are hereby <orig reg="empowered">impowered</orig> to apply to,
			 and call upon, Any officer or officers, either Civil or Military Within this
			 State, to furnish you with Such <orig reg="guard">gaurd</orig> or
			 <orig reg="Guards">Gaurds</orig>, <pb n="[3]"/> as may be adequate and necessary
			 for the purpose of taking, and Safely conveying them, to the public Jail of 
			 <name type="place">Kentucky</name> as aforesaid. I also command And
			 enjoin that all officers <del type="overstrike">both</del> Civil and military,
			 <del type="overstrike">to</del> be aiding and assisting in having the aforesaid
			 
			 <name type="person">Edward Mitchell</name> and 
			 <name type="person">John Levingston</name> apprehended And taken in
			 order <add place="supralinear">that</add> they may be dealt with as the law in
			 such Cases may direct.
               </p> 
		  
               <p>Given under my hand and seal in 
			 <name type="place">Knoxville</name> this 
			 <date value="1797-03-19">19th day of March 1797</date>
               </p> 
		  
               <closer> 
			 
                  <salute>Signed <lb/> By the Governor
                  </salute> 
			 
                  <signed> 
				
                     <name type="person">John Sevier</name>
                  </signed>
               </closer> 
		
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </body> 
	 
      <back> 
		
         <div1 type="order">
            <pb n="[4]"/> 
		  
               <p>Order <lb/> Sheriff 
			 <name type="place">Hawkins <lb/> county
                     </name> 
                     <lb/> 
			 
                        <date value="1797-03-19">19th March 1797</date>
                        <lb/>			 
                           <hi rend="lined over and under">Recorded</hi>
                        
                     
                  
               </p> 
		  
               <p>
                  <hi rend="underlined"/>
               </p> 
		
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </back> 
  
   </text>
</TEI.2>
