<TEI.2 id="tl047"> 
  
   <teiHeader> 
	 
      <fileDesc> 
		
         <titleStmt> 
		  
            <title>[Letter] 1798 July 4, Knoxville, [Tennessee, to] Alfred Moore,
			 George Walton, and John Steele / John Sevier: a machine-readable transcription
			 of an image</title> 
		  
            <author>Sevier, John</author> 
		  
            <respStmt> 
			 
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 
               <name>Holly Adams</name> 
			 
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name> 
			 
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name> 
			 
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
		  
            </respStmt> 
		
         </titleStmt> 
		
         <extent>ca. k</extent> 
		
         <publicationStmt> 
		  
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher> 
		  
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace> 
		  
            <address> 
			 
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine> 
		  
            </address> 
		  
            <date>2001</date> 
		  
            <idno>tl047</idno> 
		  
            <idno>OCLC: 47832477</idno> 
		  
            <availability> 
			 
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, Tennessee. It may be used freely by individuals for
				research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability
				is included in the text.</p> 
		  
            </availability> 
		
         </publicationStmt> 
		
         <sourceDesc> 
		  
            <bibl> 
			 
               <title>[Letter] 1798 July 4, Knoxville, [Tennessee, to] Alfred Moore,
				George Walton, and John Steele / John Sevier</title> 
			 
               <author>Sevier, John</author> 
			 
               <date value="1798-07-04">July 4, 1798</date> 
			 
               <extent>2p</extent> 
			 
               <note type="summary">This document is a letter written by Tennessee
				governor John Sevier (1796-1801, 1803-1809) , dated July 4, 1798, to Alfred
				Moore, George Walton, and John Steele. Moore, Walton, and Steele were United
				States commissioners responsible for forming a treaty between the U.S. and the
				Cherokee Indians. In the letter, Sevier informed the men that James Robertson,
				James Stuart, and Major Lachlan McIntosh had been appointed as agents to
				represent the interests of the state of Tennessee in the insuing treaty. Sevier
				stated that the state agents would do all that is in their power to aid the
				commissioners in extinguishing the Cherokee claims. Sevier explained that state
				agents were necessary because of their connections with the region at hand, and
				thus, they could better represent the interests of the people there and could
				prove advantageous to the negotiations.</note> 
			 
               <note type="Collection"> Governor John Sevier Papers</note> 
			 
               <note type="Box">1</note> 
			 
               <note type="Folder">6</note> 
			 
               <note type="Document">tl047</note>
            </bibl> 
		
         </sourceDesc> 
	 
      </fileDesc> 
	 
      <encodingDesc> 
		
         <projectDesc> 
		  
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		
         </projectDesc> 
		
         <editorialDecl> 
		  
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p> 
		  
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p> 
		  
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		
         </editorialDecl> 
		
         <refsDecl> 
		  
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p> 
		
         </refsDecl> 
		
         <classDecl> 
		  
            <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
			 
               <bibl> 
				
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl> 
		  
            </taxonomy> 
		
         </classDecl> 
	 
      </encodingDesc> 
	 
      <profileDesc> 
		
         <textClass> 
		  
            <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
			 
               <list> 
				
                  <item>Letters</item> 
				
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Treaties</item> 
				
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Government relations</item> 
				
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Land tenure</item> 
				
                  <item>Boundaries</item> 
				
                  <item>Indian agents</item> 
				
                  <item>Tennessee</item> 
			 
               </list> 
		  
            </keywords> 
		
         </textClass> 
	 
      </profileDesc> 
  
   </teiHeader> 
  
   <text> 
	 
      <body> 
		
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[1]"/> 
		  
               <opener> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <name type="place">Knoxville</name> 
				  
                        <date value="1798-07-04">4th July 1798</date>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                  </address> 
			 
                  <salute>Gentlemen</salute>
               </opener> 
		  
               <p> 
			 
                  <name type="person">
                     <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> James
				Robertson</name>of 
			 <name type="place">Mero District</name>, 
			 <name type="person">James Stuart</name> Speaker of the
			 <orig reg="House of Representatives">house of representatives</orig>, and 
			 <name type="person">Major Lochlan McIntosh</name> of 
			 <name type="place">Knoxville</name> who are appointed Agents on the
			 part of the State, will have the honor of delivering you this letter
			 </p> 
		  
               <p>Believing you are authorized by the 
			 <name type="place">United States</name> to extinguish the claim of
			 the Cherokees so far, as they may be induced to sell, they will have my
			 instructions to facilitate such extinguishment, as far as in their power, And
			 fully to State to you the claims of the people they represent </p> 
		  
               <p>permit me to remark Gentlemen, that this Appointment is not made
			 under any apprehension that the Commissioners appointed by the 
			 <name type="place">United States</name>, will in any manner be
			 inattentive to the rights and interests of the people of 
			 <name type="place">Tennessee</name>, but their remote and unconnected
			 situation with the affairs of this Country, places Many very interesting
			 circumstances and events <orig reg="entirely">intirely</orig> out of their
			 <del type="overstrike">
                     <orig reg="recourse">recorse</orig>
                  </del>
		  
                  <add place="supralinear">knowledge</add>. A recurrence and development of same
		  facts, through the aid of our agents, I am led to believe will greatly
		  facilitate your negotiation, and avail the <pb n="[2]"/> 
		  
                     <name type="place">United States</name> of some useful  particular
		  advantages, as also <del type="overstrike">
                        <add place="supralinear">together
		  with</add> And Also</del> the State which they <del type="overstrike">will</del> have the honor to represent
               </p> 
		  
               <p>Wishing you a happy and <orig reg="Successful">Successfull</orig>
			 Termination of the Charge with which you are invested </p> 
		  
               <closer> 
			 
                  <salute>I have the honor to be <lb/> respectfully your <lb/> 
				
                           <abbr expan="Most Obedient">Mo. Ob.</abbr> and very 
				<abbr expan="Humble Servant">Hbl Servt.</abbr>
                        
                     
                  </salute> 
			 
                  <signed> 
                     <add cert="appears to be different ink"> 
				
                        <name type="person">John Sevier</name>
                     </add>
                  </signed> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <name type="person">Alfred Moore</name>, 
				  <name type="person">George Walton</name>
                     </addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine>And 
				  <name type="person"> John Steele</name> esquires
				  </addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine>Commissioners on the part of</addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine>The 
				  <name type="place">United States</name> for holding</addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine>A treaty with the Cherokee indians</addrLine> 
			 
                  </address> 
                  <add rend="bottom, left, sideways to text">Letter to 
			 <name type="person">Alfred Moore</name>
                     <lb/> 
			 
                        <name type="person">
                           <abbr expan="George">Geo.</abbr> Walton</name>
			  
			 
                        <name type="person ">John <lb/> Steele
                        </name> esquires
			 <add cert="appears to be different hand and ink">
                           <abbr expan="United States"> 
				
                              <name type="place">US</name>
                           </abbr> 
                           <lb/> to settle Indian treaty
			 and other matters
                        </add> 
                        <lb/> 
			 
                           <date value="1798-07-04"> 4 July 1798</date>
                           <abbr expan="Honorable ?">Honl. <unclear>P.</unclear>
                           </abbr> 
			 
                           <name type="person">
                              <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr>
				Robertson</name>
                           <lb/> 
			 
                              <name type="person">James Stuart </name>and 
			 <name type="person">Lochlan <lb/> McIntosh
                              </name> 
			 
                              <abbr expan="esquires">esqrs.</abbr> 
                              <lb/>			 
                                 <add cert="appears to be different ink">
                                    <abbr expan="Number">No.</abbr> 9</add>
			 
                                 <lb/> Recorded 
			 <figure> 
				
                                       <figDesc>miscellaneous doodling</figDesc> 
			 
                                    </figure>
                                 
                              
                           
                        
                     
                  </add>
               </closer> 
		
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </body> 
  
   </text>
</TEI.2>
