<TEI.2 id="tl059"> 
  
   <teiHeader> 
	 
      <fileDesc> 
		
         <titleStmt> 
		  
            <title>[Letter] 1804 Aug. 9, Knoxville, [Tennessee, to] Colo[nel]
			 Joseph McMin [i.e. McMinn], Colo[nel] Samuel Wear, and Maj[or] John Cowan /
			 John Sevier: a machine-readable transcription of an image</title> 
		  
            <author>Sevier, John</author> 
		  
            <respStmt> 
			 
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp> 
			 
               <name>Holly Adams</name> 
			 
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name> 
			 
               <name>Debra Jean Roney</name> 
			 
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name> 
		  
            </respStmt> 
		
         </titleStmt> 
		
         <extent>ca. k</extent> 
		
         <publicationStmt> 
		  
            <publisher>The University of Tennessee Libraries</publisher> 
		  
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, TN</pubPlace> 
		  
            <address> 
			 
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library - Special Collections</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>The University of Tennessee</addrLine> 
			 
               <addrLine>Knoxville, TN 37996</addrLine> 
		  
            </address> 
		  
            <date>2001</date> 
		  
            <idno>tl059</idno> 
		  
            <idno>OCLC: 47833182</idno> 
		  
            <availability> 
			 
               <p>This work is the property of the Tennessee State Library and
				Archives, Nashville, Tennessee. It may be used freely by individuals for
				research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability
				is included in the text.</p> 
		  
            </availability> 
		
         </publicationStmt> 
		
         <sourceDesc> 
		  
            <bibl> 
			 
               <title>[Letter] 1804 Aug. 9, Knoxville, [Tennessee, to] Colo[nel]
				Joseph McMin [i.e. McMinn], Colo[nel] Samuel Wear, and Maj[or] John Cowan /
				John Sevier</title> 
			 
               <author>Sevier, John</author> 
			 
               <date value="1804-08-09">August 9, 1804</date> 
			 
               <extent>4p</extent> 
			 
               <note type="summary">This document is a letter written by John
				Sevier, Governor of Tennessee from 1796-1801 and 1803-1809, to Colonel Joseph
				McMinn, Colonel Samuel Wear, and Major John Cowan, dated August 9, 1804. In the
				letter, Sevier informed these men that he had received word of a meeting to be
				held with the commissioners of Georgia regarding a road that would be built
				connecting the two states, which would also run through Cherokee lands. Sevier
				commanded the men to attend the meeting, and he gave further instructions of
				the agreements to be made with the Georgian commissioners. Sevier wanted to
				make certain that both states would have an equal amount of work to do in
				constructing the road and reap an equal number of advantages from its
				existence. </note> 
			 
               <note type="Collection">Governor John Sevier Papers</note> 
			 
               <note type="Box">1</note> 
			 
               <note type="Folder">1</note> 
			 
               <note type="Document">tl059</note>
            </bibl> 
		
         </sourceDesc> 
	 
      </fileDesc> 
	 
      <encodingDesc> 
		
         <projectDesc> 
		  
            <p>Prepared for The University of Tennessee Digital Library</p> 
		
         </projectDesc> 
		
         <editorialDecl> 
		  
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p> 
		  
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with
			 Microsoft Word spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread</p> 
		  
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags</p> 
		  
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p> 
		  
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been
			 omitted.</p> 
		
         </editorialDecl> 
		
         <refsDecl> 
		  
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or
			 illustrations toward which a reference or figure points</p> 
		
         </refsDecl> 
		
         <classDecl> 
		  
            <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
			 
               <bibl> 
				
                  <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
               </bibl> 
		  
            </taxonomy> 
		
         </classDecl> 
	 
      </encodingDesc> 
	 
      <profileDesc> 
		
         <textClass> 
		  
            <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
			 
               <list> 
				
                  <item>Letters</item> 
				
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Government relations</item> 
				
                  <item>Cherokee Indians--Land tenure</item> 
				
                  <item>Roads--Design and construction</item> 
				
                  <item>Georgia</item> 
				
                  <item>Tennessee</item> 
			 
               </list> 
		  
            </keywords> 
		
         </textClass> 
	 
      </profileDesc> 
  
   </teiHeader> 
  
   <text> 
	 
      <body> 
		
         <div1 type="letter">
            <pb n="[1]"/> 
		  
               <opener> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <name type="place">Knoxville</name> 
				  
                        <date value="1804-08-09">9th August 1804</date>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                  </address> 
			 
                  <salute>Gentlemen</salute>
               </opener> 
		  
               <p>Having received notice from the Georgian Commissioners proposing a
			 meeting at 
			 <name type="person">James Vans</name> on the 
			 <date value="0000-00-15">15th</date> Instant, you will readily
			 discover the necessity of repairing to that place with the utmost dispatch</p> 
		  
               <p>Permit me to recommend in the first place an agreement to be made
			 with the 
			 <name type="person">Georgian</name> Commissioners Consigning to each
			 State an equal part of the road most <orig reg="convenient">conveinant</orig>
			 for each party to open and clear out  If this point should be settled
			 and agreed upon, very probably your place of meeting will be considered near
			 the Middle Ground  Secondly  you will proceed to explore and Mark
			 out the nearest, best, and most <orig reg="convenient">conveinant</orig>
			 
                  <orig reg="routes">routs</orig>, for <orig reg="wagon">waggon</orig> roads,
			 leading from the two stations agreed upon between the 
			 <name type="place">United States</name> and Cherokees, (<orig reg="to wit">towit</orig>) "From Southwest point and 
			 <name type="place">Tellico Blockhouse</name>," to such part of the
			 way and place as may be agreed upon by the Commissioners:
			 <add place="bottom, right">The</add> 
                  <pb n="[2]"/> The two roads leading from
			 the aforesaid points, to intersect each other conformably to the articles of
			 agreement between the 
			 <name type="place">
                        <orig reg="United">united</orig> States</name> and
			 the Indians. You will also agree and conclude upon a certain and Suitable place
			 to prefix a twin pike to be erected. As the two roads to be laid off from 
			 <name type="place">Tellico</name> and Southwest point will require
			 some time, I therefore recommend the road leading from 
			 <name type="place">Tellico</name>, to be the first marked out,
			 provided you <orig reg="cannot">can not</orig> have them both laid off at or
			 near the same time  
               </p> 
		  
               <p>I have observed that probably your place of meeting would be about
			 the Middle Ground, but you will please to Notice, that for a great part of the
			 Way leading from 
			 <name type="place">Tennessee <orig reg="River">river</orig>
                  </name>
			 there <del type="overstrike">is</del> 
                  <add place="supralinear">are</add> two
		  roads to be cut on our side, which considerably Stretch and lengthen the
		  distance, and it <orig reg="ought">aught</orig> to be so arranged that 
		  <name type="place">Tennessee</name> should not have more miles to cut,
		  than 
		  <name type="place">Georgia</name>, who <del type="overstrike">have</del> 
                  <add place="supralinear">has</add> resolved to pay
		  an equal Moiety of the expense. Those <orig reg="indefinite">indifinate</orig>
		  points it is expected will be agreed upon and adjusted, <pb n="[3]"/> in a
		  manner <orig reg="consistent">consistant</orig> with such reciprocity,
		  <orig reg="Fairness">Fairnes</orig>, and <orig reg="equability">equibility</orig>, as ought ever to subsist and Govern between
		  Sister States, taking into <orig reg="Vein">Viene</orig> mutual and beneficial
		  advantages 
               </p> 
		  
               <p>For your further Guide and instructions, you will attend strictly to
			 the Articles of agreement between the 
			 <name type="place">United States</name> and the Cherokees, and the
			 law passed by our <del type="overstrike">
                     <unclear>unk</unclear>
                  </del>
		  legislature on the Subject <add place="supralinear">at their late Session</add>
		   Should it so happen that You <del type="overstrike">could</del>
		  
                  <add place="supralinear">should</add> not agree with the 
		  <name type="person">
                     <orig reg="Georgian">Georgin</orig>
                  </name>
		  Commissioners what particular part of the road on our side, we are to cut and
		  open out, your own discretion in that case will then Govern your conduct
		  <orig reg="agreeably">agreably</orig> to the agreement and law, above quoted
		   <add place="supralinear">copies of each you will herewith receive</add>
		  I have no doubt you will perceive the propriety of making every exertion to
		  have the roads laid off and marked out as soon as possible, and report
		  <orig reg="immediately">immeadiately</orig> thereon, the manner in which the
		  same <del type="overstrike">has</del> 
                  <add place="have">have</add> been
		  conducted, the distance in Miles you suppose there may be
		  <del type="overstrike">on our part</del> to cut, <add place="supralinear">on
		  our part</add> what kind of Country the same will pass through, and whether the
		  same will require any <unclear>Canswaying</unclear>, ditching, or bridging
		   and if any, how much <pb n="[4]"/> In the <orig reg="meantime">mean
		  time</orig>, you will please forward at suitable opportunities information how
		  you are progressing  
               </p> 
		  
               <closer> 
			 
                  <salute>I am Gentlemen very respectfully <lb/> your 
				<abbr expan="Most Obedient Servant">Mo Obt Servt</abbr> 
                        <lb/>				(signed) 
                     
                  </salute> 
			 
                  <signed> 
				
                     <name type="person">John Sevier</name> 
                  </signed> 
			 
                  <address> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <name type="person">
                           <abbr expan="Colonel">Colo</abbr> Joseph
					 <orig reg="McMinn">McMin</orig>
                        </name>
                     </addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <name type="person">
                           <abbr expan="Colonel">Colo</abbr> Samuel
					 Wear</name>, and</addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine> 
				  
                        <name type="person">
                           <abbr expan="Major">Maj</abbr> John
					 Cowan</name>
                     </addrLine> 
				
                     <addrLine>Commissioners <unclear> 
				  
                           <abbr expan="et cetera">c</abbr>
                        </unclear>
                     </addrLine> 
			 
                  </address>  
                  <add place="right, sideways"> Copy 
			 <lb/> Instructions to Commissioners <lb/> 
			 
                           <date value="1804-08-09">9 Augt 1804</date> 
                           <lb/> To be
			 recorded
                        
                     
                  </add>
               </closer> 
		
            
         </div1> 
	 
      </body> 
  
   </text>
</TEI.2>
