<?xml-model href="http://diglib.lib.utk.edu/dlc/standards/tei/tei_lite_di_v4.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="um030">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Letter] 1840 Nov. 7 [to] Elizabeth Chester, Jackson Tennessee / Mary Jane Chester : a machine readable transcription of an image</title>
            <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
               <name>Lesli Wall Zimmerman</name>
               <name>Debra Roney</name>
               <name>Maha Ayesh</name>
               <name>Amy Emert</name>
               <name>Jim Cole</name>
               <name/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>University of Tennessee Special Collections Library</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Knoxville, Tennessee</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Hoskins Library- Special Collections</addrLine>
               <addrLine>University of Tennessee</addrLine>
               <addrLine>Knoxville, Tennessee 37996</addrLine>
            </address>
            <date>2002</date>
            <idno>um030</idno>
            <idno>OCLC: 50274960</idno>
            <availability status="restricted">
               <p>This work is the property of the University of Memphis Libraries, Special Collections Department, Ned R. McWherter Library, Memphis, TN.  It may be used freely by individuals for research, teaching, and personal use as long as this statement of availability is included in the text.  For all other use contact the University of Memphis Libraries, 126 Ned R. McWherter Library, The University of Memphis,  Memphis, TN 38152-6500.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>[Letter] 1840 Nov. 7 [to] Elizabeth Chester, Jackson Tennessee / Mary Jane Chester </title>
               <author>Chester, Mary Jane</author>
               <date when="1840-11-07">November 7, 1840</date>
               <extent>4p</extent>
               <note type="summary" anchored="true">This document is a letter dated November 7, 1840 to Elizabeth Chester from her daughter Mary Jane Chester. Mary Jane describes her daily life at the Female Institute in Columbia, Tennessee.</note>
               <note type="collection" anchored="true">Chester Family Papers, MS25</note>
               <note type="box" anchored="true">1</note>
               <note type="folder" anchored="true">4</note>
               <note type="document" anchored="true">um030</note>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created for the University of Tennessee Digital Library</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Quotation marks retained as data except inside q tags</p>
            <p>Errors in transcription of the printed text controlled with X-Metal 2.1 spell-checker; text has also been thoroughly proofread.</p>
            <p>Corrections and normalization represented by editorial tags.</p>
            <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens removed.</p>
            <p>Catchwords and directional notes such as "turn page over" have been omitted.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl>
            <p>ID attributes provided for only those pages, chapters, or illustrations toward which a reference or figure points.</p>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term>Letters</term>
               <term>Boarding school students</term>
               <term>Tennessee</term>
               <term>
                  <name role="Correspondent http://id.loc.gov/vocabulary/relators/crp">Chester, Mary Jane</name>
               </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div subtype="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="um030a.small.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="person">Mrs Elizabeth Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Jackson Tennessee</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <add place="left of address">postmark 18¾<date when="1840-11-07">7 <choice>
                        <abbr>Nov.</abbr>
                        <expan>November</expan>
                     </choice> 1840</date>
               </add>
               <pb n="2" facs="um030b.small.jpg"/>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name type="place">Columbia Female Institute</name>
                     <date when="1840-11-07">November 7th 1840</date>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
               <salute>My dear Mother</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I received your kind and affectionate letter on last Thursday. I <del type="overstrike">had</del> began to think that you did not intend writing at all to me for it was so long a time before you did write— but I can forgive you for that, for when it did come it contained so much good advice to me, that I read it and all <del type="overstrike">of</del> the rest of my letters over eve⁁<add place="supralinear">r</add> y night. (for I have not time to read them in the day time.) Dear Mam ⁁ <add place="supralinear">m</add> a you requested me to read my Bible; I do read it every morning of my life. I hope that you will forgive me for not writing home last week: but I thought as I had written two letters home week before last that you would not be uneasy. I just got time last week to answer cousin Rachel's letter. Please tell <name type="person">Eliza Bigelow</name>, and <name type="person">Frank Patterson</name> to write to me, not to wait for me to write to them for I have hardly time to write to you. Mam ⁁ <add place="supralinear">m</add> a although you wrote me that Aunt Narcissa's sickness was not serious, I cannot help from feeling uneasy. Tell her that I shall feel uneasy until I receive a letter from her I want her to fill the three pages. Tell Uncle <pb n="3" facs="um030c.small.jpg"/> and cousin Will they do not know how much a letter from them would gratify me. I am almost tired of asking Aunt P, cousin Jane, and cousin Martha Ann to write me. I cannot let brother John, and sister, off with one letter, they must write to me again. I am expecting Papa up to see me every day. Mam ⁁ <add place="supralinear">m</add> a Please send me up some hazel nuts by Papa if he can bring them with <del type="overstrike">conenience</del>
               <add place="supralinear">convenience</add>. I expect that you will think it a very strange request, but I have not had any thing good since I ⁁<add place="supralinear">have</add> been here. You wanted to know what I was studying and how I stood in my classes. It's of <choice>
                  <orig>now</orig>
                  <reg>no</reg>
               </choice> use for me to write you as I expect Father has received my record by this time. We had a dreadful hail storm last evening—⁁<add place="supralinear">Some of</add> the hail was nearly as large as a hen eggs, four or five pane's of glass was broken at the Institute. Sixteen panes were broken out of Aunt Walkers house, there was a great deal of lightning with it. We were all very much frightened I can assure you. I was thinking about you all at home all of the time. </p>
            <p>How many teeth has brother Sam got now. I expect that he can walk and talk I dont want him to forget me. learn <del type="overstrike">him</del>
               <add place="supralinear">teach</add> how to call my name. Do not let any of the children  forget me. Has <name type="person">Mary Ormand</name> forgotten me. I have been away from home for so long a time O! it seems to me that it has been a year. If I could receive a letter <choice>
                  <orig>oftener</orig>
                  <reg>more often</reg>
               </choice> I could pass my time more pleasantly. Dear Mam ⁁ <add place="supralinear">m</add> a Give my love to my Papa &amp; all of my Brothers and my sister, and to all of my Aunts and cousins and Uncles <pb n="4" facs="um030d.small.jpg"/> and kiss Brother Sam, King, Will, and Mary Ormand, and all my little cousins, and accept the love of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>your affectionate Daughter</salute>
               <signed>
                  <name type="person">Mary Jane Chester</name>
               </signed>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>
                     <name>Mrs Elizabeth Chester</name>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
            <closer>
               <add place="bottom of letter">
                  <note>
                     <p>
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>P. S.</abbr>
                           <expan>Post Script</expan>
                        </choice> Please excuse my bad writing and spel⁁<add place="supralinear">l</add> ing for I just wrote on a book in my lap </p>in a very great hurry I can assure. Give my love to all of the servants</note>
               </add>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
